[Music]
Welcome back to Implementing a Data
Warehouse with SQL Server 2012 Jump Start. I'm George Squillace.
I'm here with Rich Currey. And, Rich, you have a lot of good
things queued up for us in this module.
>> Yeah, this is going to be a fun one because we are going to
go back and continue on this data flow thing. We're going to
be talking about data flow, transforming data. We're going to
be dealing with a lot of the standard transforms that you use
to build an ETL process. Now, not control flow. Control flow,
after the meal break, is going to deal with workflow issues.
This is all about manipulating the data as it goes on through.
So let's go in and start talking about the beginnings of this.
Merges, look-ups, data modification. This is one of those topics
where we've got a lot of transforms that can affect the content
of our data.
Merge transforms to take two data streams and bring them into
a single one, we've got look-up transforms that can go out and
get data from somewhere based on a value in the pipeline, and
we've got data modification that can actually change it as it
goes along.
So let's start out with the merge transforms. And there are
two of them, the merge transform and the merge join transform.
Both of them, George, require that your data be ordered.
And, even better, it's got to be in the same order.
You can't have data sorted by date in one input and by product
ID in another because then there would be no way to put them together.
The merge is like taking a deck of cards, splitting it in half
and shuffling them so that they come together like this.
But in order for them to come together right, they have to be
in that same order.
>> Well put. I like the interleaving there, Rich.
>> You know, it's a visual. It works.
>> It works.
>> All right. Now, another requirement on merges is that they
have to have the same number of columns in both data flows and
they have to have the same data types in each column. Now, it
would help, George, if they also had the same logical information
in each column, but it is not a requirement, unlike the other two.
Now, if I've got a data source that has the ability to pre-sort
the data, that would be a huge benefit to the data flow. So whenever
possible, you want to have the data sorted in the data source.
So if you're retrieving it from an RDBMS, you'd want put in order
by on that retrieval, on that
select statement, that would put the data in the appropriate
order and then you would mark that data source as being sorted.
You then have top indicate what it's sorted on so that the development
environment has the ability to check and make sure that both
sources are sorted the same way.
Now, the merge deals with the records and putting two record
sets together.
What I like to say, it puts them together vertically.
>> Yeah, I like that too.
>> It takes the two record sets and it puts one on top of the
other or takes them and combines them so that they come into
a single flow.
A merge join is more like a database join. A merge join has
the ability to support inner joins, left joins, full joins that
has to be at least one column that matches from a metadata standpoint,
data type, et cetera,
and, again, like the merge, both inputs have to be sorted the
same way so that the join can be enabled. What you end up with,
then, is a single record set that matches the two records together
and creates, instead of a set of records stacked on each other,
it's side by side where the record from input A is matched up
with the record from input B and you have all the columns from
both inputs together.
>> Something's curiously missing, though. I see an inner join,
a left, and a full, but I don't see a right.
>> Okay.
George, very simply, if I were to take and flip
the tables from one side to the other, what happened to my left table?
>> Well, guess what? I gotta switch there.
>> Yeah. The left is on the right and the right is on the left.
So if you need a left join, you'd start with table A. If you
need a right join, you'd start with table B.
>> There you go. Easy.
>> All right. Let's move into our next topic, look-up transforms.
Look-up transforms, again, just like a merge and a merge join,
it is a multi-input transformation.
Merge and merge join take two and bring them together. The look-up
takes a value from a record that's currently in the data flow
pipeline and then goes out to an external source to retrieve
information from a record that has a matching value.
It is typically defined by a select statement, so it takes a
value, it uses that value to select data from that external source.
The external source can be either an OLEDB connection or a cache connection.
A cache connection is a connection that's in memory.
Now, think about this for a minute. What would be more efficient, George?
Would it be more efficient for me to look up each record from
an external database one by one or might it be more efficient
to go out and grab the record and leave it in memory in case
I need it later?
>> Let's leave it in memory.
>> That's the cache. But if I've got a couple hundred thousand
records, well, the more records that you're retrieving in that
look-up, the less efficient it is to leave them all in cache.
>> Sure. So there's a design aspect to it.
>> There absolutely is. And you can configure the cache. You can
same I want it fully cached, I want it partially cached, you
can control the amount of memory it's going to use, you can even
say I don't want it cached.
>> Very granular.
>> And here's another cool one.
You can even pre-load the cache.
>> Nice.
>> So that when the data flow starts, it goes out, retrieves the
records from the look-up source, loads them in memory, and that
way everything you need is right there and available.
>> Nice.
>> Lastly I want to talk about some of the data modification transforms.
It is called ETL.
We're changing the data as it traverses through the pipeline.
We've got the ability to change data types
with a data conversion transform.
It takes a standard data type, it's the equivalent of a SQL Server
cast or convert, as an example.
We can do a derived column. A derived column, we can take and
calculate a new value based on values that are already in the
data flow.
>> Very powerful transform.
>> Yeah. An example of that one: I've got a first name, a last
name, and I want to combine those into a full name, last name,
comma, first name. I can calculate that with an expression and
add that to my data flow as a new value or I could just use it
to replace the existing name value as well.
There are a lot of functions in there. There are all of the
standard string manipulation and functions and things like that.
Very cool.
I can do character mapping. Character mapping allows me to manipulate
the string data types...
text, VARCHAR, CHAR...
using all of the standard string functions. You can
upper case it, lower case it, all that kind of stuff.
>> And, like all along, you have some things you want to show us.
Or are we not ready for that?
>> No, we can do that.
>> All right.
>> I guess we'll let that happen now.
>> Sorry. I was playing with you a little bit there.
Let's go over to the virtual machine here, and I have a blank
slate with SQL Server Integration Services going. So I'm just
going to create a new project, and that new project is going
to be an integration services project. And just like before,
I really don't care where they put it or what they call it.
>> That's just detail.
>> We're playing.
>> For now.
>> Well, what do I need to be able to do transforms? I need a
data flow task. So first thing I'm going to do is drop a data
flow task into my control flow.
I'm going to open it up, I'm going to grab a data source >> Gotta
start somewhere.
>> You do. You gotta add data if you're going to transform it.
So I'm going to grab an OLEDB source, drop it on there. I don't
have a connection manager. I'm going to create one. I'm going
to base it on one of the ones we've already got.
Makes it nice and easy.
And you know what I forgot, George?
>> What's that?
>> I was I was cleaning up from our last little adventure I did
not recreate my data warehouse.
So let me quickly go over to Management Studio and load up a
setup script...
>> Oh, you have something handy for that, do you?
>> I always have something handy. I'm like the Boy Scouts here
in the States.
>> Always prepared?
>> Their motto is be prepared.
So let's go back and into SQL BIC. There's my error message.
I told you I forgot. Let's try it again.
I may have to go back and actually kill this. I do. I'm going
to have to reconfigure now.
Come on, you.
I love it when that happens.
>> While you're queueing that up, Rich, whenever I think of the
transformations available in SSIS, I'm always reminded of the
game Mouse Trap.
I don't know if you all remember the game Mouse Trap, but remember
the contraptions and all the moving parts and things like that?
It just always reminds me of Mouse Trap. What we're building
is a data contraption.
>> It really is. It really is. There are a lot of moving pieces,
and you do have to actually get them right. So I just went in
and I grabbed the connection that I had made earlier.
>> Perfect.
>> And we now have our list of tables to get. Every now and again
sometimes if you just recreate or go in and grab a different
version, it frequently clears it up. So let's go out and let's
look at our product table.
And we're just going to grab all of the records from our product
table and we're going to play with those.
Now, the first thing I'm going to do is I am going to create...
and let's take a look and see what our transforms are. As you
can tell, we've got a lot of them.
>> And they're categorized.
>> They are. Well, kind of loosely.
>> Loosely.
>> Very loosely. The common ones and the other ones.
So I won't say that it's a really useful categorization, but,
yeah, you're right, it's there.
Let's look at first a very good one, which is
our derived column.
Now, what did I have to do when I made my data destination aware
of the records that were coming in?
>> Going to have to make a pipeline flow here.
>> You got it. Now, when I select the OLEDB source... I just
want to give you a little hint, a little preview of things to come.
See the two arrows?
>> There are two.
>> There are. One of them is kind of blueish and the other one
is red.
And the red one is where error... is where records that have
errors go if you configure. We're going to be talking more about
that a little later.
>> The difficult ones.
>> It is.
We're going to connect the two together. My derived column is
now aware of the columns that are coming out of the source.
So when I double click on my derived column, I'm given the dialogue
that's going to allow me to create a new column.
I've got my derived column name.
I'm going to call this
NameDescription because I was tasked with putting together a
concatenation separated by a dash of a name and a product description.
Now, over here on the left side I've got all of the values that
are available to me. Variables, including system variables, and
all of the columns that are coming into the derived column transform.
>> This is a powerful editor.
>> On the right side I've got all my pre-built functions. So I
can go out and grab string functions, for example, and then just
drag, drop, and configure.
You don't have to program the heck out of this stuff.
Yeah, it's nice to program too. Don't get me wrong. I'm a developer.
I like to play in code.
But this makes it much easier frequently.
So, like I said, I'm going to add as a new column. The expression
is going to be the name.
>> Drag and drop.
>> Drag and drop, and then what I'm going to do with it,
and then the description.
Well, I forgot my plus sign so let me put that in there.
And I got a good one, right?
>> Looks like it's good.
>> All right. So let's get... wait a minute.
>> Wait a minute.
>> Red is bad, isn't it?
>> Red is bad.
>> Okay. So I gotta problem here.
If you're a SQL Server developer, this problem is going to be
a recurring one for you that's going to drive you crazy. A little
tip for all those folks that are coming into this.
SQL Server uses a tic mark for strings.
Yeah, well, SSIS is more like C#, C++.
>> It's a different expression language.
>> It is. It uses double quotes. So as soon as I change that,
batta-bing, my expression is black and we are off to the races.
I hit okay.
I now have my derived column. If I go out and I create a destination
to take that, we're going to throw this into a flat file destination.
I hook it up, I go to configure, I'm going to create a new flat
file connection manager which is going to go out to the desktop
and is going to put it into myproducts.text.
I think I hit caps lock there somewhere.
>> That's going to work.
>> Yeah, I know. I'm not going to worry about it, but I hate it
when that happens. I always feel like I'm yelling at people when
I do that...
>> Why are you yelling...
[Laughter]
>> Easy, George. Easy. Got my columns now. The product key, the
product alternate key, the name, the description, and look at this.
My name description column.
When I now go in and I hit okay, I come over to my mappings,
there's my name description. I have now added that new column
into the flow.
When I run this, we go out.
Everything looks good from here. Let's go to the desktop.
>> Looks good.
>> And my products, yelling at me to be looked at.
Eventually it's going to open up, I hope. There we go. And there
it is. Here's cycling,
here's cycling helmet, there's clothing, and here is my name
description, helmet, cycling helmet. Cool?
>> You've derived something from thin air!
>> I have. I have. And you know what? The others are very cool
as well, the look-ups and things like that. There are actually
a large number... I was trying to think of a good word to use.
The only one that came to mind was bajillion, but I'm not sure
people actually know that that's a big number.
>> Yeah.
Okay.
>> At any rate, if you look at some of these, I've got conditional
splits, I've got my data conversion where I can change data types.
I can go in, I've got SharePoint list destinations and sorts,
I've got sort transforms I can put in there. If I wanted to
put a sort in there in front of my derived column, well, pretty
easy to do. I'm going to delete the connection there.
Notice I now have problems. I'm going to throw my sort transform
in the middle. We'll come in, we will grab it, and then we will
connect it downstream.
Hopefully that's going to fix it. It should.
I have all of mine here. I'm going to take my input column, product
key, and now I define my sort type.
Sort order
and any comparison flags that are necessary.
I hit okay, I've got my sort configured, and notice it cleans
up all of the downstream errors because I've put my pipeline
in place.
>> No metadata changed up the pipeline, so everything else bowed
down in compliance.
>> Absolutely. I will say, though, George, and I'll give you a
heads-up on this one, if you start doing what I just did, throwing
transforms in the middle of a pipe that's already been established,
you'd better make sure that you've got the right connections
at either end. Because if one of the connections is wrong, just
like the wrong connection on a hose, they don't go together real well.
So what have we got next there, George?
>> So next up, we've been look at moving rows through the pipeline.
And let's just say rows moving through the pipeline don't always
fit downstream, so we have to handle that.
>> You mean I'm going to keep on down with that little one I gave
you tip on or the preview of?
>> That's right.
>> Error rows.
>> So when we're dealing with error rows, error rows occur because
there's a problem with data when you're working with it in an
expected form as it's going through the pipeline.
Maybe on my derived column I've got two columns that have values
that can't be manipulated to do the calculation. They don't
match up. Or maybe I'm doing a data conversion from character
to number and somebody put the letter z
in the character column. I can't convert a z to a number.
So what happens? What happens is that row causes an error when
it hits the data conversion. Now, normal setup is that when the
transform kicks an error on a record, that
causes the entire data flow to crash.
>> That was a crashing sound.
>> I couldn't tell It almost made me crash.
[Laughter]
So when the transform crashes, when the pipeline can't put it
through, unless you've told it something special to do, it stops
it dead in its tracks and causes the entire package to fail.
Now, if I've got a half a million records going through the pipeline
and I've got one record with an error,
yeah, that's going to be a problem, because that means that if
that one record is the 499,373rd
record, I'm got to go back and redo all those 1s because it blew
up and nothing got saved.
What you want to be able to do is take that record out of the
data flow and redirect it somewhere else so that one of your
data stewards, one of your business analysts has the ability
to deal with the exception as an exception instead of having
to redo an entire workflow that worked correctly for everything
but that one record. So that is the error rows. Now, there are
two kinds of errors that can occur.
You can have data conversion errors.
Data conversion errors means just what I said earlier. You can't
make it a number. You can't make it whatever you're trying to
make it into.
>> Like a round peg in a square hole.
>> You got it. The other type of error, however, is a truncation error.
>> That sounds scary.
>> Well, it is, but not so much.
Truncation errors have to deal with when a value does not fit
into its destination.
So if I had a VARCHAR 50 column, has the potential to hold up
to 50 characters, if I were to try and put that into a VARCHAR
30 destination, there's your truncation. It doesn't mean that
every record is going to be chopped. It means that there's a
possibility that that record is going to get chopped. When the
record actually does get chopped, that's when you get the truncation error.
Now, that could also happen if you're going from BIGINT to INT,
from a high decimal... a high number of digit decimal configuration
to a smaller number of digits. Anytime you're trying to take
a value that is potentially bigger than its destination you've
got the possibility for truncation errors. Now, that's not the
only thing that can happen, George.
>> No. One more.
>> Yep. We also have what's called the on error event. Now, and
event is something that happens inside of the package.
There are lots of different kinds of events, and we're going
to need to talk about those in a lot more detail this afternoon.
>> Yep.
>> But the on error event is a specific event that occurs that
gets fired when an error occurs. Now, the cool thing is that
when you have an on error event, you can actually configure a
control flow that's going to execute in response to the event.
And that control flow will occur
only when the event occurs. With the error event, it only happens...
it's only triggered if there is an error on a record. But, like
I said, there are a bunch of others as well.
>> And you have some things to show us, specifically some pipeline
error handling.
>> Yeah, I do. I do. And you know what? We're going to configure
that derived column that we had there to pump any errors that
it's got out to another file.
So the first thing I need to do is I need to create a destination.
Actually, yeah, I do. I need a create a flat file destination.
So in this case I'm going to put all of the errors that occur
out to a text file so that they can be dealt with by our data stewards.
Are you familiar with that term, George?
>> I am.
>> I wonder if everybody else is.
>> Go ahead and help everybody else out.
>> All right. So many times we have folks whose primarily responsibility
is to manage the data in the data warehouse. Not necessarily
operational, but in the data warehouse as well. So those folks,
their title is data steward, in many ways. So that's what we
want to deal with. So I've created my flat file destination.
It has no input column. So before I can really configure it what
I'm going to do is take the error output from derive column,
the red arrow, and I'm going to connect it to the flat file,
and it immediately brings up a dialogue box because I have not
configured that error output. So here I have choices. I have
error choices and truncation choices, and I can say what I want
to happen. The default is fail the component, which means interrupt
processing and send a failure message. I also, however, can
ignore the failure... yeah, well, that doesn't make a lot of
sense because then nobody finds out about it and it doesn't get fixed.
Or... and this is the one I like...
I get to redirect the row.
>> So you can configure this per column per problem or per problem
per column.
>> In many cases you have a very, very, very fine level of control.
Absolutely. Now that I've got my error output configured, let's
go configure our flat file destination.
Now, I don't have any records that are actually going to error.
What I want to show you on here, though, is the mappings.
Notice how the input columns have a couple of added
to it.
>> Error codes.
>> Error code and error column.
So when you get a value, a row, that ends up in error, it doesn't
just pop it out to the destination, it actually tells you what
happened as well.
>> Nice. Good forensics.
>> It is helpful. It is very helpful. So what have we got next?
>> Next up... well, in particular, you being a .NET guy, you're
going to have some fun stuff to show us here.
We have another kind of a task called the script task.
>> Yeah. The script task. So one of the things that's really cool
about SSIS is the fact that it is very, very easy to extend functionality.
Now, there is a whole lot... don't get me wrong. You're not
going to be playing in that script task day in and day out.
But the script task itself is a building block that we have available
to us where we can create functionality that does not currently
exist in SSIS, and it uses standard .NET development. It uses
either Visual Basic or C# and gives you the ability to create
not just new transformations, George, but new destinations and
new sources as well.
>> So I can use this in control flow and I can use it in the pipeline.
>> Absolutely. You can do both. And in the pipeline you can use
it as a source, as a transform, or as a destination. The only
limit to what you can do with a script transform is that limit
right there.
The one between your ears.
If you can dream it and you can design it, then you can code it.
It is literally that powerful.
>> And the framework that is provided is huge.
>> Oh, you've got access to the entire .NET framework.
You've got access to all of the class library functionality that
Microsoft provides pre-built and ready for you to use.
Now, scripts, as I said, can transform data as it's going through
the pipeline, you can create custom code to reach out to technologies
that you cannot create connection managers for, you can go out
and provide destinations, you can create hooks into an application
so that SSIS could literal be used to bring data directly into
an executing application without having to go through a database,
without having to go through a flat file or anything else.
To build a script, the first thing you need to do is know what language.
I certainly wouldn't want to try and write a book in French when
I only speak German. So, please, understand, C# and VB, very different.
If you like curly braces and double equals, which I'm going to
forgot later, if you like semicolons and brevity, C# is for you.
If you like a more language-friendly
development, something that's more self-documenting and readable,
maybe VB is the way you go.
It uses the VBA.NET editor and has the ability to communicate
back with the package to access variables and provide success
and failure so that if you've got a problem, you have the ability
to notify SSIS that it's out there.
>> And you have some things to show.
>> I do.
I absolutely do.
So let us go out, and I am going to close out this project that
I'm in because I have another one out there.
Come on. Yeah, we'll save it. What the heck.
And we open up our new project, which is down here...
nope. Wrong one.
There it is.
>> It says script demo.
>> It does.
And there is in here a data flow task. And in the data flow
task I've got some scripts.
I've got a script that's acting as a data source, I've got a
script that's acting as a transformation, I've got a script that's
acting as a destination, and I've got a script that's going to
run after the data flow task in the control flow. So we're going
to give you examples of all four types.
>> Excellent.
>> So let's start out with our script source. Now, the script
source, when you go to configure it, the first choice you have
to make is what language you're going to be using.
Script language down here.
Visual C# 2010, so that works for me because I'm a C# kind of guy.
I click on the edit script
button, and it now launches VBA, it
launches the application script editor and brings you in.
Now, we've got some things here that we need to explain. If you're
not a C# developer, don't worry about this.
But there are some things, and I just want to point out in C#
we have brought in some of the pre-built functionality from the
system name space, the data name space, the DTS name space, so
it provides us access to pre-built Microsoft functionality.
>> A bunch of references.
>> You got it. We have some methods. Methods are the equivalent
of scripts in T-SQL. They are little packages of executing code
that you call by name. One of them, acquire connections, is code
that's going to run when a connection to an outside source is
brought and opened. I've got a pre-execute which is going to
happen before the transform executes.
And then I've got create new output rows, which is the method
that's responsible for going out, grabbing the data from wherever
it is, and putting it into the pipeline. It uses
the output buffer
.AddRow method. The AddRow method is what is adds the row into
the connection. So I could go out and access, I don't know, an
FTP site somewhere out in...
across the ocean in another country, authenticate to it using
the script, go out, grab information, process it because it's
in a custom form, strip out the individual values, add them to
the row, and put them into the pipeline.
>> Go!
>> All that.
And then, of course, the clean-up. When you're done, there is
a post-execute.
That's where you would put up any cleaned-up code. And there
is a release connections which happens when the connection is
closed out.
Second piece of this, I have a script transform.
Now, again, here I've got input columns. Those are the ones
that were added into the output buffer by the input script.
And I have inputs and outputs which define what's coming into
the script and what's going to be sent out again.
When I'm in my script again I go to my edit script. It brings
up the script editor and loads in the functionality that's already
been built.
In here, again, I've got pre-execute and I've got post-execute.
Those are going to be in every script in the pipeline.
Here, though, I've got process input row. Now, notice it says
input 0.
I can have multiple inputs coming into this script from different
sources and do custom processing to combine them into a single output.
Now, this one happens to be a very simple script. It's going
to take the row from the data buffer, it's going to act on the
second column, putting it to upper case. So it's going to take
the input and it's going to put it all into upper case.
Finally, I have my destination script. The destination script now...
I'm going to show you something a little different.
We can have variables in our packages.
And the scripts have access to the variables, but only
if I add them to the read-only variables if it's going to be
read-only or the read-write variables if I need to be able to
write a value back to that variable. Here I've specified the
UserResults variable as a read-write variable... and I hope
I'm not giving away the farm here... but when I go into my script,
guess what it's going to do?
>> What?
>> It's going to put the output
into the variable. Okay. So I've got my pre-execute.
I've got my process input row.
In my pre-execute I'm creating an array called myResults.
MyResults is going to be a string array with six members.
In the process input row I'm going to take the current row and
put it in
myResults, the value of column two of that current row.
And then when I'm done executing, when I'm done processing all
the rows, I'm going to access the read-write variables, UserResults
variable, and I'm going to assign myResults to the value.
Now, that's all set up because once I'm done what I end up with
is whatever what came in from the input going through and ending
up in the UserResults variable.
When I come back out to the control flow, I go into my script
task, notice
UserResults is listed in the read-only variables.
So when I go in to edit the script here,
it now is going to take
in the main method,
create a results message,
the results message is going to loop through... remember, UserResults
has an array of strings. So it's going to go and it's going to
loop through all the strings and append them to the results message.
And then it's going to show that message and tell SQL Integration
Services that it was successful when it's done.
>> Now, Rich, I'm not a .NET guy. Can I make sure I got this right?
>> You can. Go for it.
>> So you derive some variables dynamically in the pipeline and
then you're passing that output from variable then back to the
task and you're going to use the task to show it? Did I get that right?
>> You've got that absolutely right.
>> All right.
>> As a matter of fact, would you like me to prove it to you?
>> I would. And this has reminded me of Mouse Trap all over again
[Laughter]
>> Yeah, but you know what I like about this? It's a better mouse trap.
>> Yep.
>> So let's run this.
When we run it you can see the data flow task ran, the script
task is running, here's my results, and, yes, I have values 0
through five, all caps.
[Applause]
I love it when a plan comes together.
>> There you go.
>> All right.
>> You're referencing The A-Team.
>> Yeah, that's the American TV show that has a little bit of
a cult following, shall we say.
All right. So what do you think, George? What's the next thing
on our agenda?
>> We have more mouse trap stuff.
>> We do.
>> Especially with this next line of transformation.
We have fuzzy transforms, and we have a couple of those, and
I know you have some enthusiasm about those.
>> I do.
Although I'm a little unclear on how they work sometimes.
Get it?
>> You're fuzzy on those?
>> Yeah. Hey, I got a groan from the peanut gallery.
I was wondering if they were awake. Now I know they are.
>> They were fuzzy too...
[Laughter]
>> Fuzzy grouping and fuzzy look-up.  Fuzzy grouping is all about taking
records that you're trying to say they have the same logical
entity, they represent the same logical entity, but they were
defined a little bit differently. Maybe... like I'm Rich Currey,
but maybe I'm in a couple of different systems. In System 1
I'm Rich Currey, in System 2 I'm Richard Currey, in System 3
I'm Fred Currey.
In all of those it could be the same person. There are other
values in the record that can contribute to figuring out, oh,
yeah, that is the same one. Maybe it's the same address, the
same phone number, the same city or state, whatever it might be.
So fuzzy grouping is a transform that you can use to take all
of those records that logically represent the same entity even
though they don't have the same values and associate them together.
It does require that you have a SQL Server connection because
it uses temp tables in the connection target to hold intermediate
results and work with the data as it's trying figure it out.
As you might guess, this is not necessarily a processor-free occurrence.
>> Sure.
>> There's a little work going on. So if you're going to use
this, you do... your identity or the identity that's running
the package needs to have the create table permission because
it does... it uses temp tables only.
Now, the fuzzy grouping goes through and it identifies what's
called a lead record. That's the record that has the values that
it identifies as being the right ones and then a matching record,
which contains the values that aren't exact matches but it thinks
match up with that lead record. It returns the key of the lead
record, the key of the matching record. It also gives you an
idea of how close it is by going with a similarity score.
So just because SQL Server thinks they belong together doesn't
necessarily mean that they do, but it certainly gives you an
idea of what happens... of what the possibilities are.
>> All right.
>> The other transform that we've got that works on this kind
of fuzzy logic is called the fuzzy look-up. Now, again, if I've
got data that exists in multiple source systems representing
the same logical entity but with different physical values, then
it's going to be a lot harder to match that data together.
So, again, you do have to have a SQL Server connection, but this
one, instead of providing for temporary tables, is going to provide
the location of the data that you're looking against to try and
find a match.
Now, you have to define one column as your fuzzy column.
You can have more than one, but there has to be at least one.
Those are the columns, when they're identified as fuzzy, that
are going to allow the inexact matching. You can only use string
data types or text data types. You can't use numerics or anything
like that.
>> That makes sense.
>> It does. It really does, because if the numbers are different,
the numbers are different. But if one says 3 Main Street and
one says 30 Main Street, yeah, that could be a typo. It absolutely
could be. So those are the kinds of things we're trying to find.
Now, similarity and confidence are kind of like...
we'll call them lines in the sand.
>> Okay.
>> They provide you the ability to say a match must have values
that are 95 percent similar.
In other words, it's got to have most of the characters the same.
Like 30 Main Street and 3 Main Street, they're pretty similar.
There's a good likelihood, if all the other columns are the same,
that that's a matching value.
Confidence is more of a representation of how confident you are
that they are the same.
If I've got, for example, St.
and Saint, then the values are significantly different.
>> Yeah. Of the list of characters is quite different.
>> Yeah. But when you actually look at the data logically, at
least in English, St. is an abbreviation for the word Saint.
So I have a confidence level that kind of reminds me that, yeah,
I'm pretty happy with this match. It's pretty good.
So let's go take a quick look at a fuzzy look-up and see what
we've got going here.
I've got my virtual machine squared away, and I'm in my fuzzy package.
In my fuzzy package I have an OLEDB source that I've defined
that goes out to demo DW and grabs my customers.
Now, that then acts as an input for fuzzy grouping. Now, fuzzy
grouping requires a connection manager. And guess what?
There's my demo DW. It's going to go out and it is going to look
up and it is going to base...
in the customer table we are going to put an input column of
customer name.
There's an output alias, there's a grouping youth alias, the
match type, and, yes, you can determine exact or inexact.
So if I have some columns, for example, a name column, the names
may be similar, but I want the city, state, and zip to be identical
because I know that it's not a match if they're different.
>> Yeah, then I have a very high degree of match confidence.
>> Exactly. So I can define... for example,
I could put in here my city and define this one as an exact match.
So now my look-up is based on two columns, a fuzzy match on the
name and an exact match on the city.
As I come over, I've got my similarity number. This is where
you define the similarity threshold which is calculated by the
transform and say I need this to be .85,
85 percent similar, in order for that to be defined as a match.
Now, George, have you ever run into a situation where you've
got leading or trailing numbers?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Like on an address, for example.
>> Sure.
>> 123 Main Street versus 456 Main Street.
>> Well, there are times when those numbers are meaningful.
There are other times where they're noise to the matching process.
So in this numerals column I have the ability to configure whether
I want to deal with neither leading nor trailing numbers, just
leading numbers, just trailing numbers, or both.
And then, finally, I have the ability to tell it whether case
sensitivity is important, whether Kana type is important, non-spacing
characters, character width, all that kind of stuff.
>> Lots of control.
>> Okay. Now, again, this is one of those transforms... I don't
have a real database here that's got a lot of differences where
fuzzy is going to make a difference, but this gives you a real
good idea of how the configuration goes.
>> Good.
>> All right. So this module we have spent a lot of time talking
about how you manipulate data as it goes through the data flow pipeline.
We've talked about some of the standard transforms like a derive
column, the look-ups, the merges, we've talked about some of the...
am I missing a whole set?
>> Yeah. We have more. We have more.
>> We have more. I forgot all about that. My goodness. You know,
I looked at the splitter before. We do. Let's go look at the splits.
Splitting the flow. And we've got two transforms that we're going
to be dealing with here...
>> These are useful.
>> They are. And I can't believe I forgot about them.
They're some of my favorites. Multicast which takes the data
flow and duplicates it to multiple destinations, and we've also
got the conditional split.
Conditional split allows me to formulaically determine where
a record is going to go, into which of the output pipelines.
So multicast, like I said, duplication of data, multiple pipelines.
Each pipeline has its own transformations after the duplication occurs.
>> So process some rows...
>> Absolutely....
>> or process one set of rows in the pipeline and I have another
pipeline unprocessed.
>> You could. Absolutely. And you could even, if you had, for
example, sales information that was going to the financial group
and sales information that was going to the sales group, maybe
they have different calculations that need to be applied.
So I do a multicast and then I do the sales calculations to the
sales destination, I do the financial calculations to the financial destination.
>> Good example.
>> The key is that out of that multicast... it's very simple...
you drop the transform in, you connect transforms after the fact.
There's no other configuration required.
The other transform we've got is the conditional split.
This is the one where I can take records from the data flow and
direct them out to different hoses, different pipelines.
>> So divide... sorry.
>> Yeah, divide and conquer.
Exactly. So now maybe let's take that sales example again, but
now I've got sales reps who are in different regions of the world,
and I've got managers that deal with the sales for only that region.
They don't need to see the rest of the world. So I can direct
the sales records to the appropriate pipeline based on the region
that's going to receive them.
>> Good example.
>> So let's flip back over to the virtual machine because what
I'm going to do is I'm going to take this OLEDB source that I've
got here and I am going to now split it. So we're going to come
back up, we are going to grab our conditional split.
I connect the two together. That gives the conditional split
awareness of what it's going to be working with.
>> Upstream metadata.
>> You got it. Now I go into my transformation editor. Now, let
me ask you a question, George.
>> Go ahead.
>> Does this GUI look at all familiar to you?
>> Very familiar scent to me.
>> Absolutely. It is the same GUI that you get for a derived column
because you are building calculations, building expressions.
This is the expression editor. Now, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to come in here and I'm going to grab country and drop
it into my condition, and I'm going to say country equal to,
and we'll say USA.
And the output name is going to be... oh, I have a problem here.
I'm not sure what it is yet.
I'm going to have to look at it. Give me a minute. But the
name we're going to take it US Customers.
Oh, I know
what the... didn't I tell you on the last one? Single equals
versus double equals. So I have done that and I will continue
to do that even when I remember not to do that.
>> No, I thought you were leading us into a brick wall only to
show us the rescue.
>> Oh, no. No, no, no. I literally forgot it.
>> All right.
>> In the expression language in SSIS there are two things you
really need to be aware of. Thing one, it's case sensitive.
If you notice, I drag and drop everything.
>> Please.
>> Thing two, assignment is one equals sign, comparison is two
equals sign. If you keep those in the front of your head, you'll
get it right most times.
So US Customers is country equal to USA.
I'm now going to get all other customers
and my condition here is going to be...
and I was about to type it...
actually, you know what?
Watch. Just to prove my point, and we're going to say not equals USA.
Notice the red?
>> Danger, Will Robinson.
>> You got it. The red indicates I've got a problem. To fix it
I capitalize country, it comes in, it's now fixed. So I have
two outputs. Those two outputs now are going to have US customers
and all other customers. I hit okay.
When I come out of my conditional split >> Perfect....
>> I can now create two destinations, destination 1 flat file...
>> This is the fun part....
>> I click in connect, it asks me which output I want, I choose
my US customers, hit okay, I drop a second flat file destination...
whoops. I grabbed the error. That's not what I wanted.
We will delete that one.
We will grab our second one, and now for that one we will grab
all other customers. And notice it is marked in the GUI so that
you know which one which.
>> Handy.
>> It is.
All right.
Now can we wrap up?
>> Yeah. Now it's wrap-up. We looked at a lot in this module.
>> Yeah, we did. We talked about the transforms, we talked about
building that data pipeline, not just the source and the destination
but rather all of the manipulation of the information that can
occur in between the two. Transforms like the derive column,
like the fuzzy grouping and fuzzy look-up and the conditional
splits, things of that nature. You've got ultimate flexibility
to do the T in the ETL.
>> Excellent. So thanks, everyone, for watching the Implementing
a Data Warehouse with SQL Server 2012 Jump Start. I'm hungry,
and it's time for a meal break, so we'll see you at the top of
the hour. Again, make sure you get up and move around a little
bit, and we'll see you back at the top of the hour.
>> Have one.