[Music]
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Implementing a Data Warehouse with
SQL Server 2012 Jump Start. My name is George Squillace, and
this is my colleague, Rich Currey.
>> Good morning, everyone. How are you? My name is Rich Currey.
I am a senior tech instructor for New Horizons. We deliver training
for SQL Server and a bunch of other things. I have been an implement
every for data warehousing, I've been an instructor here for
the last ten years. I focus in on SQL Server, been doing this
for, oh, way too many years, George. If I told you how many,
well, we'd have a problem. That would make me way too old.
So been there, done that. Hopefully I can help you out over the
course of the day as we talk about data warehousing and away
talk about integration services. George, how about you?
>> And, Rich, I know you're going to have an awful lot to offer
because you're enthusiastic about the topic and also have a great
amount of experience. A little bit of background on myself.
I'm also a long-term tech trainer. Love doing this. Been doing
it for a long time. Been a Microsoft certified trainer since 1997.
Been certified in every version of SQL Server since SQL 2000
and then a final kicker, 96 times in the exam booth.
>> Way too many, George. You've become a professional exam-taker,
I think.
>> Just part of the job.
>> So we're going to be dealing with implementing a data warehouse
today, and some of the things that we're going to be going over
are going to include how to design and implement dimensions and
fact tables, we're going to be talking about not just the technical
aspect but also some of the busy implications that go with it
and what it takes to make sure that you've got a solid design
to base your business analysis and reporting on. Then we're
going to work and start talking about data flows. We're going
to start off with how to extract data, dealing with data sources,
data destinations, connections, the technology about retrieving data.
We're then going to loop in on the next section to the big part,
which is transform. Transformation of data as it goes from your
operational systems to your reporting and data warehousing, your
analysis systems. That's a big part of it to support those dimensions
and fact tables that we build up. Then this afternoon we're
going to go into the workflow portion of things, because data
flow is not the only thing that we deal with. We deal with control.
Control is all about workflow, not just the data flow but the
other pieces that go along with it. After that, no project is
worth its salt unless you can get it out to the production environment.
So we're going to talk about some of the configuration issues,
things like package configurations, like environments, we're
going to talk about logging and event handling, things of that nature.
And, finally, deployment itself, package deployment, project deployment.
Then at the end of the day...
keep you in your seat...
enterprise data.
One of the biggest challenges that faces any large organization
and many small to mid-size organizations as well is the fact
that they consume the same information in multiple databases,
multiple systems.
And one of the challenges is to ensure that that data is the
same on all of those systems, not just for this one but so that
when I bring it together, when I take all those operational sources
and bring them back in so that they hook up in a data warehouse
and can be used together, that they match up correctly and that
they can be effectively analyzed to give the business the information
they need to work forward.
>> It's a full outing here.
>> Oh, yeah. We are going to be busy today. There's no question
about that. Now, some of the things that you're probably going
to want to have for a baseline here, we are going to be talking
about a lot of the basics as well as moving forward. So don't
be intimidated if you're new to data warehousing. We're not
just going to leave you sitting here. This is targeted to folks
who have some background and some understanding and who also
have some baseline experience with SQL Server.
But, I promise, even if you're new to the subject, you're still
going to get a lot of good stuff that you can use to prepare
for the exam. The 70-463
exam, that's what our going to be targeting after this.
Now, some of the supporting material that might help is, of course, 10777.
Did I get all the 7s?
>> You got all the 7s.
Triple 7.
>> Yeah, we're in an area where airlines are big, so triple 7,
you get that one wrong, it can be a problem.
>> That's meaningful around here.
>> Yeah. Okay. So this is Microsoft. So can you guess where we are?
At any rate.
10777 is a five-day class. It's offered by New Horizons, who
we happen to teach for. So if you decide to take that class,
there is a chance, yes, a chance... I know it's hard, but, George,
they might actually get us as an instructor.
>> I'm teaching in two weeks.
>> That would be cool. So that's one spot. George, the other
one, you've got a book there, I think.
>> That's right. You'll notice an MS Press book which is promoted here.
I personally own that book. And, you know, I have to say I've
benefitted a lot from that book, not only the material in it,
but also the
test preparation software that they had.
>> Where can they pick that up, George?
>> At oreilly.com they can pick up that book.
>> O'Reilly's got a lot of great books on SQL Server that can
really help you out. So what do we got coming there, bud?
>> There you go. Module 1.
>> So why don't we get started, designing and implementing dimensions
and fact tables. And what we're going to be talking about here,
we're going to first start off talking about the design issues
on dimensions. Now, there are two approaches you can take.
A star schema and a snowflake schema. And what that does is
it describes how the dimensions relate back to the fact tables.
Now, facts and fact tables are the things that hold the information
that the business is concerned about that measure...
there's a word you're going to hear a lot... that measures the
performance of the organization.
Now, they all took together. And we have to deal with how granularity...
now granularity is a measure of how the dimensions and the facts
relate to each other, how fine a level of detail we've got.
We're also going to be talking about two different kinds of dimensions,
conformed and non-conformed...
let's get that right. Sorry about that... and, finally, time dimensions.
And time dimensions are a real interesting discussion because
they are super critical to the organization, but yet they're
probably the easiest one to generate. And I'll show you a couple
of tricks on how to do those. So let's start off with star schemas
and snowflake schemas. And we've got a couple of topics we're
going to be dealing with here. I'm going to describe the star
schemas, the snowflake schemas, and then we're going to talk
about some of the processing and performance considerations.
So, George, if I talk to you about a star, what do you see?
Well, look at that. What a graphic, huh?
>> Did I give that away too early?
>> Yeah, just a little bit.
That's okay. When you see a star, you think about individual
spokes coming out from a center hub, right? So what we're talking
about here is when we're dealing with dimensions, we're trying
to show, by calling it a star schema, that every dimension is
tied directly to the fact table, the measure table, the one that
contains all the important stuff.
Dimensions give you the ability to qualify your measures, to
add meaning to what that measure is about. So a customer dimension
that's tied to a sales measure would provide meaning to who did
the sale, who bought the product.
Okay? Now, what that means is that every dimension table needs
to have all of the attributes, all of the pieces of information
about that dimension that describe the measure.
All right. We good?
>> Yeah. We're good.
>> All right. Now, star schemas, because we have all of that information
in the table, some of the attributes might have the same value
in many records. For example, if I'm a retailer and I've got
a lot of people buying my product, is it possible that many of
my customers would be in the same city?
>> Sure.
>> The same region?
>> The same country?
>> Sure.
>> So I'm going to have repeating values in that dimension table.
>> Lots of repeated.
>> And that typically is referred to as a denormalized solution.
All right. Now, let's take a look, if we can, at what a star
schema is going to give us. So if we can go over to the virtual
machine for just a minute, what I've done is I've created a database
here called Demo DW. And Demo DW I don't have any tables right now.
So this is where we're going to build an example of a data warehouse.
Now it's going to be pretty basic and I'm not going to put any
data in it. I want to do this to show you the structure.
So the first thing we have here is we have two create table statements.
The top one right here, the create table for product, is going
to build a product dimension. We've got a key value which is
going to be used to relate back to the measures, the fact table.
It is an identity column, which means that we're not pulling
the information from anywhere else. And then we have an alt
key column. The alt key is the business key or the tie back to
the original source system.
And then I add in my attributes. So product name, the description,
the category name.
When I run this script, we now have our table in the Demo DW warehouse.
I have the same kind of setup for my customer table. I've got
the customer key, the customer alt key, and then some descriptors,
the name, the email, and the geography. Now, I'm going to hold
off on that geography key for a minute. I don't want to give
away the ending on this demo.
We've got a couple more here that we're going to build. The salesperson
table, again, all of the attributes that describe the salesperson
and the date table. Now, this is a timetable, so I don't want
to go into too much detail about all the columns, but I want
it in there.
Hmm. It helps if you highlight the whole thing, doesn't it?
>> Yep.
>> Yep. One of the neat things about Management Studio but also
one of the things that can drive you nuts if you do it wrong.
So now I need to put something in the middle, so I'm going to
create a fact table. Now, the fact table ties back to each of
the dimension tables. We've got the product key, the customer
key, the salesperson key, and the order date key. And then we've
got information about the fact itself. An order number, an item
number, a quantity, a sales amount, a cost.
These are the measures, the things that we're interested in.
>> And I see a bunch of references that are also...
>> Oh, yeah. Because you have to tie it back to those dimension tables.
And that's where the product key, customer key, salesperson key,
order date key and then order number/item number are all going
to be a part of the primary key, because each measure is going
to relate to the combination of each of those descriptive records.
So I build my fact table, and now
we have... and this is the cool part. This might help some folks
out there... I'm going to come up here, and right above tables
I've got database diagrams. So let's take a look and see if we
really do have a star.
>> Oh, this is cool when you do this.
>> Yeah. So I hit my new database diagram, we wait for the machine
to catch up, because it does have to do some graphical stuff.
There we go. I'm going to refresh my add table, and there are
the tables I just put in. I highlight them all because I want
them all in, and when I add them in,
there is
my star schema.
Now, hard to see everything here because it's zoomed in pretty good.
I'm going to zoom it out just a little bit so we can see things.
Notice, single tables,
all relating directly back into the fact table.
>> Looks like a star to me.
>> Yeah. So that's what that star schema is all about. Now, that's not...
let's head back to the slides now, because the next thing that
we want to talk about is our snowflake schema.
The snowflake schema is a more normalized solution. So remember
when I was talking about the customers and I mentioned that you
might have multiple customers with the same city, the same region,
the same country?
>> Uh-huh.
>> So in that situation I end up with many records with the same values.
In denormalization, a good practice is to take those values out,
put them in a separate table. Once I do that in a data warehouse,
that's what drives me to a snowflake schema. I now end up with
all of these tables not necessarily connecting directly back
to the measures, to the fact table.
>> I see a mixture now in the diagram.
>> Absolutely. We have some that relate to other dimension tables.
So each table has to have the dimension values, the attributes,
it has to have the key, and it has to have a foreign key value
to relate to the parent dimension, the denormalized dimension
that it is a part of.
>> And I know you have some stuff you want to show us here as
well, Rich.
>> Oh, absolutely. Absolutely. So I have another script here
that's going to create a geography table. The geography table
has a geography key, it has a postal code, a city, a region,
and a country. So when I execute this script, I've now built
a table that no longer relates directly back to a fact table.
>> I see that.
>> Here's the cool part.
When I go into my diagram, I'm going to add the table back in,
and even though I've created it, does it look like it relates
to anything?
>> No, it is free-floating and unrelated.
>> So I need to make that connection. So what I'm going to do
is I'm going grab this geography key
and I need to drop it here on
my salesperson table.
And I make a relationship between the geography key and the geography
table, the geography key and the salesperson, and then I do the
same thing here to my customer table. And now
we have our snowflake. Now, the one thing you need to remember,
George, this is a small encapsulated example to show how those
relating to the. In the real world you're going to end up with
a data warehouse that can have 30 fact tables, that could have
150 or 200 dimension tables depending on how complex the organization
is and how complex the design of the data warehouse is.
>> It can get tangled.
>> So those dimensions, those snowflake and star designs,
that is a big part of determining how efficient your data warehouse
is going to be.
>> It's like a foundation.
>> It is. It is. And the actual choices that you make, you don't
have to go all star, you don't have to go all snowflake.
You can have some dimensions that use a star approach, some dimensions
that use a snowflake approach, and what you end up with is a
hybrid somewhere between the two.
>> So it's just not always tidy.
>> Absolutely. Now, the big thing with that is how you make those
decisions is all about performance.
It's all about dealing with the trade-offs on where you want
to pay the piper, George.
>> Yep.
>> There are advantages to a star schema, there are advantages
to a snowflake.
>> So you're going to take a hit somewhere, perhaps. There are
some processing and performance considerations we want to take
a look at.
>> There absolutely are. There absolutely are. A star schema
is usually going to take a performance hit in what's called the
ETL process, the extract, transform, and load. That's where
you're taking data from your source systems and you're pulling
it through and combining it, transforming it, aggregating it,
whatever it might be, and putting it into the data warehouse.
Your source systems are typically going to be highly denormalized.
So to... sorry, highly normalized. I said that backwards.
It's early in the morning here. No matter where you might be,
it's early here.
So in a highly normalized solution, we need to combine all of
those normalized tables into a single record for the denormalization
of the information.
That's the process that happens during the ETL process, and it
means that there's going to be a large amount of time taken in
large systems. But the flip side is the advantage there is that
because everything is denormalized, when you go to retrieve it
all, all of that information is right in the one record, and
it is available immediately without having to do a lot of joins,
which means your queries, retrieval of information for analysis
is going to go very quick. Now, what do you think that means
for a star schema, George?
>> I'm sorry, I don't know where you're going with that. Tell me.
>> Oh. So if I'm going to have a snow...
sorry, a snowflake schema. I said it backwards. No wonder you
couldn't figure out where I was going. In a snowflake schema
the ETL process is going to take the denormalized... the normalized information...
you know, this is tough to get it all in.
It has the normalized information
brought directly into the data warehouse or at least more closely.
So the ETL process is a lot more efficient. However, on the
back side when you're querying it, there are a lot more joins
in your queries which means that your queries are going to be
a little bit less responsive and are going to take longer to
analyze and retrieve the information you need.
>> A lot of decision-making.
>> It is. It is. And that really is the big part of getting that
design right is understanding where those trade-offs need to
occur and the decision process that goes into them.
>> So you've talked about the dimension tables and dimension design.
Now let's take a look at facts and fact tables.
>> Yeah. We've got facts and fact tables. And as I said earlier,
the fact tables are the tables that hold the measures, the information
that the business uses to measure its performance.
Things like sales, things like
orders or costs, those are the kinds of information that we need.
So we're going to talk about facts and what they are, how to
group them together, and then we're going to go into granularity
and what that's all about.
>> Important.
>> It is. It is. So a fact is basically a piece of information
that's used to measure the business results. I've mentioned
that a couple of times. Sales information, production information,
inventory information. And facts, curiously enough, can be additive,
semi-additive or non-additive.
>> And you have some good examples of those, too.
>> I do, actually. An additive fact is a fact or a measure that
can be summarized across all dimensions. For example, sales.
I can summarize sales along customers, along products, along
time, pretty much however you think about your organization,
you're going to be able to take those individual sales and add
them up and group them together to get an aggregate value.
That would be an additive measure, one that can be aggregated
along all dimensions.
>> Sometimes I've heard the term fully additive in case you ever
hear that out there also.
>> Absolutely. Semi-additive is one where a measure or a fact
is aggregatable along some dimensions but not all. Think, for
example, about inventory.
If I have a lot of warehouses that store my products and they're
in many different regions of the U.S.,
could I take the total values of each of those inventories in
each warehouse and add them up to get a total U.S. value?
>> Definitely.
>> So along geography, at any rate, that could be an additive measure.
But let's look at customers for a minute. If I have customers,
do I have inventory on a per-customer basis, George?
>> No. Those don't match. They don't intersect.
>> No. Inventory belongs to my organization, not to my customers.
So inventory can't be aggregated along that customer dimension.
It is meaningless to a customer. Okay?
>> And there's one more.
>> There is. And that would be the non-additive measure. And a
non-additive measure is typically a calculated measure. So, for
example, a percent profit.
Can I calculate percent profit for each product?
>> Sure.
>> Can I calculate percent product for a product category?
>> Okay. So if I had 5 percent profit on product A, 5 percent
on product B, 5 percent on product C, that would mean if they're
all in the same category I'd have 15 percent for that category, right?
>> No, that's not the way the money people work.
>> Oh, man.
So that means that it wouldn't be summing?
>> Non-additive.
>> There you go. You got it. So any measure that you can add up,
aggregate along all the dimensions, additive. Any measure that
only aggregates on some of the dimensions, semi-additive.
Any measure that you a need to calculate along a dimension at
each level, non-additive.
>> Good summary.
>> Okay.
Now, what have we got next?
>> Next we have grouping facts.
>> All right. So would it make sense, George, if I had two measures,
one of which was additive and one of which was semi-additive,
would they relate to the same group of dimensions?
>> Probably not.
>> No. Because they don't pertain to that dimension.
Inventory is not going to relate to a customer.
So, therefore, can I put them in the same fact table?
>> No.
>> Probably not. Because remember when we talked about that fact
table we said that the fact table needs to have the dimension
keys for all of the dimensions it relates to as part of the primary key.
Well, you can't have null values in a primary key.
Therefore if the two measures don't relate to the same facts,
they're not going to have a fully qualified primary key.
There's going to be some nulls. It means you can't put them in
the same table.
>> Design impact.
>> Absolutely. So one of the grouping considerations is to make
sure that you keep only those facts that have the same key relationships,
the same dimension relationships, together in a single table.
But that's not the only consideration, because also you may have
fully additive measures that some parts of the business use but
not other parts of the business. They just don't bother with them.
So sometimes it may make sense to create multiple fact tables
based on business needs so that measures that are common to a
part of the business are grouped together and easily available,
other measures that aren't something that they're concerned with
don't show up.
The last thing that we're going to deal with here is granularity,
because facts that don't make sense all the way up and down the
dimension, they're not going to be keyed the same either because
they're going to have different granularity.
Granularity refers to the level of detail that a fact has.
For example, it may not relate to an individual customer, it
may relate only to the collection of customers at the city level.
So that fact doesn't have that level of detail.
Maybe it is at the product category level rather than at the
product level.
Granularity is how detailed that information is.
>> So different parts of the organization might want to analyze
differently and that's going to impact my design.
>> You know, it's not even so much different parts of the organization
as it is the level of detail that the fact is available with
as well.
>> Part of the source.
>> It truly is. So some information may not be available at that
fine level of detail, some of it might not be, as you said, George,
interesting at that fine level of detail.
>> Sure.
>> So what have we got next there, my friend?
>> So design considerations. You've laid a lot of things on the
table here that impact design. Go ahead and tell us a bit more
about those.
>> Summarizing them right up, fact tables, we need to have all
of the keys to every dimension that it relates to. If it doesn't
relate to the dimension, then it can't be in that fact table.
And the primary key needs to be a composite key for all of those
dimension keys.
And like I said, semi-additive, additive, non-additive, they
all have different impacts. They should all be keyed different.
>> All right. And then next up you have some more to talk about
as far as fact and dimension granularity.
>> Yeah. We need to get into just a little bit more detail on
how this goes. And this is really talking about that how we figure
out what that granularity is and what that dimension granularity
talks about. Now, granularity, again, as you alluded to, George,
it's not just based on business needs, it's not just based on
the level of availability of the information, but it should be
driven by the business needs. If you've got order detail down
to the second, do I need to put order detail down to the second
into a data warehouse?
>> Probably not that level of detail.
>> No. Because are we ever going to look at how much did I sell
at 1933?
>> No.
>> No. How much did I sell at 742?
>> Usually we only go down to the day, maybe for some organizations
to the hour. For an online retailer that's doing global sales,
having that hourly information might be helpful for their business analysis.
But that's the key is this is all driven by business needs.
Don't ever load into a data warehouse more detail than you need.
Your data warehouse is going to be so big anyway that it doesn't
make sense to clutter it up with a lot of extra information.
>> So that's fact granularity. What about dimension granularity?
>> Well, again, just like with facts, why load more detail than
you need? If the lowest level of detail that you're ever going
to need in time is the day level, don't build a timetable that
is down to the hour or to the minute. If you need that level
of detail, then, yes, you have to create the dimension table
down to that level of granularity. But just like with facts,
it all ties together. You don't need to drive facts lower than
they need to be analyzed, you don't need to drive dimensions
lower than the facts need to separate.
>> And I know you have a few specific things you wanted to mention,
some dimension-specific design aspects.
>> Yeah. We've got this thing, it's called conformed and non-conformed dimensions.
And along with that we've got shared dimensions and degenerate
dimensions, and, oh, yeah, last and certainly not least, a slowly
changing dimension.
So let's start out with conformed and non-conformed. A conformed
dimension is a dimension that is shared by multiple fact tables,
and there's only one version of it. So there's one definition
for what a product dimension has for attributes. There's one
definition for what a customer dimension has. There's one dimension
for what the financial dimension has. A single categorization
that all aspects of the business access.
A non-conformed dimension is when we have a dimension where part
of the business uses only some of the attributes, another part
of the business uses a different subset of the attributes.
There might be crossover, but when you look at the dimension,
there's really two definitions of what that dimension needs to
have depending on who uses it. So the dimension tables are designed...
you might have two of them... for example, a manufacturing product
dimension and a sales product dimension... where each one has
a different set of attributes.
So you separate them out and show each one the way it needs to be.
>> And it looks like you have some stuff that you want to show
us about these.
>> Oh, yeah. We've got a demo coming up here. So what I've done,
if we can get over to... there we go. Let's see if pick actually
get it up there. We have the script. So what I've done here
is I've actually got two dimensions. I've got a manufacturing
product dimension which has a product ID, a name, a parent item,
a standard cost, and a color.
And then I've got a sales product where the product ID and the
name cross over. They're in both dimensions. But sales isn't
quite as worried about the parent item or the standard cost or
the color. They're more interested in the list price and in the category.
So when I build these two, I now have two different product dimensions...
oh, I already made the top one, huh?
>> Yeah, there you go.
>> That's what happens. I ran it twice. Sorry about that.
I must have clicked twice. Do my tables in there? Let's take
a look.
There they go. Okay. So I've got
>> Oh, you're in DQS main.
>> Always helps if you're in the right database. Thanks for that, George.
>> Oh, you're a great second pair of eyes.
>> All right. So there's any two dimensions. They are non-conformed
dimensions because they both deal with the same entity, a product,
but they have different attribute definitions.
When I create my fact table... ask here's a very simple one with
product ID and sales quantity... now both of those dimensions
relate in.
The flip side of that, the conformed dimension is when I would
create the single product dimension that has a product ID and
a name, the same as both of the manufacturing and sales product,
and then takes the full list of both attributes, parent item,
standard cost, color,
and the sales attributes, list price and category.
So conformed and non-conformed. I forgot. I already have a product
in there, so...
>> Yeah, we get the point.
>> But the script is there. Cool?
>> Very cool. So there were some other dimension designs that
you want to talk about too.
>> Yeah. And this is as much a qualification of terminology as
anything else, and it is something that you need to know because
these are terms that are very commonly used. And you're going
to run into them in a lot of different places so I highly recommend
that you get comfortable with shared and degenerate dimensions.
A shared dimension is a dimension that is used by multiple facts,
multiple measures, it's stored in...
sorry, it is stored
in the dimension table
and connected right in. The dimension value is... sorry, the
key is in the fact table. The values themselves are in the dimension
table along with the other attributes of that dimension.
It's when it's used by multiple measures in multiple scenarios.
>> There you go.
>> A degenerate dimension is one where the attribute that you're
interested in really is a very specifically used attribute.
It only applies to a single thing and doesn't make sense to be
having its own dimension table, its own key. It's only used
in a limited scenario. So you store it directly in the fact table
rather than creating that dimension table to support it. So shared
dimension has its on dimension table keyed back. Degenerate dimensions,
stored directly in the table.
Now, a slowly changing dimension, this is one that you're going
to run into a lot. A slowly changing dimension is a dimension
where the attribute values of the dimension change over time.
They are retained
if the attributes are updated. So, for example, if a customer
lives in Connecticut...
I happen to live in Connecticut so >> No
wonder you brought that up.
>> Yeah. You know, it's nice to give a plus for the hometown.
>> There you go.
>> If a customer is in Connecticut and then they move to, for
example, Seattle,
their history, what they bought when they were in Connecticut,
says Connecticut.
What they're going to buy in the future is going to be from Seattle.
It's important to understand what your choices are when you're
dealing with the fact that that same customer now has two different
sets of information describing where they are. At some points
they're in Connecticut, at other points they're in Seattle.
A slowly changing dimension is one where that is tracked.
So I've got a tie to the records
when they happened in Connecticut, a tie when they happened in Seattle.
Now, the cool part of the slowly changing dimension is you've
got three choices in dealing with it. You cannot retain the history.
If you don't retain the history, then anything I did when I lived
in Connecticut is going to look like it happened when I was in Seattle.
That's a great thing to do when you're trying to use history
to forecast future behavior.
I'm in Seattle. So everything I did in Connecticut needs to look
as if it happened in Seattle so that it projects what my behavior
might be in the future.
A Type 2 dimension, the attribute change creates a new record.
So now I've got both records in the data warehouse. I've got
the original that says I was in Connecticut, I've got the new
one that says I was in Seattle, and I now have a choice in how
I'm using that data in business analysis. I can look at it from
a historical perspective as if it occurred in Connecticut, I
can look at it from a forecasting perspective as if it happened
when I was in Seattle. A Type 3 slowly changing dimension, the
original attribute value is recorded in the record and the latest
attribute value is recorded with an effective date. So there's
only one record, but it's got an original, a current, and an
effective date so that you can tell when they moved from Connecticut
to Seattle.
>> And you have some things you want to show us about SCDs.
>> I do. I do. I do. So I've got... and this is a real basic
script because this really does illustrate how easy it is to
go down the road. I take my dimension table, in this case I'm
saying dim customer, and I add in an effective date.
Now, if it's a Type 3 not only am I going to add in an effective
date, I'm also going to alter the table, dim customer...
did I type it right? Of course not.
And I'm going to add in...
I've got to look at what I've got for customer columns in here
real quick.
I've got my customer key, I've got my customer name, customer email.
I'm going to add in old email as... and we're going to make
this the same,
a and now by doing those two alters, George, I end up with a
Type 3 slowly changing dimension where I'm recording their previous
email address, I've got a record of their current email address
and the date that it flipped between the two.
Okay?
>> So moving next, we have a consideration for time dimensions,
and there are some things that you wanted to talk about specific
to time dimensions as they need some special treatment.
>> Time dimensions, yes, time dimensions are kind of cool because
time dimensions categorize the when things happened.
>> So that matters pretty much for every analysis project, right?
>> Sure. What's the most common thing, common question that you
hear about any kind of business analysis? Are we doing better
now than we were a year ago? Have we improved over the last six months?
Are we getting better or are we getting worse? Those are the
kinds of questions. And the time dimension is what puts things
in perspective, qualifies them so that you can do those kinds
of analyses.
Now, we've got several different kinds of time dimensions.
We've got time dimensions... and I need to back up here.
>> All right.
>> I need to back up a little bit here, because I'm using the
term dimension, and really and truly I should be using the term hierarchy.
>> Got it.
>> A dimension is a table that qualifies all of the descriptive
attributes about your measures.
A hierarchy establishes the relationships
between those attributes.
Now, I flipped a little bit outside of the data warehouse into
a little bit of terminology that's more appropriate to analysis
services because that's where those hierarchies really come into play.
But the problem is is that you have to take that into consideration
when you're building your time dimension.
>> Absolutely.
>> A hierarchy is the relationship between different levels in
a dimension. So, for example, calendar year, calendar semester,
calendar quarter, calendar month, calendar week, calendar day,
those are all parts of a calendar hierarchy.
But do all companies run on the same calendar, George?
>> Absolutely not.
>> So some companies are going to have a fiscal year that starts
at a different time than other companies and may not start at
the same time as a calendar year does.
>> Nope.
>> Many companies have a fiscal year that runs July 1st to June 30th.
You've got to be able to represent that.
>> So I have to know ahead of time what I want to analyze and
how and then I back load, so to say, or design my warehouse in
view of that.
>> Absolutely. You create the attributes of the time dimension.
And typically they're artificially created.
They are generated.
Rather than coming from the business systems, it is a generated
table that drives the qualifications of all of that information.
Okay? So I need to have a way to relate an individual date to
the calendar quarter it's in, the fiscal quarter it's in, the
fiscal month, the calendar month, the week number of year, whatever
it might be.
>> You don't want to have to calculate all that, do you?
>> It's actually not that bad.
>> Yeah, because you have some tricks, Rich. I know that.
>> Oh, yeah, I do have some tricks.
But you need to, again, worry about those hierarchies, about
designing them and building the dimension to support them.
So let's go over and take a look real quick at a couple of things.
We are going to, first off, bring up a spreadsheet.
>> Looks like something I'm familiar with.
>> Yeah. A lot of people are. But you might be thinking why is
he bringing up an Excel spreadsheet in an SSIS data warehousing class?
>> Well, let's see.
>> This is actually one of the simplest ways that there is to
generate a timetable.
And what I've got here is an example of a timetable, or the beginnings
of one,
that is driven off of a date column.
>> I see a couple dates there.
>> Yeah. We've got January 1st, 2005, January 2nd, 2005.
I use that date to calculate, using standard Excel formulas,
a date key.
I extract the year out of it, the quarter, the month.
I get the month name, the day of month, day of neek... neek.
Wow. That was good.
First day with the new mouth.
>> There you go.
>> The day of week, the day name, a fiscal year, a fiscal quarter.
And as long as you can calculate it, you could add another column
and put it together. Now, here's the cool part.
I'm going to highlight those two ranges. Do you want me to generate
an entire month's worth of information?
>> Let's go.
>> All right.
Auto fill.
And I can go down as far as I want, and if I keep going there
and drag it down a couple of thousand rows, now all I have to
do is import it into my data warehouse using SSIS.
>> A simple CSV out of Excel and you're in.
>> Absolutely. But you know what? It is not the only way to do that.
So let's see if I can close this down without closing the entire
virtual machine.
That's going to be my challenge today, clicking on the right
x's without closing things off.
>> Lots of x's.
>> Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah.
I'm a data warehousing guy. I am not the technology guy.
And we're waiting for things to go. There we go. So I'm back
in here. You can do the same thing in a SQL Server script.
So what I've got here is a very basic timetable that's going
to insert into the dim date table the values that are driven
from a loop that starts at date 1 and ends at date 2. The starting
date for this loop, January 1st, 2005, the end date, get date,
which would be today.
>> And it looks like I can put in any date there.
>> You could. You could generate any range you want. And then
it's going to go out and it's going to manipulate using the date
functions to grab the year, the date part, the month, the date
name, the day, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. Again, if you
can calculate it, you can use it as a part of that solution.
So I execute this.
Of course, you can't just highlight one word.
>> You're in DQS main. There you go.
>> No, I was in the right one on this one.
>> Oh, you were? Okay.
>> Yeah. I had the use statement in there that time.
>> Okay.
>> Just because I forgot to put it in one script doesn't mean
I do it all the time, George. Give me some credit here.
>> All right. All right.
>> All right. So there you go. We can now go out, we can grab
and retrieve our date records from the dim date table and you
can see that we now have a date table that is fully qualified
that we can use to determine what bucket at any particular level
a fact or a measure occurs in.
>> Excellent.
>> So one of the things... and somebody actually put this in for
a question real quick. So I want to address it because it's a
pretty good question. It came in on chat, and they were asking
about whether fact tables, dimension tables and cubes can be
imported to SQL 2012 from earlier versions.
And real simple, it's a very quick and easy answer.
Yes. SQL 2000 and 8 tables are completely compatible in SQL 2012
so they come right in, everything's good to go. Cubes that were
built in Analysis Services 2008 can be brought into SQL 2012,
to Analyze Services 2012 as well. So we spent this module talking
about facts, about dimensions, about how they relate to each
other, the schemas, the design issues that you've got to deal with.
That really sets the foundation for the rest of the day, because
all of that data warehousing design, George, drives what our
ETL process is going to look like, our extract, transform and
load, bringing data from a production system into our data warehousing system.
>> And you're leading us into the next segment here, but for now
we're going to take a short break. Thanks for attending the
Implementing a Data Warehouse with SQL Server 2012 Jump Start.
Next up, data flow. We'll see you in about 10 minutes.
>> See you in a few.
>> Get up, move around, stretch, and we'll see you in a bit.