[Music]
Welcome back after a brief
stretch to implementing a Data Warehouse with SQL Server 2012
Jump Start. I'm George Squillace and here we have a Rich Currey.
>> Howdy, howdy. Guess what George? We are getting close to the
end of development time.
>> We are. We are. And there's only a couple of things left that
we need to talk about. We need to talk about configuration and
we need to talk about deployment.
And that's where we are headed. But before you could actually
do deployment you better make sure that your set up for production,
that you have troubleshot the package to make sure everything
is there, and that you configure it so that if something happens
down the road you have the ability to check it out. We need
to be able to do debugging, we need to be able to set up logging,
and event handlers, and only George, after that's all done, then
we actually do our deployment.
>> So first up, troubleshooting.
>> And troubleshooting, folks, is as much an art form as it is
an approach.
>> Well put.
>> Troubleshooting is about being the person who can't quit, the
one who never gives up until they understand and are able to
fix whatever it was that just went wrong.
You've got to be able to think out-of-the-box, you've got to
be able to be imaginative because many times the problems that
occur are not issues with a package, per se, but are issues due
to the environment supporting the package breaking down.
Maybe files that haven't been put where they're supposed to,
maybe invalid values set for parameters and things like that.
>> There's a lot of moving parts here.
>> Oh, yeah. There are a ton of them. So we really want to talk
about in here what troubleshooting in SSIS is all about as well
as the different approaches that are available.
Now in SSIS, when we are trying to figure out what problems have
occurred, that's what troubleshooting is all about. It's about
package execution and whether or not or something has executed successfully.
If something does go wrong we might need to figure out where
execution paths are pointing, we might need to find out what
variable values are at the time it failed, we might want to go
out and find out what events have transpired during the execution
process, and we may even want to just know was it successful
or was it not successful?
Now the approach that you use there are a couple.
>> I like that word approach.
>> And that's what it is. It's an approach.
It is a way that you deal with problems. Now that doesn't mean
that it's
all about how you deal with it, you also have to set yourself
up to be able to deal with it by setting up things like logging
and event handlers to be able to track through what's happening
as your package executes. But debugging is an interactive process
of monitoring things as it's running. You might want to be able
to pause a package as it's executing when it gets to a certain
point in its execution.
I want to stop it when it goes to look at that directory to grab
a file and see what that file value is.
You may want to watch the execution as it goes through step-by-step
and see what kinds of progress it's making.
You may want to examine what certain variable values are like
maybe, I don't know, the execution time, the username, if you're
debugging a security issue- >> Oh,
all kinds of things.
>> All kinds of stuff. Even programmed user variables and what
they have at the time. And here's the cool part George- >> What's
that?
>> You can even modify the values in the middle of execution to
see if that really does fix the problem.
>> Oh, you don't want to steal thunder for later though.
>> Okay.
>> I know we have some things to show.
>> Okay. We'll wait.
Now here's the other piece of this, data flows are not executions,
they're data flows. It's data going from point A to point B and
going through the pipeline. A control flow is an executable.
A data flow or the pieces inside the data flow, I should say,
are not executables themselves.
I may want to examine the records as they go from one transform
to the next, and I have the ability to set up what are called
Data Viewers to do that.
We also have the ability to configure logging. Logging is an
ability to record the messages that are being generated by the
execution as they occur and put them out somewhere so that they
can be viewed later on. We also have the ability to configure
Event Handlers. Remember I talked earlier about that On Error
Event George?
>> Yeah, I do.
>> Okay. So On Error is just a single event.
There are lots of other events that we can also configure it
to do the same thing.
Now, let us go and now we are going to delve into debugging.
What do you think?
>> Sounds good.
>> All right. So debugging itself, there are really a couple of
pieces here. We've got breakpoints which can be used to pause
execution, we've got watches which can be used to examine variables,
and we've got Data Viewers which are used to examine the data
flow in between transforms.
Now a breakpoint, as I mentioned, is an indication that when
I get to this specific task I want execution to kind of go okay,
hey Rich I'm here. Hang out here for a minute. And Rich goes
okay, I'll tell you when to continue.
It pauses it. It gives me a chance to see what's going on before
I get to that next step in the process.
>> And this sounds more like a development time activity than
a runtime activity.
>> Absolutely. You really do not want to have breakpoints kicking
in in a production package.
>> Ah, no.
>> And actually once you get into the server they're not going
to anyway. As long as you're in Data Tools that's when those
breakpoints will be effective. You can set a breakpoint on any
container, any control flow task in a container, you can configure
it to stop every time it gets there, you can configure it to
stop on a multiple of times that it gets there, so like every
5th or every 10th or every 25th, you could even set it where
it's going to stop only after it gets to the 100th
time that it got there.
Okay?
>> A ton of control.
>> Yeah, it is. It's very, very fine grained control.
Now a watch, no it's not something that you tell time with, although
that works too; a watch, okay it's getting late George. I'm sorry.
I tried for the good joke, but apparently it didn't work.
>> Shhh.
>> You should have seen the looks from the peanut gallery in the
room on that one. My apologies everyone.
So a watch is the ability to put a window up in SQL Server Data
Tools that is going to continuously display the value of a variable
and notify you if that variable changes by highlighting the value
in red.
I can set up watches for any variable defined that is currently
in the scope. Here's that word again.
>> Yep. And I see both users and system variables listed here.
>> Absolutely because it's not just user variables that you may
be interested in the value. You may have functionality that's
dependent on specific variable values for system variables as well.
Now the Watch Window is only for requested variables that are
currently in the scope. The Locals Window will display all variables
that are currently in the scope.
Now the last thing that we really want to talk about in here
about examining what's going on is how to delve into the process
that's occurring within the inside of a data flow. I can set
a breakpoint on a data flow task, but that then is going to break
when it gets to the task. I can't interrupt it. I can't set
breakpoints on the individual transformations within a data flow task.
The only methodology that I've got, the only technology available
to do it in there is what's called a Data Viewer. Now some of
you who used SSIS in earlier versions- >> Insert
sighs and cries.
>> Yeah. This is one that I personally was kind of disappointed.
It was cool but the reality is I never used it.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Not for real. You had the ability to set up histograms; you
had the ability to set up three or four different ways to look
at the- >> Scattered
plots.
>> Data. Now a Data Viewer is just that. It shows you the data.
Data Viewers do interrupt the data flow. So if you have a Data
Viewer that's in between two transforms when the data goes through
that pipeline it's going to be displayed, the first X number
of records, you can configure that, and then it's going to stop,
and it's going to wait for you to say okay, continue on and show
me the rest.
Now you can also disconnect the Data Viewer so that once it's
captured that block of records you disconnect it. The data flow
then picks up and continues. You can continue to look at the
records that it captured at the same time. Now those are copies
of records.
>> Yes.
>> They are not extracted from the data flow.
Okay? So let's go and take a look at debugging a package.
And in my Virtual Machine here I've got a couple of tasks.
I've got a Copy Source File, I've got a Load Data, and I've got
a Delete Copied File.
The Copy Source File task, I'm going to right-click on it and
when I get to the right-click I've got Edit Breakpoints. If I
go to the breakpoints notice it's now displaying a list of the
events that can happen to that particular task. Okay? Now I'm
going to give you a little preview here real quick.
>> There you go.
>> This is also going to play a part in my Event Handlers.
>> Aha.
>> Uh-huh.
So I now choose which of the events that I want it to stop on.
If I choose, for example, a Pre-execute then it's going to stop
prior to that event actually, before anything else happens to
that container.
>> Can I ask a favor? Will you widen that dialog box just a little bit?
>> I can.
>> There you go. Perfect. All right, thanks. I don't want to
interrupt you any further.
>> You were giving away my thunder.
>> Oh, bad, bad, bad.
>> I wanted to leave that hidden so we didn't distract everybody.
>> Mayday.
>> Oh, well. So, I can set up multiple events; so I could pause
this prior to it running and after it has run by setting a break
on both Pre-execute and Post-execute.
>> There you go.
>> So now I can look at the status of variables or things like
that before it runs and then again after it runs to see what
kind of effect there was during execution.
I also can set my Hit Count Type. The Hit Count Type always,
again Hit Count Equals, stop it on the third time it hits, Hit
Count Greater Than Or Equal To every time above five or Hit Count
Multiple Every Other. So every second one depending on and if
I choose, for example, Hit Count Equals then I can choose the
value I want to hit it on the third time through- >> There
you go.
>> I'm going to leave the other one on Always.
So now- >> And
there's the red symbol.
>> Yes sir. That little red symbol tells me I've got a breakpoint.
There's no X in it so it's not a configuration issue.
>> Nope.
>> So now I start my debugging and what happens?
I've got an error.
>> Error.
>> I've got a red X and I've got my breakpoint. Notice how there's
a yellow arrow there.
>> I see.
>> Okay? Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to scroll down.
I apologize because of display incompatibilities. I can't show
you a whole window at once but- >> Oh,
this works.
>> You can now see my Watch Window. I've got a Watch Window on
the Copied File and it shows me the value so I can examine to
see what kind of, what the name and path of the file is that
it's going to go and grab.
If I go to the Locals Window you can see I've got variables,
duration, status, execution result; if I expand variables now
I can see all of my variables, both user and system.
If I wanted to create a watch on a variable that I haven't put
in there already I can right-click on it and Add Watch and it
now shows up in there as well.
>> I see it.
>> You like that?
>> I like it.
>> All right. Once we've gotten through and we've been able to
evaluate, oh, you know what George? I forgot one important thing.
>> What's that?
>> I want to change the value.
>> Aha. That's right. You mentioned that.
>> Yeah. So I'm going to come down here
and notice you can click in there.
What happened?
>> It's now red.
>> Notifying me that the value has been modified. Cool?
>> Cool.
>> All right. I'm going to come back up to the top; I'm going
to stop debugging. You can do that at any time because I don't
want to keep right on trucking through here. What I'm going
to do next is removed this breakpoint, okay? So I'm going to
go to Edit Breakpoints and uncheck the Enabled
and now I'm going to go into Load Data because here I have a transform.
Now again, I can't set a breakpoint here, but what I can do is
right-click and Enable Data Viewer. I get my little magnifying
glass to tell me that there is a Data Viewer there, and now when
I go to run it hopefully it gets to that point.
No, I have an error. Where's my error? I actually do have an error.
>> I think you forgot an extension on the Products File when you
renamed it.
>> Well, you know what? I'm going to show you a little trick here.
>> All right.
>> I changed that during execution and not a variable value so
I'm not sure that that's going to do it, but that's go to Progress-
>> Perfect troubleshooting tip.
>> Oh. Remember I talked about viewing execution progress?
Here it is. You go to the Progress tab while you're in there
and it shows you everything that's happened, and there's my red
X on task Copy Source File failed. Right above it is telling
me, could not find Mod6products.text.
So I think what I'm going to do is just very quickly go out of
here and see if there is a Mod6,
Demo Files Mod6, and I don't. I've got Product CSV.
>> Well, that matters.
>> It does. It does, it does, it does. So let's change this to TXT.
Yes, I'm going to change it. And now we'll come back.
We will stop debugging. We will execute one more time.
We've got our Progress up. Hey, what just popped up with George?
>> Data Viewer.
>> You got it. So I have the ability to view what's going in between
my packages. When I go to the data flow you can see with a visual
indicator of which task is waiting.
If I detach
the flow then continues.
I'm not going to worry about the error. You've seen what I wanted
you to see.
>> That wasn't the point.
>> No. It wasn't. And my Data Viewer shows me what has been going
down the pipeline.
>> Bravo, bravo.
>> Bellissimo. And no. I'm not Italian.
>> Right.
>> I don't know where that came from actually.
>> Maybe it's catchy.
>> I don't know. All right. Let's head back to the slide deck.
What do you think George?
>> Excellent. So next up, logging. Record keeping.
>> Logging. So you saw the Progress tab there right?
>> Yep.
>> And one of the things that I might be interested in doing is
taking all those messages that are showing up in the Progress
tab and writing them out somewhere where they can be reviewed
at a later time. And that, ladies and gentlemen, is what logging
is all about.
>> I like to think of SSIS as a very detailed record keeper.
>> If you wanted to. Yeah, you can generate gigabytes of log files
very quickly in an active SSIS implementation and you generate them.
You got to read them at some point.
>> Yeah.
>> So one of the things that I kind of recommend is that you only
generate logging for the information that really crucial otherwise
you're going to end up with a management process that requires
a lot of attention to detail to make sure that you're saving
an appropriate amount of logs, that you're not filling up disk
files and all that kind of stuff. So logging, again, is the
process of persisting the details of a package,
execution, all that stuff that we saw in the Progress tab is
what's going to show up in the logs.
You have the ability to determine using logs, when a package
failed, why it failed, it can put error messages in, there are
all sorts of things that logging can help with.
>> Very powerful.
>> And it is very, very much a tool to help you troubleshoot.
Now the first thing you need to understand about logging is events.
Now I've mentioned those a bunch of times, right?
>> You have. I'm Pre-execute, on Post Execute, on Error.
>> Yeah. And those are all things that happened during the course
of a package execution.
It has to execute, it has to do things before it executes to
configure, it has to do things after it's executing, post execute,
an error can happen, there are error information messages, warning
messages, error messages, all of those things are things that
occurred during the course of an execution, and each of them
has properties when they happen. The information about that
event, maybe the time of occurrence, maybe how long it took,
there are all sorts of different things. Those are the properties
that expose the information to the developer to make it accessible
to determine what's going on. Now some properties have events,
sorry, excuse me, let's back up here. Some events have Property
Set A, some events might have Property Set B, each event may
have a different set of properties, each event may have some
properties in common with all others.
>> Sure.
>> It really does depend on what events are available before you
can, sorry, what properties are available for an event as to
what kind of information is accessible.
>> Yeah. So like a data flow task has lots of pipeline related
events that don't apply to any of the other tasks.
>> Absolutely. Because let's face it, a file system task doesn't
have a pipeline.
>> There you go.
>> That's the one. So any time that you are going to configure
logging you need to have somewhere to put the messages. And that's
what a Log Provider does. It is a destination for the information
being generated by the logging configuration.
Now because it's a destination it is a data destination, and
we learned earlier that all data destinations require- >> A
Connection Manager.
>> That would be correct. Now Connection Managers can be Event
Logs, it can write to the Windows Application Event Log, not
really what I would recommend for two reasons, number one, the
Application Event Log is visible to anybody that can get on the
machine, and number two, the Application Event Log is space constrained
which means you're going to lose a lot of the messages that get
written in there if you don't archive them off on a relatively
frequent basis.
You can go to an XML file, a text file, you can even write to
them to SQL Server if you want George, if you want to put them
into a table.
>> There you go.
>> That would make them queriable later, but again, be careful.
I would not recommend using a SQL Server connection that's to
a production instance. You might want to have some sort of a
management instance set up.
We learned about those on Wednesday, didn't we?
>> Yep.
>> Management Data Warehouse; that's a great spot in a centralized
environment to put something like that. And then finally, you
have a SQL Server Profiler destination which would send the messages
to a profiler trace.
To configure and set up logging you first figure out which of
the executables in the package that you are interested in seeing
the messages on- >> So
I don't want to log every activity. I do want to log on every executable.
>> No. I would not. I would only configure logging for the executables
that contain what I called mission-critical steps- >> There
you go.
>> Things that absolutely you have to capture and must be successful.
Then you configure the Log Provider or providers.
And this is cool because you can set up multiple Log Providers
for a package and to take all of the messages from one executable
to one Log Provider and all of the messages from other executables
to a different one. You're not restricted to one log per package.
Then you choose the events for each executable that you want
to configure and choose the information for each event that you
want to save.
>> And you're going to show us this now Rich, and you have something,
a clever way of explaining this. I find that students can get
confused by the user interface here, but you have a great tip.
So I don't want to say any more.
>> I do. But I got to tell you, you're kind of telling me what
to do here, George.
>> Am I?
>> All right. So let's go in. I'm going to close out of that previous
demo that I had going.
Come on. Too many flash-up menus there.
Yeah, I do. So now we are going to go in and look at our logging
demo, and in our logging demo I have a package appropriately
named the Logging Demo. And again, it has our Copy Source File,
it has our Load Data, it has our Delete Copied File.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to go up here to the SSIS
menu because that's where you start for configuring logging.
Once I've got it configured, George, if you look at those checkboxes
what you see?
>> I see an empty white checkbox- >> Yup.
>> Some gray background check boxes that are checked.
>> Okay. So if I told you that I can turn on and off checking,
logging, by just checking that box that's pretty cool, huh?
>> Pretty cool, pretty straightforward.
>> But gray kind of tells me it's not available for configuration, right?
>> It's something in the middle.
>> Okay. But it's got a check.
>> It does.
>> So what it's trying to tell me there, anytime you see a grayed
out selection with the check in it means it's inheriting its
settings from its parent.
So I've got my logging demo and each of these executables is
going to inherit the logging configuration of the parent, the
same events, the same properties of the events, the same log
provider destinations.
>> Got it.
>> So I'm going to, first off, the first thing we need to do is
set up our Log Provider. So I'm going to add in a Text File Log Provider.
It requires a configuration which is a Connection Manager.
I'm going to give it a Create File and then we just choose where
it's going to go. I'm going to put it up here on the desktop
and I'm going to give it a name,
Logging Demo.log.
>> Boy, that was rocket science, wasn't it?
>> At any rate,
now before it will actually, right there I need to say yes, I
want you to use this one. Because remember I said we can have
multiple providers and you can choose which one is going to.
So I check off my Log Provider, now I can go over to Details
and it shows me all of the errors, all of the errors, yeah right,
all of the events that are available to be configured for this
executable which is the package. And you can see we've got a
lot of them.
>> Lot of them.
>> Now, not every event is going to fire for every executable
in the package, but yet every event is listed.
What happens is if the event is not your main to the executable
that's currently running it will not log because the event will
never happen. So it's not a problem that they're all there, they'll
only fire for the ones that it makes sense to. So I can choose
my On Post Execute, On Pre-execute, On Progress
and we can now go over to the details.
And in the Details I can go to my advanced page which then opens
up all of the properties on each of the events.
>> Ton of columns.
>> There are, there are. And you can look. All of the properties
for the events that I've selected have been checked already.
So the default value is to be able to get all of the properties
for the event that selected. I can deselect for that particular
one because I don't care about the execution ID or the source
ID, and now when I hit my okay button it will save that.
>> But George, there's more.
>> There is because now by clicking on the checkbox for the individual
executable I've now separated it from the configuration of its parent.
When I check it, it now gives me the ability to configure a different
set of events for that executable than the one that's configured
for everything else.
And additionally, I can add in Log Providers but only at the parents.
At the child level I only have the ability to select which Log
Provider I want the messages to go to. Okay? Cool?
>> Cool.
>> All right. I'm going to go back to my parent configuration.
Let's run this.
As I run it you can see my Copy Source File failed just like
it did in the old one, so I am now going to go out to my desktop,
if I can get there eventually, I have a few windows open, and
there's my Logging Demo.log. I'm going to open it with Notepad,
and there are all of my messages.
>> On Progress, on Information-
>> On Blitzen, on Prancer, on Dancer.
>> Tag, you're it.
>> It is Friday afternoon, isn't it folks?
So all of those events you can see just by looking at this.
If you're not careful about what you configure to go into your
log you're going to be digging through a lot of extraneous information.
We've got GUI IDs, we got repeating messages, we've got a very,
very a wide
series of information and that's just on one execution.
>> Yeah.
>> Imagine if you had three weeks' worth of 10 times a day execution
and you needed to find something specific.
>> Exactly.
>> So logging. That's what it's all about.
>> And I've seen some take the logging data and then build SSRS
reports off the log data. So you can be very clever with this
if you really need it.
>> Oh, absolutely.
Absolutely. That does require though, George, if you're going
to build the SSRS reports you probably want to put it into a database.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Let's go and talk about our next topic.
>> Next up, Event Handlers.
>> Oh. So we are going to go right on with this event theme are we?
Event Handlers.
An Event Handler is very simply, a workflow, a control flow that
executes in response to one of those events occurring. So instead
of writing a log message out I can actually react to and execute
functionality and maybe a control flow or a data flow to move
data around in response to that event. That's what an Event
Handler is. They are tied to an event; they're tied to an executable.
Error Events, George, are the most common ones that are configured- >> Sure.
>> But they are by far not the only ones.
A control flow is defined and executed, you can do anything.
You can do cleanups of files; there are all sorts of things that
go in. Now to configure Event Handlers you choose the executable,
you go to the Event Handlers tab, you choose the executable,
you choose the event that needs the response, and then you drag,
drop, and configure a control flow just like you would for any
other package.
>> So scope, condition, control flow.
>> Absolutely. So I have in my VM an error handling demo that
we're going to look at real quick.
And, again, it looks very similar to the one that we've been
dealing with right along. But now I've got an Event Handler that
I'm going to specify. So in the tabs I click on Event Handler,
I choose the executable, you can see you can choose any of the
executables in that particular workflow. Once I've chosen the
executable I then choose the event that I want it to fire on.
Now that event list will change depending on the executable that
you've selected.
>> Sure.
>> I'm going to choose the On Error Event of the, let's see, Copy
Source File
and now, once I've chosen the intersection, I click on the link
and it allows me to create a workflow. I'm going to drop a simple
script task on here and I'm going to go into that script task,
I'm going to write a quick C sharp script that's going to display
a message that says, Houston, we have a problem.
>> Oh, you.net show-off.
>> Hey, you know I've got to show what I can do somehow.
So I am very simply going to say inside of my main message box
.show and again, Houston,
we have a problem. And additionally I'm going to get fancy and
put a caption on it that says- >> Oh,
nice.
>> Error. You can see the script result comes in. What did I do?
Oh, I know what I did.
I missed- >> Did
IntelliSense go crazy on you?
>> No, IntelliSense didn't go crazy. It told me I messed up because
I forgot a double quote.
>> Got it.
>> So now I've got my message box configured, I close it, I save
my script task configuration,
and now I have an Event Handler that's going to run when I execute
the package- >> Drum
roll.
>> I hope so; there is my message.
>> Nice.
>> Houston, we have a problem.
>> Will you entertain me and go to control flow?
>> Yeah. I will be happy to. What's up?
>> Kaboom, we had our error.
>> Yeah.
>> So that's what triggered it.
>> Oh, thank you. I would've forgotten to show them that.
>> Oh, that's okay.
>> But it is good to know that it only happens when the error
happens because if I went out and fixed that that message box
would not appear.
>> That's right.
>> So let's take a quick look because I think I want to show that.
>> Okay.
>> We're going out to User Source File. User Source File I think
is looking for, let's go to
SSIS and variables which brings us down to the bottom, and it's
looking for a source file that is looking for a CSV. I have,
I change that to a text, remember? So now if I executed this
package hopefully, hopefully, let's stop current execution, we
run it again,
now I didn't get my message box because I didn't have an Error
Handler on the Load Data, just on the Copy Source Flow.
>> You scoped it just to that task.
>> Awesome.
>> Did just what you told it to.
>> I like the fact that it worked the way I wanted it to.
>> There you go.
>> All right. What's next on the agenda George?
>> So the final segment here is going to different environments deployment.
>> Ah. Package deployment and- >> And
if I can interrupt for just a sec, lots of new changes here in
SSIS 2012. Really, to me, one of the biggest areas of change.
>> This really does bring in some very, very new things; and if
you've been around for a while, if you've played with SSIS before,
you're going to recognize the second topic which is package configurations;
and we're going to show you how to do it. But first we need
to do talk about the different types of deployments, and that
is package deployment and project deployment.
So package deployment
is the process of taking only an individual package and moving
it from the Dev environment to the production environment, for example.
Project deployment, however, occurs or is used when you have
multiple packages in that project and you want to move them as
a unit. And the cool thing is, remember I created project level
Connection Managers before?
>> Yup.
>> And I created project level parameters?
We talked about that; it also moves those resources to production
at the same time.
All right? Now deployment has three possible destinations.
We can deploy it the file system. In deploying to the file system
I'm not going to utilize SQL Server as the storage medium for
the package. It's going to exist on a directory, on the file
system, it's going to be accessible by SSIS, by the server, it's
going to be accessible by SQL Agent, but it's going to be managed
by the file backups and the file resources.
If I deploy to SQL Server now that package is going to be stored
in the MSDB database and is going to be backed up and managed
by the SQL Server backup process instead. Now new with SQL Server
2012 we've got to the SSIS Catalog. The catalog is a special
database that you can create in Management Studio that is the
repository for package and project level deployments.
Now package configurations
are only available in an individual package. If you're deploying,
if you have a project deployment level, project deployment approach
you are not going to have package configurations available.
They are used to set property values of any object inside SSIS
with values that are configured externally and stored in places
like the Registry, an environment variable, an XML file, SQL
Server itself, or a parent package variable. Now one thing about
configurations George- >> Yup.
>> They can be direct where you've got one level of abstraction- >> Abstraction.
>> Or they can be indirect.
>> Double abstraction.
>> Oh, yeah. Because when you've got an indirect configuration
the configuration doesn't contain the property of value to be assigned.
It contains the location of the property value that you want
to assign.
>> A pointer to a pointer.
>> That would be right. A pointer to the actual value.
So let's go and take a look at package configurations real quick.
I've got my Virtual Machine up and going; and I'm going to access
another project. Yes, I've got more George.
>> All right.
>> And we are, first off, going to go to the SSIS menu and,
do I
have it running here? No, I don't.
I've got my Get Logins Package, I'm going to go to my SSIS menu,
there it is. And I'm going to go to package, wait a minute.
What's the problem here?
I don't see Package Configurations George.
>> Uh-oh.
>> Oh.
Son of a gun. Remember I said it's only available when you are
doing package deployment. So let's go take a look at the project.
>> I knew you were leading us somewhere.
>> Yeah. So it is currently in the project deployment. I'm going
to convert it over to package deployment.
It looks like it is not compatible. Why is that George?
>> One or more features is not compatible.
>> Yes. I have a Connection Manager- >> That's
right.
>> At the project level. So you can't just convert anything over
to package configurations- >> No.
>> But here's what I am going to do. I have another project here
that I'm going to open up real quick and we're just going to
do a new project- >> Perfect.
>> It's going to be in Integration Services and we will
just drive, I don't even have to drop. Actually, you know what?
I'm not going to create a Connection Manager, and we're just
going to do an OLEDB connection. It's going to go to Demo DW- >> Perfect.
>> And now I've got something I can configure, and it's at the
package level. I'm going to go to Project, uh-oh.
I have a frozen Virtual Machine.
>> It will take a sec.
>> There it goes. It caught up.
Visual Studio is busy. Well, not as busy as I am, folks.
>> Really.
>> You keep up with me.
>> Uh-oh.
>> Give it a sec.
So to insert a tip here, like there often is there are five ways
to get the same thing done, I could also right-click on the project
in Solution Explorer and convert there.
>> Absolutely you can. So I'm going to convert this over to package
deployment model.
Everything passed this time because I did not have any project
level resources.
So just goes to show you not all packages can go that way.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm going to go to SSIS, Package
Configurations is now available, first thing I do is enable them-
>> Looks obvious.
>> Yeah, it does. But, you know, it's not always obvious Mister Captain.
>> Well, the rest of this is not totally obvious.
>> It isn't. So it now I needed to add a package configuration.
And it brings up the Wizard, it's nice to have a Wizard, I choose
the configuration type, whether it's going to be stored in a
configuration file, an environment variable, a registry entry,
whatever it is, I'm going to choose environment variable and
then you specify the name of the environment variable you want.
I'm going to call it Computer Name.
Then, now that I've identified where to retrieve the value from
I need to identify where to put it. So you can see in this package
there's my Demo DW Connection Manager. If I were to take this
connection, this package and move it to another machine I can
go into the Properties and I can assign the Computer Name Property
to the Server Name Property of the variable, and we can give
that configuration a name called Server Name, but a bing, but
a bang, individual configurations typically store individual values.
There are two exceptions. You can have multiple values in an
XML configuration- >> And-
>> In SQL Server. But other than that, if you're doing an environment
variable, registry, it has to be one value, one configuration.
Okay? Now, going back to the slides we have one more thing to
talk about here and that's the difference between package configurations
and environments.
>> Lots new here. All new.
>> This is where it really gets fun because with package configurations
I've got one thing that travels with the package.
With environments
I now have the ability to set up an environment independent of
a package and then point to the package to the environment.
So now I can configure an environment in Dev that has one set
of values and in Prod that has a different set of values but
the same environment name.
And now when that package migrates
it automatically picks up the new values.
>> Just way more portability.
>> It really is. It really is. And it provides that external mapping
so that you can then determine which property goes to which value.
You can use property expressions, and at execution time, you
can also specify the environment to be used.
>> And you have some stuff to show here too?
>> Absolutely. We absolutely do. Let's flip over, and we've got
our project deployment which is called Deployment Demo, and we
have our project in Project Deployment. What I'm going to do
is I am going to, before I deploy this, watch, I'm going to jump
into Management Studio because in order to deploy we really want
to have an IS Catalog.
>> Got to have the SSIS Catalog.
>> So I'm going to create a catalog.
I give it
a password.
The password is going to protect things using encryption and
that is the encryption password.
It set it up when you create the catalog, and that's all there
is to it. And now I have SSIS DB. And that's my SSIS Catalog.
I come back over to Data Tools and now I choose Project Deploy
or, as you were saying before, I can right-click and go to Deploy,
and it is now going to take all of the packages and their resources,
their project parameters and their project level Connection Managers,
so it loads and validates it, it's not deploying to the right area.
So I need to browse through. It connects me in, and I choose
the folder that I want. Now I can say New Folder and create one
right here which I'm going to call Demos.
>> And a folder's a container where you can dictate administrative
capabilities on that folder, security, etc.
>> Absolutely. It's what gives you the ability to control and
manage who can do what with these packages.
So now I've created, I'm going to choose my Demos Folder,
and I hit Next, it tells me this is what you're going to do,
you hit Deploy, and it puts everything out on the SSIS Server.
>> Perfect.
>> All right? So now we're going to head back over to Management
Sudio, and we're going to refresh the catalog,
and now we can see our Demos Folder, here's our projects, there's
Deployment Demo, and here's our environments.
Now we are talking about environments weren't we George?
>> Yep. Now it's time to show.
>> Yeah. So I've got my Extract DB List and what I'm going to
do is I'm going to go to Configure because in Configure I have
parameters listed, I have Connection Managers listed. So it
gives me the ability to go in and configure this specific package
for what it's going to do when it's executing.
If I look at my Extract Login List and go to Configure, again,
I don't have parameters but I have my Connection Managers.
Now when I create an environment I can right-click and say Create
Environment, and now what I'm doing is I have to give it a name.
So I can create a Prod environments, I could also create a
Dev environment, for example, and now when I right-click and
I need to scroll down a little bit here so I get to Properties,
when I get to the Properties here's my variables, and I can now
configure a variable. For example, I could say Server Mame and
the type being String.
Give it a value, MIA dash SQL BI,
I hit Okay, I've now created one there. When I go to Dev, do
the same thing, I create the same of variable, in this case Server
Name, I go to my type, String, the value here I've got a different
server out there, SQL
Dev, I don't really, but you know I had to give it a different
name to make a point.
>> Sure.
>> Now when I go to execute that package notice I've got parameters,
I've got an Output Folder, I've got Connection Managers, I can
go in, I can grab, I've got Property paths I can set in there,
when I go to Choose I can go and I'm going to go back in here
I'm going to set that and change that variable so that I can
map it, actually I don't even need to. We'll just do it right
in here.
I'm going to go to Execute, here's my parameter, I can set it,
what am I doing? Oh, gosh.
I have the ability to specify in here to use the Dev value from
the package or,
this is not showing up the way I wanted it to.
Where is Edit Value?
>> Is that the right parameter?
Do you want the Server Name or Connection String or- >> Yeah.
That's where I'm going to go. I'm going to go down and it's Extract
DB List,
that's what happens when it gets late in the afternoon.
I don't have my parameters set up. So I need to set up the parameter.
But any rate, you can specify
the environment that's being used and
I go to my value, I can specify the value directly at execution
time there. So I'm going to have to come back to this in a little
bit; so let's wrap it up. We've kind of been going long here.
We will come back to that and square that one away. How's that?
>> Awesome.
>> So in this module we talked about deployment with configurations
and environments. We talked about logging and error handling.
We talked about troubleshooting being a process and all that
good stuff. We've got one more module coming don't we, George?
>> Yep. We hope you've been enjoying the Implementing A Data Warehouse
with SQL Server 2012 Jump Start. Let's got up, move around,
take a stretch, and then final module of the day.
>> You've got it. Enterprise Data.
Stay tuned.