[Music]
Welcome back, everyone, to implementing a data
warehouse with SQL server 2012 Jumpstart.
I'm George Squillace, notice S-q-l is in the name. And I'm here
with Rich Currey. Rich, you like to cook, and curry is in your name.
>> It's a spicy combination, I will tell you that.
>> So what's up for this module, Rich? Our final segment of the day.
>> Yep. And this one kind of deviates a little bit from what we've
been talking about right along. However, it is completely, completely
appropriate in this discussion because it's talking about enterprise data.
Now, enterprise data, as you are well aware, George, is the lifeblood
of a company.
So what we're going to be talking about in this module is two
relative new pieces of SQL Server, Master Data Services and Data
Quality Services.
Now, Master Data Services is...
first came in with SQL Server 2008. We were going to give you
an overview of what it's all about, talk about the data models
and entities and attributes, hierarchies, business rules.
>> Lots of moving parts.
>> Yeah. There are lots of moving parts. So Master Data Services
is the SQL Server solution that was developed enterprise-level data.
Now, we talked about and I had a slide up way back at the beginning
of this today that talked about the fact that data needs to be
matched from different systems. We have lots of operational systems
that consume the same data, and it is a really good idea to have
a single source. Because, let's face, it, if I'm a customer in
an organization and I'm a customer of, say, three different subsidiaries
of that company, that means that I might have registered as a
customer three separate times. Maybe I used Rich Currey one time,
Richard Currey one time, and R.
Currey one time, each of those is me, but because I put my name
in differently,
the systems think I'm three different people. So Master Data
Services allows me to create a single source
for all...
for the information that's used by multiple solutions within
the enterprise.
It allows an organization do centralized storage of data rather
than distributed storage. It allows us to create a single spot
for a data steward to go clean things up.
>> A data steward?
>> A data steward. We talked about him earlier today.
And we also now have a single spot for ETL to go to take and
get all of those... all of that information distributed to the
systems that need to consume it. Now, Master Data Services uses
data models and business rules to not just define but also manage
the correctness or validity of the data.
Now, a data model is a container, George. It is a container
that has entities in it. Now, an entity is a real-world thing.
The data in a data model represents all of the entities.
So, for example, a product could be an entity. A customer could
be an entity.
A supplier could be an entity. A shipper. All of those entities
have attributes.
Attributes are the pieces of information that describe them,
just like in a dimension, George. A dimension has attributes
that are used to describe the entities there. So I create entities,
I create attributes.
Then I have the ability to create hierarchies. Hierarchies express
the relationships between entities.
Now, you might be...
you might be templed to
create one big data model. Nah. Don't to that.
Create smaller data models that are purposed to a specific part
of the business.
Don't try and do one size fits all; do different pieces that
are purposed specifically to the part of the information that
they're covering.
>> So I have to create a data model.
>> You do.
>> And I want to compartmentalize using some sort of rule book.
>> Yep.
>> Okay.
>> I may have, for example, a customers data model, a products
data model, a suppliers data model.
Each one is going to have all of the entities, all of the hierarchies,
all of the business rules necessary to validate what is going
on with the data.
>> An honest question here, Rich. So if I have multiple systems
that might have product data, I might create a products model.
If I had multiple systems that had customer data, I might create
a customer model.
>> Absolutely. And it doesn't even have to be multiple systems.
You can create a data model to control the information in a single
system with the thought that there might be more systems coming later.
>> Aha. So set it up ahead of time.
>> Absolutely. Plan to succeed.
>> All right.
>> And then you will succeed when you plan.
>> Anyway. So a data model contains both entities and attributes.
The entity represents a business object, a logical business object
like a customer, like a supplier, like a product, that can be
consumed in one or more systems. And each entity has multiple
attributes, the pieces of information that describe that entity.
It might be, for a customer, first name, last name, address,
e-mail, city, region, postal code. There could be a bunch of them.
And then the collection, each entity has members. You could
be a customer. I could be a customer. Danny could a customer.
Even Alise could be a customer.
>> Woohoo.
>> You know, the peanut gallery likes it when they get included
in the broadcast, so I had to do it.
>> There you go.
>> Now, each of those members has to have values assigned for
each of the attributes that represent that entity. Now, when
you're designing it, George, each entity is typically going to
map to tables in RDBMSs and the attributes are going to map to
the column. So if I've got five different systems that each use
product data, I'm going to create a product entity and I want
to make sure that I define an attribute for every column that
exists in every table.
It doesn't mean that I'm going to have the product name five times.
I'm going to make sure that I have an attribute for name and
it appears in all five systems so I have a single source for
that attribute value.
>> Master data.
>> You got it. And then the members will map to the individual
records in each table.
Now, next step is relationships between those entities.
And typically that's going to be the same thing as setting up
foreign key relationships. The analogy holds true. It is a parent-child relationship.
Hierarchies represent either the relationship between entities
themselves or between individual members of entities.
And that kind of falls into the difference between a derived
hierarchy and an explicit hierarchy. A derived hierarchy is
one that is determined by the relationship between entities.
You can look at it and say, hey, guess what, this category relates
to these products. There is a way to derive the relationship.
It's based on attribute values.
An explicit hierarchy is one that you're putting together.
For example, maybe I have continents like North America and Europe
and I've got countries to map to it, but I don't necessarily
have a continent in my databases.
I don't have an attribute called continent that it would make
sense to build.
So what I do is I create a... what's called a consolidated member
and I give it a name, such as what you see here on the slide,
with the consolidated member code cust US, consolidated member
code cust EU.
Now, when you've got explicit hierarchies, you also have the
ability to specify whether they are mandatory hierarchies or
whether they are not. A mandatory hierarchy is one where all
members of that entity must be assigned to one of the consolidated members.
If it is nonmandatory, then they don't need to be. So, for example,
if all I wanted for consolidated member, George, was the U.S.
and my European customers and the rest of the world I was going
let them go and just say, you know, they're not a part of the U.S.
or European customer groups, that would be a nonmandatory hierarchy.
If I then created a consolidated member called all others where
my U.S. customers were in one, my European in another, and then
everybody else was assigned to all other, I could then make that
a mandatory hierarchy.
>> And you have some things to show us now.
>> I do. I do. We are going to drop over to our virtual machine
now, and the first thing we're going to do is... I got to tell
you, George.
>> What's that?
>> You're not going to find Master Data Services in SQL Server
Management Studio.
>> Different management tool?
>> It is. It is. And it's one of our favorite ones.
Internet Explorer.
>> Browser-based admin.
>> You got it. It means no installing tools on the desktop.
And there are advantages to that, although not necessarily a
lot of them. I'm going to set my browser to .2, the installed
instance, and you're going to configure this when you install
Master Data Services on your network. I'm going to local host
port 81/MDS, and
that brings up the homepage for Master Data Services.
>> There you go.
>> Let me get it scrolled over so you can actually see the whole thing.
Now, the first thing that I want to do is I want to go into system
administration because I have not yet created a model.
So I am going to create a model. Notice I'm in add model.
I'm going to call that model customers.
>> Just for a sec, could you slide your VM title bar over a little
to the right? It looks like that's being clipped at the left.
>> It's not.
>> It's not? Okay.
>> No.
>> All right.
>> Yeah. I'm fully all the way over.
>> Okay.
>> Let's see.
>> There you go. Perfect.
>> Okay.
>> That's it.
>> Yeah. Screen looks like it's getting clipped there. Sorry about
that, folks.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm not going to create an entity
at this point because I'm going to go and do that at a later point.
When I save it, my model is now in there with the name of customers.
It shows up with metadata. I'm next going to go to manage and
choose entities.
First thing I need to do is choose the correct model. So I'm
in model, and now I add an entity. The entity I'm going to put
in there is customers.
I can assign a staging table for that entity. I can create code values.
I can enable explicit hierarchies and connections. That's what
you do here.
My choice here, I am going to not enable them.
I add my entity in by saving it.
And now I have my customers.
And notice over here
my entities.
>> There you go.
>> Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to head back over
and I need to now add in hierarchy. I need to add in attributes.
So back to system, manage...
I clicked too quick. Sorry about that.
Manage entities.
I choose my customer entity and notice I now get a new set of
buttons up here.
As I choose that, one of my buttons
is to edit the selected entity. And when I do, now I get my leaf members.
Another word for attributes.
>> And I don't know about you, Rich, but I think it's going to
take people that are new to this to get a little... it's going
to take some time to the user interface.
>> Yeah. I absolutely agree with that. This is one of those things
where practice is going to make you better and better. Now, I
know George brought that up because I searched for a moment there
because I went back to the homepage and I didn't need to, because
honestly I forget where it was for a second.
>> Actually, that's not why. I'm not contradicting; I found that
I had to wrestle with it a lot.
>> Oh, yeah. I wrestled with it all the time. And sometimes I
still wrestle with that interface. So now that I've got my entity
set up, I've got my leaf members displaying, I'm going to add
in a new leaf attribute. I give it a name. Now, because it's
a customer, guess what, we can put in a city, and that is going
to be text with a length of we'll say 400.
And when I'm done I hit save. It brings me back. I can add in
another leaf on this one, maybe I'll do phone.
And on phone I'm going to do a data type of text with a length
of call it 20 characters.
I save it. And what do you say we do one more, George?
>> Let's do one more.
>> All right. I'm going to put in credit limit.
Credit limit is going to be a number that's going to be zero
decimals, and now I choose my input mask which tells me how I'm
going to represent negative values.
Now, I'm just going to choose the minus sign here. I save it.
And now I have a list of columns
for my table.
>> Have your attributes.
>> Or attributes for my entities. Cool?
>> Cool.
>> All right.
>> We're underway.
>> We are. So what's next on our journey?
>> Next up, business rules.
>> Mmm. Because, let's face it, Master Data is nothing if it isn't correct.
The biggest myth in IT: My data's clean. You want to hear a
story, George?
>> I would. And you have a bunch of good ones.
>> I do. But I've got one in particular that I want to do here,
because I did a project back in my professional days for a multinational,
well-known, very large corporation with lots of subsidiaries,
and it was a business IntelliSense project that was going to
do business analysis to do projections for future business.
Forecasting. It was about a 14-month project. We spent the first
two months of the project working on the design of the hierarchies
and the dimensions. I say that because it is probably one of
the most critical points. We then spent the next seven months...
>> Did you say seven?...
>> trying to take data from all of these different systems and
get it so that it all correlated and was usable. There were
mismatches, there was bad information, there was no cleansing
done, so we had to do all of the analysis of the data itself
and build the cleansing. Master Data would have been a huge help
to make that happen, to create that centralized spot that we
could have then driven everything out to. Just to give you an
idea of how complex the cleansing was, the project lasted for
about five more months and we did six rollouts of functionality
in the five months compared to seven months of doing nothing
but data cleansing. So that's the level of effort that Master
Data Services will provide.
So going on back to the slide for a minute, we are going to be
talking about the business rules because they're what ensures
that data is valid and correct. Now, valid is one thing.
Validation happens at many levels in a database in an application.
Correct, however, is something else entirely. Because correct
has meaning, it has substance behind it, about determining whether
a value is the appropriate value for the entity being tracked.
Now, you set up the business rules in MDS and then you can use
either the MDS Web interface or, you're going to love this, for
our data stewards who maybe are not as technically inclined as
some of us IT folks, you can also use Microsoft Excel as a front-end plug-in.
>> A new plug-in that came with 2012.
>> It is. So let's go take a look at a business rule real quick.
We are going to bounce back into our virtual machine and we are
going to go back to our models.
I'm going to choose my customers model and now...
oh, I take it back. I'm going to go back to entities, my apologies,
and when I choose the customer entity, I now have my business rules.
So in my business rules, this is where I'm going to derive what
the validation policy is for specific records. So I create a
new business rule. This business rule is going to be check valid...
typing is a challenge at times when you have fingers as big as mine...
valid credit limit.
Okay. I've now named it and I go into expression and in this
expression I'm now going to define
what it is I want to do. So I edit my selected business rule.
Now, this is not exactly the most intuitive thing you've ever
seen, is it?
>> That's well stated, Rich.
>> Okay. So there's a couple of pieces here. The if qualifies
when I'm going to look at a particular entity.
So I can say if this is true, then apply the rule.
If it's not true, then don't apply the rule.
In here I'm going to grab an action and my action is going to
be must be greater than.
I'm going to drop that under my actions.
Now I have no condition, so then everything must be greater than.
If I wanted to grab, for example,
is equal to, I could say if, for example, customer type equals
X, then must be greater than,
and then down here I choose my attribute,
my attribute value that I want in there, so the first thing I
need to do is grab the attribute that I want. It is the credit limit.
I drop it onto my attribute.
The value
must be greater than...
mmm, come on there.
Oh, I'm sorry. I put that in the wrong spot.
>> Exactly what I was talking about.
>> Yep. This is where it gets funky. So now I got to start all
over again because I had to delete it. It's not easy to get it.
So I'm going to drop the must be greater than.
I'm going to drop my credit limit into select attribute this time.
>> Before you drop, though, look at right where you're going to
let go, it says select attribute. And then below and to the
right it says the same thing, but they don't do the same thing.
Argh.
>> Absolutely correct. And that's why I got it messed up the first time.
Because what I'm trying to do is say that the credit limit must
be greater than so it reads top to bottom. And now I'm going
to assign a specific value and say credit limit must be greater
than 500.
I save it. My business rule is now in place, and you can see
credit limit must be greater than 500. It is unconditional.
Cool, George?
>> Cool.
>> All right. So now let's go back and very quickly, what we want
to do now, is we're going to go back to our homepage and now
we're going to go to Explorer because Explorer is where we can
actually manually enter some data.
Now, there's two ways to populate a model. You can use standard
ETL because it's tables in a database. So you just take data
from point A to point B. Or if you've got some specific ones,
I can add a member. Now, I clicked on add member, it brings all
the details over here. And I can say Rich,
the city, I am currently in...
yeah, I can spell, huh?
There we go. That's better. A phone
and a credit limit.
I got a credit limit of 5,000. I'm a good customer. I'm going
to say that this is an original entry.
I hit okay.
Code value cannot be blank.
I'll put in a code value of 1.
>> Good object lesson there.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And now Rich is in there, a code of 1, Seattle.
I'm going to go back in. I'm now going to change this from 5,000
to 500 and hit okay.
>> Still valid.
>> Still valid. If I change it down to 50...
still valid. That shouldn't have worked.
>> Nope, that should not have worked.
>> All right. So I guess we got a little troubleshooting to do.
Ah. What did I not do?
I did not apply the rules.
>> So let's see what happens.
>> Business rules will be applied.
Yes. I think what I forgot is to deploy the rules. So let's
go back.
Let's go back to our system admin because you know what I didn't
do, I think once I got to my business rules I did not save it.
So manage entities, manage, business rules.
Yep, I did not publish.
>> There you go.
>> You got to remember to publish the rule, George.
Now that I've published it, we're going to go back. Notice the
status is now active.
When we come back through here, we're going to go to Explorer.
Notice I have a member in here. See the question?
>> Well, what do you know?
>> It's waiting for re-evaluation. So now if I apply the rule,
I've got an exclamation next to it, it tells me that validation failed.
>> That's right.
>> If I come over, notice the validation errors. If I now change
this to 501 and hit okay, it immediately evaluates and gives
me a green check.
>> Good tool.
>> It is. It's a very, very, very cool tool.
There's a lot more that you can do with it. Trust me, George.
>> Wow.
>> There is a ton of stuff.
>> Now, what about those circumstances where I don't feel like
manually entering in all of those entities
into the Master Data Services form there? Is there any way we
can improve our efficiency?
>> Absolutely. Just a little bit. I mean, let's face it, most
times you're going to have lots of business systems already in
place when you're implemented MDS. So consuming Master Data
is all about setting up
hooks between all of your systems. You've got a hub and spoke architecture.
You've got the Master Data Services as the central hub of your
solution and it then goes out to all of the different systems,
all of the different databases and using SSIS can now manage
the movement of the data from enterprise out to operational,
from operational back into the enterprise. With MDS you can
do your validation and cleansing, you can use that cleansed data
then to update the operational systems. Cool?
>> Very cool. So we have another part of having trustworthy and
cleansed data. And what's up next?
>> Data Quality Services is the next part of this enterprise data solution.
And Data Quality Services is, again, relatively new to SQL Server.
It is available in 2008 and 2012.
We're going to show you how to build the solution, how to access
reference data or talk about reference data. We're going to
talk about data validation using DQS and show you a little bit
with SSIS.
>> And I do want to give a test-taking tip, and that is if you're
planning on passing the certification exam, you're going to want
to have some hands-on time with both MDS and DQS. You can download
trial versions of the software to help you get there.
>> And I agree with George. It's one of those that I would highly,
highly recommend that you go out and play with it. It's out there.
It's good.
Well, like we've been talking right along, data is the lifeblood
of an organization. Incorrect data lead to incorrect analysis
which leads to incorrect decision-making which leads to, for
many businesses, bankruptcy.
So really and truly it is in our best interest to make sure that
that data is accurate and correct. Data Quality Services implements
the tools that do that for us. It gives us access to a knowledge base.
A knowledge base can contain information that's used to validate
our organizational data, not as a source of our organizational data.
And that's the big difference between MDS and DQS.
MDS is the source of enterprise information,
DQS allows us to correct that information and make it good.
We have what are called reference data services that provide
that ability to access data. Now, the first thing you need to
do when you're creating a solution is to create a knowledge base.
The knowledge base provides access to specific areas of information.
A knowledge base can have multiple pieces of information, it
can have a single piece of information, and inside of that knowledge
base you create domains.
Domains house the rules that are applied, the way that you can
correct data.
So once you've got your domain, which is the responsibility of
data, you define the rules that are going to relate to whether
a value is correct or incorrect, valid or invalid, and you can
even set up matching rules, George, to fix all those typos that happen.
>> There you go.
>> I know I can't type to save my life, so if I'm typing wholesaler,
I may get w-h-i-l
stead of o-l because it hit the wrong key. So matching policies
allow me to take values and figure out how they go together.
We ready?
>> We're ready.
>> All right. Let's see what we can do with this one.
>> So in the same way MDS requires some base object setup, DQS
is going to require some base object setup as well.
>> It is. Now, unlike MDS,
DQS is a client tool. The DQS client is accessible from the SQL
Server group of tools in the start menu.
>> Start menu access.
>> Here is Data Quality Services. Here is my Data Quality client
that gives me access.
Now, the first thing you need to do, George, is connect to the
server that's got all the information, which in this case is
Miami-SQL BI.
>> There you go.
>> Now, I just want to show you something really quick. I'm going
to go into...
well, I hate it when it does that. I am going to go into management
studio and I'm going to display databases.
>> Oh, I see something there.
>> DQS main, DQS projects, DQS data.
There's an MDS database. So I am going to tell you, it ain't free.
It's never free.
But it is well worth the price of admission. So the first thing
I need to do in this process is to create a knowledge base.
So my knowledge base, I am going to create a
DQS demo knowledge base and I am going to
create it from an existing knowledge base called DGS data.
Now, it shows me the domains that are available, so I need to
go to next in the wizard because I'm going to do domain management.
It now brings me to the next page, which is where I am going
to select
the domains that I want in my database. Notice there is a bunch
of them listed.
>> It's nice the product comes with one knowledge base that you
can work with, and it's some address-related data.
>> It is. So the first thing I need to do is I am going to be
focusing in on the U.S. state domain. Now, that means I want
to get rid of all these others. So you highlight it, you click
the X, you say yes.
>> And I don't think there's a trick for multiselecting that I found.
>> Unfortunately, George, you better hope you don't have 300 domains.
You only want ten of them. Because you've got to do this for
every domain that you don't want to use. So while I'm clicking
and waiting, we need to keep talking so these folks don't get
bored out of their mind watching me get rid of the extraneous information.
>> All right. While you're mentioning that, here's one rule of
thumb that helped me divide between where MDS helps and where
DQS helps. In fact, with DQS you want to think of having correct
column values. Whereas with MDS... and, again, this is broad,
big picture. And with MDS, you want to make sure that you have
correct rows when you might have different rows from different systems.
I can different rows from different systems that are all valid,
they are correct data, but one I want to be the winning row,
the master. So for whatever that's worth, let's go back to the demo.
>> You got it. And that's actually a great piece of advice, George.
>> I think it got it from somewhere else.
>> Well, hey, you remembered it. That's a good thing.
>> All right.
>> All right. So I'm going to change the domain name here from U.S.
state to just state. I've gotten rid of all the others. And now
what I want to do is go over to domain values. Because, guess
what, there are already some prepopulated values in there.
So you can see the state name and you can see some pretty common
occurrences that might show up.
AL is correct. But we're going to correct it too Alabama.
ALA period is not a correct value, it's an error value, but it's
still going to be corrected to Alabama.
>> So if I see ALA show up in my data, I can set up a rule that
says force it into becoming Alabama.
>> That is exactly correct. So this is just an example of some
of the things you've got. I'm going to finish her off now.
When I finish building in the knowledge base, then it asks me
if I want to publish it. For now I'm going to say no. We're going
to hold off on that. Okay?
>> Sounds good.
>> All right.
>> And how would an IT person, a BI developer like myself, possibly
know what typically invalid values will be?
>> Well, you're going to have to have some business knowledge,
number one. But, number two, there are... out in the Azure marketplace
there are publically available databases that you can bring into
Data Quality Services as a source of information.
Some of those are subscription cost.
Some of them are subscription free of charge. It depends, but
they are available out there. Many of them are public domain
and freely available. Others you might need to contact a representative
to get it. But that's called reference data.
All of that is referred to as reference data. And that's what
you set up as the source that you're going to use to get some
of this information. So if I need a listing of all the cities
in every country in the world, yeah, that would be kind of tough
to type in. Don't you think?
>> Yeah, you don't have that in your back pocket already.
>> Nope. So nicely enough there is probably a database out there.
I don't know for sure. But there is probably a database out there
that lists every country, its valid abbreviations, and every
city as well with valid spellings. Now, when you're going in
and setting up these projects, you need to do data validation.
And that's called a data cleansing project. The data cleansing
project is what gives our data stewards the ability to analyze
data in a database and manage the validity and correctness of it.
So you've got a knowledge base and you've got a data source.
The knowledge base we just talked about, the reference data.
The data source is the data that I want to check. Cleansing can
include validation, making sure values are correct. It can also
include matching, finding records that actually mean the same thing.
And it can do both at the same time. Now, here's the nice thing.
It is not assumed that just because DQS says it's right means
it's right. It does output, as a result of the cleansing process,
the records that have been affected as well as what the effects
were, showing you original values and corrected values.
>> Some great IntelliSense that it provides there.
>> Absolutely, George. So let's go take a look at a data cleansing
project and what it does. So in my virtual machine, what I need
to do now is access a new data quality project. So just like
before I need to give it a name. In my name I'm going to just
call this,
really inventive here,
cleanse project.
It's late. I can't think of any good names anymore, George.
>> That's a great name.
>> The knowledge base that I'm going to use is DQS data.
Now it's a wizard.
I choose my cleansing project. I say next.
>> Next.
>> And we wait.
>> You said say next.
>> Yeah, but I said I say next. So be quiet.
Oh, lord.
So now I've got my data source. My data source here is going
to be an Excel file. So I have... I just happen to have out
here, George, at the tip of my fingers a stores.xls spreadsheet
which contains a bunch of information.
Now, what I need to do now is map things in. I've got a city.
The city is going to map to...
and I don't have city in here. So I think what I'll do is I'm
going to add a column mapping. Okay. I'm going to...
oh, I'm sorry. What am I doing here? I'm going to validate that state.
>> There you go.
>> Been a long day, hasn't it?
>> Long day.
>> And I'm going to map it to the U.S. state. So my source column,
my domain, now I go in and I go to the next step in the process
which is the analysis of the two.
I run my analysis. It takes the inputs and it uploads in and
it processes.
As it processes, it's going through, it cleanses the records.
And it's showing me statistics about those cleanses. So how
many were correct, how many were incorrect, et cetera. Now, this
one is running for a while here.
>> Curious.
>> It is, because it typically runs much quicker than this.
>> What do we have, 11 whole rows in the stores spreadsheet I think?
>> Yeah.
>> Whatever, not a whole lot. And there you go.
>> Okay. We got preprocessing done.
>> Preprocessing done.
>> And there we go. Now we got our cleansing done. And it shows
you there were nine correct records. There were two corrected records.
When I go to the next step, I can see suggesteds, new, invalid.
I can see the corrected records. You can see CA and WA were
corrected to California and Washington.
>> Did what we told it to do.
>> And here are the ones that were valid and what their values were.
Pretty cool, huh?
>> Beautiful.
>> All right.
So headed back to the sides.
We have next...
>> Validating data with SSIS.
So... well, I have to let you tell the story.
>> No, no, no, no, no. Please.
>> Well, rather than having such a manual process of validating
data, maybe we want to raise the bar a bit.
>> Automate it.
>> Automate.
>> Because as good dBAs, I want to have all the things that happen...
that happen repetitively be automated and take all of that manual
labor out of the process. So I've got
validating tools using a data source and data cleansing project
and then a data cleansing transform, which can take and do the
exact same thing that I just did manually. You need to have
data destinations to hold the cleansed data, and you need to...
and you can also pipe it through other transformations after
the fact.
Now, SSIS is the best place to do this because now as you're
pulling your data from point A to point B, from source systems
through into destination systems, you can do the cleansing in
transit and end up with clean data with no manual intervention.
You like that?
>> I do. And it looks like you have something to show here.
>> We are going to give this one a shot. Let's head on over.
And I have a knowledge base, I have a cleansing project, so I
am going to close out of
my DQS client.
And now we are going to create... come on.
Where... I'm not at the top. That's why.
>> Your mouse by the Hyper-V buttons has made my hair stand up
on end a couple of times.
>> Yeah.
>> Because if you power those down...
>> Yeah. I've kind of... notice I haven't clicked very often.
>> You haven't. You've been very careful.
>> I got to tell you, I am the king of closing windows accidentally.
I am absolutely flabbergasted that I have not closed that Hyper-V
window once all day.
All right. So let's go back to the virtual machine here.
We're going to do a new project. It's going to be an integration
services project. And very simply what I want to do is show you
that DQS transform. So I'm going to drop a dataflow task onto
our designer.
>> Star of the opera.
>> Yep. And then we're going to come over here and we are going
to go to DQS cleansing and drop it in place. Now, first thing
is, it has no available input column. So guess what I need to do?
>> That means it's a source.
>> I need to go and grab some data to put into it. So I am going
to create a source, a data source that is going to be an OLE D...
yeah, I'm going to grab a data source, so what do I do, a grab
a destination.
I'm going to grab an OLE DB source, we're going to configure
that source up, we're going to grab a new connection manager
that's going to go out to our demo DQS,
and we are going to grab... all right.
Let's create a new connection manager.
>> Or... sorry.
>> No, got to... first... it didn't like the one that I just got.
So I'm going to create a new one that's going to go out to, I
clicked on the arrow... I haven't done that all day either, not once.
>> No, but now we can wait for that to happen.
>> And you know what? I misspoke. The DQS is a transform, so
it's going to have inputs.
>> It is. So I'm going to go out
to MIA-SQL BI. I'm going to go out and I'm going to grab data
from demo DQS. Ah, that's why. I missed a...
I did not run a script that I need to run. So my demo DQ database
isn't in there. So we're going to go back out real quick to management studio.
We are going to run a script that's out there that's going to
create it. I need to go out and grab from
mod 9.
>> Says setup.
>> My setup script. Yep. And there's my demo DQS. We'll execute it.
Now I've got my data. So I should be able to go back in.
Sorry about that, folks.
We are going to go back in.
We now have in here, or we should, anyway... I'm going to cancel
it out.
I'm going to choose my demo DQS.
>> Perfect.
>> There's my store's table.
I go to columns. It grabs the columns in the store table.
We now have our data source that we're going to put through the cleansing.
>> Perfect.
>> I connect the two.
Now I go to my DQS cleansing. The first thing it needs to know
is the Data Quality connection manager. I don't have one, so
I'm going to define a new one. It says where is your DQS server.
I'm going to point it to the one I've got on SQL BI, we test
it, we got the right one...
>> That's good....
>> we're good to go. Now, what knowledge base are we going to use?
>> Well, we only have one right now, so...
>> That's a good thing. We'll do our DQS data. These are our
available domains. Now I'm going to set up my mapping,
my available input columns. I'm going to choose my state.
The domain that it's going to map to is U.S.
state. I now have my mapping setup.
I can save
my component. At least I can once I get to where the save button is.
There's my okay.
>> Perfect.
>> And now I can take that output and put it somewhere.
We're going to create a flat file destination real quick.
>> Oh, that was a source.
>> Huh. I'm just all over it today, aren't I?
>> Just trying to cover.
>> Here's my destinations. Flat file destination. We're going
to hook the two up.
Define the output. So I'm going to create my connection manager.
It is delimited. It is going to go to the desktop.
>> Excitement's building.
>> It is. I'm getting there. Slowly but surely.
We give it a file name, which is going to be cleansed stores.
>> Nice.
>> .out, .text.
I hit open now. And that destination could be a SQL Server destination
to populate a table if I want it to.
Here are all my columns. Notice the store ID, the name, street,
city, state. I've got state source, state out, state status,
the record status, everything is there.
Now I do my mappings.
That ties it all together. When I execute the package, it reads
the data from the table, runs it through the cleansing output.
Come on, folks, I know you got it.
There we go. It goes through the cleansing.
When the cleansing has completed, it goes out to the flat file
destination where it gets written.
This is taking way too long.
>> It's working, it's working.
>> If I could put more horsepower on this virtual machine, folks,
trust me, I'd put it on there.
But at this point we can only wait, sir.
There we go. We have success.
>> Liftoff.
>> Now I go out to
my desktop. There is cleansed stores. And you can see Store
1, New York, New York, New York. It's correct. California, California.
WA, W-A, Washington is corrected.
And it says it out at the end as well. So, again, that transform
gives you the fully corrected data and you can take it, you're
doing a transform later on, use those corrected values to load
downstream data destinations.
>> All right. Everybody take a deep breath and exhale.
>> Enterprise data.
>> We looked at Master Data Services.
>> We did.
>> Data Quality Services.
>> A whole bunch of things today. And now it's time for a survey.
You'll see a poll down at the very bottom of your screen. A lot
of resources went into making this available today and they're
interested, the powers that be, in getting your feedback. So please...
>> As are we, quite honestly.
>> We are too. Sure. We want to make sure that it was worthwhile
for you. So please take the survey at the bottom. And on behalf
of Rich Currey and myself, George Squillace, thank you for attending.
And we hope to have you come back for some of the other Jumpstarts
that will be available.
>> Absolutely. Keep your eyes out on MVA. Thanks, folks.
Have a great rest of the day wherever you may be.