[Music]
Welcome back everyone to implementing a data
warehouse with SQL
Server 2012 Jumpstart. I'm George Squillace and my colleague
Rich Currey. Rich, what do we have up for this module?
>> This module we are going to be talking about data flow, how
to extract data.
The topics that we are going to be concerned with here are going
to be connection managers, a connection manager, what it is,
what it means to a project, how to get data out of a data source
and into a data destination.
>> Got to load the warehouse.
>> Oh. That's the next topic, data sources and data destinations.
What they are, how they work, we're going to talk about change
data capture and change tracking, which are two technologies
that are now available that can help us to extract information
out of our production systems.
>> And you've got to start somewhere.
>> You do, so let's talk about connection managers. What is a
connection manager? We're going to talk about package connection
managers and project connection managers.
>> Some new stuff.
>> And parameterization of connection strings, which is very cool,
very cool. A connection manager is
a definition to SSIS of the technology that we are going to use
as well as the location where the data is. It has a data source
in SQL Server. It has a data source; it has an initial catalog
and it has
an authentication, the authentication being the identity that's
going to be used to connect it. Now, other technologies have
other properties because we can use connection managers to go
out and go to Oracle, to
Informix, to a text file, to an Access database.
If there is a driver out there for either OLE DB or ODBC we can
use the connection manager to connect to that data source, so
the authentication, the connection string, all the information
that's necessary.
Package and project connection managers refer to the level of
availability that that connection manager has to a package.
Let me back up a minute here. I haven't used package yet, have I?
>> Nope.
>> So when I create an SSIS project
a project is a development effort and there might be several
different pieces and each of those pieces could be encapsulated
in a package. A package is a unit of execution, a unit of deployment,
to SQL Server integration services, so projects contain packages.
A project connection manager is available to be used by all of
the packages in the project. A package level connection manager
is specific to just that package.
Now, how do I know where I want to create it? It's actually pretty straightforward.
If I've got lots of packages inside my project that are going
to be accessing the same data from the same place, that would
be a spot where it would make sense to create a project level
connection manager. If, however, I'm only going to be creating,
going to be accessing the data for that one package then I probably
am going to want to do a package level connection manager.
It's a matter of determining how reusable you want it to be and
how many times you're going to need to maintain it. Now one
of the things that can truly, truly, truly help you in your deployment
effort in creating flexibility within your packages is the ability
to create connection strings that are parameterized. What that
means is that there may be parts of the connection that are dependent
on an environment or a machine that you're located on or something
of that nature. I don't want to have to go in and manually edit
that connection manager every time I put the package in a different
spot, so maybe I want to have the ability to dynamically assign...
>> Abstraction.
>> Yeah, abstraction's fun, all right?
Now we have two possibilities for how we can do this. The first
one is called the configuration; the second is called an environment
and they are different based on how you deploy them. We're going
to be talking a lot more about that later on today in a later module.
Property expressions are how you physically manipulate the value
in the connection string. A property expression gives you the
ability to calculate the value dynamically at runtime that is
going to be used for that property of that object within the package.
For a connection string, sorry, for a connection manager...
>> There you go.
>> Yeah, I know, too many connection words. For a connection
manager the property that frequently is modified is the connection
string property or the server name property.
Now one other cool thing is along with configurations with connection
strings and with server properties, the computer named property,
you do have the ability to also dynamically assign the value
when you execute the package.
Now, let's go and take a look at how you create a connection manager.
>> Sounds good.
>> What I've got here is I need to go in and I need to actually
create an integration services project. I'm going to go into
the SQL Server 2012.
>> We have a new name here, don't we?
>> Yeah, we do, and don't be surprised if you hear me use the
old one. The old one was business intelligence development studio,
BIDS, the new one...
>> Old habits die hard, don't they?
>> SQL Server Data Tool, so I open up Data Tools which is a Visual
Studio application just like all the other Visual Studio applications
out there, I'm going to create a new project. It's going to
be an integration services project and honestly, for purposes
of the demo I'm not really worried about the project name or
the location, though it is something that you should be concerned
about when you're doing this for real.
Oops. I don't want to hit that. I wanted to hit the okay button.
Now I have a package and if you look down here at the bottom
I have a connection manager section, but that's not the only
place it shows up.
I also have a connection managers folder up in solution explorer.
The difference between the two is pretty straightforward.
If it's in the folder in connection managers then it's available
to every package in the packages folder. If, however, it is
in the package itself down at the bottom of the screen, that's
when it's going to be specific to the package.
>> Well put.
>> Project level connection managers will also show up in the
package when you are working. So let's go create one real quick.
I'm going to right-click on connection managers, choose new connection
manager and the first thing that it asks me is what the technology
is that we are going to be connecting to.
I've got the standard technologies of ADO.net and if I scroll
down a little bit, OLE DB. You can connect to an SMTP server.
You can connect to a SQL mobile instance. You can connect to
FTP, Flat File, HTTP; I'm telling you the choices are endless.
And even better, do you want to hear something really cool?
>> Definitely.
>> They're not all there. You can actually go out and select others
and load them in and connect to other technologies adding another
OLE DB or ODBC drivers as well.
Now what I'm going to do here is I'm going to choose an OLE DB
draw connection manager. When you hit add it now asks you to
configure or to choose an existing connection. Now I've been
playing on this virtual server for a while, so I've got some
connections out there already.
>> You can just make a new one.
>> Ah, I think I'm going to, so I can show you how to do it George.
You click on new and, again, now that I've chosen OLE it gives
me a list of all of the OLE providers that are available.
OLE DB for SQL Server, I've got the SQL Server native client
which is the way all .net applications talk. I've got the Microsoft Jet.
Anybody remember what that belongs to?
>> Uh-huh.
>> That would be Access. I've got Office; I think it's Office 2013.
For the Office 12 Access database engine. I've got OLE DB providers
for Oracle, for SQL, for DataShape; I mean it's all there.
Let's stick with what we have in there, the native client and
then you need to specify the location.
I have several of them out there, so I'm going to say local right here.
Local specifies I'm going to be working on that local machine.
If it is a network-based machine, you could specify it in terms
of the instance name, so this is the instance in SQL Server that
contains the database. Once you've indicated it, you come down here.
It gives you the list of databases that are available. You choose
the one that you want.
Hopefully, I name it correctly. You test the connection. Connection succeeds.
I hit okay.
Bada bing bada bang bada boom.
>> Bada boom.
>> There you go. We have ourselves a new connection and we have
our connection manager. And again, I want you to notice, it's
up here in the connection manager at the project level. It occurs
down here in the connection manager at the package level as well.
To do a package only, the only difference is where you right-click.
If I right-click down here,
there you go.
I've got my new connection that I can create and I go through
the process down here.
>> Excellent. That's a great starting point, but you have some
other things to show us to. After I make connections managers,
what would I do?
>> After connection manager, let's go back to the slides here.
We need to create data sources and data destinations.
The process data sources and data destinations, what are they?
What are the different technologies that are available? How do
we actually go through and create them is what I want to talk about.
So let's start off with the definition of what they are.
And it's pretty straightforward. A data source is a place where
you get data from.
>> Sounds straightforward to me.
>> So using that, George, would you care to take a guess at what
a data destination is?
>> I think I see where the train is going here.
>> Are right. Let's not get derailed then.
We are going to do a data destination has where the data is going
to end up. Now data sources and data destinations are particular
and are only available when you're inside a data flow.
A data flow is a particular control flow task.
It is the part of SSIS that does the actual physical ETL.
It extracts the data from the data source. It has transformations
which manipulate the data while it's en route and it has destinations
where it can put it when it's done with it. One of the cool
things is that an individual data flow can have multiple data
sources, each of them with a different technology, and can then
also have multiple destinations that are going to have a copy
of the same data at every destination or even different copies
of the data on the destination.
When we're dealing with these technologies, the technologies
that are available include things like ADO.net
which is our standard technology for .net data access.
We've got OLE DB and we've got a fun one, a CDC sourse.
>> That's coming up later.
>> Yeah. We're going to look at that one a little bit.
That's change data capture.
We also have some filed technologies, like an Excel file, a Flat
File, an XML file and the one that's kind of cool is the raw
file, George. A raw file is a special file that's a part of SSIS
that is highly optimized for I/O, so that you can have a temporary
storage spot that if you need to drop stuff temporarily as part
of a data flow, you have a good technology to make it very efficient
to do the drop and the retrieval. We also have some technologies
that are destination only and those include SQL Server analysis
services with the ability to have a data mining model training
destination, a dimension processing and a partition processing.
Those are all tasks that are specific to analysis services.
I don't want to get into the details about what they are, but
it's kind of cool that you can drop it directly into there.
It saves you some steps on the analysis services side. And we
also have some Rowset destinations which allow us to drive records
that are going to go out to an external technology like ADO.net
for a .net application or something along those lines.
Data sources and data destinations have to communicate with an
external data sync.
It might be SQL Server or FlatFile or Excel or anything else,
but those sources and destinations rely on connection managers
to define their location. It is another level of that word that
you like so much, abstraction.
>> Abstraction.
>> So by putting that connection manager there, I can change the
details of where the data is coming from without affecting the
definition of the data flow as long as the technologies are compatible.
When you're building those data sources they are typically dependent
on either a source table or a source query. You are not, at
least in SQL Server in the data RDMS technologies, you are not
limited to grabbing the entire contents of the table as where
your data is coming from. You can define it with queries using
joins, aggregations so you can leverage the power, the resources
of that RDMS engine to do as much of the work as possible for you.
>> Very clever.
>> On the destination side, you do have to have a table as the destination.
You can't, and I hope this is kind of obvious to everybody, but
you cannot define a query
as the destination of data. There's got to be something physical there.
>> So you have some things to show and this is within the data
flow task and I'd like to call that the star of the opera.
>> The star of the opera, I like that.
>> The start of the SSIS Opera.
>> There we go.
If we can cut over to the virtual machine, what I mean to do
in this package at this point is I need to actually put a data
flow task in place, because again, this is where my destinations
and my sources and my transformations are applicable. They don't
happen in the control flow, so I'm going to open up that data flow.
At least I thought I was. My double-click doesn't seem to be
working, so we will do it the other way. We'll go up to the
tab and just go in there.
>> There you go.
>> And now what I've got is first off
everything is easier with a wizard, right?
>> Absolutely.
>> If you are not 100 percent sure of the steps or if you want
some prompting, you can use a wizard to go through and do sources
and destinations, but also as you scroll down to the bottom of
the toolbox, we do have the different types of sources and destinations
available right here.
I created an OLE DB connection manager.
I am going to grab an OLE DB source to match that.
I drop it onto my workspace.
What do you see on there that makes you kind of raise your eyebrows
a little bit, George?
>> I see the red circle with a white x.
>> Yeah. You know what that means? That means...
>> Missing.
>> Yep, gotta be configured. SSIS is drag, drop and configure
for the most part, so we're going to double-click and open up
the configuration box for the SSIS OLE DB source.
First thing we need to do is specify our connection manager.
Again, we've got choices here. Any connection manager that's
in the project is available.
It has to be in the project.
Now what's cool is... George, I forgot to create a connection manager.
>> Well, maybe you can do it on the fly.
>> Absolutely, you can do it on the fly. When you're in the source
editor, there is a button right next to
the OLE DB connection manager, the new button that I can use
to drive the creation of a new connection manager.
>> Very convenient.
>> When you get down to the bottom of the wizard after you've
gotten it, you hit the okay button, but the one thing I forgot
is to specify where the data is actually coming from.
You've got choices. You can do it from a table or view, or you
can define a SQL command, a query, or a stored procedure or a
function that is going to bring data back again. I'm going to
leave it at table or view and when I click on the name or table
or view, it goes out and it grabs. I say you know what? I want
the product table.
We come over here to our columns page where all of the columns
in the product table are selected and I have the ability to deselect
columns at which point they no longer become a part of the data flow.
It kind of drives what's going to be there and what's not going
to be there.
Once I've got that all configured, I hit okay.
Notice the x is gone and the things are good to go. So there's
a source, but a source is no good unless you've got somewhere
to put it, so the next thing we need to do is drive a data destination.
Back on the virtual machine, we are going to come down to our
other destinations.
We are going to grab a Flat File destination.
Again I've got my red x; I need to configure it. But before
I configure, this is something you really need to remember, you
need to connect to the flow elements together. You need to create
that pipeline where the data is going to flow through from one
to the next.
I'm going to click and hold on the arrow, drag it down, drop
it, connect them. I've now created the flow between the two which
means my Flat File is now aware of what's going to be coming
into it. If I don't connect them it doesn't know what it's going
to get.
I don't have my connection manager, so here I go. I create a
new one.
I'm going to choose the format of the file, which in this case
is delimited. God bless you there boys.
We are going to give it a name. I'm real inventive, George, so
I'm going to choose the default.
>> There you go.
>> Normally, you would want to give it a name that actually tells
you the destination of what it is.
>> That's detail.
>> Yeah, it is, but it's a good practice to have. I choose the location.
I'm going to put it on my desktop so we can find it real quick.
I give it a name which is going to be products.text.
I hit the open button. I've now defined a location.
I choose whether I want text to be quoted or none, what I want
my header row delimiter to be, whether I want column names.
I go to the columns page and it allows me to choose row delimiter
and column delimiters and when I'm all done I hit okay.
That now creates my connection manager. Again, a little something
you need to know, the mappings aren't done unless you click on
the mappings page.
It'll give you a red x if you don't, so remember to go over to there.
It gives me the matchings of columns that are going to. I can
change those mappings. I can delete a mapping.
I hit okay.
I've now made my connection. When I execute this simple data
flow from a source to a destination, we go out to the desktop...
>> Ba, da, da, da da.
>> There is products.text.
I open it up and voila.
>> Products.
>> Products. All right.
Data sources, data destinations define the starting and ending
point of a data flow.
Now what do we got, George?
>> Next up is using change data capture to extract information.
>> In change data capture what we're going to talk about here
is really a definition of what change data capture is, how to
turn it on in the database and then how to use it to extract data.
Change data capture was first introduced in SQL Server 2008.
It is a technology that is available in Enterprise edition only.
>> Some restrictions apply.
>> Yeah. It's one of those things that really does drive though.
When you've got an enterprise that is doing a lot of operational
systems, a lot of transactional updates change data capture is
going to make your life a lot easier and there's a real good
reason to be running Enterprise edition.
What change data capture does is use log sequence numbers correlated
to times
to determine whether or not a change in data happened during
a particular time frame.
When you enable change data capture on a table, it keeps track
of when those changes occurred so that you can define a specific
timeframe and grab all the changes that happened to that table
within that time frame. It tracks a full history of the changed data.
To turn change data capture on, the first thing you have to do
in any of this stuff is figure it out. You've got to figure
out what you need to track those changes on.
>> So I don't want to turn this on every single table?
>> Absolutely not. The only time you really want to use change
data capture is for the information that is critical to your
data warehouse, the stuff that is used in slowly changing dimensions,
in primary definitions of dimensions and things of that nature.
Once you've gone through that design process, you run a stored
procedure called sts,so_cdc_enable_db.
Just for your information, George, in the future I don't like
saying under score every three seconds so don't be surprised
if you don't hear the under score from here on out.
>> Just skip it.
>> Know that it's going to be there most times though.
Sts,so_cdc_enable_db then turns the technology on for the database
and then for each table that you want that technology set up
for, you are going to run the CDC enable table and you need to
give it as parameter values the schema name, the table name,
the role name and whether or not it supports net changes.
Many times, George, the role is going to be a null value.
To extract the data I've got some transforms
in SSIS that I can use to build an extraction process that is time-based.
Now it's not free. You do need to have a table set up in your
data warehouse to track the times when a load has started and
a load has ended, but then you've got a couple of transforms,
the CDC control transform.
You've got the CDC source transform and the CDC splitter transform.
You use those to mark and pull the data out. The CDC control
is used to mark when an extract process starts, when an extract
process ends.
>> Your high watermark.
>> Yeah. And then you've got CDC source which defines where the
extracted data is coming from and the splitter to separate the
different kinds of updates, inserts, updates and deletes, so
that you can set up different data flows to deal with each one.
>> This looks like typical with a Microsoft product. You have
a very high degree of control over how you want to process your changes.
>> Very much so. Very much so.
>> So why don't you give us a spin here, Rich?
>> So what I'm going to do first off is
close out my SSIS package. Da, da, da ta, da.
And we are going to go back over to management studio where I've
got a script that is going to turn on change data capture.
I've got demo DW, which is the database that we are playing in
and I'm going to enable demo DW to support change data capture.
>> There's the on switch.
>> Done. Boy, that was tough.
>> Not tough.
>> That's actually one of the easiest steps in the entire process, George.
Now I need to define the tables that are going to be involved.
In our design we've identified customers and shippers as two
tables that are going to be the targets of our change data capture process.
I enable that for both of those and they are going to support
net changes.
Now net changes means they are going to keep track of all of
the individual changes that occurred during a time period rather
than just the original value and the ending value of the time period.
>> So interim changes along the way.
>> So if there were six updates to an attribute value during the
extraction period, it would have all six in there.
The next thing I'm going to do here is show how we pull data
out of that change data capture window. I use here, first off
I need to get a mapping of what times correspond to what log
sequence numbers, so SQL can look inside the transaction log.
That function is called CDC
map time 2LSN.
You give it the
qualification of the time period. I've got to be careful here.
There we go. And the starting date, so smallest greater than
the from date is going to get me the first log serial number
of the period largest less than or greater sorry. Largest less
than or equal says give me the last time period, the last LSN
for the to date, and then I'm going to use get net changes, SRC
customers because that get net changes gets generated for each table.
There will be another function for SRC shippers because that's
the other one I turned on.
When I take this script and run it in its entirety, it's going
to return all of the records that were changed. How about that George?
>> No records.
>> We haven't changed anything yet.
We're going to do a couple of updates here. We're going to create
a new customer and we are going to update an existing customer.
Now we go out and we run that grab again
and we get our two changes.
If you look, I happen to know that if we inserted customer ID
6 and we modified customer ID 2.
Dollar operation tells you which operation was done. Was it
an insert? Was it an update? Was it a delete?
Okay? If I run this again,
I'm getting exactly the same results because it's the same period,
but if I use a different period, so I'm going to move the date
time forward, it shows me that no changes have happened.
>> There's your print message.
>> Coming back to the slides, what have we got next?
>> Now we have another technology we can use to populate because
change data tracking isn't going to always work. I'm sorry.
Change data capture isn't always going to be appropriate, so
we have something else to look at two, Rich.
>> That is very true. We have change tracking and change tracking
is a technology that is going to allow us to capture the changes
of data with a little bit less overhead and a little bit less work.
Of course, with that comes a little bit less detail, so change
tracking is, again, a new technology over the last generation
of SQL Server. We're going to talk about what it is. We're going
to talk about how to turn it on. We're going to talk about using
it to extract data.
Change tracking is a lightweight technology that first came out
in SQL Server 2008, just like with CDC,
the change tracking tracks only the fact that a row has changed.
It doesn't have when it changed. It doesn't have what kind of
change it was. It only goes through and keeps track of, hey,
the record changed. You might want to go through and bring the
new one into your data warehouse.
It is designed to be an intermediate solution between fully automated
CDC and fully programmed
change tracking.
>> So maybe a little easier than writing your own entirely custom solution.
>> Absolutely. If you were to try to implement change tracking
all by yourself, you would be writing stored procedures.
You'd be putting tables in. I mean, it would be a fully manual process.
Change tracking allows you to get the bulk of it done
to give you an easily implementable solution to populate your warehouse.
Now just like with CDC, change tracking has to be enabled.
You have to identify the tables that are targeted for change
tracking and you have to enable the individual tables that are
going on as well. Altered database, there's no store procedures.
There's no functions.
It is truly an altered database statement, George. You set
change_tracking equal to on to turn it on for the database and
you enable change_tracking to enable it for the table.
Then to pull change tracking out, you have a data source; you
have a staging database. You have to have an extraction log which
is going to keep track of what you grabbed and when you grabbed it.
You have to get the last version number because that's how this works.
>> All right.
>> It keeps track of version numbers for a record, so you grabbed
that last version number. You extract any records that were higher
than that last version number.
>> That's your high water mark.
>> And then what do you have to do?
>> Update.
>> You've got to write that new high water mark back to your extraction
log so that you know what version of data you actually grabbed.
>> And you have some stuff to show us related to implementing
change tracking.
>> I do. I do.
Going into change tracking...
I need to get my virtual machine up here. There we go.
So in change tracking
first thing I'm going to do is enable the database.
I alter database, set change tracking on and then I have a couple
of switches I can set.
Change retention,
I'm going to set it for seven days.
Auto cleanup,
do I want it to keep track and get rid of old versions after
they've been retrieved?
So I alter the database. I set change tracking on. We're good
to go.
Now I'm going to set snapshot isolation. That allows the database
to look at the data and manipulate the data without other users
being blocked from doing their work.
I alter database demo DW. I allow snapshot isolation so that
when change tracking goes out to retrieve the data, it's not
going to block the operational, the business users from being
able to do their jobs.
I go into sales people, which is the table I'm going to set it
up on, and I enable the change tracking. I put track update,
columns updated to on, which then allows the individual columns
to have versions.
Now I'm going to go get the current version and I'm going to
pull out from salespeople. I've got an extract log.
I'm going to get the current version of
the salespeople. I'm going to put it into
my extract log.
You can see here is the latest version of all of the sales reps.
I've got Wendy. I've got Andy. I've got Matt; they're all there.
I'm going to make some changes to the table.
Put in a new salesperson,
update a salesperson,
now here's where that isolation level, the snapshot comes in
because SQL Server does have to go out to the database to grab
the data and retrieve it and we don't want that to block any
transactions that are being done when the business users are
doing their job.
Change tracking populating the data warehouse, typically you
are dealing with pretty significant data sizes, so these queries
can take time. Snapshot isolation can allow that work to be isolated
away from the work that's ongoing, with transactions, so that
the business can continue to operate freely.
Now I set my isolation level to snapshot.
I go out and grab the previous version from the extract log for
the table I'm targeting.
And then I go out and I retrieve the data from the table.
But I'm using a change table function. The change table function
specifies that I want the changes for the SRC
salespeople since this version.
It's going to inter-join to the salespeople table, so I can grab
original and new.
I am going to highlight that entire script and when I run it
you can see here is my previous version, my current version,
the salesperson ID a name, the information is available to you,
but you don't know what the old ones are. You just know that
this is what the record looked like, looks like now and that
it changed since the last time. Cool?
>> Very cool.
>> All right. I need to back up, because I had a little bit of
a faux pas on my CDC demo.
>> What's that, Rich?
>> I forgot to show the whole SSIS side.
>> There we go.
>> Let's back up a little bit and, luckily all of this stuff is
there and I can get it going. I'm going to go back over to my
SIIS projects and I am going to open up a project that we've
already, that we have already set up and that project is I believe,
there it is.
>> That's some of the glitzy stuff about CDC.
>> Oh yeah. This is the fun stuff. This is the fun stuff.
What I'm going to do is we have a package here called extract
initial shippers.
>> Uh oh, I see red circles there.
>> Yeah. Red circles means we need to configure it, but the cool
part is we've already got our transforms in here, so these two.
I've got the mark initial load which is a CDC control task and
it's telling me that I'm missing a variable.
So in my variable I need to have, when I create and I pull out
when CDC last ran, this is where it's going to store, so I'm
going to create a variable called CDC state.
And then I also need a place to store that in the data warehouse,
so that it's available the next time CDC needs it.
I'm going to create a table in there called DBO.CDC states, and
the state name is going to be in the state name. Now it's cool
because it creates the create script when you click on new, so
you can modify that if you want to or need to.
I'm going to run that and I've now created my CDC states.
Now the thing you have to be careful of when you're configuring
these control tasks is this control operation.
Notice that there are different kinds of values. An initial
load start, an initial loads and a get processing range, mark
processed range, mark CDC start, they all have their use.
Because I am doing an initial load, I need this control operation
to do an initial load start.
I hit okay, and now I've got extract all shippers. That's the
process that's going to go out. It's just a straight data flow
task that's going to go out and it's going to grab data from
SQL and load it into the staging table for shipper inserts.
The last thing I'm going to do is mark my initial load end.
The control operation is set to load end.
Here's my variable, CDC state.
Here's the table, the state name. Everything's good to go >> Perfect.
>> Now when I run this
it goes through. It grabs all of the records. Now we're going
to go back over to
management studio for just a minute, because I really want to
show you what that looks like.
In the demo DW in the tables here's my CDC state table.
When I go out and grab the records
there is the state variable that gets written. Isn't that a
wonderfully descriptive and highly user friendly value?
>> Yeah, that's a little spooky.
>> Okay. The one thing I will tell you, see that mark right there,
right at the beginning IL end?
>> Yep.
>> IL start, IL end, initial load.
>> There you go.
>> Okay? And there are other values that go in there as well.
So there's the initial load process, but the other thing that
we have is the ongoing updates.
We have an extract changed shippers.
When I open it up, George, we have some configuration to do.
>> That's right. Work to do.
>> First thing I have my starting.
I have a,
I don't have a variable, so guess what?
We create our variable because it's a package level variable.
We're going to get into that more later on today.
And again, now I want to choose the table. I don't need to create
it this time because I created it last time. The control operation,
get processing range.
And again, down here at the bottom, mark processed, the control
operation, everything is set up correctly. I've got to clean.
I go into my data flow.
Here is my CDC source.
CDC source, remember we talked about that, back with data sources?
>> Yep, one of the sources.
>> Absolutely. I need to identify the table that I'm grabbing
it from, which is the CDC enabled table in the operational system
that contains the data I'm loading into my warehouse.
I also
need to give it the processing mode and the state variable.
That then is going to tell me the columns that are going to be available.
Now these are the columns from the table itself. The shippers
table is not a real big one, George.
Just an example. It gives me the starting LSN, the operation
and the update mask. Now that operation is going to be critical
a little bit later on.
>> Very much.
>> There is my get records, my CDC source. That drops into my splitter.
In the splitter I give it a name and then I come over here to
my input columns. There or all of my input columns, the output
alias and now I've got my input and output properties. This is
usually a very, very easy configuration. You don't really have
to do much except drop it in, hook it up, check all of your tabs
to make sure that they are good and then we go to our output.
Now the cool thing here, notice, I've got an insert output.
I've got an update output. I've got a delete output.
The splitter will read that operation variable and will then
automatically put each record to the data flow that it needs
to go to, because I'm going to have a different operation to
do on records that have been inserted versus records that have
been updated versus records that have been deleted. Cool?
>> Very cool.
>> Are right. So let's go and update some data.
I'm going to go back in. I have
an update shippers, which is going to create a new shipper.
It's going to delete a shipper. It's going to change the value.
I run it and now when we go back to integration services,
I'm going to cancel that. I'm not sure why it wanted to close.
I'm going to execute
and I have records that have gone through. Everything is good
to go.
We head back over to management studio and now if I look at my
staging shipper deletes, staging shipper deletes which is the
destination, staging
shipper inserts.
They're empty. I'm not quite sure why they're empty. I might
have had a connection manager issue there.
>> No. Actually, entertain me Rich. Just go run the package again.
Once in a while, there's a little delay with that, so go ahead
and run the package again.
>> Yeah.
Oh. It did not update.
If you look at my, let's see.
We're going to run that package again. This is an interesting one.
It might have been a time period issue because the transaction
log hadn't changed sequence numbers.
>> There you go.
>> So here we go. Now we've got the output in there and that's
what it is. There is a delay sometimes because checkpointing,
transaction log sequence numbers don't always update right away,
so when you make a change and then three seconds later you run
a transfer package, well guess what? The log serial number that
CDC is going to grab is the one previous to where the change occurred.
Once that log serial number updates, the change goes through.
Ba da bing ba da bang. Good catch George. I forgot about that one.
>> That's what happens.
>> That then is where we have been today. We've talked about
on this module data sources, connection managers. We've talked
about change data capture. We've talked about change tracking,
the different things that are going in.
>> That was a full module. There's a lot more to come.
Thanks for attending the implementing and data warehouse with
SQL Server 2012 Jumpstart. Let's get up, move around, take a
ten minute stretch and we will see you back for lots of gymnastics
with SSIS coming up.
>> See you in a few.