[Music]
Welcome back, everyone, to Implementing a Data
Warehouse with SQL Server 2012 Jumpstart.
I'm George Squillace. I'm here with my colleague, Rich Currey.
Lots of good stuff up in this next session. Before I pass the
football to you, Rich, I just want to give a shout out to our
project manager Alice.
>> We couldn't have done it without her.
>> And the wizards behind the multimedia gear, some heavy gear,
Danny and Barry.
>> Thanks, guys!
>> So, Rich, what's up in this module?
>> Well, we've been talking about data flow. Data flow is the
middle part of the ETL process, but you know what?
Data flow is only one piece of what can be a pretty complex work
flow that may involve things like sending emails, like accessing
FTP sites, going out and looping through files in a directory.
All sorts of stuff that is peripheral to the actual process of
extracting data, transforming it and loading it, but it is as
integral a part of the process as any data flow can be, and that's
called control flow. So what we're headed in to in this module
is an overview that's going to talk about all of the different
containers that are available, the tasks that they can contain
that get executed. We're going to talk about how to tie these
tasks together and control the sequence of execution with precedents constraints.
We're going to deal with the ability to pass information form
one task to another, or from one package to another, or just
from an external environment to the e-package itself, variables
in parameters.
And last, but certainly not least, George, checkpoints in transactions,
being able to control whether or not data is actually saved
and whether or not we can pick up in the middle of a flow if
it breaks.
>> There you go.
>> So lets start off with containers and tasks. Containers and
tasks are the two pieces that we use to develop a workflow.
The containers
take a series of tasks and treat them as a single unit and the
tasks themselves
that define the pieces of work that we're going to do.
So some of the common tasks that we deal with, well, they're
execute tasks.
Execute SQL is going to give us the ability to create an SQL
command and pass it out to an already BMS system for execution.
Now, the nature of the command deals with the nature of the connection.
If it's a SQL Server it's going to be a T SQL. If it is non-SQL
Server it's going to be another language. We also have to ability
to develop modular workflows by creating individual packages
that encapsulate a series of tasks that maybe has to execute
in three or four different processes.
We have a task called the execute package task where we can now
configure it to go out, grab a different SSIS package, and force
that to run a workflow. So we have to ability to build a package
to accomplish a specific process, and then to use that process
in many other separate processes.
We also have, speaking of process, the execute process task.
Execute process allows us to go out and get a non-SSIS
executable and cause that to execute. Maybe it's going to be
to open up a file using an application, maybe there is an executable
that goes out and reaches out to an application to get data,
whatever it might be.
Then we have the file system task. File system task is one of
those that gets used quite a bit because, if you think, there
are a whole lot of different areas where people bring Excel files,
CSV files, Word documents, whatever they might be, and they drop
them to be processed at a later point. The file system task
gives us the ability to manage those external files. Maybe we're
going to copy them to a new location. Maybe we're going to create
a new directory to move them into. Whatever it might be, that's
where the file system task goes.
We then have one, which is real important. You need to know
this task, the send mail task.
Send mail is for notification.
Now, many times when you've got a notification
you need to tell people when something fails, when something
is completed, the send mail task allows you to send that email
out so that other folks are aware of when that process is completed.
>> Super useful.
>> Yeah, it requires an SMTP Connection Manager.
>> No surprise.
>> No! But SMTP is pretty easy. You need to IP address of the
SMTP server and you need potentially, depending on configuration,
some authentication information.
Finally, you've got a task grouping. Now, I've got to tell you,
George, this is not an actual task. It doesn't accomplish anything.
Task grouping is more about design than it is anything else.
Task grouping allows me to take a series or a group of tasks
and associate them visually in the editor so that I can hide
them or move them around as a unit, rather than having to deal
with them one by one. So if you've got a large workflow that
has 50, 60, 100, 200 tasks you can group them into units so that
you're not constantly scrolling all over the place.
Collapse each group and then just expand it when you're working
with the tasks in that group.
Now, along with the common tasks we have a series of containers,
and these unlike groups, are actual execution issues. So I have
a sequence container. A sequence container takes a series of
tasks and turns it into a single execution unit so that the success
or failure of all of them together
is determined by the success or failure of each individual one.
So no longer are we talking about each individual task as its
own, but grouping them together for execution purposes so that
only when they've all completed would I move on.
Next we have the for loop. For loop, if you're a developer, if
you've done any coding, you've probably run into a for loop before.
The for loop allows you to create an iteration.
So I may have three or four tasks in there that are going to
run repeatedly.
A for loop you define how many times you want to run through it.
A starting point and ending point determines a set number of executions.
Now, set number of executions?
I'm going to give you an example here.
If I have Excel files that are being dropped in a directory, George...
>> Sure.
>> Let's say I have ten sales reps out there and their job is
on Friday of every week, by 5 P.M.
they need to drop that Excel file in a directory so that I can
import it into the data warehouse. Maybe they're putting their
next two weeks forecast in.
So Fred is a sales rep, and Fred is at a client until 5:15 on Friday.
My other nine sales reps got their files there, but Fred didn't.
So if I were expecting ten files and only nine of them show up,
what's that going to do to my for loop?
>> Kaboom!
>> That would be right. It is a gone-er. It's going to look for
that tenth iteration, no file there, done.
So instead of a for loop I have a for each loop.
The for each loop iterates through a collection, a collection
of files, a collection of objects, a collection of things that
you can think of. Anything that you can iterate through you can
have a for each loop
to do it, and all of them contain a series of tasks. You define
the tasks that are going to be looped through.
So what do you think, George? Should we go take a look at it?
>> Yeah, give us the tour.
>> All right. So here I've got a workflow, and in this workflow...
I'm going to zoom out a little bit so you can see it's not exactly
just a simple one. It's got a for loop, it's got a sequence container,
it goes out and sends and email, creates a folder, and I apologize
the graphic's a little bit tough to read. But as you can see
when you zoom out to the point where you can read it, it gets
now you can't see the whole workflow. But the key there is that
in my for loop I've got an open file. Kind of the situation
we were talking about where I'm going to go through and grab
a file and do something with it. Well, if I go into my for loop
you can see I've got a fixed set of expressions.
The initial expression, which is where the starting point, the
eval, where it's going to stop, and what you do at the end of
every loop, the assign expression. So this is going to go through
from one to four.
Now, what happens if one of those files is missing, George?
>> What's going to happen?
>> It's going to blow up.
>> Uh-oh.
>> So having a fixed number of iterations is not what I want.
I'm going to replace that with a for each loop.
And now I can configure in the for each loop
the collection
that I want it to use.
I've got a series of different kinds. I can do a file enumerator.
I can do an item enumerator where I define what the item is.
I can do an ADO enumerator where I give it a source object an
ADO enumerator deals with records in a record set.
I have an ADO.NET schema row set to go through the schemas in
a database so I could process all of the tables in each schema
for example.
I also
have a variable enumerator to loop through a series of variables,
a node list and a server management objects iterator, which
connects to the SQL Server management objects.
So for each file enumerator there are a couple of things you
are going to put in here. Number one, you're going to specify
the folder that it's going to point to. And this is real straightforward.
It's just a browser. Pick it and off you go. I'm going to leave
it on that C drive.
And then you specify the pattern for the files that it wants
to hit.
If I wanted all Excel files I could say Excelxx for example,
and it's going to grab only those files with that extension.
And then I can tell it do I want to use retrieve the name and
extension, just the fully qualified path, or just the name?
And I can even, George, ask it to go down and grab all the subfolders
if I want.
>> Recursion!
>> I love recursion. It makes it easy. And then finally, I choose
the variable that I want to put the value into and the index
point of it when I'm all done I hit Okay, and I have now configure
my loop container. It's going to put the file name into the f
name variable. I now populate and drag any tasks that I want
into that for each loop and deal with it.
>> So whatever task I drag in there it will loop through whatever
files happen to be in that folder with a variable number of objects?
>> Exactly. So if there are five files there it will loop five times.
If there are 25 files there it loops 25 times. You don't need
to worry about it.
>> Good programming resiliency!
>> I like that! I like that a lot!
>> Well, we have more to look at along the lines of workflow.
So precedence constraints come up next, Rich.
>> So when we're talking about a precedence constraint, a precedence
constraint very simply we've got multiple tasks to execute and
a workflow, right George? And each of those tasks typically you
have to do task one before you do task two because there are dependencies.
>> Absolutely.
>> If I have files in directory A and I'm processing them from
directory B I need to make sure they get moved from A to B first.
So what the order that things happen is determined by the precedence constraints.
Now, you've got two kinds. You've got very simple ones, which
are just drag and drop, and you've got more complex ones where
you can put in expressions where it's not just dependent on a
task status, maybe it's dependent on a piece of information in
a variable as to whether or not it's going to run as well.
Now, the simple constraints very simply, every task that you
configure in the control flow is going to have an arrow.
You grab the arrow, you drag it and drop it on the task that
you want to run next, and then you have a choice, George.
>> What's the choice?
>> The choice is do I want it to run as soon as the previous task
is done?
DO I want to it to run only if the previous task completes successfully?
Or do I want it to run only if the previous task runs unsuccessfully?
As an example, I have a task that copies files from directory
A to directory B.
When that task is completed I'm then going to take those files
and put them into a dataflow.
Now, if the copy happens successfully I want to run the dataflow, right?
>> Yup.
>> If the copy runs unsuccessfully is there any sense in doing
to dataflow?
>> No.
>> No! Because the files aren't there! But what would make sense
is to now send an email to somebody saying that the copy failed.
So now I put in my file system task and I create a dataflow task.
I connect it with success precedence, I put in a send mail task,
I connect it with the failure precedence.
Now here's the cool part, George.
>> The cool part is?
>> If I don't connect any tasks, guess what?
>> What's that?
>> They run at the same time. If I've got four tasks and none
of them are connected to each other they're going to run in parallel.
But if I've got two tasks that need to run and then the third
one runs and finally I've got two tasks afterwards, I could have
multiple predecessors, I could have multiple successors to any task.
>> Nice.
>> It is.
>> Lots of control. And speaking of control, it goes even crazier
than that.
>> Yeah, it does, because I have to tell you,
having a dependency from one task to the other is cool, but sometimes
it's not enough. Sometimes I may have an external dependency
maybe a variable where a value needed to be set to a specific
value in order to trigger the next flow. Maybe I've got a package
where when that package is executed
the IDE or the user or whoever is causing it to run has to ability
to set a parameter value that says if it's one I want to do this,
if it's two I want to do that, if it's three I want to do something else.
It's a choice, a conscious decision being made by the person executing.
So now I can add in
a condition over and above a previous task that's going to go
out, check the parameter value, and only if the previous task
completed and the value was three is it going to go do this next one.
Okay? So let's flip over, take a look at what we got here.
I am going to illustrate very quickly. We have some further
on, shall we say, dependencies here.
This first one, if you look, we have a connection between our
for each loop and our sequence container, and the color of the
connection, you can see it in the GUI, is green.
Now, I am going to throw something out here because it's important
for people to know. There are a lot of folks out there that are
colorblind, so you're not going to be able to just look at those
connectors and see green, red, or and we had this argument yesterday,
either blue or black on completion. Because I got to tell you,
George and I went back and forth for at least five minutes trying
to figure out is it blue or is it black? Okay? Yeah. This is black!
That's blue!
[Laughter]
It wasn't as obvious. So if you are colorblind let's go back
to the VM, I'm going to show you the trick. You right click
on it and it will tell you success, failure, and completion with
the check mark. And guess what? That's the way that you choose
it as well.
>> The condition is what matters, not the color.
>> Absolutely. And no, for those of you that are wondering, it
is not configurable for color. All right. So we've chosen our
success condition here and you can see down here I've got my
blue, is it blue is it black, arrow.
If I look it does say the word completion right on top of it.
So another indicator without having to right click on it, it
does indicate failure completion.
Now, some of these are solid lines, some are dotted lines.
>> Curious.
>> Yeah. That's an indicator as well.
The solid line means that it is a simple constraint. It is only
dependent on the status of the previous task.
The dotted line, however, is an indication that there are multiple
constraints involved here. It's not just the sequence container failed.
So let's take a look this particular constraint right here, which
is failure. I right click on it, and I'm going to choose edit
this time, George.
>> Fun.
>> And you can see that I now have here an evaluation operation
of constraint. I'm going to go in and change it to expression
and constraint.
Now, I designate is it a logical or or is it a logical and?
Either one is okay but I specify now my expression.
And this is where I could go out and say, for example, I only
want this to fire if counter is greater than... Woops!
What did I do? I double clicked didn't I?
>> Just over type, no problem.
>> Yeah, we'll fix that. Drag it in again.
>> Perfect.
>> Is greater than five. So now I've set up a condition where
I've got two
conditions that are in play, they both must be true.
If the previous task fails and the value of the counter variable
is greater than five
we have the next task, which is our send failure notification
that's going to run.
And you can see the fx right next to it that tells you you have
an expression condition in there as well. Cool?
>> Very cool.
>> All right.
So what do we have coming up next sir?
>> And next up we have variables and parameters. Some other ways
we can make packages dynamic.
>> You mean now I get to explain all of that stuff I've been talking
about with the variables?
>> Well, you dropped some hints earlier. You told us more was
coming up. So now the time has come.
>> Okay. Let's drop into it. Variables and parameters, they're
very similar. Okay? A variable is a storage location inside the
package that's going to store a value. It requires a name.
It requires that you have a data type. It requires that you have...
I messed up here I got confused.
An initial value.
It has a length in some cases, depending on what it is.
And it stores a piece of information. Now, there are a couple
of kinds of variables. You've got system variables, which are
predefined by SSIS, they can store information like the execution
time, like the user name, the name of the package and some of
those GUIDS.
>> Package ID, execution ID.
>> 16 bit hexadecimal numbers that are guaranteed random. I hate
looking at them they are way too long.
They all start with a prefix of the word system and then colon
colon the name of the variable. They're easy. But I'm not done.
I can create my own.
Those are going to start with user colon colon and will follow
with the name of the variable, and then I give it the scope,
which is what executables are going to be able to access the
value, I give it its data type, and I give it its initial value.
>> I don't remember if you talk about scope more coming up or not.
>> I do, but let's define it right here and right now. So if
I have a variable that's defined inside a specific dataflow,
for example.
If I'm outside that dataflow does the variable exist?
No. So it's limited to the scope of whatever is inside that dataflow task.
Now, scope can be at the task level. It can be at the container level.
Scope can even be the package level.
>> Package-wide.
>> Absolutely. You are defining where that variable is going to live.
And in defining where it lives you're identifying all of the
pieces of the package that are then going to be able to access
the value.
>> Can I mention one more thing, Rich?
>> You can, George. One of the things that was nasty in SSIS,
pardon me, something I didn't quite appreciate previously was
that once you defined scope and SSIS you stepped in a bear trap
and could not change that. And now there's a nice little button
where you can change the scope from task, container, package,
up and down at will. It's very nice.
>> Yes it is. It is very, very helpful.
>> But we have something new in 2012. What's that, Rich?
>> We have parameters.
Now, parameters are kind of like variables at the project level.
Okay? A package parameter is available at the package level.
It allows an external entry of a value to what's basically a variable.
So, for example, I could set a file name if I had a package where
I could feed the file name in. I could set the name of the file
I wanted the package to run against.
I also have project parameters, which now are only available,
you have to be careful, if you're doing project deployment.
>> That's going to come up later.
>> It is. That's going to be mod 6, so stay tuned there.
Parameters have default values. They can be set at design time.
If I set it at design time and I don't change it any other way,
then that design value is the one that gets used when it executes.
When I deploy a package I can assign a default value to the deployed package.
Now, when I deploy that means I'm making it available in either
SQL Server or the SSIS process.
And at that point I have the ability to set that parameter value
for the package. It overrides the design value and makes it available
again to everything inside the package. And then we have one
further setting. When I go to execute it I can override that
stored value, so now I've got the design default. I've got the
server default. I've got the execution value, which sticks for
only that one.
Project parameters, I'm sorry, parameters are only available
in the project deployment model. Be the package level or the
project level.
>> But there are other ways to make packages dynamic.
>> There are. They do use parameters in many cases and it's called
property expressions.
Now, if you notice when we go back and look at all of these control
flow tasks and dataflow tasks they are all configurable, right?
>> Sure.
>> And we do that by setting property values. Maybe it's an initial
counter, maybe it's the directory to look at for a for each file enumerator.
Maybe it's the name of the server where a database exists and
a connection manager. We've got all these properties
that make values that determine the behavior of that executable,
of that object. Now, a property expression allows me to dynamically
set the values based on the properties of a specific object in
SSIS based on a parameter or variable value.
So now I don't need to know what the name of a server is when
I deploy out to a particular server. I can set a property expression,
which is going to go out and grab a parameter, which is populated
with the server value so that whenever that executable runs,
and depending on where it runs, the property is configured based
on the value of the parameter.
Okay? Lets go out and take a quick gander at something here,
and I think what I'm going to do is, let's
see, I've got a connection manager here.
And my connection manager I'm going to double click on it.
That brings up the editor. We can see the usage type and all that.
But you know what? I'm also going to go out to edit.
I'm not getting it on that one.
I got to get it on, where is it? I'm not getting it there I should
be getting it there.
>> Remind me, what were you looking for?
>> I should have been getting some property expressions on there.
So we'll flip over here to the file system task editor because
I'll be able to get it on that one.
>> Or go to the properties pane, one or the other.
>> Yeah, but here's the key. We've got two pages. We've got the
general, which has the regular normal entry of values into those
editors, and we have expressions.
When I go in to expressions I click on the ellipsis and now I
get to choose the property.
Let's say that I'm going to look at is
the source path variable? The name, for example. And I can go
in and now I've got my variables and parameters together I can
take and I can drop it into the expression. I hit okay and now
dynamically the name property will now take on the value of user
colon colon f name.
>> And I saw that expression editor, Rich. So that means you
have all the things available, parameters, variables, functions,
and conversion functions. All those are available.
>> Absolutely. The only thing you can't access, depending on where
you are, is you will not be able to access information in the dataflow.
This is only to be able to access parameters and variables.
So what do we got coming up now, George?
>> Next we're going to look at maintaining package integrity,
checkpoints, and transactions. But I know you have a lot to talk
about there.
>> You know, this is actually one of my favorite topics.
Whenever you've got a complex workflow there is at least a possibility
that something may not go right. I don't know about you, I don't
get that too much.
I really do make packages that work right every time.
>> You're captain wonderful.
But there are other factors too.
>> No. Sometimes it's outside of my control, I admit it. But checkpoints
and transactions are two ways that we can manage the behavior
of our packages, the behaviors of our dataflow. When it comes
to persisting data into the destination.
That's really what it's all about. We have two scenarios here.
One is the dataflow is interrupted midstream with a problem,
and we want everything that's already happened to stay happened
and then pick up where we left off.
>> Perfect.
>> The other scenario is I've gotten part way through my flow
and everything that's happened has to be successfully completed
with everything that hasn't happened. So I can't let
what's been done stay done. I need to undo it. And that's what
checkpoints and transactions accomplish.
>> So you have some more detail here for these.
>> Yup. Checkpoints are
files that are created by SSIS while the package is running that
keep track of what has been completed by the package.
So if I have a 10-step dataflow or a 10-step control flow that
includes three different data flows, and I get through step seven
and then I get a failure, a checkpoint can record the fact that
step seven was completed but step eight never finished and it
had to be undone.
Now, when I restart that package, George, and run it a second
time it reads that file, skips the first seven steps because
they've been done, and picks up with eight and finishes through.
When you've got long-running packages that are working with a
lot of data, checkpoints can really, really, really help you
to not have to repeat things.
>> Sure. Let's say I just spent two hours FTPing a bunch of files.
The files still load in fine but something with further processing
failed, you know, why re download two hours worth of files.
>> Absolutely correct. Absolutely correct. It saves you from
repeating significant chunks of work that were already successfully done.
Now, packages are configurable. You have to tell the package
if it's going to use checkpoints. The default is that it will
not use checkpoints. But you can configure it to use a checkpoint
file if one exists or you can configure it to require a checkpoint file.
Now, the difference between those two is that if it doesn't exist
SSIS will assume that it starts from the beginning of the flow,
and will only look at that checkpoint file as a restart if the
file exists. If you do require it then that file must be there
at all times.
So if you have a workflow where it's going out to a directory
that's outside of your control, I recommend using "if exists"
as the setting because you can't really, you're not in control
of whether somebody is going to delete that file. If the directory
is under your control then you've got a much more reasonable choice.
Now, the other piece of this is transactions. Now, a transaction
is a unit of work that must succeed or fail as a unit. Now, think
of this, George.
You've got two bank accounts in two separate banks.
So you go into bank A and you fill out a transfer slip that says
I want to move a thousand dollars from A to B.
You go and thy withdraw the money form A and send it off to B,
everything works fine and everybody's happy.
But lets assume for a minute that it came out of A,
went to B, and B wasn't able to deposit it.
Now, if B doesn't tell A that it didn't get the money what happens?
>> Uh-oh. Mismatch.
>> You're out a thousand bucks. Are you a happy boy?
>> Not happy.
>> Okay. Let's go the other way.
A goes to withdraw it, it fails,
B deposits it anyway. Who's happy now?
>> Nice.
>> Yeah, George just got a thousand bucks.
But the bank that he took it from is probably not going to be
thrilled with him. A transaction can wrap those two behaviors
together so that if either on of them fails then neither one
of them works.
And that's the way I like to look at it. It's an all or nothing.
The transactions exhibit what are called the acid properties.
They are atomic, which means they cannot be broken down any further
into finer levels of independent work, and that's the key, independent.
They are consistent, which means when everything's done the answers
that you expect are the ones that are there.
They are isolated, which means nothing else can touch the data
while the transaction is working with the data, and they are
durable because when it's done it's permanent and it can't be undone.
You can set up transactions at any container level.
You can set it up at the package level at a sequence container,
at a loop container, you can even set them up at a task level.
The settings there are three of them. They can be required,
which means it will always start a new transaction when it gets there.
They can be supported, which means if there's a transaction it
will join it and they can be not supported, which means even
if there is a transaction out there I don't care. I'm not going
to deal with it. I am ignoring you.
>> And you have some things to show too.
>> Why, yes.
Yes, I do.
Let us now
go into another demo I've got here, which is going to come one
now, there you go.
I've got a package here called load data.
Load data has three steps in it, a create folder step, a copy
file step, and a load to staging table.
Now, I want this to use checkpoints. I want tit to be able to
pick up if something happens.
So the first thing I need to do is I need to display the properties.
So I'm going to go up to view properties window, and now when
I click anywhere in the background I get my package property.
In my package properties, right up at the top when you're in
category view of the properties, is the checkpoint properties.
I've got checkpoint file name, checkpoint usage, and saved checkpoints.
Now, the first thing I'm going to tell you is if you're going
to use checkpoints this has to be true.
Otherwise there is not sense in doing it. Then I configure my
usage, never, if exists, or always. I'm going to set up an if exists.
I'm now going to go to my checkpoint file name and I'm going
to specify where that checkpoint is going to live. I'm going
to put it down here in my D directory under the checkpoints right
where the package is and I'm going to call it loaddata.chk.
Now, I used a convention there. It's not a requirement.
That chk can be absolutely any extension that you can think of.
>> I've seen that before though.
>> But it's an easy one. It's easy because it indicates that it's
a checkpoint file and people are going to recognize that.
So I open it. Now, guess what I need to do next, George?
>> What's next?
>> I need to actually configure each of these tasks so that the
checkpoint will occur.
>> There you go.
>> So each task has a property called fail parent on failure,
and you can see the default value of that is false.
That means that if that individual task were to fail, the parent
would just keep right on trucking.
The parent in this case is the package. I've also go fail package
on failure, which will do the exact same thing if you set that
one on subtasks, maybe I have tasks in side containers.
Then even if one that's three or four levels down fails it doesn't
matter what its parents are set to it will just fail the package.
So you set that for all your critical tasks.
>> Super granular.
>> Absolutely. I set that to true and now the package will fail
if the task is unsuccessful.
I'm going to do that for all three steps because these are all
critical steps.
Now, notice I'm just double clicking and I'm changing it.
You can use the drop down, but when you've got toggle switches
like that it's easier to double click sometimes.
>> That's a good trick to show.
>> Yeah, I like that one. So now I'm going to start debugging.
It goes in and
oh, that's interesting. It thought the file was already there
because it skipped over the first two. Now, I'm looking here
and I've got no green checks and a red x, so there must have
been a checkpoint file out there already that I didn't see.
So let's go out to the file system. I'm going to keel out of
the debugger. I'm going to go to the file system.
We're going to go to our D drive 1077,
demo 7
- nope, demo 6. I got the wrong one there. Sorry about that.
Nope.
>> There was a checkpoints folder.
>> Yeah, but I've got to find the right spot.
There it is.
I'm going to delete that so that it's not there.
And now when we run it
you can see the first two ran, the third one didn't. So that
just goes to show you.
If that checkpoint file exists, and I didn't catch the fact that
it was already there when I set this up, it
will use that checkpoint file.
So a great way on the if exists is to get rid of the checkpoint file.
When I close this we are going to go back to that directory.
I should have kept that open, shouldn't I, George?
>> It's all right.
>> It only takes a second.
Mod 5 checkpoints, there's my load data check. Let's go take
a look at what's in there.
>> Now you're playing Curious George.
>> A little bit. Look it is an XML file and that xml file has
things like the fact that it is a DTS checkpoint, the name space,
the package ID. It's got variables like the container ID and
the DTS result.
That's how it keeps track of where it was.
As long as that file is there I go back to run this a second
time and now you can see it reads the content of the file, it
picks up with the tasks that were already there.
>> So a folder was made and a bunch of files were FTPed or copied
from some other process but the failure occurred after that,
why repeat that initial work?
>> Absolutely correct. So let's take a look at one more thing
in here because we talked about transactions.
So let's go back in here and take a look at how to set them up.
So what I'm going to do is again, I'm going to go to the package level.
And at the package level I'm going to look for a property, and
give me a second here because I don't have them all memorized.
>> There's only thousands.
>> Yeah, there are only thousands. There's my transaction option.
Now, if you look at the transaction option the initial value
is supported. So if this were to get called from another package
that was in the midst of a transaction, then it would use that
transaction, it would join into it and become a part of it.
If I want this package to create a transaction I'm now going
to choose the value required.
That means, woops, what did I do?
I must have misclicked.
>> We saw required though.
>> That should have gone in there though.
Not supported works, but required is not showing...
oh. Save checkpoints or transactions. Yeah, the two are mutually exclusive.
I forgot about that.
So lets go back up here to our save checkpoints, set it to false,
now I can go in and I can set my not supported to required and
we're good. It will still use a checkpoint file that's there
but it's not necessarily going to save things. Now that I've
got required I can go into my individual tasks and I can change
each one. Now, again the default value for each task is supported.
So when I configure the individual package it will automatically,
all of the control flow tasks in it will join that transaction.
If any one of them fail, then they all will fail and it will
undo the work that was done.
Now, here I am, I'm talking about create folder, copy file, load
the staging table. Those aren't all database stuff, are they?
No? But yet I can still put a transaction on there.
Transactions are not just for databases.
There is a service that's available within Windows called the
Distributed Transaction Coordinator.
The Distributed Transaction Coordinator is an external process
that Windows, that SQL Server, that many different services and
servers can talk to even on separate boxes that can coordinate
the activities from one machine from one process to another.
Then when an individual process is successful the DTC is notified
of that success. When all of the processes are successful it
sends that notification back to wherever the processes that were
involved in the transaction live.
Once they're all successful we get commit. If anything happens,
if any of them fail we come back out of it and none of them work.
>> There we go.
>> All right. So we talked about a lot in this module, didn't we?
>> Lots of dev stuff.
>> Yeah. We defined the control flow and the workflow elements
that go into it and how to connect them together. How to set
up conditional execution.
>> Containers.
>> We talked about containers with for each loops and for loops
and sequence. We talked a little bit about grouping and how that
works for the ability to work with things. And then we went
into package control from the standpoint of checkpoints and transactions.
How to combine and how to interrupt.
Setting up the dependencies and how to stop it in the mid stream
and how to be able to pick it up again later.
>> That's a handful. I bet everybody's ready for a break.
>> I know I am.
>> Well, thanks, everybody, for continuing with us on Implementing
a Data Warehouse with SQL Server 2012 Jumpstart. Let's take
a 10-minute stretch or so. We'll see you back at the top of the hour.