[Music]
>> So you ready to do a little Help and help me out and...
>> Yeah, do a little help, help, help?
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Because guys, this is probably the most important section of
the entire day, and it may not even seem like it at first, but
I swear to God that this is the most important thing. And here's
why it's so important.
When you go to PowerShell, you're going to stare at that console
and go now what do I do? This is the answer.
So...
>> Kierkegaard called that the dizziness of freedom. You look
at that prompt and you can do anything. You're like uh, what
do I do?
>> And it is, a lot... it affects all of us. And a lot of us,
you get past that with what we're going to do now.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> The Help system.
But I think for a lot of folks, I see it all the time, okay,
it made sense when you were doing it, but now I'm staring at
that console and I just don't know what to do. And I don't know
where to go.
And they create a solution for you. This is a beautiful solution.
So what we're going to start off with is looking at the Help
system, showing you how to get it updated, and this is actually
a fascinating feature in V3. Remember I was saying you're going
to want to be using V3, and this is going to be one of them.
The most important thing is the discoverability that the Help
system provides you. Basically, it is your... it is your Bing
for PowerShell. It is... it answers all of your needs and all
of your questions. And also, we're going to show you how to read
syntax and so forth. So let's get started with the Help stuff.
And here in about ten minutes we'll take a break and then we'll
come back in and look at all the syntax and start getting into it.
So first of all, why you need Help. Well, I just want to go
to bullet number two.
>> Exactly.
>> Can we talk about this? I'm a smart guy, but I'm not smart
enough to just know everything.
>> Absolutely.
>> So tell me what the idea here is.
>> Yeah, so one of my jokes, although it's actually true, that
is PowerShell is such a great product because I'm such a deeply
flawed human.
It's true. I'm a deeply flawed human, and I was in a position
to say, hey, let's build a tool that helps me, right?
>> Right.
>> So concretely, you know, I can't remember all that stuff either.
I'm a terrible typist, et cetera. So you'll see there's a ton
of stuff in PowerShell that helps with those things. So really
is a goal to not be able to memorize things. Actually, there's
a great story. They recently did a study of Unix admins and came
up with the support, and I was really amused by this, because
basically about 25, 30 years ago they had done exactly the same
study and produced exactly the same results. And here's what
they did. They took a bunch of beginner Unix admins and expert
Unix admins, and they said, hey, here's a test. If you wanted
to do this, how do you do it? A written test. And what was interesting
was that we scored these, there wasn't very much of a difference
between the expert Unix admins and the beginning Unix admins.
And so then it's like, oh, why are we paying these experts so
much money, you know. They can't...
objectively, they're not that much better than just some beginner, right?
And so then they said, okay, well now let's put them in front
of a machine and give them a set of tasks. And what you saw
was this huge difference in performance, that the experts were
able to perform amazing things that the beginners struggled with.
And the conclusion was that what expert Unix guys are great at
is not knowing things, but in figuring things out, okay?
And so that's the deal. This is not about you sitting there saying,
hey, it should work this way, right. No, no, no, that's not
the deal. The deal is, hey, let me figure out how to do things.
And so that's what 's all about. What you're going to learn
is a schema, right you're going to learn a set of things.
You're going to learn how to learn, and then you're going to
use those techniques over and over again. And that's why, once
you learn how to use PowerShell, and you're managing, say, Exchange,
then when someone says, oh, we got this link server, it's like
well, let me have at it. And you'll be able to go and you'll
be able to learn and learn and learn and just figure stuff out.
>> So basically, what you're telling me is that the first time
I walked up to a Unix guy and I said hey, how did you do that,
and he turned around and usually barked at me going, RTFM, he
was actually trying to educate me. He wasn't just being a terrible person?
>> No. Both.
>> Oh, okay. He was being both. And I think this is really the
moral of the story is you're not going to be able to memorize
stuff, guys. PowerShell V2 had, like, 236 core commandlets.
Okay. I might be able to memorize those. When you start working
with products, you know, Exchange has, depending on your version
of Exchange, has between 535 and 610 commandlets. You've got
500 and some odd commandlets for SharePoint. You've got 100
and some odd commandlets for Active Directory. In Server 2012,
you have thousands of commandlets now.
>> Thousands, yep.
>> There's no way to memorize them. So what they did is they
created a Help system. Now, before you go oh, no, not another
Help system, because I know, if you've... and I'm not...
okay, maybe I am. If you've used the Help system in a particular
product before and have found it unuseful, well, just remember
it wasn't spent a lot of time on. This was spent a lot of time
on by people who wanted you to be successful, knew that the only
way that you're going to be successful is to have a great Help system.
We, all of us, use this every single day, and I want to point
out, as Jeffrey was saying, it's about using the Help system,
reading and comprehending it, and then figuring it out.
We're IT pros. That's what we do. We figure things out.
This is actually fun when you get... start working with it.
But one of the challenges that we have is the RTFM side. I mean,
as an IT pro, one of the reasons I got into IT is because I was
really good at sitting down at a computer and just figuring it out.
I didn't have to read the manual. Well, that's not going to
work here. We're going to have to use and read and comprehend
the manual, and they've made it really easy for us. So let's
start doing a little Get Help stuff. First of all...
and guys, some of this stuff is in the slides so we're just going
to demonstrate it. First of all, let's talk about update help
versus the way that we used to have it.
>> Yeah, okay. So we used to ship the Help with the property,
and it turned out that there are all sorts of problems with that.
So basically, the way Microsoft works, because we ship to hundreds
of millions of people, right, it really matters that the release
is buttoned up, right, which is to say that you stop changing
things and then you test and then you test and you test and you
test, and then you release it. So what ended up happening was
that just as soon as you're putting the finishing bits on the
code, the documentation has to be done. And, of course, that
doesn't work.
But now it's cooked. Like hey, don't change it, because you might
break something. So then it gets shipped and the documentation,
there's differences between the documentation and the product,
and the answer used to be, well, you know, hey, just hang in there.
You'll release again in three years and we'll fix that.
That's kind of a crummy answer. And then there was a second problem.
The second problem is, guess what? The help is huge, right, because
there's a ton of it.
And then you say, well, jeez, I'm now going to a cloud world
where I've go a gazillion machines, I got a gazillion servers.
Want to use those, be as efficient as possible with those servers,
and you don't need the help on all those servers. You need the
help on the machine you're managing them from.
>> Right.
>> And to put the help on all those systems is just bogging down
those servers with stuff that you're not going to use. So because
of those two problem, in Windows... sorry, PowerShell Version
3, we moved to an updatable help model, which is to say we ship
and there's some very kind of like structural help that we generate,
based upon metadata. You'll see some examples of that. But then
all the help text is available from download from the internet.
So that's the way that works.
>> And let me just say that in V2, one of the challenges was if
you were using the Help system and there's an example in there,
there was a possibility, you know, that maybe that example was
wrong, and I'll show you a way around that if you're in V2 to
get the latest information for it. But really, the joy here
with V3 here is as soon as Microsoft updates a help or they find
an issue, my Help gets updated on my management station. So the
first thing that we're going to do, and then we're going to take
a break in a couple minutes...
>> Wait, can I give an example?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> So I don't know if you ever use WQL.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, right. So I can never remember WQL. I just can't.
It's one of those things, one of those... there's certain things
that just never sink in for me. WQL is one of them. And so constantly,
whenever I want to use that, I'd have to use search. And there's
something about the search... the content, I can never find it
on the internet either, right. So at some point, somebody had
exactly the same problem. So they went on Microsoft Connect and
said you ought to have an About topic for WQL.
And guess what? They went and wrote one. And so now we have
an About WQL, and it's just there. Point was you didn't have
to wait for another release. You had a problem, you told us about
your problem, and we responded. And then in a matter of, like, well...
I forgot how long that one took. But there was one where somebody
complained about an error in the documentation. Two days later,
we had an update. So it's pretty peppy. It's continuous publishing.
>> And so what you want to make sure that you're doing is you're
updating Help. And let me show you how to do that. First of
all, you're going to need an internet connection. There is a
way around that. But let's just start with the basic update Help here.
And so we've got a commandlet for that called update...
update, get it... dash Help.
>> What do you want to update?
>> Yeah, what do you want to update? The Help. The verb, the noun.
So that's working out. And I look to use dash force, and guys,
this is something that you can run every single day to make sure
you have the latest and greatest help. And what it's going to
do, it's going to go out to the internet and it's going to download
all of the Help files that you need for all of the stuff that
you have on your system.
>> See that progress bar? Says ooooo.
>> Which is what it should say in PowerShell. Oooo.
>> So cool.
>> Now look, if you have a series... a bunch of machines that
don't have direct access to the internet, you can save this Help
with Save Help.
You can save this Help as a set of files, and then you can update
from that set of files. But having the internet connection sure
does make your life a lot easier. Now here's the idea.
We're going to take a break here and so what we want to do is
make sure that you've got a PowerShell console up and make sure
that you've updated Help, because when we come back, we're going
to start using my favorite things. And let me just show them
to you real quick.
Get-Help, which, yep, that's going to get us help on stuff, but
it's also going to help us search for stuff and so that's its
most important thing. Before, though, we go, I want to show you
there's a difference. You can see people use Get-Help.
You're going to see people use Help, and you're going to see
people use Man. And I want to show you that there's a difference
between these two. Get-Help, and I'm just going to pick a commandlet
and what I'm going to do is I'm going to keep things real simple
right now. And I want you to notice my screen. It scrolled all
the way to the bottom. Now, this is not a complete Help file,
but we'll get to that after break. But I want you to notice
it scrolled all the way down to the bottom. Now watch the difference
between using Help on the same thing.
Look at the bottom of my screen. See how I've got that little
more so I can...
you probably heard that. I can space bar now and move through
the Help file. Man does the same thing. So Man, and I'll do
Get Service, gives you that same, you know, like you pipe to
more kind of deal, where you can pound your way through it.
Use whichever one makes you happiest, and probably today you
should experiment. I know, I've got friends that are just Help.
I always only use Help. I happen to be a Get-Help kind of guy,
because I like it to scroll to the bottom of the screen.
The Help system is a super discoverable, great tool to help me
find things.
And let's do a couple of examples. I'll start off, and then
you can join in. This is going to be really awesome, because...
and don't memorize or write down anything that we do.
>> Yep.
>> Swear to God. Don't do it, because that's kind of the whole point.
So let me give you an example. First of all, Help has the ability
to discover stuff. And I'm a Get Help... Get-Help kind of guy
so I'm going to use Get-Help. And I want to find out... here's my...
I want to see if there's any commandlets that can help me work
with services. So I'm going to do star service star.
>> By the way, star is your friend. Star is a wildcard, and it
says find anything at the beginning or find anything at the end.
Match anything at the beginning or end.
>> Yeah, and make sure when you mean wildcard, you use a wildcard,
because some commandlets will let you not use the wildcard and
that's not a practice to get into. So... oh, my gosh, look
at all of these commandlets. So many commandlets that have service
in them, whoa! But now is where the fun begins. Look. Is there
a commandlets that, in this list, that looks like it might retrieve
or, I don't know, get me a list of services on my computer? So yeah.
There happens to be one right here. See Get-Service.
It would probably get me a list of services.
>> Show them the up arrow. Show them the up arrow.
>> What am I...
>> You can just use the up arrow. Now watch this. Now use the
right arrow... left arrow and put a G in front of the star.
Check this out.
Now do it.
>> Oh, got a short list.
>> These wildcards are great.
>> The wildcards are great, and actually knowing how to do a good
search is really good. This is great, this is great. So here's
the idea, and we're going to do this a couple times. The idea
is you search for, probably by noun, you search for the thing
that you want to find. I want to know something about processes
or I want to know something about services, which are the examples
I'm going to use a lot. But it could be as simple as AD computers
or something like that. And you search for what you want and
when you find it, well, there's a Help file for it. So let's
go in and take a look. I'm going to do Get-Help, Get-Service.
Now, this is the simple view of the Help file and let me show
it to you real quick. It gives you the name, synopsis, syntax
which we're going to talk about here shortly, gives you a description
of what the commandlet does and some related links and information.
Now, this is not the full Help so don't panic. We're going to
do the full Help. But let's try this discovery thing again.
I want to do, let's see, Get-Help, and I want to find something that...
oh, and I'm going to use your trick. I'm going to say that would
G star
something with AD computer in it.
Because I want to work with Active Directory computers.
Oh, look. There's a command there. Get AD computer. You know
what I'm thinking? I'm thinking in my head that's probably going
to solve my problem. But to be sure, what I'm going to do is
do Get-Help, Get AD Computer and take a look at it.
And again, this is the simple Help view and we'll get to a better
ones here in just a second. But so the concept is pretty simple.
What you want to do is you want to discover what you want to
work with, and then look at the Help for what you want to work with.
Now, the concept is simple, but doing this seems to be a lot of...
a big challenge for a lot of folks. You have to become trusting
in that this is how we do it, and this actually works. No matter
what product you're working with, think of what is it that you
want to do something to. What's the noun that you want to find?
And then have Help search for it.
>> Yep.
>> Sounds like great way to get Help to work for it.
>> Yeah, we very much tried to create a world where you could
think about what you want, type it and get it, okay? So let's
just say you wanted to assign something. Well, you'd look for
assign and you wouldn't find that. You'd then quickly learn
that we use the word set and so you'd say, well, okay. So there's
an infinite number of nouns, but the verbs are pretty regular.
So imagine you wanted to get the help on the verbs, like...
>> Yeah.
>> Like you type.
>> Go ahead.
>> So what you'd do is you'd say, you'd say Get Verb, and
it shows you all the verbs. And so these are all the verbs that
you're going to learn. And you see, well, how many are there?
So you might want to say, well, get the verb. I'd like to measure them.
And you see that there are 98 verbs. And here you see we break
them up into, into, you know, whether they're security verbs
or communication verbs, et cetera. Anyway, so those...
you're going to learn those 98 things and then you're going to
be able to think, type, and get what you want.
>> And what happens often is you're not even going to learn all
98 of those. You're just going to learn a few of them, because
you'll know that what the verbs will do for you, and you end
up looking for the nouns. So it becomes a very easy process to
follow through. But let's start getting into what this Help can
do for us. So once again, I'm going to do this. Get-Help.
I want to find command that will retrieve me some services.
Now, notice, well, there is Get Service, and so I want to take
a look at what this can do for me. So I'm going to do Get-Help
and Get Service. Again, this is a simplified Help view. But there's
more to Help than just this. Once you've updated Help, this Help
can be extended or expanded upon. And let me show you a couple
of things. This is where it gets oh, just so happy for me.
Because watch. I'm going to do Get-Help on Get Service, but we
have a parameter that will allow us to get detailed...
ooh, detailed help. And here's what detailed help is going to
show us. I'm going to scroll all the way back to the top, and
Get Service gives you the synopsis. Again the syntax, which
we're going to talk about in a second, and the description.
This is what we saw before, but here's this. When we talk about
syntax, we're going to start talking about what these things
are, parameters. These parameters change how the commandlet acts.
Well, I don't necessarily know what these things mean.
Well, when you go to detailed help, look.
The parameters are listed here with an explanation of what they mean.
And so what you'll do is you'll actually be up here looking and
going I have no idea what that is. Then you can just scroll
down and get a definition of the parameters. Also, as I scroll
down here, I want you to notice something really interesting.
Now we start to get examples. Now, I want you to think about
this for a second. I've got a commandlet called Get-Service.
So let's talk about what it's probably going to do. I haven't
run it yet. It's probably going to give me, and if I read the
description, a list of all of the services on my computer, whether
they're running, stopped or paused. And it will tell me about that.
How many examples of that do you really think we need?
Well, we need 11 of them. And here's why I want to point this out.
We apparently, we need 11 examples of this, and there's a reason
for this. Because the people that work so hard on these Help
files knew that there were going to be all kinds of different
ways that you're going to want to try to use this, and they wanted
to give you examples. What happens is this is oftentimes you'll
be thinking of a business problem or trying to solve a business
problem, and you'll say, gee whiz, let me go. I found the commandlet.
Let me go look at the example. You'll find an example that is
really close to probably exactly what you wanted to do, which
is one of the cool things. So a big shout-out to all the folks
that work on...
>> You know the other thing we did was there are few of the ones
we knew people were going to use a lot, like Get Process.
Boy, you always want to spend time looking at Get Process because
there, what we did was we said, hey, Get Process, Get Service,
people are going to use these a lot. And so in our Help in our
examples, we show you not just how to use Get Process and Get
Service, but we also show you some very common PowerShell techniques
that then help you, you know, kind of lead you to the next step.
You start off saying oh, I'd like to get something... Get Services,
what do I want to do, and then you say, well, jeez, actually,
I'd like to format it a little differently or I'd like to find
these things, filter. And so we used those high volume topics
to kind of go a little bit deeper, to teach you the next level
of PowerShell.
>> Which is you're going to... as we take you through learning
all of this deep level part of PowerShell, you're going to look
at these Help files in a totally new way, and you'll see that
examples of sorting and filtering and getting the kinds of information
that you want and changing the kinds of information you want.
A lot of times, right in the examples. A lot of people, the
first thing they do is they go to examples. As a matter of fact,
there is, rather than detailed, you have a parameter called examples
that will take you right into just the examples if you want to
get there real quick. Something else that you can do, and this
is going to become a big deal this afternoon as we work through
this, there's also Full Help.
I don't know, Jeffrey, I don't know if they can handle the Full Help.
I mean, that's an awful lot...
>> Stress test.
>> There we go. Full Help.
>> Put your seat belts on.
Full Help, guys, I'm going to tell you right now, the Full Help
is very similar to Detailed, except when you're in the parameters,
there's some special information, and this is going to make,
in the next section when we're going to talk about what this
information means to you, it's actually very important to us.
And this will help us understand how the commands work in the
pipeline and so we're going to talk about that stuff in a little bit.
So right now, when you're running Get Help, you can use detailed
or you can use examples, but a little bit later on, you'll always
end up using full. Now, I want to... I promised you earlier
that for you folks that are running PowerShell V2, and even if
you're running V3, sometimes if you're running V2, your Help
files, they're not up to date and you want the latest. I need
the latest and greatest information. Well, you can't run Update
Help if you're in V2, which is why on your admin box you should
be running V3.
However, let me just show you. This is how we used to get around that.
Microsoft helped us with this.
Dash online. I love this. Dash online.
Looky what it just did. Takes me... opens up a browser, takes
me out. Look, updated, shows you when it was last updated and
here's the Full Help
for whatever it is I was looking for. In this case, Get Service.
So again, don't close that. I'll lose the chat. Dash online.
>> Can I show my favorite?
>> Yeah, because... I hope you do. I was confused by this at
first, but go ahead.
>> But what?
>> I'll show you. You go.
>> Okay. So let's swap to mine. So here we do Get Help, Get Service.
So here's the thing. You can say examples, right? Examples.
And you say oh, that's cool. Let's, let's, let's run this.
Let's, let's, let's, let's, let's do one of these, okay?
And type that and by the way, so you do, you do enter and then
left mouse button, and okay great. Now you want to do the next one.
Oh, well, so you see... the work flow's all messed up. So what
you can do is you can say
Get Help minus show. Show window. And look here. Comes up in
a window. Okay? Now this has all sorts of great stuff. One of
these is settings, and you can say, hey, I want to just see...
I don't want to see all this stuff.
I just want to see the examples.
Look at all the stuff you can have control over.
>> I know, it's amazing to me.
>> So now you just go here, cut, paste... sorry.
Paste and do that. And then the next one.
Cut, paste. And so it's a very nice work flow, much nicer work flow.
>> Yeah.
>> So again, that is this, this Show Window. And there's some
really fun stuff with Show Window. Can I spend some more time
on Show Window?
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> Okay. So now let's turn all this back on there.
So you say it's got lots of stuff here.
So now, in the Show Window, you can do things like remember...
what is it? Well, anyway, you got a find here.
So you can find stuff, like dependent. Depend. Okay. And so
notice it gets highlighted and says here, it says
18 matches, okay? And you can search. Didn't do that very well.
So anyway, then you can start searching for these things.
And so it's super nice.
>> And I think the addition of this, this was added to V3, and
I think the addition of this is really phenomenal, because guys,
let me show you. Traditionally, you're going to spend so much
time in the Help file, and you're going to want to do just that.
You're going to want to cut and paste from a Help file or you're
going to want to read a Help file while you're working in PowerShell
that a lot of times what a lot of guys would do, if you take
at my screen, I'm just going to launch two PowerShell sessions.
Now, if you have two monitors, this is great, right? So you do
Help in one and then you can work in another one. But with V3,
having the Show Window stuff, well, first of all, it fits better
on your screen. It's easy to move around. You can have the Help.
It's easier to get stuff... the part that always confuses me
is, and we're going to fix this later when we start talking about
the magical ISE, but it's the cut and the paste, man. It's that whole...
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> It's that right clicking and stuff in the console. Why can't
we fix that? Why can't we fix that? Why can't we fix that, that console?
>> Because it's horrible.
>> Okay. That's the answer I wanted.
>> So here's the thing. Here's the thing. So let me give you
a little tutorial about some of the behind the scenes stuff at Microsoft.
So there was some point where people said, oh, you know, Microsoft
stopped advancing IE, you know. Oh, that just proves what bad
guys they are. There's no competition. They stopped innovating.
No, no, no my friends. Honestly, that's not what happened.
What happened
was that it got to the point where every time we made a change,
we broke a bunch of people, right?
>> Right.
>> So then it's like people are like hey, jerk, stop breaking us.
And so... and so they stopped doing that. And then all of a
sudden, some competitors got up there, and so now they went and
started doing things even though sometimes things break.
Same thing happens with the console window. The console window,
man, every time you change that thing, you break tons of people.
You just break tons of them. And so you don't want to change
that thing very much. Now, here's the thing. Actually, I'm pretty
hostile to the console window, okay? So that's it. I'm trying
to make this thing die. I'll just be straight up about it.
Make it die. And why is that? And the answer is that there are
these things called console apps, okay. Now, a console app only
works in the console. Now, here's why I want to kill the console,
because I want to kill console apps. And it turns out that the
reason I want to kill console apps is you go and you write...
you do something on the console app and it writes directly on
to the console, which means you cannot automate it, okay?
You can't run something, get its output, process the output,
and do something with it because it writes directly on the screen.
So this is just evil incarnate. It is the enemy of automation
so we're trying to get rid of those things. So we're trying
to get everybody on to PowerShell ISE, which is a much richer investment.
So by the way, stop asking me to fix the console. I'm not going
to fix the console.
>> And that's the point is that the console... and look, I know
cut and pasting in the console and some guys go the console's
driving me nuts. A little bit later on today, we're going to
help you with, well, he hates it and so there's actually a really
cool solution to it. But I want you to wait until we get there
with the ISE. So to cut and paste in the console is, if you haven't
done it, yep, you highlight it, you right click, and then you
can right click again. So no control C, no control V in this puppy.
I think we may have something cooler for you later on. But right
now, that's how you do it. So right click and right click will
take care of it for you. Jeffrey, you know what we need to do?
We need to start to take a look at
and explaining syntax.
>> Yeah.
>> Because here's the thing. Everybody wants to work with commandlet,
but, you know, commandlet is going to do great stuff for you,
but sometimes you want the commandlet to alter its output or
change what it's actually doing for you. You know, Get Service
is great, but it's going to give you a list of all your services.
Maybe I just want the one called bits or something like that.
So the syntax of the commandlet will explain to you the options
that you have available to control the commandlet. And so at
first, it looks very, very confusing. Now, we've got slides
for this, and so it's all in the slide deck. But let's take
a look here. I've got Get Service up right now, and I'm going
to take a look at something pretty simple.
>> You know what? If you do this in Show Window, it comes out better.
>> You like it in Show Window better?
>> Yeah, because watch. Do it.
>> Oh.
>> No, you do it.
>> Let's do Show Window.
>> See, because one, you've got the zoom there down at the bottom.
You didn't notice that?
>> Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Oh, that's very, very nice.
>> The other thing is it highlights some things. So I think it's
a little bit easier to read.
>> Very easy to read.
>> And it's easier to select and say...
>> Okay. So we're going to use... we're going to use this instead.
This is much better. So take a look at this right here. See the
thing with the dash in front of it? So you'll notice that I've
got a commandlet, and then it starts followed by all of this
magical characters, and we're going to explain what all these
characters are, but the first thing I want you to notice is look
how many times under syntax I see the name of this commandlet.
I see it three times. Now, Jeffrey, technically, this is called
parameter sets, but why am I seeing three of these?
>> Yeah, so here's the thing. Imagine... take a look at the net
command, right? There's net use and net view, et cetera.
These are different parameter sets. And what happens is when
you type net view, you get one set of functionality. When you
type net use, you get a different set of functionality. So what
happens is that they then reuse the word, command net. Now, that's
essentially what a parameter set is. Now, we take a different
take on it. Net use is extremely different functionality than
net views, okay. So we don't like that. We want to be clear.
But the point about Get Service is that there are different parameter sets.
Sometimes you want to say Get Service based upon its name.
Or you're going to say I want to get service based upon its display
name, okay. So those are two different parameter sets. A better
example would be Get Process. Sometimes you want to say Get Process
whose name is this. Sometimes you want to say Get Process whose
ID is this. Or sometimes you go and just say Get Process and
get them all.
>> And get them all.
>> Yeah, so those are different parameter sets.
>> And let me show you what Jeremy is talking about. Notice in
these three different Get Services, and yeah, don't worry, we'll
take a look at Get Process too. In these three different Get
Services, look at this one. This one has dash name. Down here
in these other two, you don't see dash name. This one has dash
display name. You don't see that in the other two. So that's
what makes that particular parameter set unique. As a matter
of fact, I'm going to demonstrate these here in just a second.
But again, look at these dashes.
These dashes indicate that they're parameters. Dashes.
Parameters. Parameters will allow you to change the results of
what the command's going to do, and I want to do an example for you.
Let's take a look at dash name. I want you to notice it's followed
by these characters here. I just kind of go like this, call them
chihuahuas or something like this.
>> Chihuahuas? That's the technical term. Not many people knew that.
I didn't realize that you...
>> The official technical term now is chihuahuas. And what this
is is this is the kind of values that you can give this...
>> I think we're going to get in trouble with HR on that one.
>> Really? Okay. These things...
>> Chihuahuas.
>> No, like Pacman, Pacman.
>> Uh-huh, Pacman.
>> So these can be...
now these are the values that you can give to the parameter.
I'm going to show you. So let me give you a quick example here.
Let me lower this down. Well, I'm not going to lower it down.
I'll just do it here. Watch. I'm going to do Get Service and
I'm going to use one of the parameters. Now, parameters always
begin with a dash. So make sure you always put a dash in front
of the parameters. And now I'm going to put in a value that would
be inside those chihuahuas, and it said that the value type was
string, which means alpha numeric, and I'm going to put in the
name, which is a short name, of a service. I'm going to do bits.
Instead of getting the entire service list, this parameter now
is going to allow me to just get the service that I want.
So here's the idea. Parameters can have these arguments on them.
And a lot of parameters can take multiple arguments. And let
me show you what they look like. Let's say I wanted two services.
Notice the comma in between. Now, the space is optional, but
put a space in here, makes it easier to read.
Now I get those two. Let me show you how that looks in the syntax,
and so let's go back here. Notice up here, at dash name, that's
the parameter.
Then we have the chihuahuas with the type of data that we can
put in there the value type. See these guys inside? These guys.
And you got to do them close together, because we've got these
guys and we've got these guys.
>> Those are chihuahuas. What are these?
>> Chihuahuas, I just call them binkies because they're inside.
>> Binkies.
>> Yeah. I got chihuahuas and inside the chihuahuas you have these binkies.
If you see binkies in there, that means you can take multiple
values, separated by a comma. Now, I'll show you some stuff later
where you won't see the internal binky, and so... boy, there's
going to be a whole phrase book now. And so can only take one
value, and this is very important for you to be able to know.
But here's the part where it starts to get a little confusing.
Let me do a
little demonstration here of dash name with multiple values,
which I just did, but let me show you something else.
This isn't the confusing part. I'm going to ask Jeffrey about
this confusing part. Again, you can do wildcards. So dash main
B star means I'm going to get all the services listed that begin
with B.
>> There's no conflict between wildcards and arrays or collections.
So do this. Do the up arrow. Now do...
now comma C star.
>> Oh, yeah, yeah. This is... oh, yeah. Great point.
>> Yeah.
>> Great point. So now I get both the ones that begin with Bs
and with Cs. And see, that's awesome. That's totally awesome.
So oh, I closed my Show Window. So let me go up here
and open up the Show Window.
Here's the part where I start getting kind of confused here,
and this originally kind of threw me off is I want you guys to
notice this guy down here.
Computer name. And I want you to notice what's around computer name.
See these brackets that surround both the parameter and the argument there?
So it's not the internal binkies inside the chihuahuas.
It's these things that surround either the parameter or the parameter
and its argument.
This means you don't have to use it. It's optional. But wait,
we're not done yet. Great example is take a look at this first syntax.
This syntax up here.
Notice that everything has these around it. Which means that
there's nothing actually required that I type in. Notice I've
got them around here. Got them around here.
And every single one of them, optional. That means all's I need
to do or all's I have to do is type Get Service, and it gives
me a whole list. In other words, no parameters were required.
But take a look at this.
Inside the syntax. Look at this second syntax.
I want you to notice, look at this guy down here.
See how display name doesn't have these around it?
Well, that means if you're going to use display name, you've
got to put it in, and then you've got to give me a value for it.
Now, here's an example.
Display name, by the way, is the long name.
So it's this really long name. And I can Get Services by that
display name, but I want you to notice that you've got a choice.
Dash name or dash display name. So Get Service-display name.
And now I can type in whatever long lengthy, and I'm just making
it up, display name that I want to type in. But if you're going
to use display name, now you have to use display name and the
value that goes with it. That's what gets you into that other syntax.
Let's do something else. Let's do stop.
>> Wait, your didn't show them... so here's the thing.
>> Yeah.
>> So imagine you wanted to get like... do a Get Service B star.
>> Just V star?
>> B, B.
>> Oh, B star.
>> Okay. So look at this. The name for bit locker drive encryption
service is BDESV. Now remember we said, oh, you want to create
a world where you think about what you want, you type it and
you get it. How many of you were thinking oh, I want to get the
BDESVC service, right?
So no, you want bit locker, okay? So then you want to say, okay,
well Get Service display bit... no, you can't type bit locker.
It's bit locker drive encryption service.
So remember, partial's great because I'm flawed pipe can't remember
BDESVC, and I'm definitely
not going to remember bit locker drive encryption service.
And look, even if I could remember it, I can guarantee you I cannot...
I'm like incapable of typing that correctly. So what you do
is you type...
>> Display name.
>> Bit star. No, just bit...
>> Oh, just bit star, yeah.
>> Bit star. Something to do with bit locker. Boom, and it just works.
>> It got us by the long name which actually makes more human
sense than those little tiny short names.
>> One of the things we said was with PowerShell, it's like programming
with hand grenades, versus sniper rifles, you know. It just
sort of, just sort of like over there. I don't know if I ever
told you that story.
My buddy, college, I... my roommate used to be in Vietnam.
He was a Vietnam... 18, Special Forces. No, that was actually
the other guy that I worked with. He was a Navy SEAL. And the
Navy SEALs get their own weapons, right. So everybody else,
like you're this kind of guy, you get this kind of weapon.
The Navy SEALs, like the gun manufacturers would make them guns.
And he talked about this thing. I never quite got it in focus,
but it's basically sort of like a machine gun/shotgun, a machine shotgun.
He said, and the great thing about that was in Vietnam, you know,
you had the jungle, and you sort of only had to know, like, is
my problem over there or over there? And you'd set up with this
thing and he says you'd let loose with it and three seconds later,
your problem was gone or everything between you and your problem
was gone.
>> Was gone.
>> Focusing on your problem. Well, that's the same sort of thing.
You're just sort of like, hey, bit locker, something to do with
bit locker. Bit star.
>> Bit star.
>> And so that's kind of the model we're trying to go for is,
you know, just sort of over here or sort of over there.
Now, there are times when you need to be precise and you can
be precise. And there are times when it's just sort of like over
there is good enough. And by the way, when you need both, you'll
see how we deal with that. Through something called minus what-if
and minus confirm.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. And so and Jeffrey what I need you to help
me with is that is the...
this is the one that seems to throw most people off.
So a dash... da-da-da... means you have a parameter. And if
it's followed by chihuahuas, that means you can put arguments
on it and you get the value type of the argument, string, int
that kind of thing. And if it's got binkies in there, you can
take multiple arguments, separated by a comma. You see plenty
of examples of us doing that. And if you're surrounded by these
brackets, you don't have to... it's optional. You don't have
to do it at all. But.
>> But.
>> There's something tricky here in this view.
>> Yeah, isn't that cool?
>> Let's look at this guy. Look at this dash name. This guy's...
throws everybody off. So I don't have to type this in. I don't
type anything in, because we all know that I can just run Get
Service and get all of them. But if I'm using dash name and I
want to specify a name of a service, like bits, what is it with
these little duders inside here?
>> Yeah, this is something we called positional parameters, okay?
And so that means that if you just specify the value, you don't
have to specify dash name.
>> So...
>> This makes so... watch. Get Service.
I can do this.
You might be saying, oh, I got to type a lot. Actually, you
don't have to type a lot, but here's what positional means.
If you're going to give me a bunch of names of services, you
don't have to use dash name. See? Works the same way. Which means
so those brackets around the parameter simply mean you don't
have to use the parameter. But you got to give me the argument.
That's what makes it...
>> It gets even better, because now you can just type GSV.
>> Oh, yeah. You can use the alias to even shorten it up even further.
So watch.
>> Do you want to go ahead and do it?
>> Go ahead.
>> GSV...
>> Bits....
>> bits.
>> And so here's kind of a key kind of principle of PowerShell, okay.
The principle is we want to have this very regular, very self-describing
surface, okay. So when it's 3:00 in the morning and things didn't
go the way you wanted to, and during some IT upgrade, and you
bring up some script, you want that script to be absolutely readable.
You want to know what's going on, okay. And so that's why PowerShell
is very clear, you know. Get-Service-Name, et cetera. So that
when you're reading it, you know exactly what's going on.
On the other hand, when you're interactive, you can type that
if you want. We make it easier to type that with things like
tab completion. But sometimes, you just want to go, go, go, go, go.
And so we have all these short cuts and aliases so that you can
be very, very productive as a high speed, advanced, interactive user.
But then when you go and write scripts, we encourage the more
verbose style.
>> As a matter of fact, just to emphasize on that a little bit
further, so when you're writing scripts, this is the way that
you're going to want to do it here in the top example.
You're going to want to be very explanatory of what you're doing.
But as Jeffrey was saying, when you're at the console, free reign.
I mean, you can use aliases and shorten this up with the positional
parameters so that you can quickly get things done. You're going
to see examples of that today, because Jeffrey uses an awful
lot of aliases, and I usually, because I'm getting ready to automate
it, sometimes I just do the whole thing the first time through
where I use all the parameters and all the arguments. So you
can see that contrast between working quickly interactively with
the short, you know, short versions and then the long versions
that you're going to want to see in a script. But let me give
you a hint and then we'll do another example and then take a
look at how to work with all of this. Have you guys been hitting
the tab key? Take your pinky, take your pinky. If you're a touch
typist, this is probably not for you. But this pinky should...
>> He's showing you the official flexes move.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Warm up.
>> Want to make sure you stretch.
>> Want to warm it up...
>> Stretch it.
>> In the beginning of every day.
>> Stretch it, stretch the pinky. And you want this pinky to
hover right over the tab key always, because what you want to
do is, watch, get SE... I'm going to start hitting the tab key.
Look, look, look, it starts going through the commandlets.
I've got so many commandlets now, there's a lot of them to go through.
There we go, wait a minute. Shift tab goes backwards. Watch, dash.
I'm going to hit the tab key. It will cycle through the parameters
for me. Oh, this is cool.
>> Remember I said we'd make it easier to help type this stuff out?
The that's what he's talking about.
>> Yeah. And so look. In just about as many key strokes as doing,
like, GSV bits, just a couple of more and I can bang this out
and get it to look really nice and clean so that if I'm going
to use this in a script. So the tab key is your friend. Use the
tab key. You're going to see us use this all the time today.
Let me show you another example of finding something as kind
of a summary here of finding a commandlet and then taking a look
at its syntax.
Then we're going to show you how to put commandlets together
on the pipeline. So let's do this.
I have this business problem. Business problem time. And my
business problem is I need to get...
I need some errors.
I need the newest errors.
The newest five errors out of my system log.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> So I need to be able to look at my event...
>> Log file.
>> Yeah, the log file.
>> Yeah.
>> So I'm thinking I need to look at my event logs. I wonder
if PowerShell has a commandlet that can help me with my event log.
So Get Help star.
Well, let's see, do you have anything with event logs?
Oh, and lo and behold, there are plenty. As a matter of fact,
this is a great time now, you can take a look at the verbs.
You can just guess what do you think clear event log is going
to do.
>> That would clear it.
>> I bet it would clear it too. You know what do you think get
event log is going to do? Ta-da. It's going to... I know it
seems ridiculous, but this is the point is you're looking at
the verbs and figuring out what they're going to do and it's
not that difficult at this point. Now what we're going to do
is I want to get an event log. Now, I could just try to run this,
but I want to take a look at the help file first, so I'm going
to do Get Help on Get Event Log,
and I want to take a look at the syntax, and I also, if I have
questions about the parameters, I want to be able to see the
definitions of those parameters. So I'm going to do dash detailed
right now. And I'm going to go up here and go, hey, here's Get
Event Log.
Take a look at the syntax. Look. Get Event Log. Look at all
of these parameters. See the dashes? See the arguments that they
can have, whether they can have multiple values? And if you don't
know what something is, like, hm, I wonder what newest means,
you can scroll down and you can take a look down here. And the
reason I'm going through this is this is what we all have...
end up doing is I don't know necessarily what all the parameters
mean so a lot of times I go to the list and I read the list of
parameters first, just to find out what capabilities I have.
I know that seems like it may take a few extra minutes, but it's
worth it because I found that newest means I can get the newest
entries in the log. But also take a look at something else in
this syntax. Oops, where did it go?
Look at all of the things that are optional. But I want you
to notice something. Looky up here.
I want you to notice that dash log name isn't required, but this
guy is.
I want you to see what happens when something is mandatory and
you try to run it. So if I just tried to run get ept log, I want
you to think about this. If this worked just like this, think
about all of the... it's going to go through all of the logs
and spit all of the logs out on to my screen. Could that be
a little performance issue, especially if you're doing it to
50 machines at once?
>> That's now called big data.
>> That's right, big data.
>> Big data.
So watch. I'm going to strike enter and PowerShell is smart enough
to go hey, look, you need to know what log you want to look in.
So we're going to make you tell us what log.
So I'm going to say system. Now, of course, it's now going to
give me the entire system log, but let me just show you by using
the Help file, looking at the examples, reading the parameters,
you can start to make solutions like this. Get Event Log I know
wants a log name. I want the log name system. I also know that
I want the newest...
>> Wait. I think you can tab complete that too.
>> I think you can now too. Yes. Wait a minute, let's try it.
Didn't used to be able to do that. Let's see. Oh, look.
>> Is that cool?
>> That is totally cool. I noticed that a lot in V3, that you
can now tab complete on a lot of the things that the system has.
>> Yeah.
>> I think another reason you should be using V3.
>> Yeah, right. That's a V3-ism, not a V2-ism.
>> Yeah. So I know that by looking at the Help file that newest
will let me get the newest... I'm just going to say three entries.
But here's the thing. You guys know this, in a log file there's
a lot of that information stuff, and I don't want that.
Just so happens if you look at the Help file, you'll find that
entry type
error, that's going to give me the three latest errors.
Now, you might be thinking to yourself, well, that's not...
you know, that's cool, but I had to do a lot of reading. I could
have just opened up, you know, the graphical for this. Oh, yeah?
Well, watch this.
Thing is this.
There's a parameter in here called computer name. I want the
latest three errors from three different computers.
Here's the thing you need to kind of get from all of this.
You can't open the graphical fast enough, more or less get that
data that quick.
So in this one command that I figured out, I can get errors from
multiple computers on my display. Now, it's on my display, and
we're going to fix that here in this next section, because maybe
I don't want it on my display. Maybe I want it, I don't know,
in a web page.
Or a CSV or something like that but...
>> They missed the look. Show that again.
>> Ooh, a web page. I turned to Jeffrey and go ooh. So I've used
the Help file to build one great command and now we want to start
doing more with it. So to kind of wrap this up here, I've got
some slides in here, and like I said, everything that we've been
doing is in the slide deck so let me just kind of thumb through
here the slides. So again, questions?
>> By the way, you missed something crucial.
>> Did I?
>> Yeah.
>> What did I miss?
>> Go back to... go back to that wildcard help. Interactive.
>> Which...
>> Oh, good Lord. Go to mine.
>> Fine, fine.
>> He said Get Help, help, star event log.
And pointed out, oh, look here, you got clear, you got get, limit.
But look here. About.
>> Oh, I forgot to talk about the About Help.
>> No, this is like one of the most important things. It's About
Event Logs okay? So these are what we call conceptual topics, okay?
So you say, okay, clear screen and then... by the way, here's
a trick I do, right. So if I did clear screen. Here's the thing.
So now I want to see this. If I do clear screen and then, oh,
what was it I was going to do? Oh, shoot.
All right. Because again, I'm flawed, right? I can't... about something.
Okay. So here, so what you do is you do clear screen and then semicolon.
Semicolon is a statement separator that says do this and then
do something else. So it's a way to do two things at once.
Then I'm going to say get... I'll just say help, about event...
by the way, tab return. Event logs. So then it clears the screen
and shows me About. So here notice it gives me a short description,
describes things, viewing the event logs, goes through the discussion
about the topic. Tells you about the commands, et cetera.
And so there's quite a bit here. And then clear screen. If you
just say help, about underscore star...
>> Yeah, that's, there you go.
>> You'll see lots of About topics. Look at them. There's a...
and there's just a ton of really good stuff here. Like wildcards.
Hey, About Wildcards. About Wildcards.
About PowerShell Version 4. Guess which one I'm using.
About the ISE, About W My and there's the one I mentioned, remember,
About WQL...
>> Yeah.
>> So, so I got to tell you, this is one of the best investments
you can make is to go and do this Help About and spend some time
reading them. I mean, there's really great stuff there.
>> Yeah, and I think, I think the important side to this is that
there's actually two Help systems. The Help will help you discover
out of both of them. You've got Help system for the commandlets
and then you have this About_Help system, which, as Jeffrey just
said, is conceptual stuff. As we go through today, we're going
to be pointing out, oh, yeah, you need more information, go to
the about underscore, blah, blah, blah, blah, and there will
be more information in it.
>> No, there's more than that.
>> What's more than that?
>> Oh, so you don't know about Category?
>> Category?
>> Yeah. So Get Help plus Category, and here's the trick, right.
So you say that I know that Category takes up value, but I don't
know what value it is, right? And so sometimes we have to have
completion, sometimes we don't. Here's what I have to do. I just
like give a bad value and then often what it will do is it will
tell you...
>> Come up and tell you what categories?
>> The argument, blah, blah, blah does not belong to the set and
it tells you the set of things that you can type.
>> Oh, so you can get specifically for, like, the providers we're
going to be talking about?
>> That's the key. I'll tell you here, we did this and set this
up, and we had quite ambitious things for the Help subsystem,
and we haven't fully implemented all of them. Some of our partners
have implemented some of them, but we didn't. Like we were going
to have FAQs and glossary terms. So if you say Help FAQ, it's
not there. Okay? Like to get around to that. But in particular,
notice here, it says... where did... provider, right? So what
you can do is you can say...
by the way, tab works.
>> There you go.
>> It tells you, oh, look here are the various providers.
Now, we're going to talk about this topic later.
>> Right.
>> But if you did that and you said, oh, Get Help
Certificate, certificate, cer, tiff, tiff, tiff.
>> Tificate.
>> It will
give you information about a provider. When we get to the topic
about providers, this will make more sense. But it's a very,
very rich Help system.
>> Yeah, very rich Help system.