[Music]
>> Here we go. Let me start you out with
a concept. And Jeffrey and I are going to work through this.
We're going to talk about how the pipeline works and how things...
when objects get passed, how does the receiving commandlet know
what to do with them, if anything at all. I'm not a good guy
with sports analogies because I don't know anything about sports,
but as I understand it, there's this thing with the small white
balls where they have catcher's mitts. So, you know, the sending
commandlet is going to send some baseballs and we have to see
what catcher's mitts they get caught on the receiving commandlet.
You'll see what I mean. We have a process of by value and by
property name. And if those don't work, we have a last line of resort.
So I'm just going to, first of all, point out that all of this
is in the slides, but I'm not going to use the slides. So here
we go. Let's get rid of the sides.
Let's start with an idea. Get service, if I can spell it,
stop service. Okay. Guys, we showed you this earlier, and we
did dash what if. You know that it's going to work.
But the question that I have in my head is why. Well, here's
what's happening. Get service has... is getting a bunch of services,
a bunch of objects, and we're going to send one object at a time
across the pipeline. My question is is the receiving commandlet,
which in this case is stop service, how is it grabbing hold of
this object and how does it know what to do with it? And as it
turns out, it has lot to do with the parameters on the receiving commandlet.
And that's what I want to show you. First of all, one of the
first things we need to know when we're looking at this is when
we send...
we're sending objects, we need to know what kind of objects they are.
So I piped it to get member. Because get member shows me what
type of object
is being sent across the pipeline. This is a service controller object.
I need to know that right now. Now what I want to do is I want
to see what the receiving commandlet is capable of receiving.
To do that we look at the help file for it, the receiving commandlet.
In this process you have a tendency to get confused between piping
to get member and get help, but it's pipe to get member to see
the object, what kind it is, and then we look at the help file
on the receiving commandlet. So let me show you. Get help on
stop service. Now, I'm going to use dash full because I want
you to see everything, but Jeffrey will show you a trick here
in a second.
Let me go in here and show you. Inside we now are very concerned
with this information. We already know how to look at the syntax.
I want to go down here and look at the parameters. The parameters
have a capability sometimes and that capability is do they accept
pipeline input.
Now, think of these guys as the parameters are the things with
or without the catcher's mitt. So what we're asking is do you
have a catcher's mitt or not where you could catch this object
and do something with it. Well, a lot of times you'll see like
display name, it doesn't accept pipeline input. So there's nothing
going to cross. But let's go down this list. I often start at
the bottom, but let's go down this list.
And this is stop service. So let's see here. Dash what if.
Well, dash what if, it doesn't even make sense to the accept
pipeline input. Dash confirm. No, that doesn't accept it.
PassThru, that doesn't accept it. Dash name. That does accept it.
Now here's what we're concerned about. We have two ways of accepting
pipeline input by value and by property name. And if you're
a dev out there, we're not talking about by vowel, by ref, this
is different. But by value and by property name. The first way
we're going to try it is by value. And what you're going to
notice here is dash name supports accepting pipeline input by value.
And you would like some kind of string. Well, wait a second,
let me show this to you, let me go up a little bit further.
See this parameter called input object? I'm not exactly sure
what it does, but it accepts true by value. Look at the kind
of object it would like, a service controller. Wait a minute,
wait a minute, wait a minute. When I did get service, what kind
of object was I sending it?
I was sending a service controller. So when a service controller
comes cruising across that pipeline to stop service, the catcher's
mitt that's going to grab it is the input parameter catcher's
mitt because this name is spelled exactly like service controller
of the object type that I sent. I know this is weird, but they're
spelled the same.
So since they're spelled the same, this means we're actually
passing it by value. And this is one of the most efficient ways
to pass. So that's how get service and stop service actually work.
We're passing by value into the parameter input object because
the names match, the type of object along with what the parameter expects.
Here's where it gets a little tricky. And please jump in as
soon as you want to yell at me about something.
>> You're doing great.
>> You think so? Because, man, this was hard on me at first.
But as soon as I got this, this is...
>> You got it....
>> what made the world rock.
Let's try this. Notice that I did get service stop service.
And I want to point something out to you. Notice how the nouns match.
Well, if the nouns match, it's likely that they're going to work
together on a pipeline. It's also likely that they'll probably
pass by value. But it's not always the case. So you always want
to check to make sure. Let me show you something where the nouns
don't match.
Get service stop process. Well, these are two totally different things.
Services, processes. They're not the same thing.
So I'll bet most of you are thinking the same thing that I am.
This isn't going to work.
It can't possibly work. Services, processes.
Let's go through this process and take a look.
I'm going to do get service and I'm going to pipe it to get member.
I know we know the answer to this, but I just want to go through
the process again.
What kind of object are we sending, we're sending a service controller
object across. Now, the first thing I want to check is to see
if there's something in stop process that supports pipeline input
by value for this object. That would be the first way we would
hook up. So I'm going to do get help on the receiving commandlet,
which in this case is stop process,
and let's take a quick look.
Let me get up to the parameters. Now, guys, I'm going to shorten
this down a little bit because I know some of these parameters
just don't accept pipeline input, like what if it doesn't accept
pipeline input. So I don't even need to look at it. So every
time it says false, I'm not really interested in it.
PassThru, doesn't support it, dash name, it does support it but
right now I'm checking for by value. This is by property name.
So I'm looking for things by value.
Ah, there we go. Input object. It supports pipeline input.
It will catch it. And it's doing it by value the first way we're
going to do it, but look at what it wants, a process object.
Well, I'm not sending it. Process isn't spelled the same way
as service controller.
Not even close.
So there's not going to be a hookup here, so by value fails.
Well, now at this point you kind of go, well, if it fails, it's
just not going to work.
No. Now we move on to the next process which is by property name.
And this gets a little bit confusing. I want you to notice while
I'm in this help file.
See how the parameter dash name takes pipeline input by property name?
Here's what that's saying. The object that you're sending to
me, does it have a property that is spelled exactly like the
parameter name. That's what we mean by property name, is it's
spelled the same. And if so, I might be able to hook up that way.
If my vowel fails, I'll try this. So here's what I'm going to do.
Here's the catch phrase. Whenever you want to know everything
there is to know about an object, you pipe it to get member.
So get service.
And I'm going to pipe it to get member.
Take a look at this list.
Is there a property... and remember we don't... alls we need
is the word property... is there a property that is spelled the
same way as the parameter name. And if you look at the list,
la-la, there is. If they're spelled the same, we're going to
have a hookup by property name. And if you look at the list,
have a hookup by property name. But watch what's going to happen here.
So let's look. I'm only going to take one service here.
Service. Look at what its name is. It's the name of the service.
Okay. Wait a second. When you look at processes,
let's look at processes,
process name is also name.
These are process names. So when you use the commandlet...
oops. Clear the screen. When you use the commandlet...
hello, clear the screen. There we go.
When you use the commandlet stop process, what it wants for its
dash name is the name of a process.
What I'm sending it is the name of a service.
But here's the thing.
We do have a hookup. This is going to work, it's just your results
may be a little unusual. So let's try it. Get service.
Pipe to stop process. This should work. And, yeah, I'm going
to do a dash what if because... you know why I'm doing a dash
what if? Because it does actually work.
Notice there's a lot of blood on my screen. Now, what this means
is is that, yeah, look, cannot find the process with the name.
Well, yeah, because that's a service name. Of course you can't
find that. But if you look here, did you see anything white fly by?
Because that means it worked. Let me see if I can find something.
Oh, there's always something.
>> I didn't see anything.
>> Really?
>> No.
>> Don't embarrass me in front of my friends.
>> It's only 5,000 or 2.
>> I know. There's... there's almost always something in here
that's in white.
>> Go to mine. Let me show you.
>> Go to his.
>> Okay. So here's... I'll do a different set.
>> Okay. Cool.
>> Okay? So notice I started up calculator here.
And so I can do get process.
Calc and get calculator. And I can pipe that to dir.
And we see that calc is in this. And why is that? Because dir takes...
binds by name, and so you take a look. And, well, does dir take
a process, you know, system.diagnostics.process? No. And it
says, oh, well, I bind anything by name. Do you have a name?
And get process does have a name, and therefore it works.
>> And that's an excellent example. And so between his example
and mine, you get what's happening here, is that the commandlets
are working together, but you have to look at what you're giving
it, the information that you're giving and what it's expecting.
In the case of my get service stop process, if you have a process
running that happens to have the same name as a service, it's
going to get killed off.
Most of the time that's not the case. In Jeffrey's example,
I got a process name that happens to be actually a file I could
go looking for. So that is a good result that works out.
>> Can I show them... actually, you know what, I said that wrong.
It was actually the path...
>> The path that put it......
>> is the dir. Yeah. So dir takes a path, and process object has
a path. Now, notice in my screen we said, oh, you know, by name.
Well, you were doing it by name, right?
>> Right.
>> GSWB. And notice here's a name.
What was it I wanted to show you? Through...
okay. So notice this thing here.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Name, alias property service name. So unlike...
remember, I said that PowerShell, we're focused in on making
your life good because those people aren't focused in on that,
right, they're focused in on I'm writing this for myself, it's
going to be cool, or, hey, you're my developer buddy and we're
going to talk developer talk to each other, blah, blah, blah.
And so it's pretty inconsistent world. We're responsible for
trying to make it a consistent world for you. So whereas
you say service name and process was process name, we want to
say, no, you don't care about all that crap, you just want the name.
>> Name.
>> Okay. And so what we do is we take the type system, and remember
how I showed you XML, we tweaked the XML and we present it to
you simpler. One of the techniques we do for that is something
called an alias property. An alias property is something here,
we say, hey, we have this property name which is aliased to service name.
So the property... the object itself really only has this thing
called service name, but we say, hey, treat it as though it has
a name which... and when you ask for it, give them the service name.
And that makes it... that gives you a simplified consistent view
of the world, and it makes this interoperability stuff work.
Because if it turns out that, hey, I want to send something to
some command and it's accepting things by goo jar [Phonetic] and...
>> Right....
>> and I have one of those, but I call it a foo [Phonetic].
>> Right.
>> I just go and I say, okay, well, on my foo, you know, I'm going
to map its name to goo jar, I do that once, and then I can send
it to you.
>> As a matter of fact, this is a perfect setup for the first
stage in this. And so understand what he's... he's shown you
is that they've done a lot of work to make
PowerShell commands consistent. In other words, we had a service
name on the object, but they created an alias property called
name so it could work with other commandlets that accept by property name.
So they they're making it consistent for us. But there are times
when the greatest minds all think alike but just haven't had
a chance to get everything consistent yet. Let me give you an
example where this is going to break down.
This is one of my favorite commandlets, is get AD computer.
And I need to tell you that one of the things you need to be
kind of careful with is Microsoft, especially the product teams
when they work with this, they try to help you by not doing dangerous
things to yourself. Think about the technology underneath what
this commandlet's going to do. If I run this, who has this information?
Domain controller does. So this commandlet has to go out to a
domain controller, ask the domain controller for this information
and then spit this information back.
Look, quite honestly, if you only have a couple dozen computers,
that's not a big deal. But if you have 30,000 computers, this
could be a big deal. This could make your domain controller not
a domain controller for a while. And then when it spits the
data back, you could have some performance issues for a while.
So when you're running commandlets, you will notice, you know,
a lot of times you'll do a get commandlet and it will just run.
Commandlets that might be a little bit more dangerous, that's
not the case. What they do is they put things in them that are mandatory.
We mentioned this with get event log earlier. This is another
great commandlet that has an example. So let me show you.
If I just strike enter on get AD computer, huh-uh, bro, you got
to give me a little bit more information about this. You've got
to be... I don't want to get you everything. Really? So I'm
just going to put in a star.
This will work and it will get me everything. But notice what
I've done. I'm the one now that's made the decision to actually
get everything. So this is the commandlet that I'm going to use
for a second. So let me do this. Get AD computer.
And I'm just going to put in the filter, star, which means I'm
going to grab everything.
And I want to... here's my business problem. What I would like
to do is get the status of the bit service on every computer
in the network. I know it doesn't sound that creative, but it
gets better later. So get service name bits.
Understand what I'm trying to do. I'm trying to get a list of
all the computers from active directory, and I want them piped
to get service and so that get service will then grab the bit
service from all of them. Well, here's the thing. Let's see
if we can figure out how this is going to work or not work.
So first thing is that we do is I go through the whole process,
first of all, pipe to GMs to find out what kind of object am
I working with. I need to know this for by value in case it works
for by value. So AD computer object. Sounds great.
Probably ain't gonna happen because the nouns don't match, but
AD computer object, great.
Next thing I'm going to do is get help on get service and see
if it... dadadadada... see it if supports AD
computer object by value. And, guys, I'm going to make this a
little bit briefer. So rather than scrolling through every...
and stopping at every single one of them, let me just scroll
up to the things that say by value.
>> Can I show them a trick?
>> Yeah, sure.
>> Do that again and do minus show window.
>> So do show window, okay.
>> Yeah, show window. Okay. And so if you have... now search
by by value.
>> Oh. Man, see, this whole... this whole show... this whole
show window thing is just awesome.
>> Yeah. And then hit next.
>> Oh, wait a minute. I have to hit next. There we go. Oh, boy,
an object.
>> That's an object. Was that easy or what see?
>> See? So now look, look, look, we got it. Accept pipeline input.
You may have to watch me scroll, true, by value, we're looking good.
What kind of object does input object want? It wants a...
is that spelled exactly the same way as AD computer? No. So no
hookup by value.
>> So close.
>> Yeah, so close.
[Laughter]
>> So what we're going to do, then, is check for by property name.
Well, I have to take a look at what the properties are. And really
the only property I care about that I'm trying to send across
is whatever holds the computer name. So let's take a look at
that real quick. Get AD computer, filter star, well, gee, whiz,
just take one of them. There's a whole bunch of stuff that's
being sent across the pipe. The only thing I care about, though,
is where the computer name is. And that property is called name.
So let's go back to the show window and see if we have something
that supports name. So pipeline, by property name, and so let's
do this trick, by property name, and watch what happens. So we'll
find them.
Dash computer name. Hey, that supports by property name.
But remember what the rule is. This has to be spelled exactly
like this for by property to hook up. And it's not. In fact,
it's not spelled the same. But you know what is spelled the same
if I go down here? Oops. Wait. Which way? Looky.
>> Aim.
>> We do support by property name on something spelled exactly
the same. But look at what it says. It wants a service name.
So here's what's going to happen. If I try to run this, I'm
going to take a bunch of computer names and it's going to think
that I'm giving it service names. And unless you named your
computers after services, which would never be a good idea, this
is not going to work. The thing is... that really gets me is,
God, if there was only a way, if there only was a way where I
don't want this to be called name, I want it to be called computer
name, because if it's called computer name then it would match
in everything we're work... if there was only a way I could change
this property to say computer name.
>> And yet there is.
Do you want to show them?
>> You want to show them?
>> I don't have AD computer.
>> Oh. That's... you don't have AD computer. Well, let me show
them then.
So let's do the concept. So watch, guys.
Take a look.
Get service. And I'm just going to show you a quick concept.
I want you to see, I'm just going to work with one service to
keep it simple. You guys have seen a select properties before...
>> By the way, I don't think you've shown them computer name.
Have you shown them computer name? So, you know, get service
works against [Inaudible] computers.
>> Yes. Oh, yeah. Yeah, I should have shown you in the help file.
You'll see it has dash computer name. So I could use this against
remote computers, which is what I'm trying to get the active
directory commandlet to do.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm going to grab name and status, and I want you guys to see something.
Yeah, it's going to give me the name in the status. That's what
you would expect. But how many of you would expect to get an
error if this occurred? And usually when I'm at a conference,
this is exactly what I type. Because I can't type very well.
So it usually comes naem stitus.
Watch what happens.
See that?
Do you get what's going on here?
Wait a minute. A lot of people think that that should generate
an error. That shouldn't generate an error. That's a feature.
Let me show you. I'm going to pipe that to get member.
Look. It just created
new properties called naem and stitus.
[Laughter]
>> So here's the idea. I want you to think about this. I wonder
if I could take the existing property for AD computer called
name and change it to computer name. And the answer is yes.
However, the answer is yes,
but let me show you how this is going to work.
First of all, I'm going to select the property name
just so you can see I'm not cheating, and then I'm going to show
you some special syntax. And this syntax at first is a little
chewy, but it's in the help file for the select dash object.
And it's in the example.
>> That's going to be one of the things you want to learn.
It's a hash table syntax.
>> Yes.
>> And we use hash tables everywhere. So you're going to spend
the time, you're going to learn the syntax.
>> This syntax you must... you must... you're just going to have
keep typing it till you learn it. This is something you're going
to have to keep in. So it's an at sign with an open squiggly.
And what we have is the word called name equals and now you get
to create your own property name. What would I like this to
be called? I want it to be called computer name. So I'm going
to put in computer name.
And at this point, semicolon, and then you specify the expression
that will fill that column with data.
Well, let's do this. Expression equals.
And you're going to put that inside of squigglies. And there's
one squiggly left over. So inside here we want the current object
on the pipeline dollar sign underscore or you can use dollar
sign PS item with Version 3.
And what do I want from the object that's coming from get AD computer?
I want the original name property. So watch. Name. I'm going
to strike enter, and watch what happens.
>> Oohhh.
>> Dudes, dudettes, dudesses, oh, I've got myself a computer name
now property. Now, let me just show you how you're going to see
this on the Internet. A couple of just quicky things. This is a...
you'll hear this custom columns, calculated properties, people
use all these terms for this. But you almost never see anybody
type in this full syntax. They're going to shorten this up to
just an E, then they're going to shorten this up to just an N.
>> And why?
>> Because it's short.
>> Because I'm a fun person.
>> I can't type.
>> I can't type at all.
>> There's no way I'm going to figure out how to spell expression.
>> Expression? I know. I know. But, watch, guys, I want you to
see that this still works. So I've changed it. One other thing
I want show you, you're going to see this a lot on the Internet,
and you need to watch out for it. Used to be instead of name
this was called label. And everybody would abbreviate this as
an L. Well, I don't know about you, but when you see this on
a blog post or in a book, you can't tell the difference between
an L and the number 1.
So a lot of times you'll type it in wrong and you'll go, It just
doesn't work.
No. If you ever see an L or what looks to be a 1, always replace
it with an N; that way you get rid of all of those little ambigu-...
I can't say that word, but all those little problems, ambig-...
yeah, all those little problems.
>> Need wild cards for speech.
[Laughter]
>> So let's do this.
I don't really need this name in here anymore because I've managed
to create my own version. And I want to show you if you pipe
it to get member, see it says computer name. So looky.
When we pass it to the receiving commandlet, computer name is
going to match with computer name, by property name, and, lo
and behold, dununa-dununa-dununa, drum roll, drum roll, drum
roll, and the command was get service name bits.
>> Woooo.
>> Oh, come on, that is so wickedly cool.
>> Whoo.
[Laughter]
>> The guys in the back are going I don't know what the hell he
just did, but, okay, we'll go with it.
>> Woohoo.
>> Begging for the applause.
>> Yeah, pity applause. Golf clap. Here's the thing, is that,
you know, they're working to try to, you know, give you alias
properties to make some consistencies, but that's not always
going to be the case. Sometimes you're the one that has to do
it in-flight to make the consistency using a custom column or
calculated property. We use these a ton because there's so much
we can do with this.
So much we can do with this. And you'll see some more examples
of us using it in here.
But we do have the last...
the last possibility.
It's my favorite one.
Because everybody yells at me when I do this.
>> By the way, it's really worth spending time on this stuff.
This is the heart of PowerShell. This is the core concept, it's
the core power, it's where you get all your magic, so learning
this stuff, like spending some time, understanding how it really
works, getting familiar with the where, the pipelining, is the
heart of it. It's the investment.
>> Well, and I just have to say, and this is definitely...
for me, guys, this is what changed my ability to be productive
with PowerShell. When I learned this, this is what suddenly made
PowerShell, oh, I got this. Because I could discover whatever
it is I was looking for and now I knew how to put it together.
And if it didn't work, I knew how to troubleshoot it.
That's the important thing. I know we're going through it quickly
here, but, again, this is the most important thing and it does...
it changes... it makes you totally productive. Now, I've shown
you three ways so far...
>> By the way, and this... getting the stuff to work on multiple
machines, we're going to talk more about remoting, but that's
where you just become so productive. The number of people who
have come up to me at TechEd and had stories like... there's one...
I remember this one guy who said, oh, well, you know, his boss
brings everybody in on like a Tuesday and is like, oh, we got
to get this information from every single one of our servers,
it's top priority, got to have it by the end of the week, call
home, tell the folks you're going to be working late, doesn't
matter, we got to get this done. It's like uh, uh, everybody's
like uh, uh, uh. And so he goes back to his office and he's like,
wait a minute, I can do that with PowerShell. He says, Ten minutes
later, I had all the information. He said, It took a couple
more minutes to put it in an Excel spreadsheet.
>> Yeah.
>> So like 15 minutes I was done. I said, That's awesome.
What did you do? He says, Well, I went home, I took the rest
of the afternoon off.
>> And then he came back in the morning, showed his boss this
awesome report, he's like, Oh, you're a god.
>> And that's kind of the point, is I want to go home, so I want
to get this stuff done, right? And this is a primary way for
you to figure out how things work. So three ways we've done
it so far.
Get service to stop service. We matched by value. And that's
how we're going to try at the very beginning. When the nouns
don't match, by value probably isn't going to happen. Not always,
but probably is not going to happen. And we did get service
stop process where we had to start to match by property name,
which means the name of the
property coming across has to match the name of the parameter
of the receiving commandlet.
>> By the way, whenever you do that, that's where what if is your friend.
>> Oh, yeah. That is where what if is definitely your friend.
The third way is, well, there's a parameter that supports pipeline
input and you want to use that parameter, but what... the property
you're sending it doesn't have the right name. So you can change
it in flight using this syntax.
Here's the fourth and final. And, believe me, then we're ready
for a break here in just a second.
So get AD computer. I want you to understand my business problem,
first of all, to show you there's a commandlet... we're not
going to get a lot of time today to spend with this, with the
concept of WMI, but WMI is one of the greatest things. WMI and
SIM are one of the greatest things in the world. And I'm hoping
that a little bit later on Jeffrey will be able to have a chance
to talk about it.
But I just want to show you WMI is great for grabbing all kinds
of wonderful information. Here's an example of WMI grabbing just
some BIOS information. I also want to point out that this commandlet
supports computer name, which means I could get it from multiple computers.
If I could spell them correctly.
So understand that this the could be really useful to me. I might
want to do a whole hardware inventory, but I'm not going to want
to sit here and hand type in a bunch of computer names.
Instead I'm going to want to pipe a bunch of computer names from
an active directory. So what I'm doing is is I'm going to say
get AD computer, filter star,
pipe to get WMI object. And I want the class for BIOS.
Well, here's the thing.
You can spend the next two days
trying to get this to work.
Ain't gonna happen. If you know how to work this process that
we're showing you right here, here's what you would do, and you're
going to solve this in seconds rather than days.
First of all, you're going to pipe to GM to see what the object
type is because we want to check for by value. And I'm just
going to tell you right now by value is not going to work.
I got AD computer, but by value is not going to work. You know
how I know that? Because the next thing we do is we go look at
parameters that support pipeline input.
Well, let's do that. Get help.
Get WMI object dash full.
And, guys, I know we could do this with the show window, but
I just want you to see the beauty of this. Watch as it scrolls
by when I get to the parameters.
Throttle limit, no.
Recurse, no.
Query, no. Property, no.
>> Denied.
>> Name space, no. Locale, yeah, denied. List, no.
Impersonation, fun on a Friday night, but, no. It's filter,
no, computer says no. Every parameter says no.
No pipeline input. It will not take any pipeline input. Stop trying.
It won't take any pipeline input. So I see guys all the time
that go, okay, well then you can't do it. It's broke. They need
to fix that with PowerShell. Well, no, you can do it, just have
to know how. Let me show you. You know, I was showing you that...
how this commandlet get help... and I'm going to do the short
help for it.
This guy supports dash computer name. Well, here I want you
to take notice here. Let's look at dash computer name. See, dash
computer name and what he wants is a bunch of strings.
That's what he wants as an object, strings.
He'll take dash computer name, I just have to figure out how
to get it in there, get those computer names in there. So here's
what I'd like to do.
Get WMI object.
Whatever class I want.
And I would like to do dash computer name and get the computer
names in there. I'd like to do get like AD computer, filter, star.
Well, you can't do that because it screws up the argument, so
you have to put them in parentheses. Because remember what parentheses means.
I wasn't a big math fan, but those things are like order of operands or...
you're a smart guy, you know all that stuff. It's... it means
do this first before we do anything else. So what's going to
happen is what's ever in those parens, this parenthetical, it's
going to do that first, and that becomes the argument on this
dash computer name. But there's a small problem. Remember dash
computer name wants a bunch of string objects. I wonder what
this is providing me. As a matter of fact, let me show you.
Get AD computer. And you know how to do this now. Filter star.
What kind of object is this producing? Pipe it to GM.
It's giving me AD computer.
That doesn't say string.
Watch. Also it's giving me way too much information.
This is giving me all kinds of stuff I don't want... I just
want name. I just want to select...
I just want to select name. So get AD computer.
Filter star. Select the property name. Awesome. I've got the names.
This is what I want to throw into dash computer. But before
we try this, check it with get member.
Look at what the object type is.
AD computer. It doesn't say string here. So it's going to break.
Well, they thought of this. They solved this. What I really
want is I want
to extract those names and put them in that dash computer name argument.
In between the [Inaudible] I want to extract...
extract isn't the right word. I want to
expand this property. Now, you can only expand one. But look
at the difference on my screen how this looks.
See how you don't have this anymore? It's just the names of the computers?
Let's pipe it to get member. Looky. String. String.
>> Happy, happy.
So what we do is we... and I'm going to try to do this. I'm going
to try to right click on this.
And here's what we're going to do.
>> Right click.
>> Yeah, right click. I think I did that right. So get WMI object.
Whatever class I want in Win32 underscore BIOS dash computer name.
And here's what I want to put inside of the parentheses.
That whole thing.
Now, you might be saying, gee, whiz, that's an awful lot of work.
But as soon as you do this like two or three times, it's not
a lot of work. Because now what you couldn't solve before or
you were spending days banging your head on now just works.
And it just works because we couldn't pipeline to this commandlet,
darn, okay, forget about it, that's fine.
What do you want to use? I want to use dash computer name.
What does it want? It wants a string. So I want to grab all
the AD computers. I just want the property name. I don't want
all the other properties. I just want name. Send it to get member.
It's not a string. Oh, I need to expand that...
think extract that... those values out, and I get the string.
Now it's going to work. This is your last line of resort.
Now, don't use this as your first line of resort. That's not
the point. Because you want the power of the pipeline. So don't
do this first.
Do this last. And let me show you, and we're going to let Jeffrey
talk about this for a second, is that before we take a break
let me show you what I found out Microsoft's kind of doing to
help us out. You know how the
get WMI thing, it doesn't take any pipeline input? Well, I happen
to know that there's...
>> Wait, before you go there...
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> Up arrow.
>> Because this works perfectly. This works perfectly. But this
works in PowerShell Version 2.
PowerShell Version 3 we made it simpler.
>> Oh, let's make it simpler.
>> Okay. Hit delete, delete the select.
Oh, no, no, no, all the way from the end of the line to the select.
>> Oh, all the way from the end of the line to the select.
>> Yeah. Get rid of all that.
>> Oh, get rid of all that.
>> Yeah. More.
>> More?
>> More line. Okay. Now end paren. End parenthesis.
That's begin paren.
>> Oh, end paren.
>> Yeah. Okay. Space.
>> Oh, I see what you did. Oh.
>> Dot name.
>> Oh, I see what you're doing. Dot name. Yeah. Yeah.
>> See, that's the deal. That's... that dot name basically is
shorthand syntax to do that command line.
>> Which is what you were showing earlier with...
>> Exactly....
>> casting to XML. And, guys, one of the things is we're going
to start showing you... as we get close to scripting, we're going
to be showing you working with variables and using this dot syn-...
this dot syntax so you get more and more comfortable with it,
because now that was lot a lot easier to type as soon as you
know more about that dot syntax. So this is awesome. See, it
still worked.
And as I just showed... oh, let me show you again because I don't
think the thing was on there. Let me show you. Oh, what's going on?
>> Is this hard for you? I could go over there.
>> Well, no, it's... it's... it's something has gone awry, and
I think my...
ah, there we go. Something... the computer we were waiting on.
So this syntax, if you can see it, is... it works the exact
same way. So I can execute it. But I don't want to do it again
because it was holding up on one of the machines.
>> Oh, was it?
>> One last thing to show you, and then we'll take a break, is
get WMI object doesn't support any input, but there's a...
if you're working with WMI, there's a whole new way of doing this.
And if you were to do get help on something called get SIM instance,
and you were to take a look at the parameters and what they...
what parameters accepted pipeline input, you would see that this
is now the replacement for this. Because the new one now supports
pipeline input in the places where you want it to support pipeline input.
So the idea is that going forward some of the commands that you
may run across, especially if they're four or five years old
that did need support line input, may start to support it.
But if it doesn't, you do have this last line of resort.
Now, as a final note, make sure... this is so very important,
well, you get...
>> I was going to show them one more thing.
>> Oh, go ahead. Show them one more thing.
>> Okay. I'm going to take over your machine.
>> Okay. It's all yours, man.
>> Okay. This did not work. Yeah, right. Of course. Okay.
Here we go.
Okay. I'm taking over his machine.
>> He's going to take over my machine. While he's taking it over,
get Don Jones' book,
Learn Windows PowerShell in a Month of Lunches, chapter 9.
You've got to know that. That's the most important thing.
That's what we just did in here.
>> Okay. So now I'm going to show you something crazy freaky,
freaky, freaky, freaky powerful.
>> Oh, let's get freaky.
>> Yeah, we're going to get freaky.
>> Freaky, freaky, freaky.
Okay, sorry.
>> Settle down.
>> [Laugher] Okay. So this is pretty advanced stuff.
But why not end on something really powerful. Okay? And this
is something called...
what do we call these? We call these script parameters, I think
is the term for them. So now what we're going to do is, remember,
the original problem was get AD computer minus filter star pipe
to get WMI object
Win32 BIOS, and it was this computer name that we couldn't get
a value for.
>> Right.
>> Darn. Okay. So here's the deal.
Script block. Whenever you see the... what do you call them?
>> The squigglies?
>> Squigglies.
>> Yeah, I like to do my hips myself, but for the squigglies.
>> Whenever you see the squigglies, that's called a script block.
That represents code.
If you give a script block to a property, to a parameter which
doesn't take a script block, then what it is is, oh, you must
be asking for a script parameter.
And what it does is it takes the value of the current object,
assigns it to dollar sign underbar and runs the script and takes
the value and puts it in there.
>> Oh, this could be totally awesome.
>> And so what you say is you say dollar sign underbar dot...
was it name?
>> It was name.
>> Name. Okay. By the way, you can do anything you want here.
You could say to upper, you know, anything. But here we just
do this. So, again, what's going to happen is you're going to
run this, you're going to take the current object, you're going
to assign it to this, and then you're going to run this code.
And so each object you're going to get the value of the name,
and then you're going to run this with the value.
Is that crazy powerful or what?
>> You know, you realize that you've made that so much easier
that everybody's going to like you better than they like me now.
>> Yeah, I know.
>> Because I drug them through that long...
>> That's the plan.
>> Okay, well, it worked because I took them through that long
thing and then you just made it really short and sweet.
>> Yeah.
>> Congratulations. Very nice job.
>> There you go. So have fun with that.
>> So, folks, we're going to go ahead and take a ten-minute break.
When we come back, we get into...
>> Get him some coffee.
>> Yeah, yeah, get me some coffee because I need more. And we're
going to go into something that is going to change the way you manage.
Now you're going to take the tools that you started to learn
today and we're going to get into one of the most powerful things
in the world, remoting. And we want to talk to Jeffrey about
remoting before we get into it. This is totally awesome stuff.
So see you guys in ten minutes.