[Music]
>> Good morning and welcome to the Microsoft Virtual Academy and
this is a special virtual academy Jumpstart of getting started
with PowerShell.
>> The best one.
>> It's going to be the best one.
>> The best one ever.
>> Of getting started with PowerShell. Whether you are an IT
pro or even a dev this is the strongest most powerful management
tool you have in your arsenal to take control of your network.
And we are going to take you through today step by step.
And when I say we, well it's a very special training event today.
I am Jason Jason Helmick, but this is the inventor of PowerShell,
distinguished engineer, Jeffrey Snover.
>> Howdy.
>> And this is going to be a great even for all of us today.
We are going to take you step by step on how to get started working
with PowerShell and who better to learn it from than Jeffrey Snover.
So I tell you what Jeffrey let's start out with some intro.
>> Sure.
>> I will flip the little slide thing.
>> So howdy, I am Jeffrey Snover. I am a distinguished engineer
and I started off the PowerShell team about twelve years ago,
maybe a little bit more, and that worked out pretty well because
after having shipped a couple of versions they made me a distinguished engineer.
And then the lead architect for Windows Server 2012.
>> Awesome.
>> And that worked out pretty well. So now I am the lead architect
for Windows Server and System Center Data Center products.
So I am having some fun.
>> Oh boy, having a lot of fun. And with PowerShell and what we
are going to talk about, the Windows Management framework, all
of this bundled together. It's not just in server 2012, but it
works all the way backwards to 2003 so that we can do all of
this management with everything that we have in our environment,
not just necessarily the latest and greatest.
>> That's the plan. We are back to filling up your arsenal.
I like that term.
>> I like that term too. That's turning out pretty good. So let
me tell you a little bit about myself. I am Jason Helmick and
I work with Concentrated Technologies. I do this for a living.
I love to train on PowerShell and I also work as an engineer
and a consultant mainly doing a lot of automation with it.
I am the author of a new book that's coming out
Windows IIS in a Month of Lunches, tough title to say. And it's
not only about learning IIS, but it's using PowerShell for it.
So, just some interesting little tidbits about me, truly what
the best thing to know about me is that I get to sit next to
him as we do this. So this is going to be a lot of fun.
Let's start off with showing you what we are going to talk about today.
So as you can see from the agenda we are going to cover several
topics today and it's actually quite a few of them. We are going
to start off with one of my favorite ones which is "Don't Fear
the Shell". I think a lot of IT guys, when they first get started
with this, I hear this all the time, and they are scared to get
started with PowerShell.
>> Yeah.
>> They are not used to a command line. They don't want to say
they ware scared, but they are not used to using a command line.
>> Deep down they see that console window and they are just like, "Ah".
>> I don't know what to do.
>> Deer in the headlights.
>> So one of the first things we are going to want to do is get
rid of some of that fear. Show you how straightforward you can
get started with PowerShell. And then we are going to take you
into what PowerShell starts to look like. And then of course
we are going to talk about the reasons why PowerShell even exists.
And there are some incredibly important ones. We will also get
into the help system. That's probably one of the most important
things that we do today and the pipeline and extending the shell.
All of this stuff that we are going to do is going to make more
sense as we hit it. Looking at what objects are and drilling
into the pipeline. What is that weird character I keep seeing
between these commands? And we will get into one of the most
important advantages that you have which will be PowerShell remoting,
which will let you do a lot of your stuff in scale.
>> That's where it get's fun.
>> That's where it really get's fun.
>> By the way, so people should be doing these exercises with us.
So you should be at your computer, fire up a PowerShell window
and type along with us. That's the way you get the most out of
this course.
>> And actually I think that's the best way to get the most out
of this. I know you want to kickback and kind of sip some coffee
or whatever and listen to us, but keep your fingers close to
that keyboard and that console and PowerShell so you can work
with us on this.
>> And you should be, well are you going to tell them about the Q&A?
>> Yeah, yeah, as a matter of fact I have got a slide coming up.
Oh here, let's do the expectations things on our target audience
and then we will talk about how to join us. This was designed
for IT pros, however if you are a dev please join us on this.
This was designed for IT pros to be quick deep dive and get started
with PowerShell. There are so many guys and gals out there right
now who are trying to get started with PowerShell and sometimes
you find it really difficult. Well these are these ideas to get
you through the difficulty. And we are not just doing an introductory
level, we are going to go in pretty deep with using PowerShell.
And it doesn't matter what product you want to use it with.
Whether you want to use it with Active Directory or SharePoint
you have got to know the tool and if you know the tool then the
products are easy to deal with. So if you are an IT pro, if you
work in help desk, if you are a developer interested in what
PowerShell can do for you this is the place to be. And as a
couple of additional resources first of all we have chat available.
If you are all in on chat you can chat us questions and I will
constantly be reminding you to chat in questions. We have an
amazing support staff out there today. A lot of the PowerShell
MVP's are joining us today to help answer questions and we will
be out there answering questions. So we want you to joint in,
contribute and ask whatever questions you have. And we will
do the best we can to make sure you all get an answer to it.
>> And the PowerShell community is blessed with some fantastic MVP's.
A number of which are online and they will be coming and going
throughout the day. So don't hesitate to ask questions. You have
some rock stars out there.
>> You certainly do. And I also want you to keep in mind that
this particular virtual academy we are going to have a second
session, not the same thing, we are going to go beyond this session
further and further into scripting and tool making here in just
a couple of weeks on August first, right.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> So you want to join the MVA community. As a matter of fact
you can join the MVA community, get signed in online and as you
go through the videos available out there you get points and
for right now you can get 50 special MVA points if you put in
the code that's at the bottom of the screen. So make sure you
keep track of what's going on with the MVA community so that
you can get more sessions just like this one. I don't know do
you think we are ready to maybe get started?
>> Yeah, let's go.
>> Let's get into this.
>> My favorite topic.
>> I know and I just love talking about this. So folks, here
we go, we are going to get into "Don't Fear the Shell".
Come on, you can hear the music right. Don't fear the shell,
duh nuh nuh, okay maybe not.
>> Uh, no.
>> Okay, maybe not.
We will stop that then.
So look we are going to go through and overview of what PowerShell
is and why it even exists. And of course this is a great time
for Jeffrey to help us understand why we even have this.
And then we are going to start going into how to take some of
the fear out of running PowerShell. We will show you how to
get it installed and how to get it set up. So, let's rock and roll.
First of all, the purpose to PowerShell, I just want to point
out, do you see this slide?
>> Yeah.
>> You are, so see the "you" and the "them"? That picture of you,
that's a picture of me when I was younger. I swear to, no, it's
not really a picture of me. So here's the idea: you are sitting
there struggling with the day to day events of everything that's
around you. You have got projects that you have to have to have done.
There are things that are on fire and everything is going on
and then you have them. Your end users, your boss, all of these
people that are like, "We need this now, we need this now" and
in Microsoft environments this has been a challenge. We have
had some tools and you have had some scripting languages and
we had VBScript, but there were certain limitations that would
challenge us and it wasn't quite complete enough. It was also
kind of hard and doing automation and solving problems was a
huge challenge.
Then came a long this product that you made. So why is it, what
is it that you were trying to solve for all of us guys in IT?
>> Yeah, you know when I came to the company I said, "We need
an automation strategy" and they said, "Well, we have an automation
strategy" and I said, "Really, where?" and they said, "Well,
here" and it was VBScript. I was like, "No, my friends, that's
not an automation strategy". Then they would say, "Well here,
have got these great API's" and I was like, "No my friend that's
not automation strategy".
>> Oh, I don't even like the sound of that.
>> Exactly and so what I knew was that we needed to have an interactive
shell, an environment that someone would say, "Hey, go explore
the system, try this, try that, try that and be able to get things done".
Then from there the idea is that I notice that I type the things
over and over again why don't I put it in a script and then just
run it from there. Then say, "Well that's great, it's reduced
my repetitive strain injury now I would like to parameterize it".
Oh, so I would like to parameterize it, now I can use it for
a wide arrange of things and now I would like to share it with you.
And now we would like to use it to manage thousands of machines.
So we had this model and we called it the Admin Development Model,
which really Bruce, super star Bruce, says the average lifetime
of command line scrip, or sorry of a script, starts at the prompt
and ends at the character turn. It was very important that it
be an interactive environment so that you can explore and honestly
have fun. I mean if there are two things you get out of today's
session: one is a spirit of exploration. Hey this is a great
environment to go explore, explore, explore and then two just
how much fun it is. I mean it's just a blast to be able to use.
Then from there to be able to automate, you know, automate, automate, automate.
If we had just transformed a click, click, click experience to
a click, click, experience then okay that's good, lots of people
prefer this over this, but you really wouldn't have transformed
the platform. It's the ability to then do this, this and this
and then say, "Save
and then just click and run".
>> And I just want to emphasize that we are unaccustomed in Windows
environments of having an interactive shell a real time solve
your problem tool. I mean we have always had basic commands,
but that really wasn't solving our problem. This means solve
your problem and then literally copy, paste or hit save and now
you can automate it.
>> Exactly.
>> And it doesn't require any more then have fun finding and solving
the problem and now I am on my way.
>> Yeah, you know you might say, "Well, why do I need to do that?"
And the answer is because every body's scenario is different.
We were talking in the car last night about how in exchange the
gooey . I mean honestly we spend a lot of time talking to customers
and trying to understand the scenarios and put that into the
gooey's that just click, click, click, but the reality is and
Jason was telling me this story, that hey I did that, but then
what I needed to do was I needed to have different quotas for
these types of users verses those types users verses those types
of users and the gooey didn't help me. I had to go do a ton
of clicking. So we might have gone and said, "Oh, okay we will
add that to the gooey", but then all of a sudden if you try and
deal with every bodies scenarios in the gooey it becomes big,
complex and hideous and then you can't use the gooey.
>> And I think that's one of the biggest issues will start to
see at first. There is nothing wrong with using a graphical interface.
I mean sometimes I use it too and I use it for things I just
need to do once, one off, once every blue moon. You know, creating
a site link in active directory. The graphical is great for
that, but when you have business challenges that can't be met,
such as, and I think what we were talking about last night was
I needed to set the mailbox limits of a particular OU in active directory.
Well the graphical doesn't support that and I don't expect Microsoft
to solve that problem for me because how are they supposed to
know what my issues are? PowerShell is a way that you can solve
those issues and that you can get these business problems solved
and it doesn't take six months. You get them solved right now
and then you automate them. So the purpose to PowerShell really
is all about making you more effective getting stuff done faster
and solving problems that you probably had a hard time solving before.
>> Right, because often they are unique.
>> Yeah, very unique. So let's see here: installing PowerShell.
So right now there is a lot of, it's kind of confusing for a
lot of folks. First of all let's talk about some of the versions
of PowerShell. Nobody should have V1 right now, right.
>> You should upgrade V1.
>> So V2 came out a couple of years ago and
you should have V2 on Windows 7 and you should have it on 2008,
2008 R2 and V2 also works and is part of the update stream that
you can update for Windows XP, and shame on you if you still
have Windows XP and of course Server 2003.
Now V3 is the new one and V3 came out for Windows 2008 and for
Server 2012. If at all possible as the administrator you want
V3 on your box and you are going to see plenty of examples of
that today, of needing to have V3.
You can upgrade V3 and have that on your box for both
Windows 7 and Server 2008 R2 and that's it though, right?
>> Windows Server 2008 and 2008 R2.
>> And 2008 RN, I have got to make sure I get them all in there.
So you can upgrade to V3. Now you don't have to rush out right
now and start upgrading your servers to V3 and you should take
some cautions out there. There are some products that aren't
quite ready to handle V3 and there is plenty of information on that.
So don't be that guy or gal that makes that mistake and accidentally
upgrades a server to V3 if the product running on it is not ready
for it, but on your administrative machine you have got to have V3.
You are going to love the features we show you today with it.
>> Yeah, you should always read the release notes. We tell you
what it works with, you know, like if you have this don't install that.
>> Yeah, release notes are really good along with testing is also
really good as well. If you take a look at the slide real quick
you will see that there is a place where you can download.
It's a strange name to download PowerShell 3; it's called the
Windows Management Framework. We are going to talk a lot more
about what the term the Windows Management Framework means.
It's not just PowerShell and there is a link there for you so
that you can get it downloaded. Now today if you have V2 on your
laptop you will be fine, but probably during lunch you are going
to want to use V3. And just to let you guys know so that we can
get the confusion out of the way what we are doing today is how
to use PowerShell. What we show you how to use today is going
to work on V2, V3 and that mythical thing that's coming out sometime
in the future V4ish like stuff. So you are going to be just fine
with whatever version you have.
It's all going to be about the tool today.
Well, let's talk about launching PowerShell. How do you find
PowerShell to launch it? And guys I am actually going to demonstrate
this off of my box real quick.
One of the most interesting things here is if you are on Windows
8 you have this magnificent Windows key that brings up your desktop
for you. And to find PowerShell it's actually very simple.
Just start typing the word PowerShell. Now I have to tell you
the first thing I always do is right click and pin this to my
task bar.
>> I do too.
>> You are going to have PowerShell open more then anything else
that you work with. So you want to make sure you right click
and get this guy pinned. I have already got mine pinned down
here on my desktop so that you can see it. Now if you are working
with a pre-Windows 8 operating system you are going to have to
click on the start menus. And I have got a screen shot of what
that looks like here in the slides.
You will click on the start menu, as soon as I can figure out
how to bring the slide back up, and it's this guy over here.
You are going to go under accessories and then Windows PowerShell
will be at the bottom. And you are going to notice that there
are two kinds of them out here. You are going to see some repeats,
X86 verses ones that aren't X86.
The X86 are obviously the 32 bit versions. You don't want to
run those; you want to run the 64 bit version on your 64 bit OS.
And we will talk a little bit later about the ISE, but this is
a great scripting editor that we can use as well. So as long
as you have got PowerShell to go we are ready to start to work
with it.
>> Rock and roll baby.
>> Now, let's talk a second about comfort.
Comfort is important like these chairs right here this studio
are very, very comfortable and that's very nice. We are going
to spend a lot of time, and I am rocking back and forth because
they are so comfortable.
>> Swaying.
>> Swaying. We are going to spend a lot of time looking at this console.
And PowerShell uses, does it use every possible character on
the keyboard?
>> No actually there is the up arrow.
>> Great, it's the up arrow that we don't use.
Oh, that's awesome. Well guys this is what I am talking about.
First of all let me launch PowerShell and show this to you.
Now I am going to launch it. I am logged in as a regular user
account and I want you to notice that when I launch PowerShell
the first thing is you take a look at the top of the screen here,
see how it says Windows PowerShell? If you want to do some administration
that's not what you want it to say. So let me close this and
show you if you are in as a regular user. You want to right
click and do run as administrator. If you are an administrator
it will already launch it with administrator. If not it will
prompt you for credentials so that you can have administrative access.
We are going to talk about security later, but this is actually
an important thing. Notice as I am looking at the console right
now this is something that we are going to be staring at for
a long time. So there are a couple of things that you definitely
want to be able to tell the difference in.
>> By the way, one of the tricks that is if you are trying to
do something and it's not working, like this morning, I was trying
to set some things up and I did get VM and it showed me nothing.
I was like, "Oh do I have the wrong machine"? I recently provisioned
it, did I like forget to set things up? And then I looked and
saw that I wasn't in admin mode. So then I bring it up in admin
mode and I say, "Get VM" and you see all your VM's. So if something
is going a little wonky go check and see that you are running
as admin.
>> And I just have to say that we are going to be doing several
things today and out of those things that we are doing today
if you are not in administrative mode it isn't going to work.
It's going to be very wonky. You are going to get error messages,
access denied messages and so you want to make sure you are in
as administrator mode. Take a look at the characters that I have
on the screen. Can you see the difference on your screen what
those characters are?
>> You zoom it.
>> Well no, I want them to look at it and say, "I can't tell the difference".
I want them to go, "No, I don't know what it is".
>> Don't use zoom it.
>> Yeah, don't use zoom it then. This is important, you need to
make sure that this screen you can see these individual characters.
I have got a grave character or a back tick character and then
a single quote. And there are only a couple of pixels in difference.
So here is actually one of the most important things to do when
you are getting ready to use PowerShell. I am going to go in
here to the properties and we are going to adjust this console.
Now I am not going to change mine because that will change all
the views up, but let me kind of show you the idea here.
Under fonts you want to use a font that is nice, bold and thick
and they gave you one called Lucida console. Did I say that right?
>> I don't know.
>> I have no idea, console .
>> I say Lucida, never mind.
>> That's okay. Console is a nice font but its thinner. I prefer
the heavier weight font and then you want to adjust the font
size, but when you do that to get it to a nice font size you
are going to notice that in this preview paint that the pretty
PowerShell window is going to extend to the right and go to the bottom.
And these are all bad things and let me tell you why. When PowerShell
is giving you information it wants to sometimes put information
all the way to the right and all the way to the bottom. So if
your screen has extended beyond the boundaries of your desktop
you are not going to see anything.
And you don't want scroll bars all over the place. So let me
show you how to fix that.
>> Oh, you don't use bold? I always use bold.
>> Do you use bold?
>> Always.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
>> That scares me because it feels like you are yelling at me
or something.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Well, do you want to turn bold on?
>> I always do.
>> Okay, we will turn bold on.
>> I find, well here's the deal, when you present, if any of you
every present to the audience always use bold because it's just
easier to read a couple of hundred feet away.
>> Well it screwed up my desktop. I don't want to turn it on
now, so there.
>> Okay.
>> Now in layout, layout is where you are going to adjust screen
width so that it fits. And then what you want to do is fit just
like this in the preview window. Let me show you two things:
the windows size for width is right here and that will adjust
its width. And I will screw mine up for a second and see how
it's kind of going off to the right over there. You don't want
that, you want your width so that it fits so that you don't have
a horizontal. I think that's this way, horizontal scroll bar.
When you adjust the window width size you also want to make sure
you keep the buffer size. You don't want things going off into
the buffer where you will never be able to see it. Height is
an important one as well. I want you to notice as I scroll up
and down this height what I don't want to do is scroll that all
the way below my desktop, because then when you see data it will
get put down at the very bottom and you won't see it. So I want
it to fit on my desktop. A vertical scroll bar you have will
be okay. Make sure that for the height buffer size you get at
least 3000 or greater. And I want to warn you that when you are
working with some products that have a PowerShell console that
console is set to 300 by default. So you definitely want to
change that or you are going to lose information and not be able
to scroll back and see it. When it comes to colors . Oh dude,
I am not changing the colors because I like the color scheme
you picked out.
>> Oh, good.
>> But if you want to change the colors to something that you
like to read, you want to make it green screen, whatever or come
up with some weird color combination knock yourself out, but
I am going to leave it at the default color size.
>> Yellow is good.
>> Yeah I know, I thought the yellow would look great. The important
thing is that your console is now ready to go, it's all set up
and it's in a comfortable font. So now while we move on take
a second and make sure you have got a nice looking PowerShell
console to take a look at.
So let's see what we are doing next here. I think we are ready
to get into some demonstration stuff.
Oh, yeah, look, look.
>> Oh man that's old.
>> You have got this mild mustache going. This is great, get
PowerShell, this is awesome.
So let's talk a little bit and start of by taking some of the
fear out of PowerShell. So, before we talk about this magic word
cmdlet you needed to come up with your own commands. Not the
Windows native ones, you needed your own commands. Why the term cmdlet?
>> So there are two answers to that. So the first is that
PowerShell we wanted to have a model of composition, okay.
So the model of composition if you actually take a look at it
the commands that you write are really, really small and the
idea is that then you leverage the engine to do common processing.
So if you had each one of the cmdlets try and do big tasks by
themselves, I want to get things, I want process things and I
want to format them, then every developer would be doing things differently.
You know, well I like the term sort and you like the term order
and order by and all that. So we said, "No, no, you write the
things that you and only you can use, do and then leverage the
engine to do everything else".
So these commands got really, really small and that was the whole point.
They are really, really small and you use the pipeline to do
bigger tasks and because of that you get regularity. That is
to say you are going to learn something and then you can use
it over and over again. So that's where the term cmdlet came from.
But then when we went to bring it out the documentation people
said, "No way, you can't do that, we don't make up terms.
It's called command". It was like, "Well no, we are going to
call it cmdlet". And then it just went to the mat and was like,
"No, no, no, no". And so I said, "I will tell you what bring
up a search window" and they said, "Huh" and I said, "Search
for command". And there was like X hundred million things.
And I said, "Now search for cmdlet" and it was X thousand.
I said, "Every single one of those is related to PowerShell"
and they were like, "Oh, search engine optimization".
>> There you go, a little SCO on using the term cmdlet.
>> Exactly.
>> And I just have to say that my wife refers to them as cmdlets
because that's the way they are spelled, but at any rate cmdlets.
Now how a cmdlet looks is also kind of bazaar if you have never
been at the command line. I mean if you have been at the command
line you see DIR, but now you are seeing these verbs and we have
got this dash and we have got this noun. Why did you sort of
name it that way?
>> Yeah, a lot of people take a look at PowerShell and they say,
"Oh, it looks very much like UNIX" and by the way just so you
know we actually tried to use UNIX. We didn't start of wanting
to invent something. We started off saying, "I have got to solve
a customer problem". So there were some really great tools out
there, the UNIX tools. So my first effort was to get those tools
available on Windows, but it turned out that didn't work and
the reason why is because UNIX is very much a document oriented
operating system, which is to say that a lot of the management
is done through document or files whereas Windows is an API oriented
operating system, okay. Now both have their advantages, but here's
the thing the management is completely different. So when I
got BASH, and AWK, and SED and GREP available on Windows it didn't
help that much, why? Then you go and say AWK, AWK doesn't work
against the registry, and GREP doesn't work against WMI and SED
doesn't work against active directory. So in UNIX those tools,
those text manipulation tools are management tools, but on Windows
they are just text manipulation tools and there is not much text
so it didn't help. So we had to invent our own stuff. So then
the question is . Well we want to invent as little as possible
and so we leveraged a lot of the concepts of UNIX, the compositional
model, but UNIX, love UNIX, you guys did a great job, but on
the other hand it has weaknesses as well. And this is an area
where we looked more to VMS DCL or the AS400. They have very
good production oriented environments and they were extraordinarily
regular in their environments, which is to day you had verb-noun
and then this well defined set of parameters. And what happened,
the first time I learned it, I was a UNIX guy for a long time
and then I had to do VMS and I got on and was like, "I hate this
thing, I despise this thing, It's a piece of junk". And I would
go around telling everyone this and then it was like, okay, but
I have got to do it for my job. And I would try some more and
it was just that I hated it and at some point I had to just sit
myself down and said, "Put your big boy pants on Jeffrey, you
have got to learn this" and so it was like okay, stop, get out
of your head condemning things and just like experience it.
And so about an hour later I am like, "Hey, you know, this thing
is pretty cool" and then two hours later it was like something
new comes up and having learned a set of things I said, "Boy,
I wonder if that works?" and it worked. So what happened was
you learned this schema, verb-noun or
slashes there, but then it was a schema. You learned it once
and then you were able to do it over and over and over again.
And that was the joke at Deck. At Deck we used to say, "Hey somebody
put a phish finder on the VAX, can you manage it?" and it was
like sure show phish finder, get phish finder/nolog/confirm.
>> And it think that's really, that's the epitome of what's going
to help us all out not only today, but going forward, the fact
that you get used to, "I want to work with X". Well, I know
that I have got these common verbs that I am going to use.
I am going to be able to get this. I am going to be able to
set this, you know, change it. I am going to be able to new,
create something new. And I think that's very important.
And I started out in AS400 and my first, well while I was being
trained there was a problem and my first thing was, "Can't we
just reboot it?" and I thought the operator was going to punch me.
>> He should have.
>> Yeah, he should have. So hey guys let me show you what these
cmdlets are. Take a look at my current directory location.
Now if I was in something like DOS you guys know that I could
do CD:\, but we have cmdlets now. So watch: set-location
C;\, yeah that's cool. Now if I wanted to get something like
a directory listing in DOS you guys know you can do DIR, but
here is the interesting thing we have cmdlets for this. So get-childitem
will get me a directory listing. And if I want to clear this
screen, if this was DOS we would do CLS, but we have a cmdlet
for that called clear-host.
Please tell me that you are not impressed yet.
[Laughter]
We have got the guys in the back there going, "Yeah, that was,
let's start to take the fear out of PowerShell". One of the
things that helped me tremendously, especially when I got started
with PowerShell was that yes there are cmdlets and yes we are
going to show you how to discover and learn and use those cmdlets,
but you can start using PowerShell right now even if you don't
know those cmdlets. Let me show you, this is kind of interesting.
I am going to close my shell and reopen it again.
So if I want to change from this directory location back to the
root of C it worked, if I want to get a directory listing
DIR worked just perfectly, if I want to clear the screen, CLS,
see it's working as I would expect and here's the interesting
thing let's see if I was a UNIX guy how would I get a directory
listing, LS.
How would I clear this screen? Well, clear.
It's doing UNIX stuff and it's doing Windows stuff and it's making
me happy because I can be a Windows guy and I can start using PowerShell.
A UNIX guy can start using PowerShell. My question is why is
that working?
>> Yeah, so what we do is we have got a regular experience, right.
So you have got get child item, set location, etc and you can
always use those things. And then what we did was we put personalities
on it, which is to say we knew that UNIX guys would be coming
to this. We knew that DOS guys would be coming to this and so
we have aliases.
So as much as possible we wanted people's first experience to
not be a frustrating one. That they try a set of things and they
just work. PS continues to work.
>> Exactly and think this is one of the interesting things is
that they are aliases. And aliases think of them as sort cuts
to real cmdlets. So we are not using the actual LS command or anything.
It's pointing to a PowerShell cmdlet, but the idea was, and I
love your use of the term personalities, we built personalities
into this. It's that it makes it comfortable for whatever environment
you are coming from so that you can get started right away.
As a matter of fact let me just kind of show you, get-alias
gives you a list of the current aliases. By the way you guys
should print this out and memorize this in the next few minutes
so you have all the aliases. But this is what allows you to start
working and things like making a directory. I can make a directory,
oh boy, see I can go right to work right away. And this starts
to bring us to another .
>> If you were a UNIX guy you would use?
>> mkdir, right.
>> We could give it try.
>> Let's see mkdir Jeffrey.
>> I hope this works.
>> Awesome. [Clapping] It's all that easy.
So basically your normal command line experience you can bring
right to PowerShell, but wait there's more.
[Laughter]
Yes, there's more.
>> You are going to get a Ginsu knife out of this.
>> Even better than a Ginsu knife. Now first of all I just want
to kind of point out that we are going to talk about help extensively,
but if you want to get help you can type help. And if you are
a UNIX person and want to type help you can type MAN. Now personally
I think UNIX is kind of sexist for the whole MAN thing, but in
PowerShell if you want to get a list of aliases you can type
get-alias, but there's an alias for get alias called GAL.
And see this is what makes me so happy is that PowerShell isn't
sexist so you should use this.
Anyway, stupid, so here is where it gets really cool.
Do you know what you can do from PowerShell besides working in
an environment that already kind of feels comfortable? I can
use Windows native commands. I love this.
Ping a computer and it works.
>> Woo hoo.
>> Yeah, woo hoo. I can run notepad and I know everyone is impressed now.
Oh look, calculator and oh hey, you know what I haven't tried
this yet on Windows 8 I should try this. Do we still have MS Paint?
Oh, this is awesome.
Okay, but the point was this, is that you can still use your
Windows native commands in here. You guys are always checking
IP configuration and all that stuff. Don't be that guy or that
gal and I have to tell you, this is one of the funniest things,
I was teaching an advanced scripting class for PowerShell and
this guy, I have know him a long time, was writing a magnificent
tool to go out and do a bunch of things to a couple other computers.
And he is sitting here going, "Oh my script is broken, can you
help me?" and I am like, "Oh, well what's your problem?" and
he says, "Well the script because it's getting those two machines,
but it's not getting anything from that machine". And I looked
at him and I said, "Well first of all don't forget you are an engineer.
What do you usually do if a machine is not responding? How do
you test that?" And he says, "Oh, I will ping it." and I am like,
"Yeah, see if it's even turned on, very good". So he is sitting
at a PowerShell console and do you know what he did?
>> Yes.
>> Start program, accessories, opened up command prompt to type ping.
I literally looked at him and went, "Get out".
[Laughter]
So the idea guys is you have your Windows native commands and
they work the way you expect them to work so you have an environment
to get started in. So between aliases helping you out and between
running Windows native commands the idea is open up PowerShell.
Don't open up the command prompt, open up PowerShell and start
using PowerShell, because you are going to start them learning
the cmdlets, which we are going to do today. But you are going
to start learning the cmdlets and make your learning curve much
easier this way. It was designed for you to do it this way and
so make your life easy and just go ahead and start using it.
And make sure you show your other administrative friends.
Open up the shell and start using it. It's going to work for you.
So at least that's taking a little bit of the fear out of it.
>> Let's hope.
>> So besides having aliases folks we want to do kind of a reminder
for you.
>> Oh wait can you go back?
>> Oh yeah, yeah, I can go back.
>> Can I show them something? Okay, go to my screen.
Okay, hoo ha, perfect, let's see.
Okay, so I don't know if you know this, but the aliases we saw,
right, so we saw aliases for gal pwd, right. So there are these
personalities, but if you take a look there are just a ton of
these things.
So you notice like what are they alias to? They are all verb-noun,
verb-noun, yeah, okay, but the aliases are very regular as well.
Okay, so take a look at this: let's say gal g star, okay notice
wild cards. So notice all the G's start with get.
>> You know what I don't think I have actually ever noticed that.
>> Now here's the thing. That's sort of obvious, right.
>> Well apparently not because I .
[Laughter]
>> But, here's the interesting thing look at this one: gsv.
Now let me see if I can get zoom it working here. Look at that,
so get service, gsv. So then the question is well what about
if I did gal star sv?
And look there, so you have got some, but gsv, sasv,
start service, spsv, and stop service. So look at this sasv, okay.
So let's see, I am getting good at this, sasv is start service.
So sv for service, let's see gal sa star and look start, start, start.
So it's not always the case, right, sal al for alias, but yeah,
sa jv. So we have even tried to be thoughtful and shematize the
aliases as well.
>> And you have made them easy to search through and this is going
to become really important when we get to start talking about
using the help system which is what we are going to do next,
but you have made them easy to find aliases. And one of the
things guys I want to show you are on to what Jeffrey was showing you.
With those aliases a lot of times, get alias, a lot of times
you are going to have a cmdlet and you are going to want to know
what the alias is for the cmdlet. There is a way to do this
and we are going to explain what parameters are. They alter
the command and there is a parameter called definition. And if
I were to type in a particular cmdlet it will tell me what the
aliases are available for it. Notice in this case there are a
couple of them: ps and gsp for it. So there are a couple of
different ways to find and work with your aliases. I find it
much easier if you just memorize the list. No just kidding,
don't memorize the list. As a matter of fact don't memorize anything,
but we will talk about that more.
>> You are going to talk about that more?
>> We don't want you memorizing stuff. That just takes the pain
out of it. So questions or comments, make sure you are in the
chat rooms and you are asking questions. We are going to be
checking on you guys as we go throughout this to see if you have
any questions. And there will be a recording of this later.
I know a lot of people are asking if there is going to be a recording
of this. Absolutely, and it will be available online with MVA.
And I am going to remind you with this slide often to ask questions
and stuff like that.