[Music]
>> Oh, now, see, I was talking for like a minute and a half,
and they didn't turn the cameras on.
So back to what we were doing.
>> There they are.
Where have you been?
>> Where have you been? So here's the deal. We need to work with
the execution policy. Now I just want you to take a quick look
at this slide because it lists the execution policy for us kind
of quick. Now, we have a couple of Cmdlets that will let us work
with the execution policy, and by default, you are restricted.
In other words, no scripty allowed to run.
>> Interactive only.
>> Yeah, and I just want to point out that, see the word under
here called unrestricted. Can we just right now kind of put into
our heads that that's not an option for you to set.
>> Ditto with bypass. Bypass. Because isn't bypass like...
>> Yeah, unrestricted and bypass... so can you kind of... I don't
want you drawing on your computers, but can you just cross those off?
Restricted, unrestricted. Restricted is good...
but no. Cross off unrestricted, bypass. Can we focus on the
two that we really want you to focus on, which is RemoteSigned
and AllSigned. Do you want to talk about...
what is this signed thing in the first place that we're talking about?
>> Yeah, so basically, digital signatures. Now in the past, like
VBScript had this. That was really bad stuff. All it did was
said, hey, if a script is digitally signed, I'll run it, not
digitally signed by someone I trust.
>> Trust, yeah.
>> We took a different approach. We said it has to be digitally
signed, and you have to trust them.
>> So before we talk about the difference between AllSigned and
RemoteSigned, can you show us what it is like to sign a script?
>> Sure. Let me first go... I've created a self-signed certificate,
and if you ever wonder about that, you just say, no self-signed certificate.
You can go create your own. I've already created some, and what
I do is they're in the cert drive. I don't know if we talked
about this. There are these things called providers, get PS drive.
Okay. And you'll see the additional drives like the C drive we've
been showing, but there's a certificate drive.
So what I can do is do a dir of the certificate drive, and I
do tab completion here, current user. And what I'm doing is
I'm looking for a code signing cert. So the interesting thing
is, when I'm in the certificate drive, I can do things like...
well, I can do recurse on any drive of course, but I can say
give me the code signing certs. Oh, how strange. Then what I'm
going to do is I'm going to say OV or output
variable A.
So what that did is it got me...
did a recursive search, found me my code signing certs, and I
now put them in dollar sign A. And now what I'm going to say
is dollar sign cert equals dollar sign A to zero. So now I've
got a particular code signing cert. Okay. So now let's see.
Let me get my execution policy.
Get execution policy. And you see it's RemoteSigned. Here I'm
going to change that to
set execution policy equals AllSigned.
Oops, sorry. What am I doing? Set execution AllSigned, yeah,
do it now. So here I am, and I have this test script. Let me
just edit that test script.
Let me just get rid of this because I already signed it.
That's not right. Oh, did
you see that?
Okay. So there's my test script. Right? And I go, and I run
it, and it says, no, you can't do it because it's not digitally signed.
>> Because you went to AllSigned, which means everything must
be signed.
>> Everything must be signed.
>> We'll talk about RemoteSigned in a second, but everything must
be signed.
>> So now I say, well, I'd like to sign it because I trust it.
First, don't sign stuff you haven't understood. Like sign it...
remember I said earlier, like I take my badge out, I put it on
the table, and I say, I guarantee this is going to work.
When you digitally sign something, you're taking your badge out.
You're putting it on the table and saying, anything wrong, take
my badge. So be careful. So you probably want to take a look
at the script you're going to sign.
>> Probably, yeah.
>> I took a look at that and said...
>> That's a good script....
>> I'm good with that. So you want to set the authentication code
signature of...
I give my cert. Dollar sign cert and
the file path.
Okay, now, notice...
now when I do this... test PS1.
Cap test.
Look at that thing, look at that thing.
>> Wow.
>> So now...
I mean, that is a big beast.
>> So now if your script actually did something harmful, we know
who you are, and we can hunt you down.
>> Yes, except it's a self-signing script, so fine.
>> Yeah.
>> But yes, we can. So here's the deal. Dot slash test.
Watch what happens.
Just because it's signed doesn't mean I'll run it. So it will
say, hey, do you want to run this thing? And you can say, hey,
never run it. Don't run it. Run it once. I'm going to say run
it once.
>> Awesome.
>> Now, if I said always run it, it would have been taken that
certificate and said, I always trust stuff from this guy.
>> From this certificate.
>> And then you can run it. Here, you want to see something crazy?
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> I told you, we pay attention to this security stuff, right?
I told you that. So now imagine... imagine I go and I say...
okay. So we say now just because it's sign, I can run it always.
I can say set execution policy, and
I'll say RemoteSigned. So fine.
Now, now I can go and run this thing, and it just runs.
>> It just runs.
>> Now, watch this. Again, what did I say?
When I get a script from the internet, you don't want to just
run it. You want to examine it. So imagine I do this thing, and
I say, hey, let me look at this thing. And I see that, and I
say, hey, you know what, that's safe. I'm just going to run it.
Take a look. Does that look safe?
>> It's got a signature. And the code book's safe.
>> But wait, what if I do this?
>> Oh, that's not safe. That's not safe now.
>> Now let's save that.
>> That's kind of mean.
>> So let's make sure we do this. So now, again, you come here,
and you have this script...
>> Yeah, that's mean, man.
>> Hey you evaluated it.
>> Yeah, I'm evaluating it, and it looks good at the top.
>> Right. But what if down here, or somewhere in there, is there.
>> Somebody, yeah.
>> Let's run it.
What do you think? Should I run it?
>> Yeah, let's... no, no, because you're going to run it, it's
going to restart your computer.
>> I checked it out. I read it. It looked fine. Look, look.
>> You're right. It looks fine. Okay, run it. It looks great.
What could possibly go wrong? Nobody would have stuck anything in...
>> So check this out.
>> Oh, look.
>> Executable code found in the signature block.
So we're aware of this threat. We're aware that people, how they're
going to evaluate things, they're going to look at things, and
they're going to see the signature block, and they're just going
to say, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. So we look for people
sneaking in bad code, and so we protect you from that and say,
no, we're not running that crap. We even tell you where it is,
line 93.
>> Oh, I just got saved from this horrible thing. That's totally awesome.
>> Secure, secure, secure.
>> So here's the deal. AllSigned versus RemoteSigned.
AllSigned means every script that you download and that you create
locally needs to be signed. And just to let you know... and I'm
going to type this on my screen... there is a help file about_signing
that will basically take you through everything Jeffrey just
did to sign a script.
But let's talk about something for a second. RemoteSigned.
A lot of you now, it's going to be easier for you to start off
with RemoteSigned. Here's what this means. Anything you download,
like from the internet, needs to be signed. Do you guys know
that we know what you download from the internet?
[Laughter]
I'm just saying. A bunch of guys just went, oh, I've got to delete this.
I can't remember what was put in... Mark of the Web was put
in so that things got tagged if they got downloaded from the internet.
This is to protect you. This is a feature. And they tagged it
so it overwrote root kits. Well, PowerShell knows this, and PowerShell
knows, if you download it from the internet, if you're set to
RemoteSigned, there needs to be a signature on there. But if
you make the script locally, there doesn't have to be a signature
on it. So a lot of folks will set their policy... and this is
okay to start with... to RemoteSigned just because it's easier
to get started with,
which that's fine, but as soon as you possibly can, you really
want to go to AllSigned because I want you to think about this.
At some point, you're going to want to have this execution policy
where you can run scripts in other places.
And it would be nice to be able to control this through scripts
have to be signed. Imagine what your users might do if they figure
out how to turn on scripting policy. They might want to download
a script.
If you set this through a group policy, then you're going to
be able to help control what could be some possible issues of
users trying to do weird things. So this is actually important.
RemoteSigned is good to start with. AllSigned is really the
best to get to. Watch what happens now. And you've seen it with Jeffrey.
Now that I have an execution policy that works, I can try to
run my script, and I forgot what my script was.
Iloveyou.ps1, and lo and behold, there it goes. So script execution
policy, need to turn it on.
>> Yeah, can I tell you about the latest version?
>> Oh, oh, oh.
>> Latest version of Windows.
>> Top secret, top secret.
>> Top secret. We're disclosing. I'm going to bring you into the
circle of trust.
>> The circle of trust, I like that.
>> So the next version of Windows Server. Let's say Windows Server
2012 R2, we changed the default execution policy to be RemoteSigned
by default.
>> Which is awesome because that way you don't have to run around
to your servers or issue out a group policy to get this because
you need your servers to have an execution policy. So when modules
load and you want to load scripts from them and all that kind
of stuff, it makes life a lot easier. So Server 2012 R2, right,
is when it ships, will have the new policy, which is amazing
to have that set.
>> By the way, a number of people... I just want to clarify one thing.
We're not going to get into the details of the security, but
I want to just point out that even if you have like execution
policy to be unrestricted or whatever, an interactive user...
basically, an interactive user can do anything, and they can
bypass that. Don't worry about that. That is not a security violation.
That's not a hole. There's actually a long explanation for that.
We won't get into it here because it's not that interesting,
but just don't freak out. If somebody has access to a terminal,
basically, here's the thought. If they have access to a terminal,
they can create programs, compile those programs, and run it,
which means they can do anything. So at this point, it's just
not a security issue.
>> Remember the old thing of physical access, right? Physical access.
So, guys, we want to do a couple of things to set us up for some scripting.
One of the things we're going to do here, we're going to start doing...
first of all, variables.
We've already been using them, believe it or not. I just want
to show you... watch, I'm going to show you there's a whole bunch
of Cmdlets. So I'm thinking to myself, how would I find if PowerShell
had any Cmdlets to help me with variables? I can do this, variable,
and, oh, looky, there's a whole bunch. Clear variable, get variable,
new variable, remove variable... stop looking at the screen.
We're not going to use any of them. We don't need to.
PowerShell makes working with variables really easy. We don't
necessarily need these Cmdlets. So let me show you how easy it
is to make a variable. Watch. Variables have a dollar sign,
and there's a lot of reasons for the use of this dollar sign.
We're not going to get a chance to how the parsing engine reads
all of this, but this is not the name or part of the name of
the variable. It tells PowerShell, hey, something's about to
happen, and if it's alpha numeric after it, myvar, this is going
to be a variable. If you want to set this variable equal to something,
equals hello.
Thank you, thank you, no Cmdlets required. I just created a variable.
Totally awesome. You want to see what's inside of a variable?
Myvar. But variables are awesomely cool because variables don't
just take text. They don't just take integers.
Watch. Myvar equals get service bits.
Guess what's in Myvar right now? Wait, let me show you.
This is called Myvar.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, watch it, watch it, watch it. Get member.
Looky, look, look, look what's in Myvar. I've got a service
controller object in there. It's not just text, guys. It's a
service controller object. So I want you to notice something.
We haven't talked much about running methods, but all these properties.
There's a couple of methods here. There's a start and a stop method.
Hmm, I have an idea. I wonder if I could use this dot notation
that you started using, Myvar dot...
oh, let me see, a property status. It's already running, and
I wonder if I could get it to run a method like stop.
>> Ooh.
>> Now, I know you're all saying, well, prove it, prove it, prove it.
All right, one little thing is I'm going to do Myvar status.
And you're saying, no, it didn't work. Wait a second. If we
refreshed everything that happened in Windows constantly, oh,
my God. So there's a method to help us refresh this. So refresh,
and now look at the status. Boom, totally awesome.
Vars make your life much easier. And, of course, with scripting,
vars become very important. Now, there's a lot to do with vars,
and there's a lot of tips and tricks to working with vars.
>> Can I just tell them one thing?
>> Oh, absolutely.
>> So stop. Here's the thing. I think it's because it's Jumpstart
and it's a tutorial, like why do we have this dollar sign?
I hate dollar sign, blah, blah, blah. Here's why. When we say
dollar sign
Myvar equals get service
bits, okay, right in it just works, right? But what happens if
I do this, right? Some people are like, I don't like dollar signs.
Okay, fine. What happens?
The answer is an error, but look at the error. The term Myvar
is not recognized as the name of a Cmdlet. Okay, so when you
start a command, when you start a line with a name, the question
is, well, is it a variable, or is it a Cmdlet? And we have to know.
So that's why we have dollar signs in front of our variables
because you have to know. And this... remember I talked about
the struggle between interactive programming and systems programming.
This was the key thing. The interactive commands require a special syntax.
In programs, you're not running things out of the file system.
>> Right.
>> Right? You're running APIs and such. In interactive shell,
you run things out of the command. So when you type ping, you
just want ping to work. You don't want to have to say, oh, I
want to do something special for ping.
So that's why you just type ping.
But if you want dollar sign ping to be X, you type dollar sign ping.
That's why we have the dollar sign. That's it.
>> And that's actually very important. Everybody is always asking
about the dollar sign. When you're working with vars, you've
got to have the dollar sign. Now, a couple of little things,
a little... oh, let's play with... since we're getting ready
for scripting, we're going to take this concept of using a var
and try something here.
Let's see... there's a Cmdlet called read host.
It will actually read things from the host.
The host. So let me see. Dollar sign var equals read host.
So whatever we read in is going to get stored in the variable,
and I'm going to say enter a computer name. Guys, you can imagine
this in a script already because watch what happens. I'm going
to strike enter, and it comes up and says, enter a computer name.
I'll enter one.
Now, what's stored in var right now
is that computer name. You can now use that variable, which is
where we're going with all this, get service name bits-computer
name dollar sign var. Guess where we're going to get that information
from now? So we're going out to that... the DC in this case.
So we're storing stuff in the vars and we're going to use those
vars in our commands with our parameters as part of the arguments.
This is going to start us making better scripts and being able
to do automation a little bit better. But I want to show you
just a couple of quick things because you're going to hear this
and you're going to see this a lot, and I just have to throw
it out because I'm kind of... I want to ask about it. So dollar
sign var, if I do this, it just prints it to the screen, but
we actually have a Cmdlet that is signed to print things to the
screen for you. Let's do write host real quick. You're going
to see this a lot. Write host, dollar sign var. Same result,
except write host has things like foreground color red, background
color green.
Yea, you can play with the colors. Everybody just got really
excited because they can play with the colors. Stop playing
with colors.
We have ways for you to play with colors. You've probably heard
the phrase every time you use write host, God kills a puppy.
Don't use write host. Now, I want to be straight with you.
There are times to use write host, it's just I want you to see
what you're doing, and when you start scripting, this really
starts to matter. Dollar sign var. Watch what I'm going to do.
Rhyme going to pipe this to get member.
You would expect a result at this point. Look at what I'm getting.
I get no object has been specified. In other words, nothing
went across the pipeline. Write host just destroyed everything
that I've been working so hard for with objects.
Write host has annihilated it.
>> By the way, notice it showed DC on the host.
>> Yeah, because it actually wrote it out to the host.
>> Yes.
>> But there was nothing going down the pipeline. And the point
is we want stuff going down the pipeline.
So with write host, we have a Cmdlet that... watch this.
Write output dollar sign var. And it does the exact same thing,
but it's doing it through the pipeline. Look. Get member, looky
what I got.
I got a real object that's crossing across there now.
>> Da-dah.
>> So it matters. Everyone says, well, I lost the ability to make colors.
Get over the color thing.
Here's the deal. We have ways for you to make colors properly.
You've noticed that PowerShell has a built-in color scheme that
it uses, and as you start to script, this is going to become
real paramount. As admins we get used to certain colors popping up.
So in PowerShell, we've included Cmdlets to use the existing
color scheme. If you just play along, it will all be good.
Such as, I want to write a warning,
please don't do that.
Look, it comes up as a PowerShell warning, the yellow on black.
So it makes sense to my brain because I've seen those warnings
before or things that I need to care about. I didn't have to
go through and use write host and come up with my own color scheme.
Of course, we give you things like write error, and there's other
stuff we have. But write error being one, stop touching me.
Now it looks like a PowerShell error message, and I've generated
the error, and it's in the same color scheme in the same format.
So you don't need write host most of the time. If you want to
put something on the screen in a different color, great.
But try to stick with write output and the other write commands
that we give you to write things out to the screen, especially
when you're working with your vars because write host could and
can be somewhat problematic.
>> By the way, this is very analogous to what I mentioned about
the console. Remember I said I'm trying to kill off the console
because I'm trying to kill off console apps because apps that
write directly to the console can't be automated. They are the
enemy of automation. Write host is another flavor of a console app.
>> Is another flavor of a console app.
>> So don't do it. By the way, there are times we have a special
like dispensation for people who are trying to do this.
Here's the key thing. Say you wanted to write a script that was
well-formatted and had colors and all that good stuff, that's fine.
But use the word show.
Whenever you see the word show, you should hear in your head,
ah, I'm not going to be able to program or script the output
of that. So that's perfectly fine, but just make sure you use
the right term, show.
>> And most of the time just don't use write host, just don't
do it.
>> It's because you like dogs.
>> It's because I like dogs, and
I have to give Don Jones credit for that phrase. He uses that
all the time. So let's do something kind of fun and kind of exciting
at this point. I think that this would be...
>> You didn't show them the squiggle brackets.
>> Huh?
>> The squiggle brackets.
>> You want to show them the variables with the squiggle brackets?
>> Yeah.
>> Really?
>> That's awesome.
Here, I'll do it.
>> It scares me. Okay, you do it.
>> So here's the thing. Hey, what can I do? Like, hey, is this
an Anglo centric, English thing? And the answer is no, no, no,
my friends.
You can have variable of any sort of things, including spaces, right?
So you can say, hey, this is a test equals 4. Right? And then
this is a test. It's 4. Isn't that cool? Check this out.
You can have anything you want in here.
Oh, sorry, did the wrong thing. What the heck was that? Oh, that
wasn't good.
What did I do?
Oh, good Lord, help, help, help. Help me, help me. I'm all confused.
>> Wait a minute. What's...
>> No, I just screwed up. Oh, there we go. There we go.
There, that's what I meant to do.
>> There you go. That's sufficiently weird.
>> Equals wow.
Okay, so now...
look, that's the name of my variable. Did I screw that up?
I did screw that up. Oh, no, I did equals.
So that's the name of my variable. Is that crazy or what?
>> That's crazy.
>> But here it gets a little bit cooler because we draw this distinction
between the syntax of a variable and the semantics of the variable.
So here the syntax is just showing you it's a container.
And I mentioned you can put any parameter you want. Sorry, any
character you want. You can use unicode, et cetera. It's not
entirely true. There's a special character, and that is the colon character.
So let me make sure. Here's where I am. Imagine I do this.
Imagine I do 1..5,
and then I'm going to put that in a file, test.txt.
Now watch this. C:Jumpstart text.txt.
So check it out. I did dollar sign my parameters, and I gave
a file path.
>> Awesome.
>> And I get the value of the file, right?
>> So you're basically saying, do this.
>> It is, hey, this dollar sign syntax basically says, where do
I store my data? And in general, the way we think of variables
is you store data in memory somewhere.
>> Memory.
>> And when the process goes away, well, that goes away.
Well, look here. Here. Wait a second. So now, I get a second
command, and I can say dollar sign C:Jumpstart/test.txt,
squiggle brackets.
Sorry, slash, slash,
slash, and you get it there. No, wait. So equals.
And go to this machine.
>> And now...
>> So now I've got variables that cross.
>> That cross machines.
>> Across machines.
>> That's totally awesome.
>> Fun, fun, fun.