[Music]
>> So our third topic for the day
is getting connected with the pipeline.
And the first thing is, yeah, we're going to go through all of this.
So there's the cute module overview. But take a look at this,
what's the pipeline? First of all, look at the character here.
See this character? This is located above... like it says right
here located above your Enter key. And the reason I say it like
that because a lot of folks don't even know where this character is.
Let me give you an example.
So get-service pipe.
What's going to happen is get-service is going to go out and
get a selection of service objects; they're technically called
service controllers and you're going to see what all that is later.
But it's going to grab all of those services and then it's going
to send them. And I'm not talking about a text representation;
I'm talking about the actual service objects themselves.
It's going to send them one at a time across this pipeline.
What do you want to do next to these services? Well, let's narrow
this down a little bit. Let's just do the name Bits.
Take a look. It's running.
Take a guess what I could do if I wanted to stop this service.
You probably could guess that there is a commandlet called stop-service,
and you would be correct. There is. There's one called stop-service.
And you can specify a name. But here's the interesting thing,
I can pipe it to stop-service
if I could type it.
Here's what's going to happen, we're going to take that bit service,
we're going to send it across that pipeline. Stop service is
going to grab hold of that and do exactly what it says it's going
to do, it's going to stop the service. Now we're going to talk
a little bit later in more detail about how this pipeline works
because it's crucially important in trouble shooting. But just
take a look.
Wow, I wonder what it did? Well, let's run.
Ah, it stopped it. Now I can pipe and I can even say start service.
And I'm going to use a pass-through on here that'll show me the
results of what I'm doing.
And now it's started again. Now I know that's a simple pipeline
but that concept of taking something, sending it across the pipeline
to have something else act on it, is very important. And we
can continue. We can pipe from one thing to the next thing to
the next thing. So as an example, let's start out with a couple
of cool things. Oh, hey first of all, Jeffrey, what do you think,
I just love to ask people this... Ooh, don't... Be careful
with the Enter key. What do you
think, Jeffrey?
Is that going to do what I think it's going to do?
>> Yeah, you don't want to do that.
>> I know.
>> Guys, we're going to show you. The pipeline is very powerful.
It can also allow you to make silly mistakes.
>> It's worth pointing out, PowerShell is a powerful tool
like a really sharp knife.
A really sharp knife is super, super useful. You probably don't
want to give it to your kids, right?
You want to be thoughtful about this stuff. PowerShell, you
can do some damaging things and so often we give you techniques
to deal with that but, indeed, don't complain if you say, "Oh,
well, geez I removed all the files from my file system.
Darn, PowerShell." By the way I did that actually. I was giving
an example of how to do this and the guards that we have, and
I forgot to put that in. And I hit carriage return. And it turns
out if you kill lsass, bad things happen.
>> Bad things.
>> Bad things happen. Especially when you're in front of like
700 people doing a demo.
>> Very bad things happen.
>> I strongly do not recommend that.
>> Because I've hit the Enter on the get-service, stop-service,
and it's just not cool. PowerShell doesn't ask you, "Are you
sure?" until later on when we show you how you can get it to.
But it doesn't. So it assumes you know what you're doing.
Let me do an example here of another pipeline thing. Let's talk
about CSV's for example. Here's a commandlet, export CSV.
Guess what export CSV is going to do? It's going to take this
information and export it to a CSV. And so I'm going to put
in a path of C colon... Let's just call it service.csv.
You guys know what a CSV is, comma separated file. And, yes,
you can change the delimiters. If you look at the help file for
export CSV, you can change the delimiters and modify how it works.
But let's take a look at this CSV. I'm going to open this up
in Notepad, not the correct tool for looking at a CSV because
it's going to look at this text file. But I just want you to see...
Yep, it's all comma separated. But here's one of the interesting
rules about PowerShell is if you can export it, you're going
to want to import it at some point. You're going to want to
work with that data again.
So if you can export it, you can import the CSV. So import CSV.
I forgot what I called it. Oh, not that. There we go. And now
all the data comes back and it's formatted correctly and it's
attached correctly so I can actually work with it now. Now there
are simple examples of the pipeline but we're also showing you
some great export stuff. So besides exporting
like to a CSV...
There's my favorite.
Oops. Command line XML. I love XML. XML is the greatest thing
since the automation of sliced bread.
Great example, you guys that used to do online banking: years
ago you'd buy something and swipe your credit card, three days
later it would show up in your account. Today you swipe and
when does it show up in your account? Just as it finishes swiping.
XML, baby. It's XML.
So let's export to XML. And here's what I'm going to do, instead
of doing get-service,
I'm going to do get-process.
I like that. And I'm going to pretend; I'm going to call this
good XML. I want you to pretend something for a second. I want
you to pretend that I've taken a snapshot of a perfectly good
running machine. It runs perfectly.
And I've just snapshotted it's processes. Now if you blink your
eyes, pretend for a moment that now I'm working on a non-perfectly
running machine.
And what I'd like to do is I'd like to compare
the good machine to the non-good machine.
>> Yeah, instead of those notepad and calc, imagine that was some malware.
>> Yeah, exactly. I'm just using notepad and calc. Now compare object.
I'm just giving you an example of how the pipeline and how using
commandlets can be very useful to you. So I've got a reference object.
Now I want you to notice I'm going to use parentheses.
We're going to talk more about parentheticals. But this means,
do this first. And what I need to do is I need to import the
good XML file that represents the good machine.
And then, I want to compare that to this currently running machine.
Now when you run get-process, there is a lot of information that
comes up. What I want is I just want it to compare the names
of the processes right now and see if there is a difference.
So what I've done is I've exported my process information with
the pipeline, and now I'm just going to compare it.
Notice the site indicator points to the bad machine and is saying,
"Hey look, calc and notepad are running on that," as opposed
to what's on the good machine. This is an example of how you're
going to start to be able to build commands with the pipeline
to do something and then use other commands to achieve your results.
Imagine comparing two machines, the software that's installed
on them, and you want to make one machine look just like another.
So there are a lot of things that we can do with building a pipeline.
One last example and then we'll take a short break.
>> Can I just point out...
>> Oh, yeah.
>> So what Jason just showed you is freakishly powerful and we're
going to drill into it in the future. So what we did is we took
a set of live objects and we compared them against an XML file.
Like how do you do that? And the answer is the magic of PowerShell
and these things we call objects and object adapters. And of
course if you just tried to compare these things, it would say,
"They're completely different." So he did and he said, "I just
want to compare them based upon their name." And so what you've
done, what we've really kind of led you to is, again, you think
about what you want to do, you type it and the magic of PowerShell
is able to take this incredibly complex stuff and present it
to you in a very simple world.
>> So let me show you a couple other command line things and Jeffrey
will be adding in stuff here just so you can get the idea of
kind of what's going on. Besides exporting out to like CSV's
and XML, there are some other things you can do. So get-service.
Everybody always wants to know, "How do I put something into
just a text file?" Well, first of all you could've found out-file
by looking for get-help star file or something like that which
is totally awesome. And you'll find out-file. Out-file, if you
look at the help file for it, wants you to give it a path.
And you give it a path to what you want to use
for your text file. So test.txt.
and you can get the content...
Did I say get the content? You can get the content from a text file...
You know, I wonder if there is anything that could help me with
getting content from a text file. Oh lookie, get-content.
Help system is your friend. So you can get the content from a
text file by just using get-content.
And I think I called that test.txt, and there's all that get-service
content that I just put into a text file. But wait, there's more.
You can send stuff out to a printer. Out to a printer. Out printer.
Out printer? Hmm?
>> So there's a set of things you could send it out to.
>> I wonder how we could find a list of the things that we could
send stuff out to.
>> Yeah, no. Just out. Just start with out.
>> Start with out, yeah. Well, here, look. There's a ton of stuff
that we can send for out.
So again the help file is your friend. Besides sending stuff
out, there's also creative ways to do stuff. So get-service...
I love this. This is one of my favorite things. We also have
convert to commandlets. Convert to CSV. Now this is going to
make more sense later. But, well, you just had an export CSV.
Yeah, and we have a convert to CSV. The difference being for
right now when you do an export CSV, you're done.
You're done.
When you do a convert to CSV, we're going to leave that stuff
in the pipeline in case you want to pipeline it and do other
things to it.
>> The way I think about it?
>> Yeah.
>> Is export is convert coupled with output it to a file.
>> Yeah, excellent, excellent because, if you do an export CSV,
you have a mandatory where you have to send it to a file.
So think of it as a convert with an out-file already built right in.
So we have the converts but I want to show you one of my favorite ones.
He, he, he, he, he.
[Laughter]
Did I mention I was a web guy? Anyways, and I want to
pick just a couple of properties for this; I'm going to take
name and status. The reason I knew that convert to HTML has a
dash property parameter and it had Chihuahuas that would take
multiple arguments is because I looked at the help file. So it's
going to convert it to, as you would expect, HTML. And at this
point, ah, there it did it. It's the cleanest HTML, by the way.
It did exactly what I asked it to do, but here's an example of
me saying, "Look, I don't want it to my screen. I now want in
a file. I want it out to a file." So let's pipe it out-file,
and let's call this just test.htm.
And you guys know, if you have a...
>> Can you reduce your... go down a little bit more?
>> Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> It's getting cut off.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Thanks, guys, for telling us about
that in the discussion thing. I want to lower my command down
so that...
>> Yeah, now you can see the...
>> ...picture in a picture...
>> In all its glory.
>> In all of its beautiful glory. And you guys know that if you double-click...
Did I say double-click? Yes, I said double-click... on an HTM
it'll pop. Well, see no more double-clicking. No more mouse.
No more mouse. So what I'm going to do is just say C colon test.htm
and PowerShell will launch it up there for me. Do you get I
just made a web page?
How many developers did that take?
And if you look at the help for convert to HTML, you're going
to find that you have a lot of options to make this pretty.
There are a lot of ways to make this very pretty with tables
and all kinds of... using style sheets and so forth. So it pays
to look at the help. But this is a good example of piping from
one command to another to achieve a certain result.
So, let's take a look at what else we got going.
We got to the web page, and these are just some examples of piping
some stuff. Oh, we're going to have to talk about stuff that
kills because I almost screwed up earlier.
>> Yeah, this is fun. This is fun.
>> So let me... And, Jeffrey, you can help me out here with this one.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Because I'm going to get-service
and I'm going to do stop-service.
And I want to know if this works or not, but it seems kind of
risky to me.
>> Yeah.
>> What can I do?
>> When in trouble, fear or doubt, run in circles, scream and shout.
[Laughter]
That's what they used to teach you.
>> Okay.
>> That's what they used to teach kids in Boy Scouts when you
go on a trip.
So, no, here's the thing: when you're ever... So I once dealt
with an admin who said, "You know, every now and again it's late
and I'm doing something, and I realize I'm about to hit carriage
return or the Enter key. And I realize if I get it wrong, like
that's the end. I'm going to be fired. Muffy and Buffy are not
going to go to college. It's just going to be bad."
>> It's going to be bad.
>> And I thought myself, "Boy, what are we doing that we create
an environment where somebody, that's the world that they have
to live with." And so, in PowerShell if you ever have something
that you're uncertain of, you can always type minus what if.
Like, what if I did this? What would actually happen? And you
would get...
[Singing]
>> And it tells you what it would do but it doesn't actually do it.
>> Now the best part is that it tells you what it would do but
it didn't actually do it. And if you look at my screen, it says,
"Yeah, I would've stopped these services." Now if you're thinking
to yourself that, oh, this is a nice fast way to shut down my computer.
No, no, no, no. This is going to blue screen way before it shuts down.
Well, it won't blue screen but it's going to stop somewhere around
PowerShell service host.
>> Muffy and Buffy would not be going to college after this one.
>> Yeah. So you're not going to want to do that. But something
to keep in mind,
besides what if... And I use what if all the time because things
can be dangerous that you're trying out. We also have dash confirm.
And dash confirm is a what if with, "Do you actually want to
do this?" Now I'm obviously not going to say yes to anything
and certainly not yes to all. So I'm going to put my finger on
the L right now so that nothing happens. But I want you to notice
it is showing you both what it will do and then asking you, "Do
you want me to do this?" So people ask all the time, "PowerShell
doesn't ask me 'are you sure?'" Yeah, because PowerShell is not
for sissies. But sometimes you need that capability. So I'm
going to hit L.
And, please, don't actually do anything.
>> Yeah, that'd be good. Hey, can I show them something?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, so
at some level this isn't that interesting, right?
Get-service pipe to stop-service.
Minus what if. Okay, but who is going to do that? Right, you're
just not going to do that. But, remember what I said earlier
about this programming with hand grenades thing.
What I said was, there's this Bits thing and I don't remember
what the heck it was. So what I'm going to say is display name,
something to do with Bits or maybe it was something to do with BI.
And then, stop-service.
Now, did I get that one right? Now this is the more realistic thing.
Did I get that one right? Because maybe BI star maps to Bits
service and maybe it doesn't. So what you do here is you say
what if. And you're like, "Oh, oh, oh, oh. No. Good thing I
didn't do that." Now at this point you could go and say, "Well,
okay, why did that match? Oh I see: biometric.
And then, oh, I see: compatibility." Now if you wanted to you
could go in here and try and like tweak this thing, right, and
do this. But instead you can say, "No, you know what, it's close
enough." Confirm.
And you say, "BitLocker, yep. That's the one I want to do it
to." So you stop that. And then, this one you say, "Nope that
was the only one." So you say no to the rest. And now I've stopped
gsv bi. Nope, nope, nope, nope. I got the wrong one. Oh, you
know what? I shouldn't have stopped BitLocker. That was a bad thing.
>> Yeah, I think that might have been. >> Ooh.
>> Well, great example of a practical use.
[Laughter]
Dash confirm. No, that's perfect.
>> I am now out of compliance with corporate policy.
>> There you are.
>> These doors might come bursting open.
>> Bursting open.
>> Well, hopefully they...
>> So let's start that.
>> ...will not burst open. So, guys, this is your first introduction
to the pipeline. We're going to go much deeper into this pipeline
but the concept again is you have a commandlet. You're going
to pipe the results of that commandlet to the next one. So do
this then do this then do this then do this until your needs
are done. And what you're going to notice is as we go through
this and you get more and more commandlets, you're going to see
that the way you're thinking about solving the problem is the
way that you'll actually be building the commands in the pipeline.
Now you don't have to do everything as a one-liner. And one-liners
are great; we're going to do a lot of them in here. And we're
also do scripting where a one-liner, when it's half the page,
you're probably a little out of control at that point. But you
can is the idea. Now before we go too much further into the pipeline,
Jeffrey, let's do this. I've got a slide here so let me show
everybody where were at.
So, guys, make sure you're asking questions and all that kind
of stuff. And for all the people out in the support, the MVP's
and everybody who's is contributing, thank you so much for helping
us out and answering all of these questions that are out there.
Let's go into extending the shell a little bit. And this is
a fascinating conversation for me because I can't remember the
exact number but I think when PowerShell 1.0 came out I think
there was like 192 commandlets. That's all we could do was like
190 things.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> Then PowerShell V2 came out and there was 236... well, there
was only 236 things that we could do.
But we need to do more than that. We need something that's extensible.
So how do we get more than just the core PowerShell commandlets?
Who's responsible for all of that kind of stuff?
>> It takes a village, my friend. It takes a village.
>> It takes a village.
>> Yeah, so that's exactly the point. So the PowerShell team
is responsible for the core PowerShell environment, the language, etcetera.
And then, you have plug-ins or snap-ins or we now call them modules.
And this is where...
Trust me, you don't want me writing the Link commandlets, right?
That doesn't end well. And so what we do is we create an environment
where it's very easy for the individual feature teams to write
their stuff and ship their stuff. And that's why when you say,
"Oh, well, I want to do some stuff with PowerShell, where are
the Link commandlets?" Well, do you have Link installed because
if you don't have Link installed, you're not going to get the
Link commandlets. So the idea is that the commandlets ship with
the thing that needs to be managed. So we do this through modules.
Originally they were snap-ins.
So snap-ins and if you've got PowerShell Version 1 or PowerShell
Version 2, you have these things called snap-ins. It turns out
there were a number of limitations with snap-ins. The biggest:
you had to be an administrator to get them installed and
something else. Oh, you couldn't XCopy deploy them.
>> Yeah.
>> And modules is basically conceptually modeled after the module
or the package modules of Pearl and Python and Ruby, but actually
it's much richer than those, much richer than those. The idea
is you'll be able to package up your stuff and then XCopy deploy
it and then you import your modules.
>> So let's take a look: first of all, what Jeffrey is saying...
And I think
all of you guys have run the MMC before and you know the MMC.
You can file, add, remove, snap-in, and you get a list of stuff
here that you can add in. I want you to notice on mine, I happen
to have some of the Active Directory snap-ins. You guys know
that in order to get those I had to install something. And in
this case, I had installed the remote server administration tools
to get the Active Directory ones. Well, it's the same concept
when you're working with PowerShell. Do you have the product installed?
Well, I have the remote server administration tools installed,
and so I'm going to get those modules.
Let me show you. PowerShell has a command called get-module.
This'll show you what's currently loaded up. However, list available
will show you the modules that are available. Now I need to
just tell you right now, this is very confusing. In V2...
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. In V2, first of all, you're not going to see what you're
going to see on my screen.
You're not going to see it in Windows 7 either. What you're
seeing is Windows 8 running the Windows 8 remote server administration
tools, and I get more modules than you do.
>> Because he's cool.
>> Well, not because I'm cool, because I've upgraded.
So I know you're corporate standard, you may not be doing it
yet, but your admin box needs to be running V3. And as you're
going to want, it needs to be running Windows 8. Okay? But at
any rate let me just show you. And I'm not the guy that works
for Microsoft and I'm the one over here.
So you can see, I get this giant list of modules. And notice
one of the modules at the very top here is called Active Directory.
The reason I have the module is because I installed the remote
server administration tools. Here's what that module contains: commandlets.
Commandlets that
let me manage Active Directory.
>> And providers.
>> And what?
>> And providers. But we didn't tell them...
>> And providers.
>> ...about providers.
>> We haven't talked about providers yet but, yes, and providers.
If you have a module with commandlets, here's the beautiful thing
about PowerShell V3... You're going to love this... when you
use get-help,
get-help knows how to look through those modules even if they're
not loaded. So get-help, I want you to show me do I have any
Active Directory commandlets?
I want you to notice that, yes, there are a lot of things with
AD in it and I could've refined the search better, but that's
kind of my point. I want you to see that there's a whole bunch
of AD commandlets here. You'll recognize AD computer as this'll
give me Active Directory computers.
The get-help knows how to look into these modules, find these
commandlets to show them, so you still have complete discoverability.
And when you want help on the command that you found, get-help
get-AD computer, it'll give you the help for it. When you try
to use the commandlet... This is one of the biggest features
for me personally in V3...
And I think I may have used this one earlier so you may not see
it flashing on my screen but take a look.
Oop, it just ran. But let me do this. I'm going to close my
console and re-open it because I want you to see this if you
can catch it on my screen real quick.
>> Actually, the other way to do this is to do a get-module.
Get-module.
>> Okay, let's do that. We're going to do get-module.
>> Carriage return.
So these are the currently loaded modules.
>> Oh yeah. Right. These are the currently loaded ones.
>> Yeah, so now do it and then you'll...
>> And now, yes, thank you. Thank you. So these are the currently
loaded ones. Now watch what I'm going to do. I'm going to do
get-AD computer and watch what flashes across my screen real quick.
Boy, that was real quick. I don't know if you caught it. It actually
dynamically loaded the module for me so that I had the commandlets.
And notice, the commandlet ran.
I didn't have to do anything special. The reason I'm making
a big deal about this... And here I'll show you in get-module.
Now you'll see that it automatically loaded the Active Directory
module for me. The reason I'm making a big deal about this, in
V2, you're life sucks because it doesn't work this way. And let
me tell you, I'm sorry, sir, but in V2 this was painful.
Because in V2 get-help would not find the commandlets unless
the module was imported.
>> Yes.
>> So you had to know what the module was first then import then
you could discover. See, it didn't quite work. They fixed all
that with V3. Now it works just like I need it to work. And when
I run the command, the module loads. So I'm not loading modules unnecessarily.
>> Yep.
>> And if I'm writing scripts that are using the commands, it
just loads what it needs and I don't have to worry about it.
>> It's a beautiful world.
>> It's a beautiful world. You got any more on modules because
that's about all I've got on modules?
>> Well, you can do... Do we get to this now?
>> What do you want to do?
>> Modules on other machines, implicit remoting? No.
>> Oh no, we'll do implicit... Oh, boy, what he's going to talk about.
But, yeah. >> Yeah.
>> We'll get to that later, yeah.
>> It's so cool. It's so cool.
>> It's so cool. So let me show the slides, guys. We've got all this...
>> Yeah, that's an after lunch thing.
>> They'll need like high energy.
>> And let me just warn you right now because we're only about
30 minutes or so away from taking a meal break. A meal break, yeah.
>> That's the international term for lunch.
>> Yeah. >> Meal.
>> Because we're taking lunch. Is that don't eat a lot because
you don't want to fall asleep after lunch.
>> Have some coffee.
>> Have some coffee. So we've got everything in the slides.
And PowerShell 3 dynamically loads the modules for you. And you
can discover all of your commands. Thank God for V3, makes this
much easier. And so you can work with your commands and off you go.