[Music]
>> Now's when the fun starts to begin.
Before lunch I'm sorry to do this to you. I know, this is great.
They can handle this. This is great. We're going to talk about objects.
We're going to talk about objects and what objects are. And I'm
going to let Jeffrey talk as much about objects as he wants to
talk about.
>> So let me just show you something here.
So we've been lying to you. It's true.
It's true.
>> I'm leaving.
>> So here we've been saying get service... service. This would
be V star.
And what do you see? And what you see is text. Okay. But that's
not what's really going on. What's really going on is when I
do get service, notice I didn't say get service text. I said
get service. What I'm getting is service objects or service controller objects.
And the point of that... now don't freak out when you hear the
word "object". Some people hear the word "object" they're like
oh my God, I'm not a developer. No, no, no my friends. No.
Objects dramatically simplify your life. Okay. Now, what is
an object? Okay. Let's just try and deal with that.
>> Because I'm over here freaking out going no, no, no. But they're
going to simplify my life. I'm good.
>> So I think it was an MVP or TechEd did a great explanation
of object. An object is just a thing. It's a noun that has properties
and methods. So think about a bicycle, right? A bicycle is an object.
And it has properties. It has handlebars. It has pedals.
It has wheels. And then there are things you can do to it.
So an object has things that it has.
We call those properties. It has a handlebar, it has a wheel.
It has a frame. And there are things that it can do. You can pedal.
You can steer. And we call those things methods. So objects
are merely things that have properties and things that you can
do things to.
>> I like that so far. I like that.
>> So here we show this thing, and what actually happens is I
got a set of objects. Now, the trick is, and here's the magic,
is that we spew these objects out and we can then work on them.
And when they finally get to the display, the display says, oh
I've got an object, what the hell am I going to do with that?
There's no way I'm going to burp out this binary stuff and people
are going to figure it out. What the display does, it says now
I'll convert it to an object or convert it to text.
And the whole point about that is you want to delay the conversion
of text as far as possible, as long as possible. Because once
you have text, it's really hard to operate with. Now, you Unix
guys, anybody with a Unix background, you know what I'm talking
about, because imagine now let's go back to get process. I like
get process. So get process.
Star SS. Now, imagine you wanted to get all those things where
the handles were greater than let's say 700. Let's do this.
Get process. Okay. So you see there's a bunch of these things,
and some of them are high. So let's say you wanted to get all
those that were greater than a thousand. How would you do it.
In Unix, if this is text, it gets text, how due do that?
Let's see you've got to cut off, one, two, three lines and you
go and say I'm going to cut off zero to... let's see, that's
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, seven... I've got to
cut off these first seven characters and what do you get?
And the answer is a string. So how do you do a string comparison
that's greater than a thousand? Well, a thousand is actually easy.
You could say if the string truncate all the spaces and then
if the length is greater than three then it's greater than a thousand.
But if you wanted to do it greater than 900, then you've got...
so you get where I'm going. You Unix guys, hats off to you.
I don't know how the heck you've been coping all these years.
We call it prayer-based
parsing, like please work. Exactly and oddly it's sort of worked
fine but in our world you don't have to do that. In our world
you have these objects. Now, the thing is, when I do get process,
I'm displaying an object. Each row is the object itself.
And each one of these
displays here, each one of these columns reflects the properties.
Okay. So what did I tell you? I told you we're trying to create
a world where you think about what you want. You type it and
you get it. And the way that works is because of objects.
So what did I say? I said I wanted to get the processes.
I wanted to get those where the handle count was greater than 900.
Some number. You pick your favorite number. So when I say where
the handles... remember, where did I get handles?
Right there. Handles. So where handles
are greater than or equal greater than 900.
It worked. Why did it work? Because of objects. Objects are
so cool. Now, wait. So this is still a little bit messy here,
because these handles, I mean look at them. They're all kind
of like all over the place. Right? So really what I want to do
I want to sort them. Now, again you cut off three lines and you
do this and again it's strings.
But no, no, it's an object. So what you can do is again think
about what you want. Type it and you get it. You say well I
want to sort it by handles.
Ta da. And then you get it.
>> If you're starting to get the concept here, this is starting
to become totally awesome. Look at the difference of working
with objects. One thing that you can do to start off is to show
that these are objects. I'm just going to grab a service real quick.
And if you want to take a look at what properties... notice when
I run just get service name bits, notice that there are three
what appear to be properties displayed about this... you know
what, I'm pretty sure there's more properties than just these
three on a service. And I'm not seeing any methods here.
But Jeffrey just said that objects have properties and they have methods.
Well, there's a way to show you everything that an object has.
And it's going to become a crucial part to working with PowerShell.
So how do you find out what properties and methods an object
has, you pipe it to a very special command and I'm going to get member.
Now, I gotta be honest with you. Get member, we usually use
the alias for this. So I'm just going to use the alias. Pipe GM.
And you'll just hear me say pipe GM. When you pipe something
and get member it takes the object and it shows you all the methods.
So think of it this way. It's like if I were to walk in front
of a mirror, the mirror shows me things like well you're 6'2".
You're blond, blue eyes and you're built really well and you
have methods, you have methods like you surf and you like karate.
What do you like of my mirror.
>> That's awesome I need one of those.
>> Obviously my mirror doesn't work real well but the PowerShell
mirror being get member works very well. If you take a look
here, there's a couple of pieces of information you want to pull
out from get member. First of all, what kind of object it is.
This is going to become very important to us after lunch.
What kind of object is this.
>> Move your screen over a little bit. It's getting truncated
a little bit. Let me get this.
Does that work better? There we go. So system dot service process,
what you really are interested in right now is this period and
what comes after it service controller that's what kind of object
is being sent across that pipeline and then look at this list.
Anything with the word property in it, I don't care if it has
some other word in front of it, anything with a property is a
property that you can use and look at specifically.
Like Jeffrey was doing handles on get process. Look at all these
properties down through here. We're going to start off working
quite a bit with properties but you also have methods.
Methods like, oh, look, start and stop.
Get service has a method to start and stop a service. We don't
need a commandlet necessarily because we have a method that we
could use. We'll show you how to do that too. So get member
is your friend to show you the truth or what an object actually
contains for its properties and its methods. Let me give you
an example. Using kind of off of Jeffrey's example, I'm going
to do get service, and here's what I want to do.
I want to just select a couple of properties. The properties
that I want to see right now are name and status.
We have a commandlet called select object. Now, usually you
see this as its alias of select. Let me just show you it has
a parameter called property and you can tell me what properties
you now want to see. Well, if I've gone to get member and I've
looked at the list of properties and I've chosen the ones that
I wanted, I just type them in. I just want name, status. So I've
selected those particular properties. Now, I also want you to
notice and Jeffrey just did an example of this. I'm going to
do get child item or the alias DER is a great example.
Here's a list of files out of my C drive. Files and folders.
Right now look at how it's sorting them. Sorting them by name
and it's sorting them looks to be alphabetically to me.
Well, I want to change the sort. I'd like to sort them by length,
and the only thing I want displayed is name and length. So here's
what I'm going to do.
I'm going to do get child item.
I'm going to select that the properties I want to see are name
and length, and this is right off the example that Jeffrey was
doing, I want to sort that
by the property length.
This pipeline and the fact that objects are crossing the pipeline
and I can work with these properties and methods are making my
life a lot easier. Look at that. It's folders first then it's
the files. You know what notice on my files it's small Zs to
big Zs I want big Zs to small Zs, I want it descending.
Let me hit my up arrow key and the sort object has a descending.
Now I can change the sort order and make it descending. Is that
kind of cool? That's kind of cool. That's kind of cool.
That's kind of cool. Working with the objects. So working with
objects is all about using get member. And we've shown you that
you can do sort and you can do a select, and we're going to do
these quite a bit of selecting and sorting. But there's some
other examples. Let's see here.
Keep in mind get process. When you need to know more about an
object, this is very important, when you need to know more about
an object, because this afternoon we're going to need to know
more about an object, you pipe to GM which is get member.
GM. You'll get
the type of object it is, which we're going to need this later,
and you get all of its properties and its methods. And if it
has the word property in it, you can use it with sort and select
like we just showed you that you could use it with. In fact,
it's kind of interesting. There's all kinds of stuff you can do.
So back to an earlier example. Get event log.
Ooh, log name system. And we're going to do newest.
Let's just do newest 5.
And I want to, if I just run this you can see I'm getting all
this information across here. I'd like to take a look at the
object itself. So what I'm going to do is, because I want to
see what all the properties are. I'm going to pipe it to GM.
Wow, there's a lot more properties out here than I was seeing
in the original display. Time generated, time written. So you
know what I think I'd like, I think I'd like event ID and time
generated and I think I would like, oh, what else would be a
good property? Maybe.
>> Message.
>> Oh, message that would be perfect. That would be perfect.
So I'm going to up arrow.
Select. The property.
Event ID.
Yep. And if you take a look at the help file you'll see that
dash property takes multiple values. So I can do time generated
or time written. Let's do time written. I think I can type that one.
>> You can hit tab.
>> I can hit...
>> Version 3.
>> Version 3. Go to version 3 because you can hit tab.
>> I hit tab it made my life much easier than typing. Now I've
selected those.
There we go and now I'd actually like to sort them on the time written.
Now, guys, this is a VM. So there's not a whole lot of stuff
out here, but you get the idea. I'm going to sort on the property of...
okay I'm not getting my tab. Time written.
And voila. If I want to sort it descending I can sort it descending.
But now that I'm understanding the pipeline, I know how to find
the properties that I want. Not just the ones that I saw in the
display, but I can find all of the properties and then just select
the ones I want and sort the ones I want. Now that I have what
I want, well I don't want it on the screen.
I want it converted to an HTML file, and I just love this.
C colon error.htm.
This will actually take a file UNC. Just throw it to a Web server.
Did I mention I was a Web guy? So anyways here's the deal.
I've got this great one-liner right now that's grabbing the errors.
And right now it's from the local machine. But I can throw it
dash computer get it from multiple machines. It's selecting
out just the information I want. It's sorting it the way I want
and stuffing it into a Web file. I can now tell the other admins
when you get up in the morning, go check the Web page and if
there's any errors in there, start trying to fix them.
Because as you're going to see later, we're going to automate
this and schedule this and make this go for us. So I don't have
to type it again. So once I figured it out. But you can see
it's like figuring out a puzzle. Just to show you it actually worked.
What did I call it error htm.
DA DA. There's a whoohoo even from the guys in the back.
>> It's all good.
>> You must be a little impressed with that. What else should
we show them with objects right now?
>> Here's the thing about objects. I mentioned to you that the
objects dramatically simplify your life. It's true.
Here's the thing what we've been showing you are .NET objects.
Now these .NET objects are actually very well behaved objects.
But you know the world is a messy place. And not everybody has
your best interests in mind. And so in particular there's a lot
of people who use .NET in a way that is good for them but not
good for you. Okay. And in particular, what they do is they hide things.
And this is ubiquitous. This happens in WMI. It happens in ABSI,
Active Directory. Happens in XML, et cetera. Now PowerShell
we have exactly one customer and that's you.
I'm focused on making your life great.
So what we do we go and we say these guys didn't help you, we'll
help you. Right, we will take their stuff and we'll adapt it
for your needs. Now, let me just give you an example of this.
So here I have... I got this XML file. Okay. So r and d j.
Let me see if I can bring that up.
Can I do this? Open. Can I do an open? PowerShell.org.
We'll talk about that. That's cool. Can I do an open?
Yeah, I wanted to say C, Jumpstart/R.
And here's my XML. And it is the
tragedy of Romeo and Juliette.
It's beautiful. Look here
you've got personas. You've got acts. And in the acts you've
got speeches.
And you've got speakers and you've got lines.
Now, by the way, this next thing that I'm going to show you I'm
going to show you the way to do it in PowerShell version 3.
In PowerShell version 2 you can do it but it's harder. And the
stuff I'm going to show you requires version 3. So we have this thing.
We'll call it dot assign X. And what we're going to do is we're
going to cat that file. Cat is the same as get content.
Remember I'm an old Linux guy Unix guy. I'm going to say cat
r and d. And what I'll do is I'll cast it like XML. I'm going
to copy this file and cast it as XML. Now I'll have an object
I'll assign X which contains the XML. Now this is really dot XML.
The way you can tell that you can type type and you can see it's
an XML document. So this is XML. Now, have you ever worked with XML?
>> Not in its raw form.
>> It's hideous. It's hideous, like kicking a dead whale along
the beach. All sorts of effort and seems like nothing ever ever
happens just hideous. But not in PowerShell. So in PowerShell,
again, I mapped this hideous world to your world. Remember, what
does this thing look like? Like blah, blah, blah. Right?
Here when I said I see dollar sign x.play.
Oh, look at that. So then here are the acts.
Oh, look at that. I could say well give me act 0 and give me
the scene and here are all the scenes. And I can say, hey, scene
0, give me the speech.
And there are all the speeches. Look. Is that cool or what?
It gets better. Here, if I get rid of this index. Remember, it
gave me a set of things, and I selected the first one. So now
what I'm going to do, because PowerShell version 3 I can go and
say, hey, I want all the scenes and I want all the acts.
And it gives them all.
Now select, now what I can do I can say I'd like to group them
by the speaker and I would like to sort them by count.
And if you're going to... if you're in theater, you definitely
want to be Romeo and not the third musician. Because the third
musician has exactly one speech whereas Romeo has 163. Now, let's
just think about this a second.
Let's just think about this a second. So here I have this XML
and the point is that there's a bunch of XML in the world like
you didn't ask for it but somebody decided hey I'm going to give
you some XML. Thank you. Thank you so much. But... so it's
like, like what, what, what, this hideous horrible world.
Again if you've ever dealt with XML you know exactly what I'm
talking about. But what we do about is we're able to...
by the way, if I wanted to get the history of things that I typed,
you would type get history.
So here are the things that I typed. So what I did was I...
so first was I got the content of that file and I cast it to
XML here. Somewhere. Somewhere. Here. Right. And then I showed
you that it was an XML document here.
And then you are able to ask for the play. We're able to see
that it had an act. I drilled into act one. I saw that it had scenes.
I drilled into scene one and saw that it had speeches and I got
that speech. And then I removed all those, and I got all the speeches.
And then I selected the first one to find out what the properties
of that speech were. I saw that it had a speaker and so I grouped
it by speaker and sorted it by count. And it's that simple.
>> And what's really amazing about this is noticing we're utilizing
the pipeline, and we're building these results as we move along.
We're utilizing the objects because it's an object-based pipeline,
and so even...
>> Actually you know what he's right. If you're in version 2
we didn't use the pipeline, but that's exactly the point.
In version 2 you would have had to use the pipeline. Back when
we did this to get everything, what you would have had to have
done is something like... because we fixed it you would have
done something like I think it was this, you would have to say
through select minus expand, scene...
I think I even got that wrong. Through select, minus expand, speech.
And I did get this wrong. Anyway, so a bunch of pipelines, very,
very powerful stuff. And in version three we simplified it with
the dot syntax.
>> The dot syntax you're going to see quite a bit today as we
start utilizing it. But combining that along with the pipeline
really makes it very powerful. Now, a couple of other things
that Jeffrey was showing you that I want to highlight. And we're
going to need this information for this afternoon. So along
with working with objects, Jeffrey also showed you a filter.
So let me give you an example. Get service.
We have a commandlet called where object. Now where object is
a way for you to filter out only the data that you want to see.
Usually you'll see it abbreviated down to where. That's using
the alias that way. Now, there is a parameter called filter script
that has a couple of squigglies.
Squigglies. Whatever happens in the squigglies is your filter.
Now, I'm going to show you a couple of ways to write a filter,
because this is what you're going to see on the Internet.
First of all, almost nobody uses the parameter name filter script.
So it's the squigglies. I want you to see something. This is
special symbol. Now, we're going to talk about variables later.
But the dollar sign is a special indicator for you. And in this
case dollar sign underscore means
the current object crossing the pipeline. Now, notice I've got
get service. That's got a whole bunch of objects. We're going
to send one at a time across the pipeline. I want to grab hold
of that for a second because I want to do something to it.
It's stored in dollar sign underscore. Now, in V3, there's another
way we can show you to do this. But hang on a sec. Let me show you.
I want to look at the property status.
And if it's equal to running. As a filter, I want you to think
about this. This is going to filter out only the things that
equal to running. Now, I know you might be saying what the devil
is this EQ over here. Why isn't it equals. Why isn't it equals?
>> So here's the thing. Bruce Payette, superstar, rock star, wrote
this book PowerShell in Action. He goes and describes all the
reasons why we made the language choices. If you ever get to
the point where you're asking deep questions like this, Bruce's
Book, PowerShell in Action, is the book to answer it.
Here's the thing we struggled with this one over and over again.
Honestly. As we started and designed the language in the system,
we struggled with saying, hey, we want to be interactive and programmatic.
And in Linux, UNIX where we had come from, you have these big separations.
You start off with one tool and then that tool fails you.
So you've got to throw everything away and pick up another tool.
You try and write it in the shell script it's not power enough.
You throw it away write it in AUC and Grab and SED, and it's
not powerful enough and you throw it away then use it in PERL,
that's not powerful enough you throw it away pick it up and write
it in C.
That's my joke that Unix is a sequence of failed tools.
What we wanted to do was to have one tool that would work whether
you wanted to do it interactively or you wanted to do this rich
systems programming level. And it turns out that's hard.
Never been done before. Never been done before. And we did it.
And honestly we just struggled with this. Hey, turns out there's
a reason why interactive shells have a syntax the way they do.
There's a reason why programming languages have the language
syntax that they do. And so we struggled with this and so we're
able to finally get this nice match between those two. And part
of the ramification of that... one of the ramifications of that
was we needed to use... by the way when we chose a programming
language we chose the C style.
So the C, C++, C#. So we chose that style of things that's why
you have squiggle brackets versus beginning and end and do and
done or do and OD.
>> Which always confused me.
>> I like the terse kind of language.
>> Exactly.
>> Programmers do too. By the way, who is going to write most
of the commandlets the programmers you want a world that's friendly
to them. That's what we did. Turned out from the grammar, from
the parser, if you had equals there, it got ambiguous. And we
tried and tried and you couldn't resolve that one thing.
That's why we have dash EQ. And let me show you guys, so let
me, I'll show this to you a couple of ways dash EQ means equals.
So as you can see I'm getting the services that are I filtered
out the ones that are stopped, just the ones that are equal.
Here's the important thing. You know, these are redirect characters.
Like file redirect in a shell in a console. You can't use them.
So they created and you can find these by doing get help.
They're comparison operators. You can either do it by looking
for comparison. You'll find the help file for it which is about
underscore comparison operators that lists all of these and you're
going to see a lot of them in here. Or to see all the operators
get help on operators, because you're going to see us use these.
You've got arithmetic assignment, comparison operators. Let me
show you a couple of quick examples with this.
On this filter.
So I've got status equals running. Let me show you the V3 way
to write this. Now it's important that you get used to seeing
it as dollar sign underscore because you can see it on the Internet
this way. And guys like me still use it that way. But there's
a new way to write this
called PS item, which makes a little bit more sense to a lot
of folks that this is current, holding the current item crossing
that pipeline. So get used to seeing it. It works the same way
as dollar sign underscore as you can see it will come across.
You're going to notice that I'm probably going to use dollar
sign underscore because it's just what I'm used to using but
PS item works but we can extend this filter even further. I want
it that it is equal to running and dollar sign underscore.
Ooh and the name is like and when you use like, now you can use wildcard.
So I want it like
B star. And I think I have some services. Aah. So this filter
now lets me filter down data. Now, I need you to think about something.
I'm going to do some pseudo code. Somebody is going to yell
at me when I do this. Pseudo code means it's not really doing anything.
So get stuff,
sort, then where
I just want some stuff.
And then out to a file. Now, let me write this another way.
Get stuff.
By the way, don't try that commandlet it doesn't work.
Where, which I can't spell, some stuff, sort.
And then out file.
Which do you think is going to be the best performing way to
write this?
If you think about it, think about what's actually happening here.
I'm getting stuff.
And in the first one I am sorting it. I'm sorting all of it.
It's all sorted and then I'm handing it to a filter that says
but I just wanted this.
Throw the rest of it away. Thanks for all of your hard work,
have a nice day.
As opposed to the second one which is get stuff, I just want this.
And now sort it.
Done. So it does matter where you filter and where you sort.
Refer to this as you filter as far left as you possibly can.
And you can see examples today where the where object may not
be the filter that's furthest left. As a matter of fact you
see some cool examples where you want to keep in mind filters
far left and sometimes that's with the commandlet that's starting
the process. So you know Jeffrey I think we're at about meal time.
>> Yeah, you know so, by the way, this where command is something
you're going to want to spend some time with. That's one of
the most powerful things like on the face of the planet.
>> You guys are going to have questions after this. Now, I'm
going to give you some references to go to. As a matter of fact,
Don's got a great book out there that you really are going to
want to take a look at. I'll mention it a little bit later on.
But when you have questions, when you have things that are burning
desires for PowerShell, I have a place for you to go. And since
Don is here, let me just show it to you, if I can figure out
how to work
Windows here. Here we go.
I'm so used to the PowerShell stuff I forget... here's this
place called PowerShell.org. .org. And look this is centralized
place for you to find a ton of resources, but one of the most
important things out there is when you go out here, you'll see
the forums. You can go out there and you can ask questions and
get answers and a lot of MVPs and a lot of super gurus are out
there and it would be even great if some day you decide to help
answer some questions. But we've got forums. We've got free
e-books out there to help you with some of the specialized topics
we'll be getting into today.
>> Free. PowerShell. People's favorite word free.
>> I want to point out we've got articles.
There's a PowerShell summit.
Information coming up, tickets are going to go on sale. Not trying
to be a sales guy. Just letting you know. The podcast. The power
scripting podcast has a ton of information especially over the
last five years of PowerShell and power scripting podcasts out there.
And entire script repository. Go to PowerShell.org and ask questions
after this event. We'll be happy to help you out. And Don's
the guy in charge of this, and one of the people responsible
for this. So thanks Don. Glad you're helping us out today.
Before we get started into chapter 6, there were some things
we were noticing in chat that we'd like to kind of talk about
and address.
>> Exactly. So one of the questions had come up around case sensitivity.
And again... so whenever you wonder how does PowerShell do things,
think, hey, what would somebody who is severely flawed do.
And of course that's your best predictor. So we try and be as
case insensitive as possible. So wherever we have the opportunity,
we make things case insensitive. There are however certain PowerShell
commandlets, other teams that require case sensitivity. If that
ever happens, it will be highlighted in the documentation.
But if it's not highlighted in the documentation, you can assume
case insensitivity.
>> That's what my wife says. She says you're very case insensitive.
I said no, I'm very case sensitive. She said no very case insensitive.
Then I have to show her comparison operators where you can specify.
But, no, I'm very... anyways.
>> That almost worked.
>> It almost worked. Back to you. You wanted to do some more
stuff on where.
>> I wanted to party on where.
Here's the thing with where. So originally we tried to design
this where. So let's refresh our memory. So we have get process.
That's too many things. So then what we said was we want to filter this.
So we pipe this to where. Right? And we have a squiggle brackets.
Now, originally the way this worked was
we hired some smart guys and we said, hey, we need SQL against
objects against live .NET objects. And they said uh-huh, they
said go at it my friend this will be straightforward. Let months
later they came back and they had only done a small subset and
the syntax was wonky and it was just clear, oh, that's why SQL
has like a couple hundred guys working on this. Turns out it's
some hard problem.
>> It's hard.
>> So we took a different approach. And what we did we threw
all that code away like three months of code, threw it away and
literally, literally we replaced it with three lines of code.
Three lines of code. And here's the kicker.
>> Does that mean we can police all the SQL guys now too.
>> It's far more powerful than SQL. Wait a second. Three lines
of code far more powerful than SQL I'll prove it to you.
That's pretty bold.
Here's the three lines of code.
So where basically takes each object that comes in the pipeline.
It assigns it to a variable. Step number one. Assign it to a variable.
Dollar sign under bar. Now it's dollar sign under bar and now
dollar PS item. We assign it to a variable. The second is we
evaluate the code within the squiggle brackets. We run the code.
And three,
if the code returns true, we pass the object on and if it doesn't,
we throw it away.
So it's that simple. So, now notice... so that's why you're
able to do things like, hey,
handles greater than 1,000. 1,000. Okay. So we grab the current object.
Notice here the first object here is... oh let's see, this thing.
And it's handles is 82.
So we take this object, which is the row.
We assign it to dollar sign underbar. And then we evaluate this.
Hey, are the handles greater than 1,000? The answer is false.
So you're going to see that object doesn't get passed on.
If ever it's true, we then pass on the object as it is. And you
see all the things are greater than 100. Now, remember the algorithm.
It's important to memorize the algorithm. There are very few
things you memorize in PowerShell. This is one of them.
Assign the object to dollar sign under bar. Evaluate the code.
If the code evaluates to true, pass the object on. If it evaluates
to false, don't do that.
Now, notice I never said that you had to use the object in the expression.
Right? So what's that mean? So I could have said now here I'm
going to limit it. I'm going to say star SS. We'll do a subset.
Makes it a little easier. I can say where
dollar sign false.
Notice I didn't use dollar sign under bar.
Nothing passed on. Because it always evaluates to false.
Notice I can say dollar sign true. And it always succeeds.
Okay. So what I'm really talking about... so that's literally
how it works. This isn't a joke. That's literally how it works.
Now the point is these are not very useful. And this is useful.
But the thing I want to point out here is that you just run the code.
The code can do anything. In this example, it's a simple expression.
But you could have put a very complex expression. You could
have put a script. You could have put ten pages worth of code here.
Calling up your mother to ask her opinion on things.
Looking things up in Active Directory. Checking things in SQL
you can do anything you want in the end it has to evaluate to
true or false and that's how it works. It's incredibly powerful.
There's one other thing I wanted to say about where.
That is a lot of people who begin with PowerShell look at these
squiggle brackets and they said aaah. It's like mouse.
And so we have a very simplified version of where. Now, this
isn't as rich as this where. With the squiggle brackets you can
do anything. The simplified where you can do very subset of things.
You can do things where, a property, operator value. So what
you do... and you don't have to have the squiggle brackets.
There you go. There's the deal. And you don't have to have dollar
sign under bar.
So you get rid of that. And you can just say where handles greater
than 1,000.
And voila, it works.
>> And I think for a lot of admins getting started especially
with filtering because filtering is going to be one of the most
important things you do.
This simplified syntax can be really helpful at first until you
get more used to the squiggly brackets. Now, like Jeffrey said,
though, there are limitations there. As soon as you want to
start doing multiple criteria and as soon as you want it to call
up your mother and check with her first, that's going to require
the squiggly brackets. But I really like the simplified...
>> Can I tell you I use this thing all the time.
>> The simplified one.
>> As a matter of fact, when we look at doing some remoting stuff
with software and all that, I'll just use where install.
Make it short and sweet. It's going to get really cool, guys.
That was awesome.
Okay. Let's get serious for a moment.
Maybe you ought to keep us both on screen because we both have
to have this serious look on our face.
We're going to go into the pipeline now.
But deeper. Deeper. Deeper.
>> You're committing all sorts of HR violations today.
You're just like Captain Inappropriate.
>> Packman.
>> Inappropriate.
>> Here's the deal.
What we're going to show you is something that's very advanced.
And you need to know this. You need to know this. But what's
going to happen is that you're going to see the concept here
and it's going to happen really quick and then you're going to
need to practice this, and you're going to have problems practicing this.
So I'm going to give you a couple of references right now before
we get started. First of all, you're going to want chapter 9
out of Don Jones's book lunches...
>> PowerShell and a Month of Lunches.
>> Learn Windows PowerShell in a Month of Lunches, chapter 9 you'll
want that chapter, and it will take you through everything that
we're going to do and you'll get a chance to try it. Let me
tell you how important it was. I was sitting if you've been to
a conference before, I'm sure you have been, I was sitting in
a conference and you know they had the... you know like TechEd,
they're enormous. They put speakers... they put the rooms over
there and rooms over here and a football field in the middle.
Now, that's where all the sponsors go. But there's this giant
football field and they don't put a lot of seats in there.
So you see all these people sitting up against the wall and working
on stuff. Well, I was sitting up against the wall working on
a problem with getting two commandlets to work together in Exchange.
I couldn't get it to work together and I said to myself, I said:
It's a problem with the guys that wrote the commandlets.
It's a problem with PowerShell it just doesn't work I just can't
solve that problem. And not but a few moments later you and then
shortly after that Don Jones, you taught me how to figure out
how the pipeline works and suddenly, with this knowledge, suddenly
I could get that solution to work. And I guess what the moral
of the story is is that as soon as you understand this, the answer
is you can always get it to work. So never give up. It's just...
it's a little tricky at first.
>> This is one of those things I used to have a physics professor
who would say this problem is simple once it's solved. So we're
going to help you solve it. When you first look at it you're
like what the heck, what the heck and then at some point there
will be this moment of clarity and it's super super simple.
It really is.