[Music]
>> And we're back for our last session for today.
>> Last session. Last and best.
>> Last and best session for today. Guys, this is...
>> Before we forget, we should just give a super shout out to
the MVPs answering all those great questions. Hoorah.
>> [Applause] Yeah.
>> Thank you. And just representative example of the awesome PowerShell community.
Join. Be part of the PowerShell community.
>> Yep.
>> Let's go.
>> And so, guys, what we're going to do, is this is kind of a
warmup for what we're going to do on August 1st where we go through
all the details in this. This is more than just a warmup, though.
You can start immediately using this today. I like to refer
to this as immediately effective. And so let's start off with,
though, thank God you're not physically in this room, because
what I'm about to show you I've actually had people threaten
to hit me.
>> Oohh. I'm here.
>> So you have to imagine that... no, don't hit me, man.
Don't... you just got punched by Jeffrey Snover. That's going
to look really good on my resume. So we've been spending all
of our time in the console. And, God, I love the console and
we've been working on commands, and here's what you want to do,
you want to work stuff out in here, copy it, and, like we did
earlier, paste it into a script. But I want to show you something
that comes with PowerShell, and it's the ISE. And...
>> Oohh.
>> Yeah. And oohh. And this is... so I'm going to close this console.
And, guys, I want to show you this real quick so that we can
kind of get into it. But I'm going to start the ISE.
And, you know, they're going to do that picture in picture thing,
so let me lower this thing down here a little bit.
Now, I'm going to show... don't yell at me, please. Don't yell
at me. First of all, there's a scripting pane up here. Down here's
a console pane. Then there's this commands pane. I'm going to
simplify this screen real quick. Boink. And I want to show
you these buttons across the top. You can have the scripting
pane on top and a console on the bottom. You can have them side
by side. Which if you have two monitors, this is awesome...
>> Yeah....
>> to put this between the dual monitors. But I'm going to make
it even simpler. I'm just going to go to one pane and so I can
kind of shorten things up a little bit here. And bring this
down a little bit. Here's the part that you're going to threaten
to beat me to death with. I'm going to hit control R. That flips
me between the scripting pane and the console. And you might
be asking yourself, well, this looks kind of like a console.
Yeah, this is a damn fine console. Remember this morning when
we were talking and Jeffrey was saying, hey, look, we can't touch
that original console thing that...
>> Oh, control R toggles.
>> Huh?
>> I didn't know that.
>> What? Control R?
>> Control R toggles.
>> Yeah. It's awesome.
>> Oh. I keep trying to remember control D versus control I.
Like D, what the hell does D mean?
>> No, I think Bruce Payette... I think Bruce Payette did something
with control R, and I'm like, oh, oh, oh. So, yeah, control R.
>> Well, I learned something.
>> Oh, that's... yeah, right on, bro. So here's the deal.
I'm going to type something here and you're going to see that
this is not the console that you think we are. First of all,
let me clear it up. Now watch.
I'm going to do get...
wooo, look at what it's doing. Look at what it's doing.
Dude. This is like...
it's intellisense helping me through here. This is like totally awesome.
And watch. You might notice that it's also
color syntax.
So here's the deal. And we're going to ask Jeffrey about this,
because this is the coolest thing in the world. You've got a
console that has color syntax coding which helps a lot when you're
typing to see if you're typing in error, and it's got this help
flying at me as I'm typing.
Is this your solution to the console going forward?
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Because this makes it a lot easier.
>> Yeah. Right. Spend a couple hours with this and stop asking
me about improving the console.
>> Which is what the thing was this morning is don't ask about
improving the console because they're doing it right now.
And this is the way to do it. So let's use this console and let's
take a command here. Let's do a get WMI object. Yeah, it's okay,
it's okay, it will all be good. Win32 underscore logical disk.
I just want to show you... I want to get something to work.
And I'm going to type something in you probably haven't seen before.
You will. But I'm going to do device, filter on device, ID equals C.
I want you to see what it gives me as an output. Well, absolutely
nothing, because I screwed up the filter.
And so what this command now gives me is it gives me some useful information.
It's giving me... I'm having a scroll issue here. Hang on.
It's giving my drive C and it gives me free space and size.
I don't like the numbers, so I'm going to do something in flight.
I want you no notice I'm building a command to make sure that
it works first, and then I'm going to show you how easy cool
this gets. So what I'd like is I'd like to select. And I'm only
going to take one property for this demonstration. So I'd like
to use the free space. But you know what I can't stand?
Is, okay, let's just do free space.
Watch. I don't know about you, but I don't really like that number
because that number is like in bytes and it's like not making
me happy because I want to see it in gigabytes or something like
that because...
>> Can I point something out?
>> Yeah.
>> Can you go back? So you did get get WMI object. Do get SIM object. Yeah. Wait.
Yeah. No, let's start from scratch.
>> Okay. Let's start from scratch.
>> Yeah.
>> You want... you want get SIM object.
>> Get SIM object.
>> Get SIM object. Or SIM instance.
>> Instance, sorry. Yeah. And say Win32 logi-... and then tab.
>> Tab.
>> See the red right there?
>> Oohh. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Oohh.
>> Now, go back.
>> Oh, I've gone too far. Oh, go back, go back, go back.
>> Cancel, cancel, cancel. Logical. And then control space.
Control space.
>> Logical. And then control space.
>> Yeah.
>> Oohh.
Oh. That's awesome.
>> Intellisense against the WMI name spaces. Is that crazy?
>> Oh, guys, when you start working with WMI, one of the hardest
things is dealing with the name spaces and finding the classes.
And this is one of the most important technologies out there.
We haven't had time today to go through it, but this is awesome.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Yeah. So you're going to be wanting to use get SIM instance
instead of the old-fashioned command that I'm going to use right now.
>> Okay.
Okay.
>> And so I'm going to do select free space. I can't stand that
number, so I'm going to do a custom column, and I'm going to...
just like we had done earlier, because I don't like that, I'm
going to create my own. There's a reason I'm doing this, but
don't panic, we're almost there. And so I'm going to call it
free GB and... whoops. It would help if I put in something to
tell it what I was doing.
>> And...
>> You're not showing the best practices.
Hit cancel. Hit carriage... hit cancel up to the pipeline.
Now hit carriage return.
>> Oh. Well, but... but... but... well, it doesn't do that in
the ISE. It does it only in the console.
I know what you... so here's what Jeffrey is saying, and I'll
show it to you in there, in here. Because I want you to see this.
Because you guys... this will actually be really interesting.
I want you to see that... watch. So I'm doing this long line
here, get WMI object, Win32 underscore logical disk.
Logical disk.
Filter. And device ID
equals C colon. And, guys, here's the thing, is that I want to...
that's great and that's fine, that's dandy, but I'm going to
start typing this long command that's going to be wrapping around.
A really great way to work at the console is to realize that
there are certain things that automatically give us line continuation,
the pipeline being one of them. Watch what happens here when
I strike enter after the pipeline.
See these things [Making noise]? This means...
>> How do you spell that?
>> I'm not sure, but it means you're... we get it. You're still
on the same line, just keep typing. So from here I can do my select.
It becomes easier to read and it's easier to edit when you're
doing stuff in real time. Select. And I'll do my at N equals
free GB and... whoops. It's late in the day. E equals...
and I'm going to take the current object across the pipeline,
I'm going to grab its free space. And I want to see it in gigabytes,
so I'm going to divide it by
1 GB. We have these built-in things to help us with math, because
I'm not good at math, so these help me with math. And so the
number looks... strike enter on this line. Number looks better,
but I'd like it all rounded up. So I'm just going to do this
as an integer real quick.
Now, I'm going to do it as an integer real quick but it's going
to yell at me because I didn't run both lines.
So let me do this.
>> Oh, I'm sorry.
>> No, that's fine, that's fine. And so as int. And...
oops. Now I screwed something up.
>> Brackets.
>> Hang on. Brackets. I forgot the brackets.
I'll get you good line of code.
Don't panic. This is all in the slides too, so if I fail to type...
boom. So I've got a nice line now. I've got something that's
giving me information that I want. It's pretty cool, got it
all worked out. What I'm going to do is cut and paste. Now, from
here, you know, cut and paste is kind of hard to do, but if you
did this over here, cut and paste is real easy to do, because
you know what's funny is they figured out how to use things like,
oh, let's see, this old technology called control C control V.
So I'm going to say control C. I'm going to hit control R to
flip the screen. I'm going to control V.
Oh, yeah, baby. Now I've got my line. Now we're going to start
having some fun because we're going to save this as a script
right now. File. Save as.
We'll save it here in my scripts folder. We're going to save
it as... well, we did I love you. Let's do this as...
let's just call it diskinfo.ps1.
And I can run it from right here. If I run it, boom, shows me
a result. Well, it helps if I clear the screen and everything
else I typed. But I can run it. Boink. And it shows me the results.
>> Happy, happy.
>> I'm going to hit control R. Everything's good.
Now we want to start adding stuff to this. So let's make this
a little better. First of all, you know, this is a nice script
and all this, but if I give it to somebody else, all's it's doing
right now is getting information off the C drive on the local machine.
That's not cool.
I want it to be able to get it from
whatever computer I want it to get it from. Now, I could sit
here and hard code this.
>> Dude, you didn't spell computer name right.
>> I'm not spelling anything right. Computer.
Name. Local host. And this will work, but... go ahead and save it.
That's fine, but here's the problem.
If I give this to a friend, what are they going to have to do?
They're going to have to go in here and edit my script. And I
don't want people editing my script. What could possibly go wrong?
>> Especially if you digitally signed it.
>> Especially if I digitally signed it. So what I'm going to
do is let's do a simple concept. Let's make a variable up here
called dollar sign computer name.
And let's set it right now equal to local host just to have some
value in there. And instead of... we'll put the variable in here.
Now, this is kind of common to a lot of other scripting languages
where what you would do is you put your variables up here so
you'd make it easier for somebody to edit your script. I still
don't like this whole editing my script thing, but I want you
to see that this still works, right? All's I'm doing is putting
it into dollar sign computer name, still prints it out, everything's cool.
You know, let me show you how to test the script properly from
the console, because I'm about to blow your mind. Something that
these guys have done is awesome. So let's run the script from
the console. Since a lot of scripts get run from the console,
I actually like to test them from there.
Yep, CD scripts.
And so we called this disk info.
Run it.
We're good.
>> Happy, happy.
>> Happy, happy. But you know what? I've been learning PowerShell,
and as an administrator, this isn't exactly what I expect. I expect...
I don't want to go in and edit computer name. No, when we have
commandlets and stuff, we get parameters that we can adjust.
So you know what would be really cool I think? I think it'd be
really cool if
there's this special keyword called param.
Open parentheses, close parentheses,
indent, so that Jeffrey loves you.
>> That's right.
>> Make it look pretty. I want you guys to notice something.
I'm going to save this. So I'm going to hit control S and save it.
I'm going to go back to my PowerShell console.
And watch this. I'm going to clear the screen, .diskinfo dash...
oh.
I just made a parameter.
>> Oohh.
>> It was so easy to make a parameter. So now I can type in any
computer I want.
Now, I'm not selecting out a computer name which we will fix,
but I want you to kind of get the concept of
I just put a variable in there. Matter of fact, let's do another one.
Let's just call it bogus.
Just so you can see... I'm going to go back here. Watch, watch,
watch, watch. This is so cool.
Let's do...
>> Oohh.
>> I'm making parameters on the fly for whatever I need.
This is becoming what's called a parameterized script. And what
you're getting is it's starting to
smell, look, and feel more like a commandlet and it's making
my life a little bit easier.
>> Mmm.
>> I'm liking this. So let's try this. There's another thing
that would be really nice, is if for an instance, at least, gethelp.diskinfo.
>> Yeah.
>> Look at what PowerShell is doing?
PowerShell is
starting to build that syntax for me. But computer name, it
says it's an object. No, let me go in here and you can strongly
type what the variables are. We didn't have... haven't talked
much about that, but I what this to be a string so when I go
out here and do this again,
notice it's now making it a string. And I want you to notice
that between the chihuahuas, it says string, it doesn't say that
it can take multiple objects. We don't have any of the binkies
in there. So here's how we put binkies
in there.
>> Oohh.
And I'm starting to actually get syntax now built on these parameters.
And the only thing I've had to do so far is add one keyword different
from what I'm used to and this one called param.
But, wait, there's more.
>> But wait, it's better.
>> We're going to turn something on so that you can use
parameter attributes.
>> Yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah.
>> So let's do commandlet binding.
This turns on something called parameter attributes. And here's
the thing. I don't really want to have local host in here.
>> Oh...
>> What I want to do... oh, what do you want me to do? What?
>> Just hit save.
>> Just hit save. Yeah? Yeah?
>> And now do get help.
>> Okay. Oh, I see what you... okay.
Now...
>> He added one line of code.
>> One line.
>> One line of code. And watch what happens. What?
>> Well, that wasn't... that wasn't very...
>> Did you save it?
>> Did I save it? I think I saved it. Oh, well, we got common parameters.
So, yeah...
>> Oh, yeah, okay....
>> it did it, we just need to do the... yeah, so we got common parameters.
So this is actually making the syntax full. Watch. Watch.
So commandlet binding will let us use something called parameter
attributes, things like making things mandatory. Let me show
you an example. I'm going to get rid of this default and
I'm going to go in here and I'm going to say parameter...
I got to spell this right... mandatory...
mandatory... equals true. And I think I got the syntax correct.
Now, I want to point out that this is a parameter attribute.
I'm going to say mandatory is true. It only affects the next
parameter after it. It's not going to affect bogus. So watch.
Look at what happens to the syntax on this.
Notice up here I had the brackets around it. Now look.
There's no brackets around that. This is going to become mandatory.
So watch as I start to try to run this. I'm going to do disk info.
I'm going to run it. You've got to give me a computer name, man,
so it's mandatory now.
DC. And now it works. I can do it. I made it mandatory. I can
also then do... of course I've got the actual parameter. So in
just two lines of code we're making our own parameters on our
script, a parameterized script, and we're getting syntax.
But you know what? I want to be a nice guy when I give this to
somebody else. I want to be a really nice guy. When I give it
to you, I want to be a great guy. So what do you say we add
in a little bit of help.
>> Love it. Love it.
>> Let's do some help. Guys, this is a block comment. Now, usually
when you type in comments, see how they're in green?
Usually the parsing engine there will just ignore what's ever
in there. But with PowerShell, watch. I'm just going to type
in a couple of things.
Synopsis. I'm going to say this is the short explanation.
It's okay if I have typing mistakes at this point because tired.
Description. This is the long description. Yeah, everybody's
going to be making fun of me because I can't type in. I'm going
to type in parameter...
whoops, whoops, whoops. Parameter. And I'm going to say computer name.
And I'm going to say this is for remote computers. And just
a couple more things here real quick.
Example. Let's do an example of... oh, let's do disk info dash
computer name, you know, remote. And let's do one more.
This is for... this...
>> Do we do an example?
>> This...
>> Oh.
>> I can't type of at all. This is for a remote computer.
Watch. Look, guys. Just a couple of things. This is going to
be totally amazing.
Watch, watch, watch. Get help.
Looky. Does it
look like PowerShell help now?
>> Woo woo.
>> Woo woo woo woo woo. So I've got name, synopsis, look, it's
building the syntax, I got description. But, wait, that's the
short help. Watch. Watch, watch, watch, watch, watch.
Full... oh, now look what PowerShell's built for me. It shows
me the parameters, parameter definitions. I've got an example
down here. For crying out loud, this is what I want. I want
to give this to somebody else that works for PowerShell because
this is what they expect. Oh. This is making me so happy.
>> No, can I just point something out?
>> Yes, absolutely.
>> I can never remember any of this.
>> I can't remember any of this either.
>> Well, you did.
That's pretty good. I can't do that. So show them the amazing
control J.
>> So, guys, I'm going to hit...
>> That's the only way I can deal with it.
>> And here's the thing. And when we come back on August 1st,
this is going to become one of your best friends. So I'm going
to start a new tab. I'm going to hit control J. It's going to
bring up snippets. Now, I want to point something out. Not quite
done with this demonstration yet, but these snippets, look at
this, commandlet snippet, it gives you the basics of putting
this together. And the advanced one, the complete one is super
rockin' cool. So we've got comment blocks, we've got some of
the constructs and the loops that we're going to be using on
August 1st that you'll be able to work with to help you build this.
So you can actually pick a snippet and, look, it auto creates
all these possibilities for you. And, oh, look, it... see?
All's you got to do now is just go in and...
>> So if you are a deeply flawed human like me and cannot spell
synopsis, control J.
>> Yeah, this is what my problem is. So you can use this as a
template to fill it up. But, wait, there's more. We're not done yet.
Because here's the deal. This is nice. This is a parameterized script.
And you can do a lot of powerful things with parameterized scripts.
But, you know, I want to take this to the next level just a little
bit more so you can get an idea of where we're going to go on
August 1st.
>> Take it to 11.
>> Take it to... my amp goes to 11, it does.
So we're going to crank this bad boy up because my ISE goes to 11.
Save script, no. Let's do this.
So that you can see the typing, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to remove the help for it right now. Okay? So don't freak out
on me, I'm just going to...
>> Wait. Why are you doing that?
>> Well, because I want them to... oh, I guess I can just scroll...
yeah, let's do this.
>> No, no, no. Click the button.
>> Oh, click the button.
>> Collapse.
>> Oh. Dude, that's...
>> Because ISE goes to 11, dude.
>> Because ISE goes to 11. So here we go. Guys, right now we're
running this like a script. I don't know about you, but we ain't
done this all day long. We haven't typed in and run this script.
What we've been doing is we've been running things likes verb,
dash, noun, verb, dash, noun.
God, I'd like to do the same thing, too, if only I knew how.
Well, here's how.
Going to add one more keyword
to your day of fun. Function. You need to give it a name.
Now, we're going to give it a proper name.
Verb dash noun. Don't do this, Gimmi dash stuff.
No, gimmi is not on the approved verb list, so knock it off with
making up your own verbs. There's...
>> And everybody, you've got do it at least once, right?
But, here, we're going to do get dash, and we're just going to
call it disk info. Now, the function, it has an open squiggly
and then when you're done with your code all the way at the end...
>> But wait. Show them... forget it. Oh, we're going to do ISE later?
>> Are we going to do what?
>> Are we going to talk about ISE a lot next time?
>> Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Well, what do you want them to see?
>> Get rid of the last squiggle.
>> The last squiggle?
>> Yeah. Get rid of that.
>> Get rid of the last squiggle?
>> Yeah. Okay. See the first squiggle? See that squig-...
see the yellow?
>> See the red? Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> Missing closing...
>> Missing close... so it's trying to help us understand where
we're making mistakes.
>> Isn't that cool? So you see the little squiggle. It's actually
pretty useful. Really useful.
>> And you guys see on the screen the little red squiggly that
Jeffrey's talking about is this one right here? And so if you
leave your mouse over it, it tells you, hey, you're missing something
here, bro, and in this case...
>> Dude.
>> Dude. And so...
>> Dude....
>> we're missing that bottom squiggly.
>> You'll let go into like 2.
>> Yeah.
[Laughter]
>> Exactly. So I'm going to indent this so that it's easier to read.
So you can see that I have a function. Now, don't do what I'm
about to do, because this is just... I'm going to show you something
much cooler than this. I'm going to save this. And I want to
show you. Here's one of the interesting things. I'd like to
run that script and then use that function. Well, here's the
challenging thing. Watch. If I run disk info and I hit enter,
what happens when you run a script is the script runs, it executes,
and then everything is discarded out of memory. This is a good thing.
But here's the problem. I just ran a script and it has a function
called get disk info. So what happened is the script just ran,
it just made this function up in memory for me, and when the
script ended, it just killed it. So there is no get disk info.
>> No, not so much.
>> So I'm going to show you a unique way to do this. Now, this
is great way for testing, but I got a better solution for you.
>> Mmm.
>> Dot space.
>> Oh, showing them the dot.
>> Dot back slant... I know, I know...
>> I love it. No, it's awesome.
>> This retains the stuff in your script in memory. So watch.
I'm going to run it.
>> That's not the right explanation.
>> Okay. But, well, then you tell them.
>> Okay. So here's the way it works. So what happens is there's
a stack, right, and so what happens is when you run something
in general you create a new stack and you put all your variables
in that stack and then when you do an exit or a return that stack
goes away and they all get cleared up. When you dot something,
what happens is it runs... it doesn't create a new stack, it
runs it in the current stack. So any new variables or anything
that gets created, they get created here. When you exit, you
just exit. But they stick around.
>> But they stick around.
>> Yeah.
>> So...
>> Dot sourcing. You UNIX guys will... you've like caught right
on to this. This is dot sourcing.
>> But isn't that what I said, only not nearly as well as you
said it.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So watch. Get disk. Watch. I'm going to hit tab completion
at this point. Get disk. Get disk image. Get disk.
>> Woo.
>> Hey. Tab completion. Look. Looks like a commandlet.
Looky, looky, looky. Computer name. DC. We are rock and roll.
I don't like having them do this dot source stuff.
>> Boy, did you... when you hit that commandlet... by the way,
do it again. Do it again.
>> Do it again?
>> Up arrow, up arrow.
>> Up arrow.
>> Dash O tab. Oohh.
>> Oh. Out... oh. Out variable.
>> Out variable.
>> So let's...
>> A.
>> What do you want to call it, A?
>> A. Everything's A.
>> Everything's A.
>> Yeah, dollar sign A.
>> Dollars sign A. So now I'm going to let you guys see that it
just sent it out to the variable, some of those common parameters
that we can use. So now we've got this stuffed into a variable.
It's awesome.
>> So what that meant was when you put that commandlet binding
there, it said common parameters, there's a bunch of common parameters,
and these are functions, you know, just by putting that one thing
on you say, hey, PowerShell engine, could you do some stuff,
work for me, could you like give them... I'll put variable and
then could you do like error action and error variable and warning
action and warning variable? Oh, really cool stuff.
>> Well, you know, let's take this one step further, and you can
certainly throw stuff into this, but, guys, this is going to
be meat of what we do on August 1st.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's... you know, this is nice, but this isn't something
quite yet what we refer to as an advanced function, although
it's getting there, and what I want to be able to do is I don't
want to have to dot source and run this as a script. That doesn't
make sense to the junior admin that I want to give this to.
>> It's really worth the investment. It's going to take some time.
>> Right.
>> It's not going to be the simplest thing in the world.
It's going to take some time, but you really need to invest in
learning about modules. Okay? Because modules are the future.
They're really worth the investment.
>> Yes.
>> You know, why don't we just like settle in and teach them how
to do it.
>> And teach them how to do it. So you guys ready? Hey, hard core,
here we go.
>> Woohoo.
>> Yeah. Wake up, wake up.
>> We're going to hard core how to make a module.
>> Wake up.
>> First of all, I'm going to show you the cheesy way to make
a module.
>> Oh, cheesy.
>> File. Save as.
Notice my script?
That's it. That's it. That's it. That's how you make a... PSM 1. Watch.
Watch.
>> You can now go to sleep.
>> Yeah, you can... watch, watch, watch. Now, look, because it's
not in the special place that we're going to talk about, I'm
going to have to manually import this module and this module
is called PSM1.
So this is kind of like the old V2 way we'd always have to work
with modules.
>> Do dash, though.
>> Oh, but watch. What?
>> Do it again.
>> What do you want to do?
>> Do it again. Slash. Slash force slash verbose.
>> You want to do...
>> Dash force.
>> Force?
>> Force.
>> The other force.
>> And then dash verbose.
>> Verbose.
>> And this just shows you...
>> Yeah. See?
>> Ah, removing one of the imported. Oh, I love that. I love that.
>> Yeah, it's importing the get disk info.
>> And this is actually when you... and especially...
especially on August 1st when we're working with, you know, you
have to reload modules, you have to do... this is actually very
useful to have around. So I've got a module that's imported.
Now I can just do get disk info. But, you know, this is still
not exactly the way that I want it because I don't want to have
to say here's this thing, I made you this pretty module, it's
a PSM1 file, and you're going to have to import every time you
want to use anything in it. That just doesn't make sense.
>> Dude, how hard was that? It was easy.
>> I know it was easy, but you guys have like magical locations.
>> Oh, there's the magic. Yes.
>> Yeah. So...
>> You're going to let them in on the secrets.
>> Well, I don't know. Let's see. Can I catch ENV...
is it PS module path that shows us all the magic?
So there are two paths here.
These are the magic locations right now as far as we're going
to talk about, and the magic locations, if you put your module
in these locations in a special way, they too will be dynamically loaded.
>> Dude, what are you doing there? That's odd.
>> What, what, what?
>> I never do it that way.
>> What do you want to do?
>> Show it my way.
>> Okay, well, do it your way.
>> Okay, switch me. So what I do is I do... I do... oh, let's
make this bigger.
>> Woohoo.
>> I do dollar sign. Okay?
>> Wow.
>> And that looks the same. But check this out. Because we need
to do dollar sign...
>> Dollar sign....
>> we can do split.
>> Split.
>> Split. Split.
>> Let's do it your way.
Yeah.
>> And then you break it out. Then you can read it.
>> Yeah. Let's do it that way. Let's do it as...
>> Okay. Let's switch back to him....
>> split. Oops. So I can't spell split. I can spell spit, apparently.
And what are we... we're doing on what, the semicolon?
>> Semicolon.
>> Yeah.
>> There's quotes. Quotes.
>> The quotes, quotes, quotes, quotes, quotes. Ah. Oh, now we
can read the two paths. This makes a lot...
>> Much better.
>> So here's the first path that I want you guys to take notice of.
This is the path. And I'm going to show this to you graphically
for a second just so you can kind of see this. I'm going to
go out. This where PowerShell gets installed. Windows System32.
And there's a reason I'm showing it graphically. Sometimes this
makes more sense. And so I'm going to go out where it says Windows
PowerShell, and you'll see this folder called modules. And you
see all these modules? These are modules. Here's the thing.
Don't put yours here.
>> Yeah.
>> This is not for you.
A lot of guys will say, oh, just put it in there because I know
where it is, all that kind of stuff. No. Don't put your stuff there.
This is the special place for Microsoft. You have your own special
place, and that is this one.
Your account documents Windows PowerShell modules. But this
doesn't exist. Let me show you. Let me show you graphically.
Sometimes this makes a little bit more sense. So I'm going to
go out here to users, and I'll go out to student company is my account.
And it's my documents through here.
You see, there's no module called Windows PowerShell and there's
nothing called modules. So you will need to make it. Now, I
know, I'm making it graphically just because I happen to be here,
but you can do it with PowerShell of course. Windows PowerShell.
And then underneath of it, you make...
it'd been faster if I'd done it in PowerShell. Oh, my God.
What the hell's the matter with me? So modules...
>> Because now you're going to have to type it right.
>> Now I'm going to have to type it right. Now, here's the thing.
And this is very, very important.
The name of your module... you know the thing I call diskinfo.psm1
needs to be the name of the folder that you're going to create here.
They need to match. So I'm going to say new folder and I'm going
to say disk info.
Now, I've got this folder. Let's do this.
I need to put my module in there. So let me go grab my module,
which was this PSM1.
Disk info.
I'm going to take it, put it out to here.
Oh, yeah, I should have never done this graphically, but, well,
I'm here.
I'm going to put it... now, here's the important thing. See?
Look. Module name, the module folder name. And then the name
of the dooder inside.
Watch. Let's close this so you know I'm not cheating.
Let's see. I wonder if I can get some help on...
>> Wait. Did you start a fresh window? Is that a fresh window?
>> Yeah. I started a brand-new one, >> Missed
it.
>> Started a brand new one. Oh. Here. Just in case anybody missed
it, I don't want you to miss it, I'm not cheating. Let me close
this thing out. I'm not cheating.
Brand-new window. Get help.
Is there anything... commandlets on disk information? Hmm.
Hmm. Wait a minute, wait a minute, wait a minute. Hmm.
>> Oh, right there first. Number one, baby.
>> Hmm. Help found my commandlet inside my module. And, well,
let's just try it. Get disk...
not image, info. Dash computer name. DC. Oohh.
>> Okay. The guys in
the back... you can tell that we're getting up to the end of
the day because the guys in the back are now going aahhh.
So let me just show you the coding, and, Jeffrey, please go ahead
and add in. So all's we're really doing is doing functions.
We're properly naming them so that they look like commandlets.
Notice I just gave it a little bit of help. There are about
underscore comment based help files for this to help you with
this or you can use control J to get the snippets. And notice
I took a working line of code, the only thing I did was I added
param, couple of variables in there, maybe an attribute, and
believe me on August 1st we'll talk a lot more about attributes.
>> Attributes rock.
>> Oh, they totally rock. So with this simple little bit of code
and saving it in the special place as a PSM1 file, I've made
a module. In fact, like all modules, I'm not just going to put
one function in here, I'm going to put as many functions...
I'm going to make as many tools as I need, and I'm going to put
them into this module. So I'll just make it foo and I'll make
function bar.
No, I know they're not properly named, but you get the idea.
Now with that module, I'm just adding more and more tools to
this module now. If you do that, save it.
Save it.
>> Save it?
So...
>> Import it. Import.
>> Import module. And it's... I forgot the name.
>> Disk info.
>> Disk info, right?
>> Yeah. Minus force.
>> Force and verbose. Or...
>> That's fine.
Hmm.
>> Oh, did you expect it to come up and do whole you're using a...
>> Yeah.
>> Not improved? You know, and what he's talking about is...
and matter of fact I have to play with this, I think...
>> Foo dash bar?
>> Well, let's do gimmi dash foo.
And, yeah, bar dash foo.
And let me save it.
>> Oh, you know what? It's the force. That's the problem.
>> Oh, it's the force that's doing it.
>> Yeah. So remove it. Remove it. Remove module.
>> So remove module.
>> By the way, so force basically says you're telling us we know
what you're doing, ignore all the errors, just do what I told
you to do, dang it. So watch what happens if you don't type force.
>> And this is actually disk info.
Oh, dude, I don't know why it's not saying it.
>> Hmm. Interesting.
>> Okay. I don't know why it's not saying it, but here's what
usually happens. If you use an unapproved verb, it comes up and
it says in yellow knock it off. Stop using unapproved verbs.
>> Don't be a dope.
>> Don't be a dope. So use approved verbs. And what are we doing
on this... I see something up... it gives us... oh, oh, oh.
I... they were trying to... you guys don't understand what's
up on the teleprompters in here right now.
The guys... the production team was trying to be f'ing funny.
[Laughter]
>> They didn't use the appropriate verb.
>> And so, first of all, here's what they typed in so you all
can see it. They said dollar sign mention this pipe to...
and I can't even read what character they're using.
>> Star? Is that star?
>> This is... will you guys... up on sight,
and then was it a squiggly? A squiggly.
It gives
us good feedback
end squig-... this is... this is... have you guys been awake
at all today? This is the crappiest PowerShell I
have ever seen.
>> This is remarkable. We've been busting our bums all day long,
and you type this in?
>> Please, one of the MVPs of the forums, somebody, you don't
even have to be an MVP, take this and show them how it really
should be done in the Cliff Note version.
>> Yeah. Are you guys good at AV?
>> I thought we had a Good Will Hunting moment there.
[Laughter]
>> Not so much. Good at AV? That's good. Keep doing that.
>> Yeah, stay in AV.
>> Stay in that.
>> What I think they're trying to say is that there's a poll up.
Am I correct?
>> A poll.
>> There's a poll up? And it's a real important poll. So make
sure you do the poll up on the site because the feedback for
this session is very important.
>> Super important.
>> As a matter of fact, we're starting to get kind of towards
the end of what we've done for the day, but your feedback on
the session is very important.
Just so that you know, we're going to dive deep, deep, deep and
we're going to do it in a day. So it's going to be definitely
a day of...
>> Chewy....
>> chewy, chewy stuff into tool making, basically making tools.
Going to show the different kind of parameter attributes, more
about the help, how to... see, we've only scratched the surface.
Our commandlet right now doesn't accept pipeline input, it's
not making changes, so we're not supporting what if and confirm.
And, you know, we might want to make our own views.
There's so many things that we're going to want to do.
So we've actually still got a lot of work to do. We're just
not going to do much more of it today.
So...
[Laughter]
>> Before we do a review, is there anything you want to add to
the stuff we've done today, tell anybody anything?
>> No, I think we... I think we've been having fun. We walked
through a bunch of stuff, a ton more, a ton more. But, again,
the key things I want you guys to walk away with are, one, this
spirit of exploration, right? Go explore. Explore the help.
Explore the help. Explore the help, explore the forums. Go out
on the Internet, try some things.
When you get confused, ask questions. Do not be embarrassed.
Do not sit there and say, oh, that's a dumb question. No, no, no.
Ask that question. You have a great community that will give
you help.
And just hopefully you've seen the sense of fun. There's just
an incredible amount of power in PowerShell, and it's fun to
do this exploration. By the way, and it's safe, too, because
you go and you have the minus what if and the confirm and verbose.
So, you know, it's... you can explore and you can have fun and
do it safely.
>> And do it safely. And notice that we've been having a lot of
fun today because it's been a joy for the two of us to be able
to spend the day talking with everybody about PowerShell.
Because it is just a lot of fun, especially when you get past
some of the learning curve stuff. So we did get help. And the
amazing discoverability of get help, of finding commandlets,
regardless of what product that you're working with, it will
find it for you, and then you can go into the help files, the
examples, the rich... the syntax that's in there, the definitions
of the parameters. So get help is definitely number one tool.
Something you definitely want to get good at, though, is that
middle piece we did just after the meal break of understanding
the pipeline and how the pipeline works. Because if you can't
figure out how to get two commandlets to work together, you're
just not going to have a lot of fun. That's so very important.
So remember Don Jones has a great book on Learn Windows PowerShell
in a Month of Lunches. It's chapter 9. I know it sounds like
I'm trying to sell a book; I just want you to have more resource
information on working through that. And go out to the forums
on PowerShell.org and ask about that. Also the thing that really
changes, and I have to say, you know, understanding the pipeline...
>> Yep....
>> that made a huge difference for me.
When V2 shipped and remoting, that's what changed administration
for me. And it's changed it forever. The remoting, being able
to hit multiple machines, being able to do multiple things at
once, being able to put those into scripts...
>> Yep....
>> has really, really made a huge... a huge difference.
>> So that's the stuff everybody's, you know, partials run all
of our Web sites and all of our big Internet sites, and then
that's why, because they've got a gazillion of these things,
how am I going to do things.
>> How am I going to do things. And I think you guys have seen
today a great example that PowerShell, you can learn it, you've
learned a lot of it today, and......
>> oh, you know what I didn't tell them about?
>> What? What didn't you tell them?
>> Our sacred vow.
The sacred vow.
So... so here's the sacred vow, the whole story behind the sacred vow.
The sacred vow is basically the story that says, hey, you're
IT pros, your hair's on fire, the last thing in the world...
we know the last thing in the world you want to do is take your
time to go learn a new tool. And yet here I am and I'm sitting
here asking you to learn this new tool. And why? And the answer
is because it's going to help you. And there's a set of things
that you have to learn. You to learn the verbs, you have to learn
the syntax, you have to learn the pipeline. And you have to
learn how to do things, how to explore, et cetera. But my sacred
vow to you is that if you learn those things, I'm going to do
everything in my power to reuse those words, those concepts,
those techniques over and over and over and over again so that
your investment in learning is the best payback, the best investment
you ever made. Now, let me get concrete about what that means.
When we decided, hey, we need to support workflow, the original
design for workflow was this very unusual thing, oh, you know,
you got some weird syntax for workflow steps and workflow sequences
and all that. And I said guys, whack, you forgot our sacred vow.
Our sacred vow is they've already learned PowerShell. Use that
over and over and over again. So now when you... when we teach
you about workflow, what you're going to see is you just type...
instead of function foo you type workflow foo. And then you
write PowerShell. And the difference is that now it looks just
like PowerShell except it's got very different semantics.
It isn't run by the traditional PowerShell engine. We take that
PowerShell syntax and we transcode it into a Windows workflow
object graph and we give it to the windows workflow engine to
execute its execution engine. But you, your experience, looks
just like PowerShell, even though underneath the covers it's
very, very different. Why? Because of our sacred vow. You learn
this stuff and we're going to do it over and over and over again.
Use those techniques over and over and over again. You learn
how to manage exchange, you're going to be able to manage link.
Having learned those two things, you're going to be able to learn
how to manage Azure and SQL and all that because the sacred vow.
We take that super serious.
>> And I have to say, it's a great honor to sit here next to Jeffrey
Snover, and it's been a great honor to be able to talk with members
of the PowerShell team, because, guys, you got to realize, that
sacred vow, they've stuck to it. They've stuck to it over several...
the last five six years that I've been doing this. There's one
guarantee that I've always had, and that's if I'm going to take
the investment to learn this, they're not going to screw me on
the back end by suddenly ripping everything out, replacing it
and totally changing everything. Nope. I'm going to get commandlets,
I'm going to get parameters. I've got a scripting environment
that makes sense, that's stable, that's being moved forward.
It's always going to be improved, but I know exactly what to expect.
And I know what to expect when I go to active directory, to manage
exchange, to manage whatever. It's the same. And that experience
makes this initial investment a little painful at first, but
it will pay off and it will pay off for years and years and years.
And you've heard it from the architect, they are so totally committed
to that.
So little bit of information of how you get some more information.
So let me just... yeah, we're going to leave your guys's mistake
up on there, a very embarrassing thing that you did.
>> And I want to just put up a couple of things for you all.
First of all, you know that at the MVA, where you're at...
or, yeah, MVS, MVA stuff, we're going to have another presentation.
This is going to be on scripting and tool making.
Now, it's on August 1st, but if you're watching this as a video,
look for the next title, Scripting and Tool Making. So we're
going to do that. It's going to be awesome. It's going to be
totally awesome. A couple of other things. If you have a question,
please don't... the only mistake you're going to make if you
have a question is not ask it. So there are a couple of places
you can go to get an answer. Of course PowerShell.org. I think
I've said that like 15 times today. But, trust me, the community...
nobody gets paid for this. We're doing it because we actually
care and we want to help. Go ask a question; you'll get an answer.
We've all been through this. I also want to give you something
else, something that's kind of uncommon. I betcha you guys do this.
But every time I talk to a group of IT pros, something happens
that's kind of bizarre. I'll ask this question to a bunch of
IT pros: How many of you use Twitter? And everybody will go like this.
That's not the correct answer. Knock it off.
>> So... and I'm not saying go... go... I'm not saying set up
Twitter and start tweeting us what you had for lunch. As a matter
of fact, don't do that, please.
But you need to get a Twitter account, even if you just want
to look, because where you're going to find the things that are
going on is at a Twitter hashtag called hashtag PowerShell.
That's where you're going to hear him, you're going to hear the MVPs.
And I'm not saying that they're just talking about here's a cool command.
No, you're going to see pointers to here's how I solved this
exchange problem, here's how I solved this SCVMM issue.
Here's how I built this.
This is where the latest and greatest information is happening,
so get on Twitter. And while you're out there on Twitter following
the PowerShell stuff,
there's always @jsnover.
That's him.
>> Show them how to... do they know how to use Twitter?
>> Show what?
>> Bring up IE.
>> You want me to bring up the Twitter?
>> The Twitter, yeah.
>> Well, now, I'm just... the Twitter. And Twitter. I don't
know if I can use it this way.
>> Go ahead.
>> You're going to have to help me. Because this is actually...
>> How hard can it be?
>> Well, I have to sign in.
>> Don't you know how to do that?
>> Well, okay. You want me to sign in? Really?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Don't laugh at my sign-in.
It is what it is, guys. It just is what it is.
>> Oops, I think I did the password wrong. Let me... let me...
oh, wait a minute. I'm signing into my Twitter. You're going
to see all the stuff that I follow.
>> Well, just...
>> Oh, wait a minute. Oh, for crying out loud. Why won't it let
me in? Oh, wait a minute.
>> How hard can it be? How hard can it be?
>> Oh, wait a minute. Wait a minute. I know. I know. I know.
>> Oh, my lord.
>> I know. This is... I don't... this isn't how I get to it.
Oh, and now it's making me type in all the device stuff.
Are you kidding me, guys?
>> What? How hard can it be? Here, switch to mine.
>> Switch to his. I think his probably works.
Oh, there you go.
>> Did you finally get it?
>> No. We're looking at yours.
>> There's mine.
>> There's... there's... there's... let's see. Let me see if
I can finally get in. KS... what is that, a W? I hate these things.
EBA...
>> You're missing it.
>> What am I missing? Had a turkey sandwich for lunch.
>> Never mind.
>> That's... that's... I can't get signed into mine.
>> Twitter's awesome. Yeah.
>> So Twitter's awesome. So you're going to want to follow...
>> So here's the thing. Even if you can't get ahold of Twitter,
like obviously can't even use Twitter, but can use PowerShell.
So clearly PowerShell...
>> Did you guys see the problem I had with the Internet today
and he had to teach me... what was it is, the host file?
[Laughter]
>> NC hosts. Exactly.
>> NC hosts.
>> So if you can't use Twitter, it doesn't mean you can't use PowerShell.
>> That's right. That's right. So use PowerShell. So, ladies
and gentlemen, on behalf of the folks at MVA and of myself, I'd
like to thank you for attending this full-day session. And I
would really, sir, like to thank you...
>> Oh....
>> for spending the entire day. It's been such a great fun.
>> It's been a blast.
>> Had a great time with you.
>> I had a great time with you.
>> Don't you guys forget... remember, fill out those polls.
We really do... Microsoft really pays attention to that stuff.
You know, I know everywhere you go they're like, oh, yeah, fill
out the poll. No, no, no. We pay attention to that stuff.
If I get a bad mark, they'll fire me, so please, please, please...
>> Just saying. Just saying. Fill out the poll.
>> It's been a true honor to be able to...
>> [Inaudible] Yeah, exactly. It's been a true honor to have the
actual architect, Distinguished Engineer Jeffrey Snover, be able
to sit down and talk with us about PowerShell. God knows I've
learned a lot, and now I have to go and study because now I've
learned more and I have to study. Thank you sir. This has been wonderful.
Thanks a lot.
>> Yeah. Great.
>> Thanks a lot, guys, and thanks for joining us. We're going
to see you at the next one, scripting and tool making.