[Music]
>> So when we're doing remoting... >> Yes.
>> And remember, invoke command, we're now going to use the alias
ICM for this, just to abbreviate things.
We're actually starting a remote PowerShell session.
>> Yeah.
>> Like you said.
We're feeding it a command.
Then we're closing that PowerShell session and leaving?
>> Right. So we start a TCP connection.
>> TCP.
>> We start a process.
>> Process.
>> We load the CLR. We load PowerShell. We initialize PowerShell.
We run all your profiles. There can be up to four profiles.
>> There you go.
>> We run those, and when those are all ready, then we take the
code, we execute it, and we throw all that away.
>> And then we throw everything away. So this is important.
When you're using remoting, we're going to connect to that box.
We're going to start all this stuff up. We're going to climb
up this mountain. We're going to give it your little tiny code,
do that, and then we have to tear all this down and walk away.
You can imagine that, if you're going to do a lot of invoke commands
in a row, that's not very efficient. So there's a way we can
make this more efficient, and I want to demonstrate it using
variables first, and then we'll take a look at some cool things
we can do with this. So watch, guys. I'm going to go to...
I'm just going to do this on DC first. I'm going to show you
what's happening. I'm going to do dollar sign var equals 2.
I'm going to go to the domain controller. I'm going to set up
PowerShell, I'm going to set a variable,
and I'm going to destroy PowerShell. So what happens is, if
I now ask it what's that variable on output...
on DC,
well, is anybody shocked that it's not there anymore? When the
console dies, everything dies. This is why PowerShell has to
run all the time. So nothing dies. But, no, when the console
dies, when that execute... when PowerShell exe on that other
side dies, everything dies with it. What I'd really like to
do is I'd like to be able to connect to the machine, go through,
start all this up, and leave it up.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I'm in.
>> You in for this?
>> Yeah, we call those things sessions.
>> Sessions.
>> You'd like to create a PowerShell session.
>> We're going to create a power... so watch. Let's create the
PowerShell session. So what I'm going to do, I'm going to set
this equal to a variable called sessions.
Equals new PS session.
I'm going to specify the computer, and right now I'm just going
to keep it real simple. I'm just going to use DC right now.
So what happens is I've created a session that's going to keep
PowerShell running on that remote machine. Now, I'm only doing
it to one machine right now, but it's on that remote machine.
Just to show you. We have a Cmdlet for get PS session. It will
show you what sessions you have. Notice, out of session to that
computer, it's open, life is good. What I can do now is start
using invoke command, and instead of using dash computer name,
I can specify that I want to use this session. So ICM...
we're going to do the exact same example again. So let me just
go ahead and clear the screen here. I'm going to do ICM.
Computer... no, not computer.
>> It's just a dollar sign.
>> Yeah, dollar sign session. Of course, I had to make it long
and hard to type. But I'm going to do the same thing, var equals 2.
And this time I'm going to go back and check on it.
Whoo, whoo.
>> Fast, fast, fast.
>> And this now gives us a lot of power to do a lot of really,
really cool things. So we can keep this session open, and we
can continuously fire things. We can reference variables that
we have open. This is going to make our lives a lot easier.
>> Happy, happy, happy.
>> Can I show them the difference in time?
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> Do measure... do you know measure command?
>> Measure command, yeah.
>> Do measure command on... just invoke command minus command
name, computer name.
>> Oh, you want to see the difference in time?
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, I wonder if that will... do you think it's going to be
apparent here? Computer name DC.
>> Yeah, get process.
>> Oh, get process. Yeah, that's good. Get process.
>> No, no, no, you wrap that whole thing in a script block and
put measure command at the beginning.
>> Wait.
>> Measure.
>> Command.
See?
>> So what's happening here is that the measure command is going
to take what we're running, and you can see what it's doing.
It's showing us how long this is taking.
>> Yeah.
>> I love ticks. But, anyways, milliseconds. 886 milliseconds.
>> Now do it with a session.
>> So let's do the same thing. So I'm just going to do measure command.
>> Just do up arrow, man.
>> Yeah, what... me and my up arrows.
>> Down one, there. Now change computer name DC. Change it to...
>> Okay, let's do that.
>> It says 886.
>> 886 to session dollar sign sessions, boom.
>> Five. Probably even faster but...
>> It's going to be actually even faster. Here's the thing.
It is faster doing it this way, but now when it's really going
to pay off being faster, phew, want to see something cool?
>> Yeah.
>> I'm going to draw.
>> Okay.
>> Watch. This is when sessions and remoting change your world.
So I want to prove to you that I'm not lying to you. First of
all, I'm going to kill everything. So you know that I'm not...
I'm going to kill the Shell, boink, and you bring up a new one.
That way you know I have a clean shell, and I'm not hiding...
no rabbits up sleeves or anything like that. Here we go.
Quick demonstration, but see if you catch what's going to happen here.
First of all, $servers equals...
>> Ooh.
>> Let's do S1 and S2.
So you guys know when $servers...
well, you know. Cool.
Watch. Show you that I'm not cheating. Nothing's being hidden here.
Start... let me do it this way.
$servers. Oh, typed.
>> Do you need some coffee?
>> Oh, yeah.
$servers and watch, watch. I'm going to use a Cmdlet called for
each, and what's this going to let me do is iterate through each
one of those coming across the pipeline. You know it's in $servers.
I've got two computer names.
I want to grab the current one across the pipeline and use it
in a special way. So what I'm going to do is start http...
oops. Start iexplore
http dollar sign underscore. Here's what I'm going to do.
Start an iexplore for each one of these and go to the servers
and show that there's no websites there. There's no default pages.
It's just going to come up and give me an error. This can't
be displayed.
So that's not that big of a deal, but I just want you to see
that I'm not hiding anything. So now let's do a session, and
let's do something cool.
Session.
>> Just type dollar sign S.
>> You're right. I type in way too much. Equals new PS session.
And what I want to do it too is $servers.
Boom, I'm going to get my sessions to these remote boxes.
Now, just so that you see I'm not cheating.
>> Multiple sessions.
>> There's my sessions. Multiple sessions. You know what I want
to do? And this is an actual business problem I've had several times.
Did I mention I was a web guy? I just... anyways, so here's
the business problem. I need to deploy...
actually, I had a friend call me up on the phone. I need to
deploy a web...
50-server website load balanced, and I need to copy the website
out from the developers, and we have three months to do it.
Can PowerShell help me with any of this?
Seriously, dude? When's the last time you had a vacation?
Well, this conversation went on for a while, me talking about
vacations, and him talking about this three month long project.
Let's do it. So with the session that we have right now...
>> Dude, we don't have three months.
>> What's that?
>> We only have like a couple of hours. We don't have three months.
>> Okay, okay, okay, so you want to challenge me. Okay, fine.
Okay, fine. So invoke command on the session that I just made,
which now is shorter, dollar sign S. Here's what I want to do.
Install Windows feature, web dash server. Now, I know, guys,
this isn't going to be all that cool and tricky, but here's the thing.
For web services, every component that you need of the web service,
you can just put in comma and specify every single one.
This doesn't have to be web service. This could be Hyper-V servers.
This could be whatever it is you need deployed. I want you to
see it's happening on...
ooh. We're over here ooh.
Pretend that the sessions for dollar sign S was 50 servers, 1,000 servers.
Now take a look. It comes up, and as it shows me as it's finishing
the installation on those remote boxes, and I'm maintaining this session.
Yeah, it's still doing ooh.
>> It's not serial. It does it in parallel.
>> Yeah, it does it in parallel. So what happens is it's not going
to this server and going to this... it's going, dudes, install.
Come on. We're talking less than four minutes, I've just deployed
as many web servers as I want. But wait, we're not done.
Watch, there's more. Watch. I'm just going to up arrow for once
and go back to this command. Watch.
>> Oh.
>> Oh, come on.
>> Yeah.
>> But wait, there's one more step. Guys, we've got to make our
own web page. [Singing]
>> Three months, baby.
>> We're going to make our own web page real quick just to prove
you can still do this. Yeah, just make this default htm, and
you say MVA and PowerShell rocks.
Going to save this. I want to deploy this.
I want to deploy this. So I'm going to $servers pipe.
For each one of those servers, I'm going to have it copy item...
God, I love, I love, I love the item commands to work with stuff
because we're going to take that default htm, and the coolest
thing about PowerShell Cmdlets is they give you more capabilities
than you've ever had before because the destination can be a UNC.
So I'm going to say back slash, back slash, dollar sign.
Remember, that's the current object. That will be those servers.
And I want it to go to their administrative share, and I want
it to go to inet pub.
This is where the default web page is stored. And let's
go up and run it again.
And lo and behold.
>> Aruba, Bahamas. We're going.
>> It's vacation time now. So in other words, in just a couple
of minutes, I've deployed out, in this case, a web server and
a website. It's a small demonstration, but the idea is this.
It changes how you think about administration.
>> Now it's, instead of sending guys out, going, go out there
and install this and install that and let me know when you're
done in three months. Now it's get somebody with a screwdriver
to rack these things. As soon as they're powered up, I'm going
to remote into these things, install what they need.
I'll probably script it so I never actually have to type these
four commands again.
Boom, it's done.
Now that I've got the script, if I need to add more, just add
some more. Just add some more. Totally awesome.
>> Or give it to me because I have a problem. You give it to
me, and I just do it. Like it might be more complex. I really
don't understand this web stuff. I can say, oh, I have this problem.
And you can say, hey, Jeffrey, here's the script I have.
And you look at it and say, boom, boom, boom, mine is what if,
do it. Off to Aruba.
>> Off to Aruba.
>> And the thing is that's the thing that people sort of don't
get until they get it, and that is the transformational effect
of these technologies, remoting, in particular. The fact that
all of a sudden you're able to do just phenomenal things, massive
things in a heartbeat, things that your boss is probably thinking,
I'm just not even going to ask because that's going to take so long.
We don't do things. And so you end up with this sort of static,
brittle, ossified...
excuse me. Ossified data processes and structures. All of a
sudden now, with these tools, you can become fast.
You can become flexible. You can become agile. You can do things
you never thought of doing before all because of the power of PowerShell.
It really is transformational.
>> It is transformational, and also, my CTO doesn't like the answer
it's going to take three months. He really likes it when I give
him the answer of it will be done within the hour. As a matter
of fact, it's done now. I'm just testing.
>> Yeah.
>> I mean, that's the whole point to this is that your management
totally changes.
>> Is or like that guy.
>> Not only are we in scale...
>> Or like that guy, I'll have it to you in the morning. I'm going home.
>> Yeah, I'm going home. That's the whole thing. Now, one other
thing in remoting I want to show you right now.
>> I think we're promoting like slacking off.
>> Slacking off, I know. Everybody's leaving.
There's one other super cool thing in remoting that I want to
show you before we get through the rest of scripting.
And I have to do it with a new console.
You know...
>> I don't.
>> I'm not going to be at this machine tomorrow.
>> Oh, oh.
>> And you know what, in fact, when I'm out on vacation and I'm
using PowerShell Web Access, who knows?
I'm going to be at some box.
The thing is that, guys, I've been using Active Directory Cmdlets.
I've been using all kinds of stuff from modules that are installed
from the remote server administration tools. You know, if I
want to manage Exchange, I need the remote server administration tools.
I am going to need to install the Exchange management tools.
And I do a lot of SCVMM stuff. I'm going to need to install,
oh, man, all the VMM management tools.
God, it's going to take me a couple hours to do that.
>> Oh.
>> And as soon as I go to a different machine...
>> Eh.
>> Eh. None of the Cmdlets. None of the modules will be there.
None of it exists.
So I'm going to show you what I think is absolutely the coolest
thing in the world. I use it constantly because on my box, I
don't install anything. I don't install the remote server administration
tools, the exchange tools, nothing. And here's the reason why.
I don't have to.
>> Put your seat belts on because this is freakish, freakishly
powerful, freakish.
>> This is the new world order because here's the deal. I don't
have time to be installing tools every time I sit down at a box.
And the other thing is, if I walk up to a server or something
like that, unh-unh, you're not going to be installing anything
on there. So you need a bunch of Cmdlets. I'm going to need
the Active Directory command... I don't know why I'm starting
to do it like this, but it's kind of like soul.
>> It's like watching Godfather.
>> Yeah. It's like watching Godfather.
>> Goodfellas.
>> I don't know what I'm doing.
>> Are you calling me funny? Are you saying I'm funny?
>> Funny? You're saying I got PowerShell and stick that in an SO.
Here we go. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to create a
session to the servers that have the Cmdlet that's I want.
Now think about this.
You really want the Cmdlets from the servers that naturally have them.
A domain controller has the Active Directory Cmdlets. An Exchange
2007 server has the Exchange 2007 Cmdlets. An Exchange 2010
server has the Exchange 2010 ones. I couldn't get all those
tools on my box if I wanted to but watch.
>> And you don't want to.
>> And you don't want to. So dollar sign S equals new PS session,
and in this, I'm going to... just going to hit a domain controller.
So I'm going to establish a session to this domain controller.
Import PS session.
Module. Guys, do you see what I'm doing?
There's a module on that remote server called Active Directory.
So I'm going to say give me that module, Active Directory.
Now, because I right now on this VM I do have the RSET tools,
I'm going to prefix it. So there's a prefix, and I'm going to
call it remote so you know it's coming from somewhere else.
Then we're going to ask Jeffrey to explain how this magical stuff works.
Watch. As soon as I do this...
oops, I forgot to give it the session.
>> Dollar sign S.
>> Darn, dollar sign S. I was going to do it all in one line,
and I screwed it all up. I forgot the session.
>> Oh, yeah, no, you can't. That's a string.
>> Oh, yeah. So let me do this. Dollar sign session. There we go.
>> Way back machine. You didn't see that. Click, click, click.
Men in Black.
>> Men in black, men in black. So module
session dollar sign S.
I don't know if you know what just happened right now but check
this out.
I wonder if I have any Cmdlets. Now, pretend that I had no Active
Directory Cmdlets. So what we're going to do is I wonder if I
have anything for remote. Remote, remote, remote. Ah, let's
do this, remote AD. That should work.
Dudes, dudettes, you see what's scrolling across my screen right now?
Looks and smells like I have all these Cmdlets I just asked for.
Look at all these Active Directory commands. See that's prefixed
with remote. So I have these Cmdlets... as a matter of fact,
I can do this. Watch, get remote AD computer filter... ooh.
>> Fitler?
>> It's his brother. Anyways, the star. Look, it ran.
Look, look, look.
I got these commands from a server. Nothing's installed.
How is this working? Explain to me how this is working because
this is like freaking me out right now.
>> It's magic, baby. Magic, magic, magic.
>> I love magic.
>> So here's the deal.
Let me show you this. So here we've been showing people get command...
sorry. Get help. Get help. Get process.
And that gives you this. But there's another thing, and it's
called get command. And people have often asked, well, what's
the difference between these two? Get help versus get command.
And the answer is that get command is more structural, programmatic information.
So watch this, dollar sign C. Hello. Oh, wrong one. Plus sign
C equals get command. Dollar sign C.parameters.
And now let's take a look at this parameter saying name.
Oh, sorry, name.
And look, we've got all the information, the name, its type,
et cetera.
And so what happens is when I go and I do that import, what I
do is I go to that remote machine. I load the module that you
asked for, and I do a get command on all the things, and I get
that data structure. And what I do is on this side, now on my
side, I go, and I take that information, and I recreate a set
of scripts with exactly the same signature.
And then the body of the function basically says, hey, when you
go do this, gather all that stuff up and run it over there using
invoke command.
>> So I don't actually have these Cmdlets on my machine. I have
like a proxy.
>> Yeah.
>> Or a shortcut.
>> Exactly.
>> That is saying, take all the information from the parameters
and then go run it on the source machine.
>> Exactly. So do this. Do... on your machine now, type get command.
>> Get command.
>> Get dash star AD computer.
>> Get dash star.
>> AD computer.
>> So look, notice, one, the get AD computer is a Cmdlet.
That Cmdlet is.NET code. But look at the function.
>> Yeah, what's going on there?
>> So now take a look and do this. Type parentheses, paren get
command, get remote AD
computer, end paren.definition.
>> Ooh, ooh, look at this.
>> Look at this. This was dynamically generated code.
>> Dynamically generated code on my side.
>> On your side.
>> That says grab these parameters.
>> So you know what, let me just say, in PowerShell version 2
was a pivotal technology. In PowerShell version 1, Cmdlets had
to be.NET.
In PowerShell version 2, we said Cmdlets could be .NET or PowerShell itself.
So now PowerShell scripts are full Cmdlets.
>> Which you're going to see in a little bit, guys.
>> Now, this was a transformational technology because what it
means is now all of a sudden you can write programs which generate
Cmdlets dynamically, and that's what we do here. That's what
that import PS session does. We go, and we get a data structure.
We have a program that dynamically generates a PowerShell script
that has exactly the same signature as the.NET Cmdlet on the
remote machine, has exactly the same signature. I gather up
all that information, and I then run it on the remote machine.
>> And I think what the... so to make sure the concept is good
is that we're, just like Jeffrey said, this is... it looks and
tastes and feels like the Cmdlets are here on my machine, but
they're not. They're functions that are going back and running
it on the remote machine. So think about this. Who's going to
be better at running get AD computer anyway, your box or the
domain controller. So first of all, that's going to be faster.
But you were telling me about this scenario, and I love this
scenario about the guy who had to do a migration from Exchange.
>> Yeah.
>> Of... I had to do a migration from Exchange 2007 to Exchange 2010.
You're not going to get those tools all installed on your box,
but you can import both sets of Cmdlets. Prefix one with 2007,
prefix another with 2010. Now you've got both sets of Cmdlets
all in the same place, and you can get the two products to work together.
>> Exactly.
>> I think that is.
>> It's doing the equivalent of like get... I'll just say v1
and v2. Get v1
user pipe to set v2 user.
>> Right.
>> And what's happening is he's on this box. He's getting the
users from this machine, and he's setting it on that machine.
This is the power of this stuff. Now all of a sudden... it used
to be integration was just painful, right? I've got to find all
this stuff? I've got to get it all in this box so it bloats the box.
I'm running out of disk space. Oh, wait, this guy updated something.
I've got to patch it. Oh, wait, they require different versions
of stuff, blah, blah, blah, just hideous, hideous, hideous.
And now the answer is, hey, dude, I'm sitting right here. I import
the stuff from there. I import the stuff. I import the stuff.
And I'm sitting here, and by the way, type, type, type.
Look, you get tab completion. Watch this, watch this.
>> So get remote, and look... well, here, let me do remote AD
so that we...
look, yeah. All the tab completion.
>> See all the tab completion.
>> You've got help, everything. And help will discover all of this.
So you've got full discoverability. You've got full help.
It looks and feels like it's here, but it's running in the best
place possible, which is on those machines.
>> Yeah, magic.
>> And I didn't have to install anything. Now, this is referred
to as implicit remoting, and you probably are going to want to
do this yourself. It's already in the slides. We'll also give
you some more referenced for the implicit remoting, and to be
honest, when I'm managing, I literally, this is what I'm doing.
I don't install anything on my local box because I'm not too
sure as a consultant what box I'm going to be on. So I'll just
implicitly remote the command I need when I need them.
>> You know what, we missed... here's the other thing that's so important.
When I imagine I'm going to go get this stuff from different
things, over here, I might need a different set of credentials
than over there.
>> Right.
>> So instead of having to type the credentials all the time,
you create the session with the set of credentials. You import
the Cmdlets, and those credentials are then used.
>> And, guys, there's a dash credential parameter on this.
So when you create the session, you use the credentials that
you want to use when you do the import of the modules.
Then it's... you're using those credentials and over and over
and over again so you don't have to keep track of all of that.
It really makes your life a lot easier and cuts down on all the
minutia and tools and all this kind of stuff.
>> Really encourage you guys to go try this, even if you do it locally.
Let me show you something. I'll just show you how to do it locally
because it's just so freaky.
Here, I just hit dollar sign S equals new session. And that
will connect to locally, right? Your local machine. And you
can do import PS session.
Dollar sign S, minus... and we'll just like do one command.
Minus command, get process, minus prefix.
Prefix, WOW.
So now all of a sudden, you've got get WOW process.
And it just works.
>> There you go.
>> So the point is just try it. Because you don't necessarily
have to have access to some remote machine with the main controllers
and all that stuff. You can do it on your local box.
But it is so freakishly cool, you just want to have fun with it.
Give it a try.
>> It's seriously going to solve a lot of business problems for
you going forward. Just grabbing the Cmdlets from the machines
that have them. You've got the correct versions of whatever product
you're working with. Implicit remoting is truly a God send for this.
Guys, we're going to take another ten-minute break, and we're
going to have our last session.
>> For today.
>> And it's going to be on... we're going to start scripting.
We're going to start seeing what the script looks like. So come
back and join us in ten minutes, and let's automate.
>> And in two weeks, we do the advanced one. Now, the advanced
one, we roll up our... they're already rolled up. We roll up
our sleeves, and we get into the scripting, the automation, et cetera.
>> The hard-core stuff. This is a taste I think you're going to
enjoy, and it will get you working and get you prepped for what
you need in two weeks. So see you in ten minutes.