[Music]
>> We're back. And I have to tell you,
now we're going to talk about one of
my most favorite things and you get to talk about.
And we're going to do this twice, guys. We're going to do kind
of a short section of this to get you started and then, we're
going to get into scripting, teaching about variables and stuff,
and then hit remoting this topic again with something called
sessions that will be outstanding. But, remoting: this changed
how I manage in scale when it comes to the entire Windows, the
products, the platform, everything. This, when it released with
Version 2, literally made me a hero overnight. So you have to
tell us about what were you trying to solve with this.
>> Sure.
>> What does this thing do? This is unbelievable stuff.
>> Yeah, so in PowerShell we have this idea... We talked a lot
about it in the past; we don't talk so much about it now I guess
because we already delivered it... this notion of universal
code execution, which is to say that you have code and sometimes
you want to run the code here.
Yeah, that's what we do. Everything we've been showing you today,
we bring up a console window and we type the code and the code
runs here. But actually it's a generalization; here is a generalization
or a specialization of anywhere. Like, sometimes I want to run
the code there and sometimes I want to run the code there and
sometimes I want to run the code on those machines.
And sometimes I want to run the code on those machines on myself
and sometimes I want to give a different set of credentials.
And sometimes I want to run it and get the results back immediately
and sometimes I want to run it and then get the results back later.
And sometimes I want to run it in a way that I can do anything
and sometimes I want to run it in an environment where, "No,
no, no, these and only these commands you can run," in secure environments.
And so there's this notion of this universal code execution model.
And, oh, by the way, sorry, the last one was sometimes I want
to run it and I'm going to run it for such a long time that I
might want to like shut down the machine and bring it back up
and have it continue to run.
>> Right, go somewhere else and maybe check on it or something.
>> Exactly. So this is the notion of the universal code execution model.
And remoting, of course, is intrinsic to that. Coupled with
that are notions of jobs...
Jobs are things that run in the background... and then workflow
which we added in PowerShell Version 3 which the idea that says,
hey, I'm going to run this and at any stage after any command
I can suspend things, shut down the machine, bring it back up
and continue from where I started.
>> See, this sounds awesome. Now what we had before is like with
the remote server administration tools, I have a graphical like
I can direct users in computers. It will connect to a domain
controller over DCOM using RPC, right?
>> Yes.
>> And there are a lot of challenges and problems with that: firewall
challenges, right...
>> Yes.
>> ...and all kinds of a mess. But what you guys created, though,
solves all those problems.
>> Exactly. So here's what we did: first, we wanted to solve all
of those problems. So http? Super important. Next was, we already
had a protocol that went over http, our standards-based management.
So you probably heard we talk a lot these days about standards-based management.
In fact, at TechEd's I'll show up and bring up a Linux box and
I'll show on a Linux box I can enumerate all the roles on a remote
Windows Server and then install roles on a remote Windows Server
from a Linux box. Just crazy stuff.
>> I saw you do that demonstration for the first time I think
it was like a year and a half ago and I just went, "Ahh!" >> You
head just explodes.
>> I know.
>> So this is because of this standards and WinRM or WS Management
Protocols; WinRM's are an implementation of that. And so for
PowerShell remoting we leverage WinRM and we added streaming
extensions to it. And that's how it works.
>> And WinRM is the service that you're going to see that's running
underneath all of that. As a matter of fact I've got a couple
of slides here and then, we'll talk some more about this.
If you take a look at the slide here as an overview of remoting,
basically what this comes down to is you can go and touch...
Just as Jeffrey went through the scenarios, using what you've
already been typing in at the console locally, you can pick that
up and now fire that at whatever it is you want to fire it at.
And it's over remoting which is going to give us a lot of cool characteristics.
It's going to be fast. It's going to be easy to cross firewalls
because we only have one port to deal with and we're dealing
with a secured port. So here's the idea: if your machines are
in a domain, this isn't going over just http plain text.
>> No.
>> It's getting all encrypted...
>> All encrypted.
>> ...with Kerberos.
>> Yeah.
>> And then, of course, if you're going across the Internet or
across firewalls and you want to put on SSL or if you even want
to do SSL internally, you can put on SSL if you want that full
encrypted tunnel.
>> Well let's be clear: we'll encrypt it twice.
>> We'll encrypt it twice at that point.
[Laughter]
If you really need it twice encrypted, we'll do it twice.
But here's the idea is that you're hitting whatever machines
you want securely and with what credentials you want and nobody
can read it. Nobody can use a protocol sniffer and sniff out
what's going on. So this is actually really cool stuff. You know,
enabling remoting is definitely one of these things that comes up.
First of all we just need to tell everybody that you have to
remoting on kinda, sorta, maybe.
Kinda, sorta, maybe because in prior versions, not Server 2012
but in prior versions, remoting had to be turned. And this can
actually kind of a hard conversation for some security people
to have or some admins to have with their security people in
that, "I'm going to turn on this really cool thing that lets
me do whatever I want to whenever I want." And the security guy
goes, "No." >> Yeah.
>> Which is exactly what they should say. But as soon as they
understand remoting and how it works all of a sudden it's like,
"Oh, well yeah, this is perfectly fine." >> Yes.
>> So there's this conversation that has to happen to get it turned on.
And if you guys take a look at the slide here, what I've done
is I've shown you a basic way to turn it on. I'm actually going
to demonstrate this on one of my machines here. But there's
a cmdlet that you can use called enable dash PS remoting.
Now if you want to walk around to all of your servers and type
enable PS remoting, knock yourself out. But there's a group
policy and I have it written down here for you; it's much easier
if you use the group policy to enable remoting. But here's the
deal: you have to turn this on. Let me say it again.
You have to turn this on.
We're going to show you all of these great features, but none
of it is going to work until you turn on remoting. It's not
necessarily and easy conversation. There's a free e-book on
PowerShell.org, secrets about remoting.
>> Yeah, great book.
>> Which will not only take you through every possible scenario
but is the information that your security guys need to know so
that they understand that it's secured and what ports it uses.
This has to be turned on.
It's not because I'm just saying it, it's because you're running
out of options now. A lot of the new administrative graphical
tools are made to use PowerShell and PowerShell remoting.
Server 2012 is a great example with the new server manager, right?
It's using all of these capabilities that are built in and if
you don't have it turned on, you can't manage anything with anything.
So you've got to get it turned on. And as a side note, Server
2012: it's turned on by default.
So it's going to get turned on.
>> Just to be clear on that one: so as you know, we are secure
by default and released by release. We continue to shut things
off by default and you have to turn them on.
In the course... This has been going on for quite a number of years.
It's been exactly, to my knowledge, one time where we went the
other direction, where we turned something on by default instead
of off by default. And that was?
>> It's got to be PowerShell remoting.
>> PowerShell remoting. That's right. So for Windows Server 2012
we turned on PowerShell remoting. It was a big issue. The security
guys are like, "What are you talking about? Maybe you didn't
get the memo, we're going the other direction." And it's like,
"Okay, well let's talk about that. Why is that?" And the answer
is of course, Windows Server 2012, right, it is a cloud operating system.
A cloud operating system says, "Hey, it's not about this server,
it's about these servers. I need to be able to manage things."
And, therefore, remoting of large numbers of systems is a critical
function; it is the core of a cloud OS. And so they said, "Okay.
Well, I'm willing to entertain that. That makes sense. But we've
got to be sure." And we said, "Okay, well let's walk through
it." And we showed them all of the things we had done. And actually
they've been involved all along.
And step by step by step we went and did the thread analysis,
and they were convinced, "Yeah, this is safe to do." And so when
you have that conversation with your security guys, you just
point to that, "In the history of this server, one time we switch
and turn things on by default, it is PowerShell remoting." So
go for it.
>> Yeah and I think that's a really great concept because Microsoft
is not going to turn on something that is an easy to use attack service.
It's just not going to happen.
>> Yeah, we put an extraordinary amount into the security of making
sure that this is going to be a secure environment. We've got
pen testers who have been evaluating the design, the code, etcetera.
Yeah, we spent a lot... Look, we started PowerShell after Bill
Gates' famous security...
>> Memo, yeah.
>> Right? And what started that security memo, what started that
whole boof-o-rama?
"I love you." >> I
love you, man.
>> .VBS >> Oh,
you're talking about that. I was just saying I love you, man.
Sorry.
>> Oh, that's special. Okay.
>> Okay.
>> I don't think there's anything wrong with that. No, it was
scripting had caused that big "I love you" mess, and so we knew
that scripting was going to be a key vector. So we just spent
a ton of time making sure we were secure, secure, secure.
>> So now that we've jumped up and down enough that you not only
have to turn this on but it's secured to have it turned on.
Get it turned on. Let's start to show you some of the cool things
that you can do. Now like I said, we're going to hit this topic
twice as we learn more and more about it. So this is all in
the slides but let me take you through here and as soon as I can...
There we go.
Well, maybe not quite.
>> I can do something.
>> I think you have control of my machine.
>> No.
>> No?
>> I gave it up.
>> Okay, my machine is just moving slow for a second. Oh, here
we go. Okay, so let me do something real quick and, Jeffrey,
please jump in. First of all I'm going to do a one-to-one connection.
And you'll see exactly... Watch, I'm just going to type enter...
It's a cmdlet...
PS session... PowerShell session... and I'm going to put in
a computer name that I want to go to. I'm just going to say
DC; it's one of the VM's that have running. Watch what happens
to my prompt here. Did you see what happened?
Guess where I'm sitting right now? Guess where I am right now?
I'm on the DC. I'm on the DC. You don't believe me? Watch, I'm
going to clean up this path a little bit. Watch. Host name
and I'll do IP config. That information is coming from the DC.
So I can actually do a one-to-one connection and I can trouble
shoot and I can manage a single system this way as if I was sitting
on there. As a matter of fact let me...
>> Think of this as a secured telnet.
>> A secured telnet. I love that. And let me show you why I think
that this is also so important that you just get used to managing servers.
When you just need to do one thing to one server, this is a great
way to do it. Get used to this. Have you guys seen Server 2012?
Let me exit out of this and let me just show you. I'm going
to go out to
my domain control and I'm going to show you Server 2012.
This is, to me, fascinating.
Welcome aboard.
>> Oh man, that is...
>> And by the way, what you guys did with the color scheme on
here is just awesome.
>> It is.
>> Yeah, the background, the color scheme. This is totally awesome.
>> It's XEN-like in its simplicity.
>> It's very XEN-like in its simplicity. Yep, you guys probably
figured out that this definitely... We used to refer to this
as the core installation; and, yeah, it was Server 2012.
This is now the default installation.
>> Yes.
>> And for a good reason: performance, security, all that kind
of stuff. So let me show you, you would be managing the server
that way anyways. And I don't want to screw this up so let me
get rid of him.
So doing that single session, that inter-PS session to a machine
that you want to do work on, it gives you that one-to-one connection
and you can now do whatever you want on that machine. But here's
the big one so let me exit this.
You guys have been watching all day long and you know you're
going to be doing a lot of good, hard work on stuff like this.
I want to do get-eventlog log name system,
and I'm just going to do newest 3. Now I could do entry type
and all this other stuff but I just want to keep it short and
simple because let me just show you. I'm going to take this
and I'm going to copy this.
What I can get to work here and what Jeffrey was saying is the
whole point is it'll work anywhere. So here's what I'm going
to: I'm going to invoke-command.
This is a remoting command.
When you use this dash computer name, it's using PowerShell remoting
not the old DCOM RPC stuff which is what a lot of the older cmdlets use.
So this one is using the good stuff. And then, whatever you
put in the squigglies is exactly what we're going to do. Whoops, sorry.
Wait a minute. Put in some computer names and I'm going to be
brave and risky.
Whatever you put in the squigglies is exactly what we're going
to do. And in this case, watch.
So over remoting...
Was that approval back there that we heard?
>> Woo-woo.
>> A knock or something?
I want you to get that what just happened is, is by using PowerShell
remoting I just hit three different systems all at the same time
and said, "Give me this information." I can now convert this.
I can put it to a file. I can put it to a web page, whatever
it is I want to do with it but I just used PowerShell remoting.
And, Jeffrey, this is actually so powerful that admins need to
be a little careful, right, because things like... I don't know.
>> Restart computer.
>> Yeah, that's a good one. Restart computer, all of a sudden
takes on a whole new dimension because whatever you fill that
with, that's what it's going to do. Dash computer name, I could
be grabbing the computers from Active Directory, a CSV file,
a text file.
>> You're making me nervous, man.
>> I know, at the moment I'm actually very nervous too. I need
to get rid of that so it doesn't actually...
>> Why don't you type minus what if.
[Laughter]
>> And so it's going to restart those machines. So this is a
one-to-many connection. Now, Jeffrey, one of the things that
comes up all the time is if I do get-service and I'll do name Bits.
How's this working? It's actually sending the commands to the
machine and then, how am I getting this data back?
>> Yeah, so literally what happens is we go and we create a connection
to that remote machine.
So there's a TCP connection. We then fire up a PowerShell connection.
We load .NET. We load PowerShell. We take that code and we squirt
it across the wire. We then execute it. We logged you in, use
your credentials to log you in. We then execute the code there.
Then, we get those objects and we serialize those objects.
We move them across the wire and then, we reconstitute them;
we deserialize them and emit them as though they happened here.
>> Okay. Okay, so let me see if I can get this straight because
you're going to have to explain the serialization stuff.
>> Yes.
>> But let me see if I can get this straight. So we're connecting
to these remote machines and we're actually starting a PowerShell
session on those machines and having the command run on those machines.
So it's not my computer working harder, it's those machines that
are doing the work.
>> Yep.
>> Now the serialization, you're squirting this stuff back. Serialize, deserialize?
[Sound] What does this mean?
>> Exactly. So what we do is we take the object and we transform
it into something that can be moved around and reconstructed anywhere.
>> Okay.
>> So concretely anywhere. Like, I'm over here... I go talk to
your machine and it's Windows talking .NET. And then, I can
bring it over here and it can be Linux. Now there is no .NET
on Linux so how is that going to work?
>> Right?
>> And so I've got to serialize it into something that can work anywhere.
Now imagine I go and I say, "Well, hey, I talked to Exchange
version whatever and I get the objects here, but I don't have
Exchange here." So how do I recreate Exchange objects?
>> Right?
>> Again, that's the problem. So what we do is we take these objects
and we turn them into essentially a property bag. Now it's just
a bag of properties. And then we take them... You know, the
properties have names and values and the values have types.
Now here's the trick: the types are not the infinite set of types there.
If you tried to do that it would never work. So what we do is
we render it down to a set of, I think, 26 or so types.
Which, you know, I put my badge on the table and I say, "I guarantee
that these will always work. If these don't work, fire me." >> Well,
there you go.
>> Forever. Forever. Because you know what?
An Exchange
mailbox, 30 years from now, probably going to change. But I
guarantee you this, a 64-bit integer isn't going to change...
>> Isn't going to change.
>> ...30 years from now.
>> Yeah.
>> So it's those types of things: integers, strings, int's, GUID's,
things like that.
>> Oh, okay, yeah. GUID's. Things that are...
>> Secure strings.
>> ...going to be the same.
>> Exactly. So then I take that property bag and I just turn it
into XML. I then bring it over here and then I reconstruct the
property bag.
By the way, let me correct something.
>> Sure.
>> Show your screen.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So you said that this was remoting. In fact, invoke
command is not remoting.
>> Oh, what is it?
>> Remote command is the way we do everything. Remember we have
this kind of underlying system...
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah.
>> And then, we've got...
>> Great definition.
>> ...syntactic sugar on top of it. So go remove the minus computer name.
>> So let's do this.
>> Well that whole DC 123.
DC, yeah. Get rid of that. Okay, and hit carriage return.
Okay, so that worked locally and that's the same as if you hadn't
typed invoke command and squiggle brackets. Or rather, say when
you just type get-service minus name Bits, we transform it into
this and then we run it.
>> And then we run it.
>> This is the universal code...
>> Universal code.
>> ...execution.
>> And this is what makes it so easy especially if you're an administrator
you work out what you want first then you can just put it in
the squigglies and it's going to work at the other side.
>> So from here, pipe that to get-member.
Okay, scroll up.
And what do we have?
>> Service controller...
>> No, look at the beginning. System.
>> System.
>> That's service process; that's service controller. Now add
a computer name to that line.
>> Oh, yeah. So let's do this. Let's have it go to dash... and S1.
>> DC1. Okay, S1. Yeah, whatever.
Now go up. Look at the beginning.
>> Deserialized.
>> It's deserialized. Ding, ding, ding, ding, ding. Now a deserialized
object is incredibly powerful but it's different. So if you
scroll up a bit.
>> Oh, I'm scrolled up all the way.
>> Did you do a clear?
You didn't clear.
>> No, I did a clear.
>> Don't do clear and do it again. Do the local command.
Notice... See these methods.
>> Right.
>> See the start and the stop method?
>> See the stop, yeah.
>> Okay, that's because it's a live object and you can do methods
on it. Go up to the deserialized one.
>> Yeah, it's...
>> Yeah, there's just one method. Two strings.
>> There's one method, two strings.
>> Exactly. Because the object itself is gone and what you have
is representation of the object. Now it turns out that that
is extraordinarily powerful. Now some people say, "Oh, well it
should be the same everywhere." No, no, no, no, my friends, it
should be. The point is that because we have this live
deserialized concept, what it means is that when I've over there
I'm able to take advantage of the remote. I'm able to take advantage
of the full richness of the object system. Be able to do everything
in a very light-weight way, very high performance, low latency
way and then, when I bring it over here I can still do a ton
of stuff but I can't do that. So the way we refer to this is
islands of optimization in a sea of interoperability.
>> Okay, islands of optimization in a sea...
>> Of interoperability.
>> Of interoperability. Which is to say it's poetic.
[Laughter] >> It's poetic.
>> So that means I can go to any of the machines and I can interoperate.
I'm guaranteed to do that. And then there are times, however,
when I'm doing all of the code on one machine that I can optimize.
I have the live objects, I can do things, etcetera. And that,
by the way is what allows us to do the layering GUI's on top
of PowerShell because we have these nice high speed, low latency activities.
If you tried to layer everything on top of a deserialized object,
you know, you've got a lot of recreating objects, a lot of inefficiency.
>> Right, right.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, guys, this is our first hit into remoting. So we did one-to-one.
We did one-to-many. Now we've got more remoting to do because
we're just getting started with the remoting, but now it's getting
to that time for us to... Oh, you know, before we get into scripting,
I just...
>> Oh no, we've got to show more here.
>> Yeah, I know. There's a problem I have.
This is cool but...
You know one of the problems I have?
>> I know a few of the problems you have.
[Laughter]
>> One of the things I run into is
wouldn't it be cool if...
You know, when I go on vacation I don't know about you but I
like to go to places with beaches.
>> Oh yeah. Oh yeah.
>> That have the little drinks with the little umbrellas in them.
When I'm sitting on the beach, the last thing that I'm going
to have is a laptop.
>> Yeah, right. Not so much.
>> I mean not cool. Not cool at all. But things still go wrong
back at the office. And so, I am going to have a phone.
>> Ah, I see where you're going.
>> You know, it'd be so cool if I could maybe have PowerShell
here and I could launch a script which we're going to be doing
this afternoon or I could type in these commands and I could
do all of this kind of cool stuff. It'd be so cool if I had
PowerShell here or on a tablet...
>> If only you had PowerShell Version 3.
>> If only you had PowerShell Version 3 and at least one
Server 2012 box. It could be a VM, but I want to show you something
kind cool.
>> Have you picked up on the fact that we're big fans of PowerShell
Version 3?
>> Yeah, were huge fans of PowerShell V3. So, guys, I want you
to watch something. I'm actually going to take you through...
This is kind of a cute review... not a cute review. I can't
believe I said the word cute. This is a review. Over what?
We started off with today discovering and utilizing cmdlets and
in this case using a feature that I just think is wickedly awesome.
So here's what I'm going to do. I'm going to enter a PS session
to a server I have out there called PWA. Now this server doesn't
really have anything on it. It's just a generic Server 2012 box.
Key is, 2012. It can be a VM somewhere but it's got to be 2012.
What I'm going to do is there's a cmdlet out there called get-WindowsFeature.
Get-WindowsFeature is part of the server manager module.
What it does is it lists for you all of your roles and features
for your server. And if there are X's in it...
>> Oooh.
>> Yeah, I know. Oooh, I love it. If there's an X, that means
it is installed. If there's not an X, it's not installed.
Well, I'm going to use this cmdlet to see
what features
are available for PowerShell. And in Server 2012 we have something
down here at the bottom called PowerShell Web Access. I'm about
to change the way...
>> The world as we know it.
>> And it's not me. The only thing that I'm changing is I'm showing
you how to set it up. You're the one that changed the world.
>> Well, the team. The team. The team.
>> So, yeah, the team. The team.
So it's called Windows PowerShell Web Access, and this is pretty cool.
So I want to install this. So we have this install Windows feature
cmdlet that'll let me install Windows
PowerShell Web Access.
I've used get-help. The install Windows feature will let me choose
whatever thing I want to install and away it goes. Now here's
what it's going to do.
>> Oooh.
>> Oooh. It's going to install IIS because this is going to be
a web thing. So it's going to install IIS. We have .NET 4.5
on here and it's Server 2012.
When it gets this installed, we'll also get a new module with
some additional cmdlets, six additional cmdlets. So what we're
going to do is use get-help to find them and then use them.
Because in like three steps, I'm going to have one of the coolest
features in the world turned on. So watch. I'm going to clear
my screen. This is just to let me know that I have my updates
turned off which it's a VM; right now it does. But it exited
with success. No restart needed.
Awesome. So clear my screen. And, guys, notice, I'm doing this
all on a different server, right?
>> How cool is that?
>> Yeah, I know. That's totally, wickedly cool. So I'm going
to do get-help.
>> This is not your dad's server.
>> This is not your daddy's server. I love that. So it's called
PowerShell Web Access so PSWA. A lot of us just refer to it as
PWA, PowerShell Web Access. But PSWA. And you're going to see
that there are six cmdlets. By looking at the verbs you could
probably figure out the first place I'm going to go is to install
a PowerShell Web Access application. Technically what's going
to happen is we're going to create a web application by default
off of the default web site when we installed IIS. Now we didn't
need to install it; that happened for us automatically. You can
alter these defaults but I'm just going to take the defaults
for right now.
Now install PWSA. And I'm going to...
You've got to use HTTPS for this because this is going to be
something that you hit from anywhere in the world back to your home.
So we're going to need HTTPS. You can't do this with HTTP.
Now and if you don't have a good certificate to put on your web
box right now, for testing purposes they have this option of
use a test certificate. Now my screen freaked out a little bit,
but use a test certificate. It's going to put on a temporary cert.
Just remember this is not the cert that you want when you go
to production. So what's going to happen is, is that it creates
in IIS terms an application pool for the web app, creates the
web app, points the web app to where the files are and we're
almost ready to go.
We just now have to tell it who's allowed to use this. Now this
is going to be one of those rare do as I say not as I do.
And let me tell you why because I'm going to do get-help again
on PSWA.
We need to create who's allowed to use this and what they're
allowed to go to when they use this.
So we need to add rules, and you're going to want to add granular
rules that make sense. In other words, is there a group of administrators
that you want to be able to have PowerShell Web Access and what
machines should they be allowed to get to or remote to when they
use this. You're going to want to keep control on this.
You're not going to want to do what I'm going to do just for
easy sake. So let me show you what you're looking for here.
So add
PSWA authorization rule. And let me just show you,
what computers do you want to be able to remote to? So you can
make this list. You can create it as a computer group. You also
have another parameter you're going to need is either by user
group or user name, who's allowed to use this. So you going
to want to fill out the user name, what computer and we're not
going to get a chance to do
different kinds of configurations but you can control through
different configurations what cmdlets a person is allowed to
use when they get there which is actually totally cool.
These three things, you need to specify.
>> Just to be clear, that's for things like, "Hey, I'm going to
let these people come into these machines and all they can do
is read-only operations." Like they can do gets but they can't
do sets. And then, this guy on these machines he can reboot the
machine, okay, but he can't read data things like that.
>> And that's a really important point: these users, I've got
administrators that have full capabilities but I've got a guy
who is allowed to reset passwords when we gets there, that kind
of stuff that you can control. Don't do what I'm about to do
in real life. If you're just testing out a VM, that's fine.
But what I'm going to do is for those three parameters, I'm going
to do star, star, star.
[Laughter]
Yeah, I know that means everybody can do everything to everybody
and it's just,
yeah, not cool. But for demonstration purposes...
>> Summer of love.
>> The summer of love. At this point I installed the feature,
I installed the web app and I have not created a rule.
>> Anarchy.
>> Anarchy. This is so freaky cool, guys.
>> Yeah.
>> Let me exit out of that machine. This is so freaky cool that
I'm going to... This is start process. I'm going to use start
and I'm going to start iexplore with HTTPS and I'm going to go
to that PowerShell Web Access box, the box I just set up,
PWA, and it's going to do the default web site. And there's
a web application underneath the default called PSWA. You can
of course alter all of this to make it cleaner, but watch what happens.
Secured site. As a matter of fact, let me make this just a little
bit zoomier.
>> Zoomier.
>> Zoomier. So this is the temporary certificate. Remember in
real life when you go to production, you're going to replace this.
Continue to web site.
It's going to come up; it's going to ask me. Oh, lookie.
It's going to ask for some credentials. So let's do this.
>> Doesn't it look like Outlook web access?
>> Yeah, we need to talk about that.
So here I'm going to put in my credentials.
And what computer do I want to remote to and work with?
Well, let's go mess with the domain controller; I feel kind of
froggy today.
Get it.
>> Oh, do a host name. Do a host name. Show them where we are.
>> Oh, this is so cool. It's PowerShell through a browser.
It's PowerShell through... You made PowerShell work through...
But, guys, gals...
>> On the beach.
>> On the beach through any browser.
>> Any.
>> It's funny that
it can be Safari. It can be IE. It can be Chrome. It can be
on any device, a Microsoft device, a non-Microsoft device, your
phone, your tablet, your laptop, anywhere in the world, you've
got PowerShell. And I want to point out that not all of these
things have tab buttons when you use them.
But, look, I'll just even type a get-serve...
Lookie, they gave you a tab completion button.
I mean, come on. They thought this through. This is so totally awesome.
Now a lot of you right now are going, "Wait a minute. Wait a minute.
Wait a minute. Wait a minute. Wait a minute. What about security?"
Stop it. It's just like getting your e-mail. It's the same thing
as getting your e-mail. If you have Exchange, you've got a CAS-Role
out there probably in your middle tier or protected by Threat
Management Gateway, whatever you have, it's the same thing.
You can put the box right next to it. It's the same thing.
So everybody says, "Well, this is going to be dangerous." No
more dangerous than you checking your e-mail. It's over HTTPS.
You control who has access to this. You can even control what
cmdlets they can run.
This is one of the best tools. And for a guy like me that's traveling
all over the place,
I don't have a laptop necessarily with VPN to my network all
the time. Sometimes the only thing I have is the tablet in my
hand and I can run scripts... Which we need to do scripts...
and I can have access to PowerShell and remote to any box that
I want to remote to.
>> Dude, you've undersold it.
[Laughter]
>> I've sold it.
>> Undersold it.
>> I've undersold it?
>> The security. Yeah, absolutely. No, this is more secure than that.
Okay, why? So let's see what we're comparing ourselves against.
So there you are and you've got your laptop and you connect to
your domain controller versus you're on your phone or this device
or that device. And you go
HTTPS to a browser or to a web site that then goes and talks
to the domain controller, okay? Now on that machine, that web
server, you're not setting that up so that people are surfing
the net, that web server that you go to. On your laptop you're
off there surfing your net. You're at this new site, that new
site, maybe some dodgy sites.
>> Dodgy sites?
>> Yeah. You're reading your e-mail and people are saying, "Oh,
click here for something wonderful." >> Yeah.
>> And so the risk of using that same box to manage your domain
controller is...
>> Oh, yeah.
>> ...is pretty dodgy.
>> And so that's why the professional sites, they set these things
up called Jump Boxes. What they said is, "Okay, look, take your
dodgy device, whatever, and then you go to this machine." Now
this environment is safe, safe, safe. You get to do one thing
on this environment and that is go to these other environments.
>> And, you know, I think that that is such a great description
because a lot of you guys probably have... you might refer to
them as Bastion boxes.
>> Bastion servers, yeah.
>> Bastion servers where that's the whole point is that my laptop
might be the wrong tool to be managing Active Directory with
because of all of the weird things on it. But this is a controlled
server, a controlled point that I'm going to that isn't going
to have all the garbage and viruses and worms and crap on it.
And this becomes your Bastion point or your Bastion server.
This is awesome. This is a huge time saver, anywhere in the world.
And this is why... I heard this from Microsoft I think it was
in the year 2001, "We want to get to a place to where we can
be anywhere, anytime on any device," I think was the phrase.
And when this feature came out it was, "I can do PowerShell anywhere,
anytime, any device. You win." So awesome feature. Before we
wrap up remoting... Now we're going to do sessions in a little bit.
>> Okay. I think there was a key point we didn't nail. You got
the remoting, man.
>> What would you like to do? Let's leave this page.
>> Yeah. Okay, so go back to where you did the get-event log.
>> Okay. So you just want the get-event log?
>> Invoke command.
>> Yeah, on the three...
>> Okay, invoke command.
>> ...machines. Oh, you're going to do it all over. Computer name.
Oh, wait. If you want, you can just type CN. But anyway, that's fine.
Get-event log.
>> So, yeah. Get-event log.
Log name, let's do system.
Notice tab completion is working in the squigglies, guys.
Let's do newest three.
>> Yeah, good. Carriage return.
Okay, so here's the question: why did we return objects?
Like that looks like text to me and that looks like what I wanted.
Why don't you just do that? And the answer is because it's objects
and objects are awesome. So now what you can do is you can take
that and do... Oh. Go back. Just run it.
>> All right.
>> I need that.
>> Just run it. Okay.
>> Because I can't run this. Okay, so now what you can do is you
can say pipe to sort time. See these aren't sorted by time.
So you get three...
>> So sort it by time.
>> ...from this guy and then three from this guy and three from
those guys. Then say select... oh, sorry, format table.
>> Format table.
>> Let's just say time and message.
>> Property time and message.
Oh we need to do time...
>> Time written?
>> Yeah, time written so let's do time written.
Oops and I need to actually write it in here. You guys get the
idea but let me just get the...
>> And then, maybe it's auto .
>> Oh, this is getting better. And then, with the format commands,
guys, the format commands are wonderful. You should take a look
at them. Format table is one of my favorite ones because it has
auto size.
>> Is that crazy?
>> That is totally crazy. So looking at that one-liner.
What we're bring back... And this is a great thing... is that
we can then continue the pipeline and sort and select and still
work with this.
>> Exactly. That's why the power of objects is so important because
when you and do this stuff, it's not about text. It's about
give me the objects. And now all of a sudden when I'm over there
and I'm doing stuff, I can manipulate the objects there.
And that's great. But when I do remoting what I can do is I can
the objects from a very large set of machines, bring them here
and operate against the objects. So imagine... You say, oh,
I got somebody and I need to give them a share. You can go out
to all of your file servers, get the disk space from all of your
file servers as a collection of objects, sort it by free space
and then, you can say, "Give me the top three." And then, you
can look at those and say, "Yeah, that's the one I want." Imagine
how else you'd do it. You go to this one, find it, write it down.
You go to that one and write it down. You go to that one and...
>> How many of you guys are just still sending people out to do that?
>> Go check that file server and see how much disk space it is.
Put it into the spreadsheet so we can keep track of this as opposed to...
And there's several ways to do it, what he's talking about, but
as opposed to...
Let's just use, what is it, get-volume, right? Is one of the
new commands?
>> Get-disks.
>> I think get-volume will give you free space and size.
>> Okay. Look. We're going to find out in a minute. Oh, size
remaining and size.
>> Ooh, ooh. Yeah, yeah. Do it. Do it. Do it. Do it. Do it.
Do it. Do it.
>> Do it. Do it. Do it. So let's do... What do you want to do?
>> Invoke command.
>> And we'll do it to the...
>> By the way, can we show them the short way?
>> Yeah, and then...
>> This is time. Here's the short way.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, ICM.
>> ICM.
>> And then the names. Comp...
>> No, just CN.
>> Or just do the names, yeah, because it's positional. So DC,
S1, S2.
>> That's the short way.
>> And we want to do...
>> Get-volume.
>> ...let's see, get-volume.
>> And pipe it to sort size remaining.
>> Get-volume sort size...
I can't spell anymore. It's been a long day... sort size remaining.
Let's just try that and see what we get. Oh god, look.
Look, look, look. Size remaining...
>> No, wait. Wait, wait. Now here's the thing. Go back up.
Scroll up.
>> Scroll up. Scroll up.
Okay, notice how the formatting... No, I want to show the previous text.
>> Oh, the previous one. Okay.
>> So notice here, it just shows you drive letter, da, da, da,
to size. But now you go scroll down, notice we have PS computer name.
>> Yay.
>> When the objects come back we add properties to it. And we
add, "Where did this thing come from?" So when I do this sort
and then we go down to the bottom, I can see, okay, there's my volume.
But where did that volume come from? And the answer is S2.
>> That's right. So, guys...
>> Party on my friends.
>> Here's the thing: that cmdlet you can just say just show me
the C drive. You can sort and filter this out more where I just
want to see the computer name and size remaining and just get
a nice, short, terse list then export to CSV. You got your report
done and you did it on as many computers as you wanted to in seconds.
>> Oh, should we show them select last?
Yeah, show that.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> So like if I had done this to like lots of machines and they
were file servicing lots of stuff on it, this would be pretty big.
And you don't want to mess with that. So what you do is you
say select minus last.
Let's pick the last three.
>> And what it'll do is give you the last three, just exactly
what you think it would do.
>> Boom.
>> Boom. And there's the last three.
>> PowerShell rocks.
>> PowerShell so rocks. We have first; we have last. There are
all kinds of ways. This is the importance of taking a look at...
>> Skip.
>> ...those help files. Skip, exactly. So make sure you look
inside these help files because you can do it. It's not something,
"Well I can't figure out how to do it." You don't need bizarre
long links of code; you need to look at the help files.
They really thought this stuff through.
>> And if you get stuck, PowerShell.org...
>> .org.
>> ...forums.
>> And ask on the forum.
>> Yeah, lots of really helpful people out there. And just as
a side note, it's fascinating how strong the PowerShell community is.
>> It is, yeah.
>> You guys have noticed that this is not necessarily the easiest
tool in the world for you to learn. It's the most powerful one
in your toolbox but it's not an easy tool to learn because you're
just staring at a prompt, "And now what do I do?" We've all gone
through this, and so the PowerShell community is so strong; they
want to help you so avail yourself of those resources. And I'll
give you some more here a little bit.
>> Yeah, can I riff on that a second?
>> Yeah.
>> So here's the thing: we found as we were rolling out PowerShell
that the community just flourished and it's like wow. And people
are having a blast. Now here's the interesting thing, it turns
out that this, this like hurts the community. No, seriously.
It hurts the community. Why? And we noticed this because as some
point we were putting things together and then, we were like,
"Hey, did you see what Bruce did?" No, what did Bruce do?
We all run into Bruce's office and he shows what he does.
And it's like, "Oh man, that's awesome. Can you send that to
me?" He sends it to me and I'm doing it. And then, I change it.
And they're like, "Oh, Joe, check out what Jeffrey did." And
everybody comes running. And we were having a blast with this.
And we talked about this a little last night, we said, "Boy,
we're really having fun here." And computers always used to be fun.
And then for some point they stopped being fun and it just seemed
like it was a job.
>> It became mundane.
>> And I think it was because of this damn thing, the mouse.
And so here's the idea: I never, never, never say, "Hey come
one, guys, did you check to see the way Jason was clicking that mouse?
My god, you are such a clever guy. Did you see the snap on that
thing?" >> See,
I love you, man, because I work on my mouse moves.
>> Well, no that's the point. So when I see program, when you
script and you write together this command line, I see how you
think and I'm able to say, "Wow, that's really clever.
That's really neat." Then I say, "Oh, can I have that?" >> Right.
>> And you give it to me and all of a sudden you've helped me.
Like say you're a god at clicking that mouse, right? How can
you help me? Like, step back and be impressed, I guess.
>> Nice clicking.
>> You can't help me. But with a script you can help me. And I
can take it and I modify it and it meets my needs. And I look
great to my boss. And now all of a sudden, you know what, two
things: one is you feel good because you helped me. Two, I have
a debt of gratitude to you. I mean, thank you very much.
That's very awesome. And I'll buy you a beer or something like
that, and also I say, "Hey, you know what, I should help other
people too." So really you should help other people. First, be
aware there are lots of people in the community out there more
than willing to help. You should not be suffering in silence.
No, no, no if you're confused or anything, I guarantee you nobody
is going to be... you should not be embarrassed by any of your questions.
People aren't going to make fun of you. That's not going to happen.
The barrier for you asking a question should be extraordinarily low.
Just ask the question in a form, in Twitter. Twitter is a very
useful place as well. Just ask that question. People will help you.
And it turns out and then you should participate. You should
say, "Hey, I found this clever way to do things." You should
blog things. And here's the great thing, right, so you might
now I've been doing this PowerShell things for a little while.
I blog things. I blog things and say, "Oh, here's what I do."
And people will say, "Geez, why do you do it that way? Why didn't
you do it this way?" And it's like, "I didn't know you could
do it that way." And so the community is teaching me how to do things.
Honestly, it's just a wonderful thing.
>> And I have to say it's truly amazing. And remember when computers
were fun when it wasn't, "I need to reset a bunch passwords,"
and you just sat there and went like this....
>> Click, click, click, click.
>> Where now you're actually going, "Oh, I'm going to figure out
how to reset these passwords. Or I'm going to figure out how
to do X, Y, Z." Awesome.
And now I'm going to automate it so I never have to do it again.
But it was fun figuring out the problem. It used to be fun solving
the problem. And PowerShell has brought that back, and the community
is really strong with that. Folks, so here's what we're going
to do. Is let me show the... Just to let you know that all of
this stuff we did in remoting is in the slides. And I'm just
going to go through these real quick. But it's not the end yet
of remoting; we've got some more stuff to do but we want to start
some automation and some scripting to come up. And so we're
going to kind of get started on this before we take a break.
So if you have questions or comments, please make sure you're
jumping out there. And we're going to come back to remoting in
just a second. But before we take a break, let's get started
on this concept of automation. And to do that, we need to start
to talk about things like security because we're going to start
about scripting now. And so we're going to take the commands
that you're building as one-liners and so forth, and we're going
to take those commands and now automate them by putting them
into a script and just telling the script to run them for us.
No major deal yet. It's pretty straightforward. But to run a
script requires some special security. So we're going to talk
about security. We're going to talk about variables, a place
to store your stuff. Maybe a little bit with quotes and then,
we'll start getting into the automation. So the first thing off...
And by the way, that's a picture of me right there, the big guy.
>> Ooh.
>> On the next screen, usually people say that's the picture of
me but .
>> I see.
>> Oh no. The guys in the back are going, "Yep, that's it." So
PowerShell is secured by default several different ways.
Now we had some problems in the past with... Like VB script,
you double-click on it and it runs.
>> Oh god, yeah.
>> Talk a little bit about what PowerShell does for us.
>> Yeah, so okay again remember it is secure by default. We did
this: secure, secure, secure. So what happened if you weren't
around then, people came in one morning...
>> Oh god, yeah.
>> ...and they got their mail, "I love you." And they're like,
"Oh, I feel special. I've got a secret admirer." And even the
people like, "I bet that's not true, but it might be." >> That's
right. So, "I want to find out." >> "I
want to find out who loves me." Click, click. And then it would run.
You click and this thing would run. And guess what? Bad things happened.
>> Bad things happened.
>> Anybody who's like giving you something free or promising to
grow or shrink your body parts just with money, it just doesn't work.
And so too if somebody sends you love, don't click on that stuff.
Anyway, so with PowerShell somebody sends you that and you double-click
on it, it brings up in the editor. It doesn't run it.
>> It doesn't run it.
>> That is the key.
>> So let me do a quick demonstration of that. Let's just make
a really quick script. And, guys, it'll get cooler than this
but I'm going to make a really quick script. And I've been doing
this get-service Bits all morning; I'm getting sick and tired
of typing this in. And I'm going to make sure that it works.
It works. I'm going to take this right now and I'm going to copy it.
And I'm going to start up Notepad and I'm going... Yeah, we're
using Notepad right now. Don't worry, we're going to get to the ISE.
I'm going to paste it in there. File, save as. And here's the
magic to making a script... Well, let me put it on my desktop
so we can see it... is what do you want to call this script?
Let's call it...
>> I love you.
>> ...I love you. I love you. And let's .PS1. PS1. And I don't
actually want to put it on my desktop.
>> No.
>> I'm going to put it under my scripts folder here so I can get
to it. And wait a minute, there's a scripts folder right there.
Iloveyou.PS1.
>> You've got to get rid of the text.
>> I got to... Oh.
>> Yeah. All files, right there.
>> All files. And save.
>> Stick with me, guy, I'll help you out.
>> You're the man. So I've got a script. What I want you to see
is, yes, I'm going to show you this graphically first because
I want you to see what Jeffrey just said. I'm going to go out here.
And if somebody were to send this to me, Iloveyou.PS1, and I'm
going to double-click it. See? Brings it up in Notepad or whatever
editor you have set for it....
>> They didn't love you.
>> They what?
>> They didn't actually love me. It didn't execute my script.
Now this is a good thing for so many reasons as you guys already know.
You don't want scripts to automatically execute. But I want
to bring something up: a lot of the security that we're going
to be talking about in the next thing which is execution policy
which we're going to do before we go on break, I need to tell
you that this security is designed to take an unintentional user
to stop them from doing unintentionally malicious things.
In other words, I want you to think about I downloaded a script,
I double-click on it; I didn't want it to run. I wanted to look
at it.
This helps you.
Now if you are a power-user that wants to be malicious, can we
change this?
Well, yeah.
>> Power.
>> I mean, yeah. I know how to change the association of PS1 to
make it actually execute. That's not just a good idea.
>> Yeah, don't do that. Don't do that.
>> The point is, is we're not going to stop you from doing that.
But this helps you from making foolish mistakes like this.
So let's try to execute this script and watch what happens.
There's another security feature. The whole path thing, you
make us type in the path.
>> Yeah, well, first just try and type it.
>> So C colon scripts and it was Iloveyou.PS1....
>> Well, no just CD to there. CD to that directory.
>> Oh, okay. You want me to CD to it, okay.
>> And then just type I love you.
>> Oh, I love you.
>> Ipe love you?
>> No, that's not going to work. IP... Well, I love IP but .
>> I love IP.
>> I love IP. IP therefore I am. There we go. I love you. What? What? What? What?
>> See. It says, "No. No, no, no, my friend." >> No,
not recognized as the name of a cmdlet, a function or a script file.
Check the spelling.
Well...
>> Look at the suggestion. Have you ever noticed that?
>> Oh, oh, dude.
>> You haven't noticed that?
>> That command I love you was not found but does exist in the
current location.
>> You never noticed that?
>> I never noticed that. Tricky, tricky.
>> Yeah.
>> So now that's just going to confuse me more because it's going
to say... Oh, but then it actually tells me how to solve it.
>> Yeah, type dot slash. Now here's the reason why. This is what's
called kind of a trolling attack. So what happened is...
And this is only time UNIX problem. You're admin and you CD
to somewhere and you say, "Current working directory." And a
bad guy would go in that directory, and they'd put something
called print working directory. They would rename Iloveyou.vbs
to print working directory. So you CD there. You do print working
directory; you run that code.
And bad things would happen. And so what we said was, "No, no, no.
If you want to run something in the current directory, you have
to be clear that that's what you want to do." We're very big
on intentionality. You have to tell me that that's what you want;
otherwise, no.
>> I remember root kits used to come in...
>> Root kits.
>> ...and there was a DIR root kit. And you would go DIR and
you were running the root kit.
>> Yeah, bad.
>> Yeah, bad, bad. So what this prevents from is... Let me show
you this two ways. One is I could try to run the script by typing
in the full path to the script, I love you, or I can be in the
current directory and let me show you that one. If I'm in the
current directory with the script and try to run it,
it's dot slash Iloveyou.PS1 and that's what that general message
at the bottom told you to do because it saw it there. This will
run my script.
Oh, no. I'm a failure. I'm a failure in life because it found
it, but it says it can't be loaded because the running of scripts
is disabled on this system. For more information . In other
words, you're not allowed to run scripts. And when we come back
from break, we're going to show you why you're not allowed scripts
and then how to change that. So we'll see you guys in ten minutes.
Yeah? Ten minutes. >> Cheers.