[Music]
>> All right, welcome back. That was a quick 10 minutes, Tobias.
>> Yes, yes. I am pretty sure it wasn't.
>> I barely had time to get my hair cut. But we're going to continue
our conversation. What we did to set up the class, we started
out with some basic commands, just kind of make sure everyone
understood what we were talking about, and if you hadn't heard
some terms in the recent past, I just wanted to make sure everybody
was comfortable with some of the terms. We did some basic SELECT
statements, then we moved into the second module, where we talked
a little bit more. We started adding things like DISTINCT and
ORDER BY, so we did some sorting, some filtering and kind of
took it up a notch. What we're going to do in this module is
talk some about the data types, because those are a very important
part of data integrity and referential integrity, because making
sure when we're creating our columns, when we're creating our
tables, for instance, that we have the appropriate data types
applied to them. So we're going to look at and we're going to
talk about the different data types that are available to us,
the usage of the data types, how you may want to convert a data
type from one to a different one. Not every one can be created.
And then we'll end up doing an introduction in some of the SQL
server functions or types of functions that are available for
us when we're working with SQL Server 2012. So we're going to
introduce these data types and built-in functions. Let's begin
with data types, because this is very important when you're adding
your content or creating the objects that are going to be created
here, and they kind of fall into seven general categories, exact
numeric, approximate numeric, date and time, character strings,
Unicode characters, binary strings and then some other ones that
kind of fall into the Other catch all here.
So these are... SQL Server supplied several built-in data types
within these categories, like ints, so integers or characters
or dates or binary strings. So we're going to begin by talking
about exact numbers, so we're looking at precision or we're looking
at the idea of having an exact number. We have a tinyint, which
is zero to 255, so if there's a value or a field that's never
going to exceed 255, you can use tinyint, and you notice it only
stores or consumes one byte of information. If you have smallint,
that goes up to 32,768, so a value to that or minus 32,768, so
if you're going to store a value in between that range, you can
do a smallint, two bytes of storage, and I'm not going to read
the entire slide to you, but you'll see the idea here, tinyint,
smallint, integer, Bigint, quintillion. I didn't even know there
was a quintillion word out there, but that goes out to quintillion
something or another.
We have bits. That's a one, zero or null that's always returned
to us, decimal or numeric. We are concerned more about the precision.
Money and smallmoney... they must be looking at my paycheck for
that one. So those are some of the exact numeric types, and here's
an example. I could declare a variable called mydecimal as a
decimal with 8,2, so that's going to define what number of decimal
points are available and what kind of content or to what the
precision we can store content in there. So we declare these
items, and we have to take into consideration what kind of content
is going to be stored in there. We also have the approximate
numerics, where we introduce the float or the real, and it depends
on the type that you're using or the value that you're storing.
It's anywhere between four or eight bytes for the float.
It's four bytes for the real. So it's good for you to understand,
as you're deciding what data types to use for the contents to
be added to your data, the storage size that's going to be consumed
and the type of data that you're going to be storing in those
columns, as you identify those columns and those data types.
Under the binary strings, we have binary(n) was anywhere between
one and 8,000 bytes. Varbinary, variable binary, one to 8,000
bites, plus two for storage, if you're looking at the number
of bytes, plus two for storage. And we have varbinary(MAX), one
to 2.1 billion approximate bytes, so actual length, what actually
you're storing there, plus two additional bytes for storage.
>> That may vary a little bit.
>> That may vary a little bit? Talk to me about that. Why would
that vary?
>> It depends on how we store these binary large objects.
Yes, if you store less than a certain amount, it will be plus
two bytes of storage, but if you extend past a certain limit,
we'll have to structure the data differently and you'll pay a
bit more of an impact on storage.
>> Okay. Okay, so this is good to know, some of these little tidbits
like that, that there might be some variations to what we were
seeing here because of the type of content that's actually being stored.
Other data types, we have uniqueidentifier, for instance, a global
unique identifier. Now, that global unique identifier, the GUID,
how do you pronounce that?
>> You're the American, right? I'm a humble foreigner.
>> I'm going to put you on the spot here. How would you say that acronym?
>> GUID?
>> GUID. Okay, good. I always poll this no matter where I teach.
I hear GUID. Most places, especially in the Eastern United States,
and I hear GUID more in the Midwest and some of the Southern
parts of the States. So I always ask.
>> So now we've extended this. In Sweden, it's GUID, as well.
>> It is GUID?
>> GUID.
>> Okay, so it's either GUID or GUID. I'm always curious on how
people pronounce it, so just curious. Just make a mental note.
Do you yourself call it GUID or GUID?
So when you're talking to people, some lay people will say GUID,
I'm like, what's a GUID? I have a friend that says, how do you
pronounce squid? Well, squid is a word. It's not an acronym,
so I use GUID, and I was just curious what you used. So that's
good to know. Anyways, back on topic.
We have cursing... sorry, cursors. It's really not a storage
data type, and we will see how we use those a little later on.
Tables, we'll use those as a data type, so it's not a table that
we've been talking about where we store content in. You're going
to see with some of the upcoming examples where we actually use
table as a result where we can store result sets into it.
So we have some unique other data types that we use, like rowversion
is another one, that we have available to us that we can use
when we're generating content here.
Parse is a new function that was introduced in 2012 that converts
strings to date, time and number types.
Is this replacing anything, or is just new functionality?
>> No. This is net new functionality.
>> Okay, so nothing's going to go away. Or like you said, we
don't normally rip anything away from people, but nothing's going
to be deprecated. It's just a new functionality.
>> Correct. An important thing that we also added, so parse is
converting basically strings to whatever other, more exact data
types that you have, and the typical example is obviously numbers
and dates.
So actually, I can go ahead and just throw an example in, because
it might be somewhat interesting, because this is obviously a
common problem.
By the way, this Cyrillic character I'll use for something else
a little bit later, so don't worry about that one.
SO let's just say we want to go and SELECT * FROM Sales.SalesOrderHeader,
and my favorite topic happens to be dates for whatever interesting
reason, so let's just get the OrderDate here. That's enough.
Okay, so the format I'm getting back here is dependent on the
client application, how it wants to format it. Now, this format
I'm getting back is actually very, very nice, because this is
the ISO format. It also happens to be the ANSI format, year,
month, day, and it's interesting, this ANSI, it's short for American
National Standards Institute, but apparently...
>> I know where you're going with this.
>> Apparently, here in America, they don't adhere to this this standard.
>> We prefer month, day, year.
>> Yes. You prefer the one I can't get. That one and Fahrenheit
I still struggle with. Anyway, if I just want to go and convert
something first, parse is obviously the other direction, so if
I want to convert something to a date... in this case, I can
say, okay, this ISO format, and
see if I can remember the syntax. And I can say here, well,
we'll use Swedish culture, it's called, to parse this. so now
it goes and apparently automatically now says... well, automatically,
obviously, since I told it, but uses the Swedish culture, versus
if I want to parse it using American culture, I can do that.
And we support all cultures that Windows supports here, so now
it happens to be, we do both of these, we happen to get them
correctly, and that's because we can figure out exactly what's
being used here.
>> Nice. The other thing that's interesting though is what if
I do...
this is hello in Swedish.
But apparently, it's not a valid date. Now, an interesting thing
that we added is TRYPARSE, and we do this for CAST and CONVERT
that we'll get to later, as well. That's basically, if it fails,
don't fail the entire statement, return null instead.
>> Oh, nice.
>> So this can be very, very useful. For example, you can say
WHERE TRYPARSE this string in this way is not null... so now
you'll get everything that actually can be converted or parsed
into a date-time.
And the other one I wanted to show is FORMAT, which is the other
direction, so PARSE is going from string to an exact data type,
and FORMAT is the other direction. So FORMAT this one as...
I'll see if I can remember what it is.
Let's say, with Swedish culture,
so that's the picture string. So this is now the picture string
I want to format it using. I can add the culture, as well, but
in this case, I won't actually care about the culture. I'll just
tell you, please give me year, then give me a colon... for whatever
reason, right...
month:day:hour, in 24-hour format, and now that's exactly what
I get back. So this is also super-super useful, because now you
can easily in SQL return the formats that you would like, and
that obviously works for numbers, as well.
>> Awesome. Yes, that's a great demo, definitely, to see that.
So daytime, we'll introduce the general idea of the different
data types that we have. Just kind of a high level and some of
the categories. We're going to drill into character data types here.
And there's really a couple of variations of that. We have the
CHAR, the VARCHAR, and we have the Unicode, which is NCHAR and NVARCHAR.
And then it looks like the TEXT, the NTEXT, are going to be deprecated,
so we want to start leaning towards using the VARCHAR(MAX) and
the NVARCHAR(MAX) instead, so you're prepared for that.
Now, when they say deprecated, any ideas when that may happen,
as the SQL crowd... what was your title? Didn't you create SQL
Server back in 1940, '50, or something?
>> No. I'm very young.
>> Very young. No, it was a compliment, how smart you are.
>> Also not very smart. So I actually don't know the exact details
of the deprecation plan for TEXT and NTEXT. Overall, we're very careful.
Deprecation means you should avoid using it, because we may run
into problems in the future and we may have to remove it, so
when we announce something for deprecation, it will stay in the
product at least three releases, but after that we may remove
it, depending on the need for removing it.
>> Because I know a lot of people will see it's going to be deprecated,
I've got to rewrite everything before the next release comes out.
So that's why I was curious. When I hear the word deprecated,
no matter what product it is, do I have to hit the panic button,
or can I like, okay, I've got a few releases.
>> For SQL Server, at least, it's three releases.
>> Okay, awesome. So we've got character data types here, and
here's the CHAR and NCHAR that understands or introduces the
CHAR and NCHAR are fixed rights, and then we've got the VARCHAR
and NVARCHAR, variable lengths, and it gives you some storage
information here, and it talks about the VARCHAR(MAX) and the
NVARCHAR(MAX) and the storage requirements there.
>> So here, I wanted to use just a brief demo with this Cyrillic
character, to just show the
basically use of Unicode.
>> So that's a demo on the...
you had that character on your screen that I saw earlier and
I just didn't know what it was.
>> Exactly.
>> So let's see what that demo is, see what this little odd character is.
Well, not odd in a bad way. I've just not seen it. Unique, that
sounds better, right? I think that's better than odd.
>> Sure.
>> Special.
>> It's a character used by a lot of people. At any rate, the
most important thing here, this also comes from backwards compatibility,
so Unicode, it's a standard, basically, a set of characters that
is supposed to span
all required characters around the world. Now, this keeps extending
and things change quite frequently, but overall, in SQL Server,
you're safe. We support up to UTF-16, which is a broad spectrum
of characters. At any rate, if I do this,
again with the Swedish using the Latin characters,
this string is now
typed as a VARCHAR string, right? So whatever character set you
installed on the database when you set the collation, that's
what we're going to use. So in this case, this works just fine,
but let's say I just want to add the Cyrillic character here,
what happens now is we will go and try to convert characters
that are not in this character set into the character set, and
Windows has an API for this, and it will return a question mark
if the conversion fails. So the important thing here to note
is using strings like this is very dangerous if you use Unicode
data, which you should do. So, overall, you should definitely
move to using NVARCHAR wherever you believe you will need other
characters than the default character set installed.
>> Is there any extra overhead when you're using NVARCHARs or Unicode?
A little bit, right?
>> Yes, so basically Unicode... first, we supported UCS-2, which
is two bytes per character. If you use UTF-16, which is a different
collation, it uses sometimes... it's called surrogate characters,
and then you use four bytes for a given character.
But, at any rate, if I put the capital N in front of the string,
now you'll see we handle it correctly.
So that's important. It's not just important that you use the
right data type, such as NVARCHAR and NCHAR and NVARCHAR(MAX),
but you also need to type your strings this way.
>> All right, awesome. Good stuff.
Okay, so let's take a look at some of the things we can do with strings.
For instance, we have string concatenation, where we can actually
merge two different columns or multiple columns. In this case,
here, we've got the SELECT BusinessEntityID, FirstName and LastName,
and then we're going to concatenate FirstName and LastName as FullName.
So when we run this, we're going to see BusinessEntityID, FirstName,
LastName, and another column will be added over here, and that's
going to actually display FirstName and LastName as FullName
in a column. So we can do that. We also have introduced what's
called CONCAT() function, and this was... what we're going to
do here is select AddressLIne1, City, StateProvinceID.
We're going to CONCAT the AddressLine, plus City, plus PostalCode
AS Location, and we're going to grab this information from the
Person.Address, and again, it's going to store that information.
And what this will do, it will convert nulls to an empty string
before the concatenation, so you don't end up with some content
in there, a role that doesn't contain anything that makes any
sense to you. Now, the cool thing about strings, just like we
had talked about, we're going to talk in the next session here,
like date and times, we have some functions that can be performed.
So I can take a string and I can use like SUBSTRING, for instance,
and I can pull a section of that string out that might be important
to me. I can take a look at the length of the string, so if I'm
trying to... hey, if the length of the string is greater than
nine or is equal to eight, I'll go out and perform some other
task for us. We can change the case on it, so if a string comes
in, it's lowercase and I need to get it in uppercase, we can
modify that string text. So we have these functions available
to us to allow us to take content that we may have imported from
a FOT file, for instance, and we want to modify it, or we want
to maybe extract certain portions of it, before we add it to
a table.
And we can use these string functions to perform some of these
functions on character data types, for instance, before we go
in and add that data. Now, Tobias talked about this a little
bit earlier. I think we talked about the LIKE...
maybe it was. Maybe I'm confusing it with my other session, but
the LIKE predicate is used to check a character string against
a pattern, so we use the percent sign, for example. That was
kind of like a wildcard. So I want to go out and I want to go
out and find anything with a name that has N... what did we use?
We had mountain in here before... that has MOUNT, and then we'll
put a percent sign in there, and it will be a LIKE. So anything
that begins with a MOUNT, and it will actually return anything
that returns with a MOUNT and any number of characters to the
right of that. So it could be mountain, for instance, and it
could be... I can't think of another word with mount on the end
of it. So that would be an example where we could use that.
If you're trying to just use a single character in place or just
a wildcard for a single character, it's an underscore instead.
This gives us flexibility to return results or look for results
or retrieve results that we're not 100% familiar with or may
not know the exact spelling, or maybe it's spelled differently,
and it gives us some flexibility of writing queries that allows
us to query the content without knowing exactly what it is that
we're looking for, by either using the percent or the underscore,
as an example, to return that content. And as an example down
below, where we're returning the ProductLine, Name and ProductNumber
from the product table WHERE name LIKE Mountain%, so anything
to the right of mountain. Because you might have mountain bikes,
you might have mountain lions out there, and this will return
anything that includes the name Mountain and any number of characters
to the right of the word Mountain. So it gives us some flexibility
when we're performing these SELECT statements.
>> And with regards to performance, it's just interesting to note
that, if you have an index on the Name column in this case, we
can still use the index and seek through the index to find Mountain-something,
whereas if you put a wildcard in front of the word, we won't
be able to use the index for seeking. We have to scan the entire index.
Now, if you need it, you need it, but it's worth noting that.
>> There is some overhead.
>> There is definitely overhead with using wildcards in the beginning
of the string.
>> Okay, character data types.
Let's see here what we have for demos. Do you have anything
you want to show, Tobias?
>> Yes, well, I've already shown the Unicode thing.
>> You did the cool stuff.
All right, let's see here.
Okay, that's cool. That's true. That was probably the cooler
thing than anything I've got in here to show them, so let's go
ahead and talk about date and time data types. We did a little
bit of a demo on that where we were doing some conversion with
the parse. But we have some data types here, older versions,
supported DATETIME and SMALLDATETIME. We now have DATE(TIME),
DATETIME2 and DATETIMEOFFSET that we can use, that were introduced
in SQL Server 2008, but we can use these for determining the
type of date or time or a portion of the date and time that we
want returned to us, some interesting or new data types that
were introduced for us that allow us... and again, notice the
storage for the DATETIME2 that was introduced. Six to eight
storage bytes. If you go back to the old DATETIME, there was
eight storage bytes for that available.
>> And I can show a quick demo here, which is important for you
guys to know, when you still use DATETIME, because that's obviously
going to be the prevalent data type out there, DATETIME, rather
than the new data types, even though they definitely offer benefits.
So one thing that's important to know is precision is down to
every third millisecond, so this is important inquiries, right,
because the very common query is give me everything for the day, right?
So get all orders greater than midnight, greater than or equal
to midnight and
less than or equal to the end of the day. Now, if you do less
than next day, that's the safest bet, but just to show you, what
can happen here is I'll just use a string here and I'll say...
and CAST is a function just for converting. So I'll say okay,
what is it, today is the 13th and then 23:59:59,
and then you have milliseconds in there, so you will go naturally
in and say this, right,
as DATETIME?
But if I go and execute that, that's apparently tomorrow, because
the last millisecond will be 047, so this means that if I go
999, it will round up naturally and correctly up to the next second.
If I do 998, it will go and round down to 997. So 997 in DATETIME
is the end of the day. So that's just an important thing to know
when you use this data type. Again, if you just say less than
tomorrow, if that's your predicate, you're obviously safe.
But it's an important thing to know of.
>> All right.
So DATETIME, data types, literals, and this is an example of
where we just actually do a query of a
SalesOrderID and where OrderDate equals a specific date.
And these here are DATETIMEs and they have language-neutral formats
and some examples of these.
Write down... yes, that's amazing, how they go down to the milliseconds
nowadays for information.
>> Or even nanoseconds, DATETIME2 and TIME.
>> Nanoseconds.
>> Down to 100 nanoseconds is the max precision that we have.
>> 100 nanoseconds. That's amazing. That's really good, to be
able to do that.
Working with DATETIME separately, here's where we get this example
where we have
the declared DateOnly, DATETIME, and then SELECT the DateOnly.
Notice it returns... at this point, it returns just the date
and nothing to do with seconds. It just uses all zeros for the
seconds, as if it's midnight. If I did it the opposite day, where
I'm looking just for the time, the date's going to be set to
January 1st of 1900, and then you'll have the time for that portion.
So just some ideas and
awareness of different returns that you'll see, results that
you'll see, depending on what you're trying to do with the date
and time.
>> And it's obviously more efficient than to go and use just our
new data type or TIME data type, if you're just interested in
storing a time or a date.
>> Querying date and time values, again, we've just seen how to
query one of them. They talk in here about values are stored,
queries need to account for time past midnight on a date.
That's pretty much what you were just talking about with the
precision of that item there, so we won't spend too much time
on this. But it's good to understand what the options are and
take advantage of these new date and times. Some functions that
we have, we can GETDATE, which grabs a current date and time.
There's no time zone offset for that. We can do a CURRENT_TIMESTAMP,
which does the current DATETIME. SYSDATETIME grabs a current
date and time, and then we have SYSDATETIMEOFFSET. This does
include a time zone offset, and you can use just a simple SELECT
CURRENT_TIMESTAMP, and it will return that information for us.
We also have date and time functions for DATENAME...
use year, month, day as the datepart. We have year, month data
as datepart. We have DAY, MONTH and YEAR, and all of these are
items that we can do to extract the portions of a date out to
return that information about a date that we might want to drill
down to and get into some more detail of.
Some additional functions that return date and time from parts.
Here, we return a type of data... of date, excuse me. We have
DATETIMEFROMPARTS, DATETIME2FROMPARTS.
We have the OFFSETFROMPARTS, and just to give you an idea, the
functions that return date and time from parts, you have some
examples down below of how these would be completed for us, as well.
Some additional examples and functions that modify. We can do
a DATEADD where we want to add intervals of a specific number
of days, as we're seeing here. ENDMONTH, we're trying to look
for the end of month for a particular start date.
DATEDIFF, we're trying to determine the difference between two dates.
So I want to know how long a project is taking, so I have the
start date, I have the end date. I can determine the number
of days it took for that project to complete by using the DATEDIFF
as an option here. The ISDATE is available for... to determine
whether a date or time is a valid value, it contains an actual
valid value when we're adding these dates and times, here.
We had just seen an example that Tobias did using the CAST option here.
Here's an example of that. SELECT CAST AS DATETIME as date, AS TodaysDate.
It can return an error if the data types are incompatible, so
if I'm doing a SELECT CAST this date, and then I want to return
that as an integer, we're going to get a little bit of feedback
on that, as in the explicit conversion from data type to int
is not allowed. So, again, you can convert different columns
or different data types. Not everything is convertible to every
other data type, so you have to be aware of what can be converted
from one date type to another date... or one data type to another
data type, and understand what those are before you start going
out and trying to use the CAST or the CONVERT commands for performing
those conversions.
Here's the CONVERT command here. It can be used in SELECT and
WHERE clauses. Another example is SELECT COVERT(CHAR(8)) to a
CURRENT_TIMESTAMP, and here's the ISO_style we had talked about
earlier, as how we can determine how we want that date to be
returned to us, what style do we want to use? In this case, here,
we're using the ISO_style.
So date and time function data types, are there any other date,
time function demos you want to see, you want to show?
>> No.
>> That we haven't discussed, and we had examples. I don't know
if there's anything that's unique.
>> Not really.
We talked about the every third millisecond. The other thing
that's more interesting, as an anecdote, is that the date time
data type starts at 1753. So if you want to store dates before
1753, you would have to go and use the DATE or DATETIME2 or DATETIMEOFFSET
data types. It has to do with 1753 is when basically the British
Empire moved to using the Gregorian calendar rather than the
Julian calendar, so that's why this 1753 was picked.
>> Okay, 1753. I'll have to remember that. All right, we have
some built-in functions that we can look at and take advantage
of, as well, that are available to us, and some of these include
the scalar functions, grouped aggregates, windows and rowsets,
and we're kind of categorizing these by scope of input and type
of output.
So if we take a look at scalar functions here, we've got items
and categories. We've got configuration, cursor, date and time,
security, string, system and these can be used for us to be able
to perform functions on these types of data. So here's an example
of a date, time functions where we're doing a SELECT SalesOrder
and grabbing a year from that particular date. A mathematical
function, looking for the absolute value. We're doing a CAST.
We've already seen that one.
A metadata function, where we're doing something, we're selecting
database name as current_database. So if you're working in or
programming and you want to be able to retrieve the current database
that you're in, you can use this SELECT DB_NAME, open and close
paren, and it will return that current_database that you're working in.
So it's a good way to determine where you are to make sure you're
executing the commands that you want to execute in the appropriate
database here.
Some Windows functions that we have, we have the RANK function.
We OFFSET. We have aggregate and distribution functions.
This here is doing a SELECT TOP(5) of ProductID, Name and ListPrice.
We're doing the RANK and ORDER BY, by ListPrice, and then we're
going to return that in descending order.
What's the RankByPrice?
What's that going to provide for me?
>> So Window functions overall are super, super interesting, and
it's one of these things that you need to spend a bit of time
playing around with and thinking about to kind of get into the
groove of how you use them, but once you do, you will never want
to go back.
They are super, super, super useful, and let me actually show
a few examples, because this one... and I know we've got some
feedback on the chat, where you want me to go a bit slower.
This one, I'll definitely... it's very good feedback, but this
one you'll have to take away that you'll need to spend some more
time with to actually get into the groove of it. But I'll show
you some examples.
So let's just look at kind of a
common thing. Let's say we go and SELECT star FROM...
let's say SalesOrderDetail, and we'll pretend this is kind of
like a transactions table
for a bank.
And let's just do this for a specific customer ID, or let's just
do this.
And ORDER BY
OrderDate, SalesOrderDetailID.
Oh, sorry, there is no OrderDate in here. I'll just do this.
Okay. So, first of all,
one thing that you may be interested in, in your set, just returning
a row number, so which
row is this in the particular set? So I can go and just add here
and say, give me
the row number, and it's kind of like a ranking function, or
it is a ranking function. But rank would give you, if multiple
rows have the same value, you'll get the same rank, whereas ROW_NUMBER,
you'll always get a new row number, even if they're returning
the same. So I'll say, okay, give me the ROW_NUMBER, and obviously
ROW_NUMBER makes no sense without actually knowing the order.
And SELECT, again, is executed before ORDER BY, so you can't
really use whatever is in the ORDER BY clause. Plus, you may
want to have multiple ROW_NUMBERs, because you're calculating
something, so the actual function uses this OVER clause to know
about the ranking.
So ORDER BY, and I want this, let's say, ordered by SalesOrderID.
That's RowNum1, and let's just run this. And you can see we
get these row numbers that now start adding up.
What I can also do is say, well, I don't just want ROW_NUMBERs.
I want ROW_NUMBERs per
order, so then I can add the PARTITION BY clause, PARTITION BY
SalesOrderID, which means for every order,
I'll get new
ROW_NUMBERs as they basically reset.
So we see here the RowNum1 keeps increasing, whereas RowNum2
keeps resenting as I get into a new order.
So that's what ROW_NUMBER does, and that's what these kind of
functions do, is you tell them, based on the set, here is how
you do your calculation, and you do
ROW_NUMBER, RANK, DENSERANK and so on. The other thing that's
interesting to mention is on aggregate functions. Now, we'll
get more into grouping later, so GROUP BY and so on, but aggregates
are very useful, together as Windows functions.
So we're using the OVER clause, rather, so let's just say I want
the sum of
UnitPrice here.
Now, if I try and execute this, we will complain and say, oh,
why do you combine an aggregate with all of these non-aggregate functions?
Because what does this mean? You want the sum of UnitPrice per what?
Well, you have no grouping, so it will be the sum of one value.
That doesn't make sense.
But what you can go and do is you can say, give me the sum based
on something.
So I can now tell it, well, I actually want this sum partitioned
by something. So SalesOrderID,
and then we can say AS TotalOrderPrice.
And as you can see now, the TotalOrderPrice will be the same
for all of these rows that adhered to the same order, right?
So in this case, this aggregate is actually run across these
rows, based on the window that you define. So the PARTITION
BY clause defines the window for this calculation, so each partition
has its own window that it calculates over. What I can also
go and do is say, well, I would like also the total price across
all orders, so over everything.
Oh, now I managed to zoom it.
This is great.
>> We'll have to come out.
>> And now I can draw something here. Okay, hello.
Stop, Mr. Zoom.
Okay. This is very interesting.
I have tried Ctrl-1. That doesn't seem to...
but it doesn't want to go back.
Let's call this demo finished. You got an introduction into Window
functions, and we'll see if we get back to it a little later,
as I try to figure out what's going on with my machine here.
>> Yes, the last piece I wanted to talk about is we can use the
CHOOSE option here, and then we're going to wrap up this module here.
We can use this option to SELECT, CHOOSE three, and we've got
three items in the list here. We've got Beverages, Condiments,
Confections as CHOOSE results, and then we can choose the different
items that we want to choose, so just a way to create a hardcoded
list, but a list of items that we can choose to work with.
We did some cool built-in function demos, so we're just going
to kind of wrap this up.
SQL Server associates columns, expressions, variables and parameters
with data types. Bottom line, when you create a new table or
a new object, we need to understand the type of data that's going
to be stored in there. It's not to be taken lightly, because
you have to make sure that you're able to store content, the
appropriate content, that will enforce data integrity.
And you also have to understand how that content's going to be used.
For instance, if I enter a character field, I'm not going to
be able to perform any calculations on that. So you have to
understand what type of data is going to be stored and the type
and purpose or use for that data. And we introduce seven categories
of built-in data types, as you can see here, exact number, binary
strings, date and time, character strings, and we talked about
some of the functions that are available for the string, specifically
the left, right, the replace, the upper, the lower, if you want
to change the casing of it and the substring. We talked about
the LIKE, specifically I can use the percent as a wildcard to
the right.
If you use it to the left, especially when it comes to indexes,
and that will be any linked number of characters for that wildcard.
Underscore is for a specific character. So let's say for instance,
state code, I know it begins with A, but I can't remember if
it's AZ, for instance, and I can't think of another state code,
all of a sudden, that begins with A.
>> WA?
>> WA, there we go.
>> I'm sorry, begins with A.
>> Begins with A, yes. So another state code, Arkansas, whatever
that one is. AR, I think? What is it?
>> AK.
>> Whatever is AB. Obviously, I need to pick up on my geography
here, but we can actually use A_, and that would replace just
a character or do a wildcard search for a character. So I know
a state code that begins with A. Obviously, I don't know my
state codes. I know AZ, because that's where I'm from, but apparently
I don't know the rest of them. Several date-time data types available,
some of the newer ones that we talked about, the DATETIME2, the DATETIMEOFFSET.
Make sure you take a look at those, try to utilize those.
We're down to nanoseconds for those.
Also, we have some functions associated with those DATETIMEs,
like GETDATE, CURRENT_TIMESTAMP, SYSDATETIME. So we can use
those types of functions for us to be able to retrieve content
that we're looking for specifically to dates. So we talked about
some scalar functions, kind of introduced those briefly, as well
as grouped aggregate. We got a really cool demo on Windows functions
from Tobias. That was really cool.
Some other functions we just briefly talked about are like CHOOSE,
and so it's good that we have these functions that allow us to
work with these data types when we choose to work with these
data types. So this is the way for us to introduce the idea of
what data types are all about, how important they are for us
to choose the appropriate data type based on what type of values
are going to be stored in there and what maybe calculations or
tasks that we want to perform with the data that's stored in there.
And then we talked about some of the different functions associated
with the different data types, like the character data types
or string data types, the DATETIME data types. We introduced
some of the functions available for us to extract content or
portions of those to retrieve and use those portions in a result
set, as an example. So what we're going to do is we're going
to break for 10 minutes, and when we come back, we're going to
go into our next module, and the next module, we're going to
get into more detail about understanding more about different
options we have for advanced queries with SQL Server 2012.