[Music]
>> All right, folks, welcome back,
and we again appreciate you joining us and sticking
with us today. We've gone through six modules already. We have
two remaining modules, so still some cool, exciting stuff left
for us to discuss, so don't go away. You don't want to miss.
The next piece here we're going to be introducing is programming
with T-SQL.
There's enough components or pieces to this where you can actually
do some really decent coding with it, so we're going to introduce
some of the programming elements within T-SQL.
We're going to talk about the fact that you can provide some
error handling, so if your script doesn't work correctly, there's
a way to do some catching and management of the errors, and we'll
talk about the use of transactions when you're scripting out
content using T-SQL. So we're going to spend some time talking
about that. Now that we're comfortable with retrieving content
and updating content and the implementation of defaults, constraints
and triggers, let's take a look at how we can manage content
and T-SQL programming elements that are available to us for doing so.
We've been mentioning this a little bit all day about the batches,
the fact that we can create T-SQL batches, which is really just
a collection of one or several T-SQL statements that are sent
to SQL Server, then they're parsed to make sure they all make
sense and things are all in place. They're optimized, and then
they're compiled and then they're executed, as according to what
we're asking for that script to do. Some statements that you'll
find in there that will include CREATE FUNCTION, CREATE PROCEDURE,
CREATE VIEW. These can't be combined with others, so there are
some restrictions you have to be aware of when you're looking
at creating batches and making sure you can combine those types
of batches together. This here is an example of a CREATE VIEW statement.
We're creating a view. We saw this earlier on, just creating
a view, using a SELECT statement to define what columns we want
in the view. We're deciding where we're going to pull the content
from, and we have a GO on the end of it. Remember, that's our
batch terminator. And this will create this view for us within
a batch environment. Remember, the beauty of a script or a batch
is the ability to have multiple T-SQL statements, and more importantly,
if we save that out, we can schedule that to run at a later time.
Now, batches are important to understand because they're parsed
for syntax as a whole or as a unit. Syntax errors can cause
the entire batch to be rejected. Runtime errors may allow the
batch to continue after the failure by default, but by default
you also won't know that, so you have to be aware of that.
So the good news is batches can contain error handling. And you'll
see a couple situations here where we've got an INSERT INTO batch,
and it's got a couple of values, a couple of rows of values we're
adding, and underneath here we've got an invalid batch, where
we're doing insert into a table, and that table doesn't exist.
The batch is not going to give you any kind of error handling
indicating that that was an issue, so we have to build in our
own error handling to make sure we cover everything that we want
to cover.
Now, most often, we're going to want to reuse a batch, so what
we're going to want to do is include variables.
This here is an example of creating a batch or a variable, so
we're going to declare SalesPersonID as an INT 5. We're going
to select OrderYear and we're going to do a count on the distinct
CustomerIDs, and then from there we're going to do a SELECT statement.
We're going to grab the YEAR from OrderDate, and we're going
to specify that as OrderYear. Grab the CustomerID. We're going
to grab both of these from the SalesOrderHeader, where there's
a certain ID that equals the ID that we passed in. So the beauty
of this is, I can reuse this batch, because what I'm going do
is, every time I run it, I'm going to pass it in a SalesPersonID,
and this this job is going to run or these statements are going
to be run against this SalesPersonID that I passed. And with
that, we'll go in, and we'll create this AS DerivedYear and we'll
GROUP BY OrderYear. So this gives us information and is an example
of using variables and the reuse of batches by supplying variables
that I can include whenever I want to execute that batch.
Some additional information on working with variables. You can
declare a variable, supply... declare and initialize at the same time.
You can supply accessed create multiple variables and we can
use these and pass these as parameters into procedures, as they're
shown here. They're executing a procedure called ProdsByCategory.
@numrows = @numrows, @catid = @catid, or category ID, and this
allows us to execute this procedure, use them in variables that
we're passing in here.
The other thing we can do is, if we get complex names and we're
trying to simplify how we're working with some of the objects,
we can create what's called a synonym. A synonym is an alias,
or it's a link to an object. Now, that object could be a local
object or it could be an object on a linked server. They can
be used for referencing these objects, and as you can see here,
we're going to create a synonym around the MyProduct table, and...
I'm sorry. We're going to create a synonym called MyProduct for
AdventureWorks.Production.Product, and then we're going to be
able to query the product table using the synonym to shorten
that name used required for us to reference that object. So we're
going to SELECT ProductID and Name from the synonym called MyProduct,
WHERE ProductID 5, and then we'll execute that. So if you have
lengthy names, link you would in maybe a LINQ server or even
some of the product names that your object names, that you're
using, if they're multiple-part names that you're using, we can
create a synonym for that, and we can use that for
accessing that content. These are like any other object. We create
them with a CREATE statement, we modify them with the ALTER statement,
and we toast them with a DROP statement, because the toast statement
isn't there yet, and it doesn't sound like it's going to get
there in the near future. Is that what I'm hearing? Correct.
>> Okay.
>> I just wanted to make sure you haven't changed your mind.
It's been a few hours. I thought maybe you might give in just
a little bit. Nope, >> no.
It's >> not
going to happen, so I've got to write my own. Okay. So batches,
variables and synonyms, we've got these available to us here.
Let's go ahead and take a look at a couple of these here that
we've got some set up here.
Let's see, where am I? I've got to get into my image this way, here.
So here we've got the idea. This is what we saw earlier.
We've got DECLARE @SalesPerson_id INT is 283.
That's what we're looking for for a salesperson. We'll see if
that's even valid. But we're just going to grab this, highlight
it, and this is a statement that I walked you through so you'll
have at least a little bit of understanding what it's doing for
us here. We'll try to execute it, and it doesn't like Sales.SalesOrderHeader,
so let's see what I did wrong here. Sales.SalesOrderHeader the...
problem is I'm not master database here. I should grab my USE statement.
So let me go ahead and throw that back up there. There we go.
Now we'll run this baby.
And you'll see by order year, 2005, '06, '07 and '08, customer
accounts, 13, 24, 25 and 22 for the salesperson 283. So that's
the number of customers they had in 2005, so 2006, they almost doubled.
2007, they increased only by one, and in 2008 they decreased
by a couple, so starting to slack off a little bit there.
So that's the idea of how we can use variables within a procedure
and then execute them within that procedure. I also want to
take a look at the idea of that's... a little too early for
that piece. So that's why we're going to look at that piece.
We'll come back to this piece a little bit. It's usually an
IF OUT statement, but we're going to come back to that in the
next session here. So we'll just jump back to our Windows.
Is there anything else I wanted to demo in here? We did the variables.
No, that pretty much covers the variables.
All right, so that's good for that one. Let's jump back to our
slide deck here, and inside of here, I'll get the full screen
so you can see everything that's going on here.
And we're going to look at control of flow options here, how
we can control what's going on in a batch and how we can control
the route that it takes, if you will, to be able to execute that
batch or the statements within that batch.
So SQL provides additional elements that control that flow and
the execution of statements within there.
The default is for statements to execute sequentially, but we
can throw things in there like an IF ELSE, a BEGIN END, a WHILE
or a RETURN, and that's going to control what happens. So, suddenly,
just going sequentially down through the batch file, it's actually
going to control using some of these control of flow language
elements to be able to decide what rows or where we want to go
within that batch. So for here, for an example here, I've got
IF OJBECT_ID is Production.Product, and it's a user product,
if it's not null, then print, I am here and contain data, so
don't delete me. So that's just a basic statement, just a basic
IF statement. Now, if we take it to the next level, we can throw
an ELSE in there. IF OBJECT_ID is not null, then print, I am
here and contain data, so don't delete me. Otherwise, which
means it doesn't exist, we can say, table not found, so feel
free to create one, so we can specify this. Now, we're controlling
what's going to happen here. So now I can go out there and create
a table based on this else statement, or I can just bail out
of here and say I want to purge data or I want to select perform...
a SELECT statement, because I know there's data that resides
in this table. So we can use this. Very helpful when we use
the EXIST operator, as well. But it's another way this IF ELSE
allows us to control the flow of our content. We can also introduce
the use of a WHILE, so what we have here is we're going to declare
a variable called BusinessEntityID as an integer, and also as
a title, as an NVARCHAR(50), and while BusinessEntityID is less
than or equal to 10 so... we're going to give it some parameters,
we're going to begin and we're going to do a SELECT Title and
JobTitle from the Employee table where Business ID equals what
we passed in as Business ID we... began with 10 here.
We're going to print the title
or the NVARCHAR for that BusinessEntityID, and then we're going
to set the BusinessEntityID to equal what it is now plus one.
Because, eventually, in order for this WHILE loop to end, we've
got to get it up to number 10. So the first time it runs through,
it's at number one. When I execute this one, it's going to increment
it to number two. It's going to run through the WHILE loop a
second time, a third, all the way up until it's number 10, and
at that point it will end that WHILE loop and the idea of
displaying content from the title and the BusinessEntityID.
Now, we can also within here use a BREAK or CONTINUE option to
break out of this loop, if we want to, so those are ways for us.
We don't have to wait for the WHILE loop. We can set up conditions
in there where, if a certain condition is met, hey, don't go
up to number 10. We have a way for you to bail out of here.
So control of flow options, do you have any cool demos you want
to show for control of flow options? I've got some of the ones
I've just shown. I can use those, which is fine. Go >> ahead,
show the demos. I have something in mind for error handling and transactions.
Okay, >> perfect.
So let me jump over here, then, and we're going to go back in
to this image here, and let's let this download a bit here.
So in here we've got the IF ELSE statement that we saw a little
bit earlier. All right, so over here, we've got IF OBJECT_ID
is not null, then print, I'm here. If it is, then print, table
not found, so feel free to create one. So this is using the
IF ELSE statement.
So let's go out here. I'm here and contain data so don't delete
me gets printed out for us, so it found this object from this
table called OBJECT_ID. It found an object called Production.Product.
It's of the type of user, so it's going to display that content
for me.
Now, with that said that's... more error handling over there.
We can also, like I said we... can set up a WHILE loop. I showed
you an example of that. I didn't bring that back in. I should
have brought that in for us. But we have a WHILE loop. We saw
how that would work, and so this is just an example of how that
would work for us. And again, we'll make these available for
you, so you can take a peek at these babies at a later time.
So that's the idea of using control of flow options, using just
one example of those. We also have and... what we're going to
introduce next is error handling structured... exception handling.
So what we can do is use the TRY to run a block of commands,
and then we use the CATCH to catch any errors, so it's called
the TRY CATCH, obviously.
It won't work for everything, so syntax or compile errors won't
be caught. Some name resolution errors won't be caught. But what
this does, it executes and move to the CATCH block of commands
when an error does occur. So we're using the TRY, we're going
to the TRY. If there's an error, it jumps out and down to the
CATCH environment and it uses the syntax that's in the CATCH environment.
This one, you don't need to check every statement to see if an
error will occur. If an error does occur, you have to decide
when we introduce transactions if an... error does occur, do
we want to roll back the transaction and how we want to respond
to that transaction, and we'll introduce transactions here in
just a little bit. But this does some of the error checking for me.
Now, we could also query the error object, so common error object
properties that you'll find are ERROR_NUMBER, ERROR_MESSAGE,
ERROR_SEVERITY, ERROR_PROCEDURE and ERROR_LINE. Those are functions
that we can query, and the properties associated with them are
on the left-hand side and the descriptions on the right-hand side.
And if you remember that raised error message that you saw earlier,
there was a couple of numbers associated with it. There was
a severity level number and there was an error number a severity...
level and a state number that was associated with that. So these
are parts of the error message that you can create to generate
your own messages. Values respond or returned correspond to those
in that information that's in the sys.messages view that's available
here as an object, as a table here a system... table available
to us.
So this is an example of a TRY block. What we're doing, we're
going to begin the TRY, and we're going to force an error.
We're going to try to perform a division by zero, which we know
will error out. So we're going to do a BEGIN TRY and then SELECT 1/0.
If there's an error, we're going to jump down into this BEGIN
CATCH, and what this is going to do is it's going to report information.
So the ERROR_NUMBER is, and so what it define is, in the CATCH,
we define what we want returned to us. Well, I want to know
the ERROR_NUMBER. That's one of the items in that table I showed
you previously. I want to know the severity of that error.
That's right here. I want to know the error state.
If there's a procedure, I want to know if there's an error procedure.
I want to know what line number that error occurred on, and lastly,
if there's an error message that's returned, I want to see what
the error message is that's returned so I have an idea of what
I need to try to troubleshoot. So this is fairly straightforward.
You know it's going to generate an error, because we're trying
to divide by zero, which for some reason it doesn't work, whether
it's Celsius or Fahrenheit. So the TRY and CATCH blocks won't
catch everything, just to let you know. So this is an example,
we get a BEGIN TRY up here, table does not exist. We're going
to do a SELECT * FROM * IDontExist table, and we're going to
END TRY. The CATCH is going to be BEGIN CATCH, SELECT ERROR_NUMBER
and ERROR_MESSAGE. The bad news is, we're not going to use this here.
We're going to just jump out, and it's not going to pick this
up, because some name resolution, like it can't find this IDontExist,
the TRY CATCH won't work for that. So not all errors can be
caught by TRY CATCH. Some syntax, some compilation errors and
some name resolution errors won't be picked up by the TRY CATCH.
So what you need to do is make sure you test everything and not
assume that's going to catch the fact if there's an error.
Cause an error on purpose that you would want to be thrown over
into the CATCH area so it would execute and display the message
that's associated with that. Speaking of THROW, here's the using
the THROW statement. Tobias talked about that earlier, where
he said instead of using the RAISERROR, you might want to use
the new SQL Server 2012 THROW statement.
It's kind of replacing and I'll use replacing... in quotes, here.
The THROW allows choices when handling your errors, so we're
going to perform that BEGIN TRY and the SELECT. We're going
to divide by 100 100 divided by zero,... and we're going to
set that up as a problem. And then at the end of the TRY, we're
going to BEGIN a CATCH, and the PRINT, Code inside CATCH is beginning.
The MyError is going to CAST an ERROR_NUMBER as VARCHAR, and
then we're going to THROW that. So THROW was introduced in 2012,
and we're going to use that THROW that's going to give me some
choices for what happens and how I respond to an error that occurs
in this case here, in that TRY section. So we can use the THROW
for passing parameters to a user-defined error, or without parameters
to reraise an original error, the error that was caused originally
by that. Now, you said, are you ready do you want to... go show
this cool demo, error handling. Yes. I'm not so >> sure
about the cool part. But we will I'm absolutely confident it's...
>> going to be cool. We'll show something. Yes, >> let's
do that. So, first of all, just mentioning a little bit more
details around this whole what we catch and what we don't catch.
The big thing here is really around what type of error it is,
so just like Brian mentioned, if it's a syntax error, we won't
be able to catch it, as well as if it's a name resolution error,
and that's due to the fact that we haven't started executing yet.
So when you send a batch to the server, what we start with is
just we get a bunch of text, right? So we look at the text and
say what's in this text? And if I can't figure out what's the
text, I don't know that there is a TRY, CATCH, etc. hiding in
there, so the error happens before the TRY block is actually started.
Same goes for name resolution. If you're trying to reference
a table, when I try to compile the statement, I don't know what
it is.
But you can get around these things if you're generating SQL
statements automatically or manually, rather. Then... you can
catch it. So I'll just show an example of that, and we'll show
some other examples that are interesting, especially with regards
to THROW.
So starting out, we'll just do BEGIN TRY,
just SELECT 1/0, as
Brian likes. That seems to be his favorite error,
and CATCH. So let's just start with this. If I just execute
this, aha, clearly, divide by zero.
Now, the point of the CATCH clause is always if anything happens
within the TRY block, provided I get to start executing, I'll
move to the CATCH block. So if I just execute this, you can see
I didn't get any result back.
Now, we can just put an empty THROW in here just to see that
with THROW it just throws whatever we caught in the CATCH block,
so we get the actual error message back.
So now, with regards to this syntax error, so let's say I do
hey in between here, you can see it didn't catch it, because
we didn't manage to parse this. So this text that came to us
didn't make sense. But what I could do is I could say, well,
I want to execute. So you can execute stored procedures, as Brian
already showed. You can also execute what's called dynamic SQL,
which means I pass a string in, the server compiles it and tries
to run it. Now, that thing actually happens within the TRY block.
So I'll say here,
_BEGIN scoobidoo.
There we go.
And now you can see incorrect syntax near scoobidoo, and let
me just add a SELECT 1 in front of this. We see
clearly the SELECT 1 happens. So you can see how in this case
we catch name resolution error or,
for example in this case, the syntax errors. So that kind of
makes sense.
Now, the other thing I wanted to mention, which is more somewhat
less clear is this RAISERROR, why you should look at using THROW instead.
And let's just try it quickly. So RAISERROR, and why I say RAISERROR
and not RAISEERROR is there is only one E. Definitely, yes.
And I >> look
at >> this
as the intelli-sense of the '80s, right?
So it's a little bit shorter.
And I say okay. The error message will pass an error here, and
16, 1.
So this is the message we're going to send to the client.
This is the severity level. It can be zero to 25 16 means miscellaneous user...
error. The more important thing is, if it's below 11, the client,
like .NET, ODBC and whatever, won't raise an error on the client
side, so it's considered an informational message. If it's above
10, it's an error message. If it's above 19 in SQL Server, so
in 20 and up, it's considered a fatal error, and we'll go and
cut your connection when we see that. So that's obviously, you
then can't... go and handle those errors. So RAISERROR 16, and
then after that I'll just put the SELECT 1.
And as you can see, both of these happen, right? So by default
with RAISERROR, the only thing we actually do is send the error
message to the client, but we continue processing. Okay, so
that's all fine.
Let's now say we create a procedure that's called sp1,
and all it does is RAISERROR 61,
and then we create a procedure sp2
let's just have sp1.... That's going to be enough, probably.
Okay, good. So someone has been using sp1 for a long time, right?
So let's say that they do BEGIN transaction, and we'll go into
transactions a little more later, but then they do a bunch of
stuff here, so SELECT 1 is super-important. And they do COMMIT
transaction after.
And this clearly works fine, right? So we sent there error message
to the client, and then you go continue to SELECT 1, and then
you go continue to complete your transaction. Now, someone,
and this procedure has been there since the beginning of the
ages, which is very common with databases, right? So I'll go
ahead and say, well, I want to use this in a TRY block.
And then I'll have BEGIN CATCH, END CATCH,
and let's just do a THROW in here to re-throw the error. So the
procedure looks exactly the same as before. I didn't change this.
I just changed where I'm calling it from, and now when I run
this, you notice that SELECT 1 doesn't happen, right? And COMMIT
didn't happen, either, so the transaction is still open, and
I have to go and COMMIT it after, right? So this is a pretty
big problem, right? This means that, depending on how the procedure
is dynamically
executed what's the word?
Sorry....
How it's called, how it's nested so if it's nested...
inside a TRY block, it behaves differently than if it's nested
not with inside a TRY block, which control flow now depends on
how the caller calls the procedure, which can be a huge cause
of errors. So this means that RAISERROR can sometimes change
your control flow and sometimes not. So that's a big reason
why you would like to avoid using it. So THROW, the difference
is just that THROW always breaks. It always aborts. So if I
just try this exact same thing,
I'll just copy this,
and instead of this, I'll say THROW, and I have to say the error numbers.
I'll just say 50,000, which is the lowest that you can throw
yourself, the message, severity level sorry, severity level is...
always 16 with THROW, and then SELECT 1.
Now you can see we never got to SELECT 1, because THROW automatically
aborted the batch.
So now sp2, we'll just do the THROW here.
I will do EXEC sp2,
and we can see that it never got to SELECT 1 or COMMIT, so we
would find this bug immediately, right?
It always behaves the same, meaning that now when I run this
sp2 in the TRY block, it behaves just as if I ran sp2
outside the TRY block, so THROW is just more consistent than
RAISERROR, and that's why we recommend using THROW instead of RAISERROR.
Very nice.
Okay, so >> speaking
of transactions, great segue for transactions for us. We're going
to talk about transactions in this next piece here. I got a
little ahead of myself. Let's talk about there we go, transactions,...
that baby right there. So we're going to talk about transactions,
because a very important part of our especially for programming, we...
want to make sure that certain transactions or statements are
handled consistently, or if you have multiple statements that
need to happen all at once, and if one doesn't work, then none
of them should work. That's pretty much where you're going to
want to use a transaction. So let's say you're in the banking
industry, and you want to move some money from your savings to
checking account. Well, there's going to be an update statement,
and the update statement is going to so we're going to...
move from savings to checking. We're going to update the statement
to say deduct $500 from my savings account. I'm going to have
another statement update statement that says... add $500 to
my checking account. Now, if I can put that inside a transaction,
I could update $500 update, run the statement... that goes against
my savings that deducts the $500, but if the system happens to
bail on me at that point, it never gets to that second statement
that says, oh, yeah, you're supposed to deduct $500 from savings,
but oh, by the way, you're also supposed to add $500 to the checking.
If I don't have that in a transaction where it's handled as a
single unit of work, I'm not going to have that $500. I'm going
to lose $500. I'm pretty sure my bank doesn't use transactions,
and I'm losing money all the time, so it's got to be because
you're not using transactions. I don't know. It seems like money
just seems to disappear. But, anyway, we'll look into that.
So information like that, where it has to be handled as a unit
of work, if one fails, then everything has to fail, we can surround
that as Tobias just pointed... out, we use a BEGIN TRAN and a
COMMIT TRAN to say, hey, look, this is not just a single statement
that needs to execute. This is a series of statements that need
to execute, and if you can't complete, get down to that bottom
piece where it says END TRAN, then we don't want anything to
occur in that transaction. We want to roll that back. So that's
what we're looking at, that's what a transaction is all about here.
So this is an example. It's a group of tasks defined as a unit
of work. These two tasks make up a unit of work. INSERT INTO SalesOrderHeader.
We have a new order that came in. Well, this is the general
information about the order in the OrderHeader table, but the
details are in the OrderDetail table. So we want to make sure
if we're adding content in the SalesOrderHeader table, that the
content or the details about that also get added into the details table.
So we want to make sure we can do that. And if we can't do that,
then we're going to have a problem, so we need to make sure that
we have a way to resolve that problem or how we're going to manage
that problem.
So the need for transactions or issues with batches. So we have
a batch with transaction management. We're going to do that
insert into this one succeeds, this... one fails.
We have the idea of catching the error, but the problem with
this is this is simple error... handling, but it's not going
to repair the fact that this already got inserted.
The information in the SalesOrderHeader was added, but this wasn't.
Hey, by the way, we had a problem, but we still have inconsistency
in our data, because we have information in the header table
but we don't have information in the detail table. So what we're
going to want to do is we're going to want to introduce, as we
were just seeing just a little bit ago, the BEGIN TRANSACTION.
Hey, what I want to do as a whole entire unit of work is I want
to include this in the TRY CATCH, but what I want to do is begin
a transaction, and I want to insert into the header table.
I also want to need to insert the details about that into the
details table. And then if nothing happens, if both of these
are successful, meaning there's no errors, then we're going to
commit that transaction. But oh, by the way, if there's a problem,
what we want to do is get into the BEGIN CATCH, and what we're
going to do is we want to clean that up. And what we're going
to do is say, hey, if you threw me down in here from the TRY,
there must have been a problem with that unit of work.
Something or everything didn't execute. It could be two commands,
it could be 200 commands, statements.
If they all 200 I don't care if 199 executed.... If all 200
of them didn't execute, then we want to, instead of committing
that transaction, we want to roll back that transaction, which
means it's going to back up to the SalesOrderHeader table, it's
going to roll back that and not apply or insert this record into
that SalesOrderHeader information. So we talked about briefly
earlier today, we talked about the... idea of items get written
into the transaction log and then eventually they're written
to the MDF file or to the data file. This is what's going to
happen, is it's going to see when we roll back that transaction.
It will never commit that or write that to that MDF file, to
kind of say it in an easier term here.
So we create a unit of work by indicating that we want to use
the BEGIN TRANSACTION statement. That marks that starting point
of an explicit user-defined transaction, and then we wait and
we apply all these in order, and we wait for that COMMIT TRANSACTION.
If we never see that COMMIT TRANSACTION, then we know there's
an error. If we have a BEGIN, we need to have a COMMIT TRANSACTION
or we need to have a ROLLBACK TRANSACTION in order for that.
So a BEGIN TRANSACTION and then an END TRANSACTION, and we can
have a COMMIT or a ROLLBACK associated with those, to make sure
that we have that content associated with that information is
updated, like I... talked about with my checking and my savings accounts.
So here's my BEGIN TRAN. All right, we're going to insert in
the SalesOrderHeader table. Here's my SalesOrderDetail table.
If we make it down to the COMMIT TRAN, everything's beauteous.
We don't need to worry about throwing anything into the CATCH
block, and we're going to be able to make sure our content is
added in both tables. In my case here, is added to both my savings
and my checking account were updated appropriately. As this
is alluding to, this is updating. It's adding content into my
header table and to my details table to make sure that content
remains in sync with each other here. So in your T-SQL code,
if a transaction is successful, we want to make sure that we
commit that transaction. If we have any issues, we want to roll
that transaction back, so this is where we begin the CATCH.
Now, the TRY failed. It's going to push us down into the CATCH block.
We're going to select the error number, and we're going to ROLLBACK
that transaction, which means anything that was supposed to be
applied up top into the TRY block, supposed to be applied to
that header table, don't apply it to the header table, because
we never made it down to the details table. That content was
never added. We got thrown down into this CATCH block, which
means something happened up top and we want to make sure that
nothing gets applied to those tables, because otherwise we'll
have a header
a row in the header table,... and we won't have any details about
that row that's in the header table. So if that error occurs,
we're going to ROLLBACK that transaction, and we'll have to retry
that transaction to see if we can get that transaction to be successful.
So we'll just come back around and try that transaction again.
Now, by default, SQL Server doesn't automatically ROLLBACK transaction
when errors occur.
To roll them back, you can use the ROLLBACK statements in error
handling, as we just talked about, or enable this exact oh, back
to one.
I call... it XACT_ABORT, but specifies whether SQL Server is
going to automatically roll that back. When this is on, your
entire transaction is terminated and the ROLLBACK on the error
will occur, unless it's occurring within a TRY block. If it's
off, which is your default setting, you should decide how you're
going to handle the error handling for transactions, and it's
easy to turn on using this statement here if you want to turn
that on. So demo on this, do you have anything lined up for us?
Yes, yes. I thought you'd have >> something
slick >> for
this one. I was thinking of that, yes.
>> No, so we'll this is one of these pretty... important things, right?
So show the kind of standard example and just what you need to
think about, and then we'll show that sometimes rewriting what
you're doing and rethinking it may get you a more efficient solution.
So I'll just do this common example that Brian mentioned, which
is I want to take out money from one account and I want to add
it to another account.
Or, rather, in this case, I'll just say you want to withdraw
X amount of money from the account and I want to double-check
that the money is actually there and then do the withdrawal.
Okay, so let's take a look here. You can put it in my >> account
after you withdraw, if you want to. I can give you that number.
I'm okay with that, totally. Thank you, Brian. That's so kind
>> of you. Yes, just trying to be a >> team
player. It's all good.
So let's take >> a
look here. So let's just start by creating the Accounts table,
and I'm pretty sure that people work at banks I'm sure some of
you are... listening. That's what you guys do all day. I need
a new Accounts table, so I'll add it and then you can start taking
your money in and out. So just do this.
AccountID and Balance, and this is a very simple bank, so all
we do are integers. This decimal stuff we don't really care for.
Nice, just round it up.
Rounding.
>> Okay, so that's our Accounts >> table,
and then I'll just insert a row into it, so INSERT Accounts VALUES,
this is my account number, and I have 500 pirate money in my account.
So now, in order to be able to show this, I need to use two connections
to the server to kind of show the problem, because it's a timing-related
issue, obviously. So I'll say BEGIN TRANSACTION, and what I want
to do here is, I want to check if there is enough money in the
account, and if there isn't, I want to abort, right? So IF, let's
say, EXISTS,
SELECT * FROM the Accounts table and * by the way, there...
is no benefit in using SELECT 1 or anything like that, so SELECT *.
We're just checking for the existence here. As soon as we find
at least one, we'll abort the query. WHERE AccountID is equal
to Scooby Doo and balance is at least let's say I want to...
take out 400.
So as long as rather, if this doesn't exist,... then there is
something wrong, right? You don't have enough money in the account
or the account doesn't exist. So, in that case, what I want to
do is I want to ROLLBACK the transaction.
And you may argue, why do I start the transaction at all.
We'll look at why I want to do this. And then I want to THROW,
which will abort the execution and exit, the error and say,
"Tobias is too poor."
And then state 1. I guess I'm not getting >> any
money from you. Correct. Okay. And then I >> want
>> to >> actually
do the withdrawal. So if I get down here, that means THROW didn't
abort, so then we want to take out the amount, so UPDATE Accounts,
SET Balance,
and now we'll this kind of in stages. So now I'll do the calculation
in the app, so what I pass in is I want to take out 400, and
I did the calculation in the app here and say, well, it's currently 500.
The app happens to know, so I want to set the Balance to 100,
which is obviously a problem.
So just do this and COMMIT TRANSACTION.
So this is kind of V1 of our banking app, and presumably we'll
be fired for this at some point if we were actually working at
a bank, right? But now this because this is a timing...
issue, I will have to kind of manually execute this and pretend
that I am the control flow statement, so we'll say that this
is basically Connection 1, and this is since you probably figured out...
that myself and Brian are underpaid
young people that run around trying to afford what is we are trying...
to afford? Going to Disneyland. Disneyland, that sounds good.
We >> like
Disneyland. So we >> have
this scheme, now. We know the bank is new, which means they have
new software, and new software, potentially there are bugs.
Because it has been run for a fewer amount of time, fewer time
than older software. Hasn't been thoroughly tested or >> debugged.
So the plan is, Tobias >> is
going to go into the bank and try to withdraw money from his account.
Brian is going to exactly at the same time go to the ATM and
withdraw money from Tobias' account with Tobias' card, so I use
my ID and he'll use my debit card. Then, hopefully, we get some
extra cash for our Disneyland trip. And we have synchronized
our watches. Are you ready? Yes, ready. Good, so there >> we
go.
>> Now we're at exactly whatever time it is where you are watching from.
We'll see us doing this. So this is Tobias in the bank, Connection,
and then we have the Connection which is Brian
at ATM.
They tell me it's automatic teller machine. Automatic teller
machine, I think, >> was
the last time I knew what it was. This is so simple to >> understand.
So we sync. I am standing at the cashier and trying to hold his
or her hand so that they press the withdraw button exactly when
Brian is going to punch in start on the ATM. So okay, what happens?
Tobias' transaction starts, Brian's transaction starts.
Bank checks does Tobias have enough money in the account?
Yes. We get the row back. Clearly, there is enough in the account.
The ATM checks, is there enough money in Tobias' account?
Yes, there is. Great. Now you start wondering what kind of locks
are being held in the table right now? Well, by default, in SQL
Server we use read
committed isolation, which means we take a look on the row to
make sure there is no write-exclusive locks already being held
on the row, and then we release the lock. So that guarantees
we did a committed read.
There is no uncommitted data there. So this means if I go to
a third connection and just check what locks are being held,
we can see there are currently no row locks or any locks of that kind.
Just trust me, there are no locks on this table right now.
So the
bank computer continues. Obviously, this didn't happen, so it
goes and withdraws the money from my account and sets the new balance.
Done. We don't commit yet, so now if I go back and check the
locks, now we have an exclusive lock on that row in that table,
so the row is locked.
At the same time, Brian's ATM also goes on because it found that
there was enough money in the account. It tries to do the update.
It has to wait, because the row is locked, right? We go back
and check, and now we have, yes, Tobias has a grant on the lock
on the row and Brian is waiting to get an update lock on the row.
So what happens? Well, Brian is waiting, or rather the ATM is waiting.
The bank machine commits, I get the money from the cashier, thank
you, 400 pirate money. At the same time, ATM works fine, ATM
commits, and Brian gets the money.
I say goodbye to the cashier and then exit the bank, and we meet
outside, and now we have 800 pirate money versus having just 400.
And the bank at the same time checks what is the balance on the account?
Well, it's 100.
Okay, so this is an example of where we actually lost data.
So this is great for me and Brian. We go, oh, okay, perfect.
We're off to Disneyland. Disneyland >> trip
is looking good.
>> And hence, a little bit later, maybe we'll do this again.
And this is very hypothetical. Very, very, very hypothetical.
By the way, my name is not Tobias, and this is not Brian.
My name is Frank.
Shhh.
>> Okay, so next time, >> the
bank doesn't do too well, because me and Brian obviously tell
our friends that, oh, there is this scheme you can do. You just
have to have synchronized watches. So bank upgrades. Now, the
system is going to do Balance -= 400, so we're going to actually
do the subtraction at the data layer, rather than up in the app,
so the upgrade obviously happens at the ATM and the Teller.
Yes, teller thingy. So...
>> I >> just
do a quick let's say I get my... salary again, my 500 pirate money.
We come back, we want to do the same thing, so I begin the transaction
inside with the teller. It checks, it has money.
At the same time,
Brian starts. The ATM checks, there is money.
The update happens.
Brian's update happens or rather, it queues now,...
commits. I get the money from the cashier or from the teller,
and Brian gets the money from the ATM. So this is all good.
We managed to get 800, but if we now check the balance on the
account, wherever we did that, V2
of the bank software is way better, because at least now they
know we're over. Two separate transactions of 400 >> each.
Now we're minus 300. Yes. So now they'll probably >> charge
me some overdraft thing, but then you could obviously they don't
have limits on... how much you can take out, so I'd take out
a lot.
So let's say that the bank doesn't really like
giving me this loan without having approved my credit limit,
so let's look at V3
of the banking app. So now instead, what it's really about is
when the SELECT happens, I want it to keep the lock on the row.
That is the problem that we're seeing.
Because the check doesn't keep the lock on the row, the update
can succeed. So I'll say what I want is obviously Brian's or
whatever transaction comes in second, wants it to queue already
up in the SELECT. So I'll say WITH(UPDLOCK).
And this is there was someone in the... chat that asked about
FOR UPDATE. This is basically the same thing. So there are three
basic lock types in SQL Server. There's shared locks, which means
two shared you can have on the same resource, often called read locks.
Exclusive lock, you hear on the name, only one can have an exclusive
lock on any resource. Update lock is basically compatible with
shared, but not other updates or
exclusive locks, obviously. And what this means is, while I have
an update lock, no one else can take another update lock, but
other people can read at the same time. So it improves concurrency,
and what it means is it means I'm reading now, but I have an
intent to update later. So as long as you're reading and not
intending to update later, go ahead. If you're also intending
to update later, then no, not good. So V3 of the software, let's
look at what happens.
I get my salary again
and have to wait a little bit extra because I was negative on
the account. It begins the transaction, it checks and there is
enough money.
And now, when we check the locks, we can say, aha, the SELECT
made it so that I got an update lock on the row. And now, when
Brian's ATM goes and starts, begins the transaction, you can
see how it queues on the select. So it waits here, and if we
now check the locks, we can see that I have my grant on the update
lock, on the row, and Brian is waiting. So now,
obviously, my transaction then continues, withdraws the money
and you can see Brian is still waiting. And then commits.
I got the money from the cashier in the bank, and now Brian got
no rows back, because this wasn't true anymore, so what he gets
is this, Tobias is too poor. So now in V3 of the app, we fixed
the issue.
So you can see how it's not actually very complicated, but it's
important to know exactly what goes on and not think of transaction
as something magical or weird. It's just very logical.
Now let's just look at how we could make this just more efficient,
so V4 of the app, just for performance reasons now, what we could
do is this.
And we don't actually need the transaction BEGIN and the COMMIT TRANSACTION...
statements anymore, but I'll just leave them in there, or I can
remove them just to be clear that I don't need them. So what
I do instead is I'll just take this WHERE clause and put it here.
So on the update, if I have enough money, right, let's add the
give me the money again.... I've got another salary. And then
I just check. IF ROWCOUNT we have you could also use the...
OUTPUT clause, but ROWCOUNT is practical here. So IF ROWCOUNT
is basically not 1, right, then something is wrong. So let's
add BEGIN TRANSACITON. We know it shouldn't update anything,
but let's just to be extra clear.
So do the update, take out the money if there is money, and then
we say, well, if it didn't update one row, that means there wasn't
enough money, so then we roll back and throw out the error.
And now you can clearly see, I don't have to think about this
with UDP lock or anything. I'm getting better performance because
I'm only executing one statement instead of SELECT and UPDATE.
So I'll try this, it works fine.
Run again.
Can't do it. Can't do >> it.
So that >> gives
you kind of an intro into transactions and what you need to think about.
And you don't need to >> use
them all the time, but definitely when there are certain things
that you need to work, use as a single unit of work as we introduced earlier.
Batches are just a series of SQL statements. Maybe they're fine
running sequentially, but there may be situations where you need
them to run as a unit of work. Then you're going to need to BEGIN
and a COMMIT transaction with some error handling on that to
do a ROLLBACK in the event you need to a ROLLBACK. You'll be
using variables. There's a way for us to pass parameters into
procedures to allow us to reuse that procedure multiple times,
procedure as one example, to reuse that stored procedure multiple
times, just by passing a different value in with that parameter.
Synonyms we looked at for making a shorter names for us to be
able to access content, whether it be local content or content
on a LINQ server. These are some of the control flow options
that we saw earlier on slides. We go the IF, we got the IF OUT,
and we saw a really good demo on the BEGIN and the TRY and the
CATCH and how that can be very helpful with error handling.
And we kind of wrapped up with talking about transactions and
the series of transactions and how that block of code has to
all be successful. All the statements have to be successful.
Otherwise, we're going to roll that back so that nothing gets
applied to the database. And we looked at using the BEGIN, COMMIT,
ROLLBACK transactions, and we can also set something at the system
level for the aborting on a transaction if... it shouldn't be committed.
So that's what we did in this module. What we're going to do
is we're going to take a 10-minute break, and when we go take
the 10-minute break, we are going to come back and we're going
to in our final chapter, we're... going to wrap up by talking
about querying information. What kind of information do I have
readily available to me to see how my system's running.
We're going to look at dynamic management views, we're going
to look at some of the system tables available to us. We're going
to look at ways to look at our queries to see if they're running
as optimal as possible, and if not, some ways that we can try
to optimize those queries. So we'll see you back here in 10 minutes.
Enjoy your break.