[Music]
>> Well, welcome back to Module 8,  the final module.
It's kind of sad. We've been... we spent all day
with you and... or evening, depending where you are in the world,
and we've enjoyed our time with you. We, by the way, Tobias
and I, both shout out to the local bank, and we were not able
pull off what we... so apparently they're running V4 at the local
bank at least, so just to let you know. Most banks aren't V4.
So we don't want to plant any bad seeds, like I'm going to go
try this tonight. So we just tested it. It's all quite good.
V4 is out there for most banks, so you probably don't want to
try what we were talking about earlier on. So what we're going
to focus on now, folks, is retrieving SQL Server metadata.
And we're going to look at a couple different ways we can do that.
And then we're going to look at query, performance, ways to monitor
query performance and ways for us to improve query performance.
So this is the final module, and, again, it's kind of sad, but
we're going to talk also about store procedures. We talked a
little bit about how to use them and where they come into play
and everything, but we talk about creating and executing store
procedures in this final module as well. So let's go ahead and
move into system catalogs in DMV, Dynamic Management Views.
And system catalog views are built-in views that give you information
about the system catalog, oddly enough, right? You can use any
standard query method to return metadata. You can look at column
list, you can use joins, wheres, order bys. And some of these
views are filtered, that's going to display only certain objects
for you. So what we're seeing here as an example is select a
name, object ID, schema ID, type, and type description from sys.tables.
And this is going to be... it's going to include display content
for us that's going to include information about the system objects.
Now, with that said, because we want the sys.table, we also have
another thing called sys.objects.
So the first command returns information pretty much about user
tables, but the second command returns information about user
objects and system objects. So you'll get more information, but
maybe not want all that information about the system information
or the system objects that are available out there. Another way
that you can retrieve information is using what's called information
schema views. These return system metadata according to the ISO
standards, so they can be used by third-party tools. They map
to standard names or to catalog in your domain to your SQL Server
names like your database use find data type. And as you can
see here, I can retrieve information from these information schema.
So the first one that we show here is .tables. I can retrieve
information about the different tables that are being used by
SQL Server, how the columns are being used by SQL Server.
And, again, here I can get a little bit more specific. This would
return everything about every column. I want to find out where
business entity ID is being used. What table in the schema or
in the database is business entity ID stored in. So if I need
to make a change to that, I'll understand the repercussions or
the impact if I need to change that as an example. So I can
actually go in and throw a where clause on this and return that.
And of course you can throw an order by in here and sort it,
so you can see how... you know, where the business entity ID
is sorted by a table, if you wanted to. So it's just a way for
us to retrieve metadata about the system or about how SQL Server
is functioning.
We also have functions that we can use. We've seen a couple
functions here. We've got the select version and we have the
two at signs. And this is like a version for that that returns
the SQL version. We can also look at the product version.
One will show you the version name and the other one will show
the version name and the number associated with the version,
was it version 11 dot whatever it might be for SQL Server 2012.
You may be concerned about the collation that you're using with
your SQL Server environment. SharePoint requires a unique collation.
It involved collation of the box.
It's not used by SharePoint. So I may want to determine what
the collation is for our SQL Server instance before I install
SharePoint before it starts communicating with that. So I can
use a server property called a collation to determine what collation
is being utilized for this instance of SQL Server that's installed.
>> And we can just mention that this... at that something...
-inaudible- functions
called global variables but they have nothing to do with variables.
They're just functions that don't text up parameters.
And these are mostly there for backwards compatibility. So typically
they're replaced by database property, database property X, column
property, server property, and so on.
>> So, yeah, so again what we had talked about earlier about the
idea of like some of the functionality you've seen for several
versions and it just kind of hangs out for this because we're
kind of used to it and we want you to be able to continue to
use that. But as you're looking around and working with SQL Server,
see if there is a better, more... maybe more improved way performance-wise
that may have another option for you to retrieve that information
or perform the tasks that you're trying to perform here.
We can query DMVs and functions. Here's a dynamic view that
we're looking at here, select session ID, login time, and program name.
And we're going to retrieve that from this assist.DM underscore
exec sessions. And that can specify, like I said, with a where
clause in there what I want to be able to do with that.
Same with the dynamic management functions that when their query
does table valued functions, we mentioned those earlier on, we
can just go ahead and do a select statement on that, specify
what exactly... what type of view I wanted to reference and specifically
a specific object. In this case here we're looking for that sales
order header object to find out or retrieve information about that.
>> And we have a charge number of DMVs and DMFs, so dynamic management
functions and views. So it's definitely useful to spend some
time in going through what they are.
And as this will help you with either debugging issues in the
server that you're finding to make your app faster, whatever
it is, or maybe you want to build some automated monitoring.
So it's worth spending some time going through all of these,
just till you get at least a hunch of what you can actually see.
And it's one of SQL Server's strengths is really the amount of
monitoring we allow you to do. It's actually quite impressive.
>> Yeah. And so yeah. We'll take some time to understand those,
but they are very powerful and worth doing it. And there's nearly
200 dynamic views, or DMVs, in SQL Server 2012. Again, they
include information about catalog information, administrative
status information.
The DMVs are server scope at the instance level or database scope,
depending on what you're looking for.
The underlying structures may change, so a lot of people...
what you don't want to do is write a select statement against
a specific DMV and keep that and think that's going to good forever,
because they do tend to change. So it's good to understand what's
available out there and be able to understand that you can query them.
But be careful about writing procedures that's going to go out
and execute against them in the event that they do change.
And there's a different categories of these DMVs. There's database category.
There's a query execution related categories. There's I/O statistics
categories for your input/output. There's operating system or
SQL Server operating system information that's available to you.
And there's a category on transactions. And we saw how powerful
transactions are and how important they are for us as well.
So these are all types of views, are categories of views that
are available out there, and there's a slew of them to go through...
I already used plethora, so I can't use that again. I'm going
to switch to slew now... a slew of them out there to go out and view.
So you want to go ahead and peek at those.
All right. So system catalogs and DMVs. Are there any special
ones that you like to show when you do demos or...
>> No, there's plenty of them.
>> There's so many of them, I just...
>> Yeah. But DM exec overall is one of ones that you use quite
frequently as well as DMOS to look at different wait stats in
the engine. So typically when you're... overall when you're
looking for... to improve performance, a big thing for you is
to look what is the server actually doing.
And if it's waiting for something, what is it waiting for.
So it may be waiting for I/O, for example, it's waiting for the disk.
If it's waiting a lot for disk, you may want faster disk or more
memory or things like this. So there is... it's really like
a pretty huge subject. But overall definitely DM exec, DMIO...
or, sorry, DMOSDMIO are useful to start looking more deeply into.
>> Is there a class available just on performance with SQL Server?
>> No, that's basically all of these are performance related.
>> Okay. All right. Stored procedures. We could also use stored procedures.
And with stored procedures we reference those a few times.
We have system stored procedures, we have user-defined stored
procedures that can be created. So with stored procedures, what
we can do here is we can execute them. And a sample here, example
here is we just want to execute SP databases. We're not going
to pass any parameters. I want a list of all the databases that
are available. Of course I could pass a database, a specific
database name. It would give me information about that particular database.
Same with the SP help. I just want general information about
the table. I can actually get that information by typing SP help.
If there's a specific table, in this case here sales.customer,
I could supply a parameter for that and get specific information
about that single table. So depends what you're looking for.
I can get information about every database, about every table
if I want to, about the system if I want to, about a specific
table using SP underscore tables. It depends what I'm looking for.
I can decide to just give me information about everything or
specific objects if I'm focussing only a particular object that
I'm trying to fix or optimize.
>> And typically
there are some exceptions. SP underscore help is very useful
because it just gives you a lot of information about an object.
But typically you're better off looking at catalog view, so selecting
from sys.databases
or sys.objects, sys.tables, sys.procedures and so on sis.-inaudible-
and so on, rather than using these legacy stored procedures.
A lot of them are the way you used to retrieve metadata back
in the day, and we're keeping them for backwards compatibility,
but the richness that you get from querying catalog views and
DMVs are typically way greater.
>> So common system stored procedures, we just look at a few of
these, SP databases, SP tables, SP columns, again, we're going
to look at the use of the dynamic management viewers, or DMVs,
or system catalogs, are ways for us to access this similar information.
Unlike the system views, there's not an option to select which
column returns. So if I want some information about SP databases,
I type in SP databases. If I supply a database name, I get all
the information about that database name. I can't be picking
and choosing what information I want about that database or about
that table or about the columns. But we have a little bit more
flexibility when we're using the system catalogs or the views
and the functions that are available to us.
We can execute a system stored procedure. Most of these are
marked with... they are marked with SP underscore as the prefix.
They're stored... the system store procedures are stored in a
fifth system database that's a hidden database. This does not
display when you go into the SQL Server Management Studio.
It appears in the schema of every user and system database.
The best practice for execution include using the exec or execute
statement rather than just typing in the stored procedure name.
You want to include the sys schema name so it knows exactly what
you're calling out so there's not any issues with a naming convention.
And you can name each parameter and specify the appropriate data type.
So they're showing again another stored procedure down here with
a parameter of object name, and we're calling out the table called customer.
So we're specifying what it is that we want to see here.
But we need, again, if I could execute this, SP help provides
a ton of information. But it will probably be overwhelming with
the type of information it's providing me and it's not going
to give you the detail that you want to... or it's going to
give you too much detail. It's not going to be the detail filtered
in a way for you to be able to access that content.
Your stored procedures can be wrappers for simple or more complex statements.
And we can use the create procedures statement for building these
if we want to create a new stored procedure.
And this is a way to create a procedure here.
We're creating one called products by product line. We're going
to use the at num rows as int, so we're going to create a couple variables.
We saw that earlier on how do so. We're going to select the
top number of rows based on the number of rows that were passed in.
And we're going to grab the product ID and list price from the
product table where the product line is equal the prod line which
is a variable that we actually passed in as well. So this procedure
is going to allow us to pass a couple parameters, plus limit
the number of rows, but we want to return information from the
products table based on a particular product line. But we have
some control over what's being returned to us. Even though,
you know, we're using a stored procedure, we can pass parameters.
This itself I would pass in this example here the production.products
by product line. I only want to see 50 rows. I want to look
at the product line with the M category. So I would pass that
and I would get a result set from that giving me information
specifically about that product line. But I don't want to see
everything, every product within that product line. I only want
to see 50 of them. So this gives us information about that.
So we're using a select top. We're going to get the top 50 with that.
And we can do an order by clause in here. That would give us
return that content in a specific order.
>> Okay. I can go ahead and just show an example of
using a stored procedure relating to just the banking app that
we did before.
So let me actually just grab that example that we already had.
And we are publishing these script examples that we do. So the
demos are online for you to download under the FAQ section of
the Web site.
So let me just grab the V4 of this thing. And let's say that
this is actually what we wanted to make into a stored procedure.
>> So that would make more sense. Stored procedures are good
for various reasons, one of which is just management of code.
Right? So it's also that you don't have to generate all of this
code on the client side, you can just send the procedure name
and the parameter values to the server and we'll go ahead and
execute that. So I'll call this greater procedure SP let's say
account withdraw.
And we'll have some bugs in it, but that we won't worry about.
So I have to pass in account ID and I have to pass in the amount.
And we remember these were... both of them for ints.
>> Right.
>> And you don't actually need begin/end in the beginning of the procedure.
But I typically put it there for... because it looks...
it looks nice.
>> Yes, it does.
>> Set no count on is fairly common to use. It just means that
after each statement we don't return number of rows affected
back to the client. There are some client drivers that will believe...
that will basically interpret that as an empty result set.
So it's fairly common that you do set no count on to also reduce
the amount of data sent back to the client. And then I just
go ahead and kind of replace here and say, well, this is actually
this guy, and that's this guy and account ID is this guy.
And then we're good. So now I've created this stored procedure
and we can go ahead and execute it. And it's definitely recommended
that you pass the values in by name. So that means I specify
this parameter name and I say, well, this is account ID, something,
and amount that I want to withdraw is let's say a hundred, and
this account doesn't exist so I'll get the error message back.
But obviously now it's way easier for you as the app runs, right,
you don't have to change the app if you need to optimize the procedure.
There are lots of discussions to be had with regards to where
the app code should lie and so on. But that's one of the reasons.
There's also reasons of we can cache the execution plan that
we have to build around this on the server side which minimizes
CPU that we have to go through in order to go and execute this.
And the other thing that's useful is also we don't have to go
and parse in order to do all that work when we get the call because
if you just use a remote procedure call, you'll just say use
this name with these values and go. And which definitely can save...
give you a performance boost. But that's basically how you simply
create the procedure and run it.
>> All right. And we get to expand on our example on the checking
account in our banking industry, or banking option that didn't
quite work out like we had opened because V4 was rolled out.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. So we've looked at the performance or we've been
looking at different types of queries, whether they be...
specifically spend a lot of time on select statements.
Let's take a look at improving SQL query performance.
Writing well performed queries. So let's... just some basic
ideas here. So only retrieve what you need. So in the select
clause, if you only need two or three columns, specify those
columns instead of doing... specifying, you know, the asterisk
which brings back or returns all the columns for you. If you
don't need all the rows, use the where clause. You're not causing
any additional performance on the server. So be very specific
about what you want retrieved. You can improve search performance
of the where clause. Avoid expressions that manipulate columns
in the predicate. So be fairly straightforward with the type
of information that you want returned to you.
Minimize the use of temporary tables or table variables.
Use windows functions or some of the set base operations that
we talked about earlier on in the class today.
Avoid cursors and any other iterative approaches. Those require
some extra overhead that would slow down your query performance.
Work with your DBA to arrange good indexes and to support the
filters and the joins and the orderings. So if you're coming
in new, maybe you're, you know, a SharePoint person and you want
to work with your DBA because you want to roll out SharePoint
which is installed on top of SQL Server, you and your DBA every now...
my recommendation is you and your DBA should have lunch once
a month. You should take your DBA to lunch once a month and spend
some time with them and understand what they're doing and why
they're doing it. If they're doing upgrades, you may be planning
on going on vacation at the end of October and you're finding
out, well, they're rolling out a... you know, they're upgrading
from 2008 of SQL Server to 2012. Well, that might cause you
to change your vacation plans. There's things like that that
you will learn by just having a conversation.
There's things you may learn about SharePoint that you can talk
to your DBA about and say, hey, look, you know, I understood...
I understand that if we do this in SQL Server it will help me
in my SharePoint world. So just getting to understand or know
your DBA or DBAs, your team of DBAs and having good camaraderie
with them will be important for you to help them and help you
improve the performance with some of your queries because you
can indicate to them what you're doing for joins and what you're
doing for sorts. It's like, oh, maybe we need to put an index
on that particular thing. Depends on how large of a shop that
you're running or a business that you're in. Those conversations
can be beneficial to both of you by spending some time with your DBAs.
Learn how to address different tasks with different query approaches.
We've looked at different ways for doing... there's a few things
that Tobias showed us today that were like, wow, we can do it
that way or we can do it this way or we can do it that way.
So there's so many... often different flavors or different ways
we can slice and dice the content, try to find out the best way
for us in performance-wise so you can improve performance by
using the most appropriate or the best way for us to do that
knowing that there's a little overhead involved with one way
versus another way. Indexing in SQL Server we talked about, a
little bit about indexes.
SQL Server can access. The query optimizer determines whether
it's going to retrieve content using a table scan which means
it's going to read everything in that table or it's going to
check to see, oh, wow, we've got an index on this or indexes
on that particular table. It may be faster for us to access this
content using an index. So index are often used. And if you're
grouping or joining or using that order by clause, and if it
will help you avoid the table scan, that would be beneficial
to when you're performing a query on your database that's stored
in SQL Server.
Index performance considerations. Check your query execution
plans so see if their indexes are present.
Make sure those are being used when you expect them being used.
You can overindex. You don't want people to think, oh, everything,
if I'm going to apply an index to every column because it improves performance...
well, if you have too many indexes, it doesn't improve performance.
And, remember, indexes are beneficial when you're retrieving
content, but there is a little bit of an issue or performance
concern when you're inserting update content. And so if you're
starting multiple indexes thinking everything's going to be,
you know, much faster if you have all these index, if you have
every column index, that's not true. It's nothing that you don't
want to do. So for those query writers who aren't DBAs or developers,
you need to understand the overhead involved with indexes and
not just focus on the idea that, oh, wow, indexes are going to
help me improve my performance when I retrieve content. You need
to understand that too many indexes is bad and there's some overhead
involved when you're inserting and updating content that's on
a table that has indexes.
Your distribution statistics describe the distribution and uniqueness
or selectivity of your data. By default your statistics are created
and updated automatically. You can update content if you just
did a bulk insert of your data and you want to... the query
optimizer to be able to take advantage of the index that's on
there, you can actually cause your... force your index or your
statistics to be updated. It's all driven by statistics and your
query optimizer looks at the statistics, start to determine which
index to use. So these are items that you may want to look at
and understand for the most part I don't need to be worried about
updating statistics. It's done for me. But there might be options
or a task that you perform which would require you to update
those statistics and give you a better performance with your indexes.
Cursors. Kind of... they contradict the relational model which
operates on sets of data.
It would typically require more code, more overhead. Some alternatives
to that are the aggregate functions that we introduce, windowing
functions that we've introduced. There are some unique situations.
More cursors, like generating dynamic SQL code and performing
some of the administrative tasks that we perform. Because, remember,
when we're looking... we've been looking at retrieving content
and more from an end user or developer or information worker,
remember, all the tasks the DBA performs for managing SQL Server
are done using stored procedures and DMVs and executing queries
similar to what we've executed. So these can be used as options
as well.
So improving query performance. Any suggestions on that?
>> So I would suggest we hold on the demo and then we can go...
once we go through the execution plan bit, I can show a bit more
demos around the query performance, indexing and looking at the
execution plan.
>> All right. Excellent. So we're going to come back to this
demo, because we're going to move into the next section, which
is monitoring SQL Server. And Tobias, he kind of just really
touched on a little bit when he actually was in a demo earlier,
he brought the execute plan. He showed you a couple of ideas.
So we're going to expand on that a little bit more here.
The execution plan is what's the process involved with executing
a query. There's the parsing, resolving any variables or any
components that need to be resolved, optimizing it, compiling
it, and then finally executing it. It sounds like a lot when
you say it that way. It's done in split second. But that's all
required when we're actually executing a query.
There's some tools that are available to us for accessing the
execution plans to show how the query was executed, how it could
be executed. We had a question in the chat earlier on, you know,
the query plans, what's the difference if you... the actual
or the X or the...
what's it... the actual... or what's the other one?
The... we'll see it when we go in there. I keep forgetting...
I just answered that question on the last break and I'm already
having a brain cramp. But estimate. The estimated. So the estimated
is like... it doesn't actually execute the query plan or the query.
It says if I did execute it, this is what I would use. This is
the results that you would see or this is how that query would
be executed. Where the actual would actually perform the query
that you're trying to execute and it gives the results as well.
That's the question I was thinking about. Oh. And there's a
slide on that which I didn't realize that was coming up. I thought
that was a few slides away. But here's an example of that.
>> Are you getting tired, Brian?
>> Apparently. It's like, wow, it's the next slide, all's I had
to do, hit the down arrow and the answer was in front of me.
So here's the estimated execution plan which does not execute
the query. Just displays how it would execute the plan.
Here's the actual. It's going to return the next on the queries executed.
And these are the plans that was actually used by the SQL Server
chosen by the optimizer when that query was executed.
All right. So now I'm going to look before I actually speak.
All right. Here's how I get access to the estimated execution plan.
I can display that here. And also include the actual execution plan.
So we'll be able to see Tobias is going to demo that for us when
we go into the demo here.
And he's also going to talk about how to interpret it. What does
this mean. Because you can hover over these icons as you're seeing that.
>> No, no, no. I was going to talk about the Disneyland trip.
>> Oh, the Disneyland... I thought we couldn't do that because the...
V4 fixed everything.
>> Well, we got two, three...
>> We've got a few... yeah, we've got a little bit of money.
That will get us through the weekend at least.
So read the plan right to left, top to bottom. Hover the mouse
pointer over. It's show you that when we get in there. The thickness
of lines between operators indicates the a relative number of
rows passing through. So, I mean, there's some visual items that
are going on that you should be familiar with because that will
give you an idea as to what's happening. So the visual is in
addition to the rollovers of detailed information, will be beneficial
when you're looking at the query plans and how to optimize or
how to interpret those query plans.
Again, here's statistics time on or set statistics I/O on.
This gives us information about the parsing and complying of
a query or the amount of disk activity generated by a query.
So these are... this is information that will give you additional
information, or these are commands that give you additional information
about how the query optimizer is working for us here.
All right.
You're off to a really cool demo, aren't you? You're smiling.
I can tell you've got something really groovy-gized up for you.
>> Well, we'll sneak around here and have a look.
>> All right.
>> So yeah.
Let's take a look at what we can do to, you know, improve query
performance and understand what's going on. And this topic is
obviously more than what you would fit in in a few minutes of
demo, but this is to give you kind of an insight of what you...
where to start and what there is to think about. So I'll just
start by stealing this
sales.sales order detail table and we'll use that as kind of
an example for the demo. So I'll just make a copy of that, sales.index
test just call it.
Okay. So now this table is
what's called a heap.
And that means it's... there's no clustered index on the table.
And okay. What's a clustered index? Well, a table can be of
three types in SQL Server 2014. In SQL Server 2012, which is
the current version, we can be two types. So it can either be
a heap, which is just
nonsorted bunch of rows, or it can be a clustered index which
means it's sorted on some row. So let me just use simple system
procedure here to just check what's the current indexes on this table.
>> Are you going to leave us dangling on the new... on index
in 2014?
>> Well, yeah, so it's... we already have the public betas out
there with it, but there's new types of indexes in SQL Server 2014.
>> Looking forward.
>> So that's seems pretty clear.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Testing does not have any indexes which means by definition
has to be also a heap. So let's just try and say, okay, let's...
we want to run our query on this. And we'll use just a bit of
a complex...
complex but...
a bit of a query with multiple parts to it so you get some insight
into what's going on. So let's say what I want here is
by sales order IT, so by order I would like the sum of unit price
multiplied by order quantity I think the column is, group by
sales order ID. And I want this only where
for a certain customer. So where customer ID...
and that's a bit too broad. Let's see.
Let's see if we can get something
that is a bit more interesting.
Special of variety. Let's use that as an example. So okay where
special offer ID
is 1.
Group by sales order ID.
So now... and then let's add also... finally we want this sorted
by the...
this total field.
So that's the full query that we have from start.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. And it's fast. So, you know, done. Heading home.
>> That's it. Right? Exactly. We've got to the bank...
>> So let's turn on this execution plan business.
So I'll click this one, include actual execution plan.
There's really no reason to go and look at the estimated execution
plan unless the query takes a long time to run or posts an update
statement and you don't want to run it, right, update delete
or something like this. So the... a nonselect statement.
So include the actual execution plan.
Run it again. And we'll see what SQL Server actually did.
We first apparently we did a table scan, okay, so we see there
the predicates that it employed during the table scan, it actually
looked for specific offer ID equals 1 when it scanned. So this
means it went through all of the rows in the table.
And the thickness of arrow is important like Brian mentioned,
so we see all of the rows that match this go to the next step
where there is a compute scaler. And you go and hit properties here.
You can see exactly what the definition of this computation is.
So the computation is apparently this which if you just look
at it it's going to take the unit price and multiply that by
the order quantity. Okay? So that's apparently what we do there.
Then we take that and move into a hash match aggregate. So that's
the grouping...
>> That's my favorite.
>> That's the grouping. And the grouping we can either do a sort
to group or we can use that hash operation in order to sort that.
And apparently we decided to use a hash match rather than a sort,
which is typically...
which is definitely more efficient. Now, when you see a hash
match aggregate, that's typically an indication that you don't
have the right index in place.
And just like Brian mentioned, if you create perfect indexes
for all queries, you'll end up with index sprawl. And if you
have a hundred indexes on a table, that means that table is actually
a 101 tables, right. So if you do an insert, it's 101 inserts.
So that can be costly, right?
>> And then we apparently do the sort, the order by total at the end.
So we even get a suggestion here from the engine saying, hey,
what if you create this index. And you can actually right click
and say give me the missing index details and we can just go
and create that. But let's...
let's look at this in a bit more detail. So we'll turn on the
statistics I/O. That's typically the most interesting one to
look at, because the I/O used is independent of the locks that
happened during the execution and how busy the server is.
And rather than statistics time which obviously depends a lot
on how busy CPU is and so on and locking all of that. So I'll
execute this again. We'll look at messages. And it tells me
per table how much work we did. And we can see here that we looked
at index 1 and we scanned it once. During those one scans, we
read 1494 pages, which are 8K units, from memory. So if it said,
you know, 10 here, that's during those 10 iterations through
the table, the total was 1494.
And then physical reads is out of those 1494 how many did I have
to go to disk to fetch. And it makes sense that these are in
memory since we just created the table, right?
And then we have some more detail later, which type of lookups
we did.
But basically the fewer of these the better. That's the general
rule of thumb. So let's say that, okay, this one was actually
this many pages and we had a table scan and we had a hash thing
give in there and hash aggregate and we also... that's enough.
We will indicate that this is not perfect, right? So what you're
interested in when you look at the execution plan is typically
a smaller plan is better, fewer steps, that kind of makes sense.
Thinner arrows are better, less values move between. And you
want to avoid things that seem to use...
touch a lot of data, so scans generally are not the best.
And this hash operations are costly because we're putting lots
of stuff into memory in order to probe the results, probe the
hash table. So let's say, okay, let's create an index on this database.
So we'll create a cluster index first, just to see what that
would happen.
So the
clustered index, I can specify up to 16 or always with indexes
I can specify up to 16 columns in the key. The key can't be
larger than 16 columns or 900 bytes wide. And the clustered
index is sorting the actual table. So you're basically sorting
the table and then you're adding a balanced tree structure on
top of the table. And the logical query processing is typically
what you're after. What has to happen first is where, so we probably
want to create... use the special offer ID as the first column
in the index.
Now, let's just
do this as the example.
Create the index
and then run the query and see if there is a difference. So now
we see, ah, there is a cluster index seek that happens instead.
It takes the rows goes to the next place, it calculates unit
price times order quantity. That's the hash match scale and then
the sort. And now we ended up touching, oh, more pages.
Well, what's going on. Well, apparently special offer ID is pretty
big right so when we restructured the table we were unlucky in
a sense that we actually ended up using more space.
So that was obviously perfectly rehearsed. Let's do special
offer ID 2 and let's drop the index and try again.
See if
Tobia's fat finger again... okay. So 1592. So dropping the
index obviously is not like we two and move everything around
again, we just drop that balanced tree structure. So okay.
Now... is it
the same amount of rows?
>> Yes, I think it was.
>> Oh, sorry, sorry. It's a table scan. I'm...
>> Yeah.
>> It's getting late here. Okay. 159 pages. Table scan hash
aggregate -inaudible-.
Okay, now we create the clustered index.
Do this again, special offer ID 2 is hopefully a little bit smaller
than 1.
And, yay.
>> Yeah, 48.
>> 48 logical reads.
>> Nice.
>> Now we can go home.
>> Yeah. Now we're up.
>> Okay. So 48 pages and we see this is an index seek. And that
basically means we're using the balanced tree structure to work
it down, to find the right place in the index and then just follow
the linked list until we find special offer ID not 2 anymore, 3.
But we still have a hash aggregate. So I'll probably say this
is great. But let's just say it's okay.
Now I want to show the problem with the clustered index is that
we can create only one, because we're structuring the table itself.
So let's say we already had a good clustered index and we can't
create another one. So let's say that there is already a clustered
index on...
let's say there
is already a clustered index on...
dadadada, okay.
On sales order ID which I'm not using in this query.
So that will... and this is the common thing that you'll find
when you optimize of course. There already is a clustered index
there and changing it you have to obviously look at what you're...
what problems you're creating. Okay. So this seems...
so now we're in this other space where we have to create nonclustered indexes.
And nonclustered index means basically take whatever columns
I ask to include, right, in the index and create a new table,
shove all of the data in there, but only those columns and add
a pointer back to the table. And they're a little bit different
types of pointers you can read up on later. But put those in
that separate table, build the balance tree structure, and now
you allow to query optimizer to pick that index as well.
And you can imagine if you create a hundred of those, you have
a 101 tables, right, like I mentioned before.
So we have the new... this new index.
And it's now clustered index, it's not on the right column anymore,
right, it's on not special offer ID. So we're back to having
a clustered index scan, which is the same as a table scan.
So I'm scanning the clustered index, which is the table, right,
it's just a sorted table. So and
we're getting to this 1574 pages. So let's just pretend it's
the same as this. So I want to improve on this. I'm go ahead
and create a known clustered index.
And you can have up to 249 known clustered indexes on a table.
But you probably don't want that.
And I want to have this index on special offer ID.
Which is basically the same as before. Now, what happens is
we take just special offer ID, copy that to a new table, sort
it, create this balance tree structure and have the pointers back.
Create that index. And let's run the query. Hmm. Still at 1574.
Well, that's odd. What's going on?
So aha. Still doing the clustered index scan. Oh. So the query
optimizer didn't notice it was this great index there. I can
go and force the index to be used instead.
So we'll say with index... and this is typically something that
you do mostly for testing
at the index hints. So basically when you access this table,
I want you to go through the physical structure
NC IDX, the nonclustered index I created.
So now I know better than the query optimizer, so I'm telling
it, boss, you have it all wrong, let's do it this way instead.
And now the execution plan looks like this. We seek the index.
So we go to this other structure. We find special offer ID 2.
But for every row I have to go and fetch unit price, order quantity,
and sales order ID because those don't exist in the table.
Actually, sales order ID happens to be the pointer in this case.
But at any rate, logically, you are to go and fetch this from
the base table. So now for every row in the... that we're returning,
you have to go and fetch from the base table which becomes a
lot of I/Os, right? So now
we're actually using 10570 I/Os. And you're doing a join here
between these two tables in essence behind the scenes. So, wow,
that's table... that's basically index seek plus lookup to get
the rest of the mid callers that were not in the index.
And then apparently we could do the aggregate immediately.
And then this is super bad obviously. We made it worse.
So let's see what could we do instead.
Well, we don't obviously want to have to do these lookups.
So I'll say, well, special offer ID I want in there and I want
to include...
and I'll just move the clustered index to another column to make
another point, so let's just put the clustered index on order quantity.
There we two. And obviously when I rebuilt the cluster index
I have to rebuild the noncluster index. So now we want to improve
on this, so we say special offer ID, it's the index, and I can
also choose to include additional columns in the index just to
avoid these lookup. So I say, well, I need sales order ID in
there because I group by sales order ID and I need unit price
and order quantity in there. If I have all of those, it shouldn't
need to do the join down back to the base table.
So I'll go ahead and recreate the table... the index.
So again it sorts based on special offer ID and just then adds
into the index these other columns.
Now, when I go execute that, I get 17 logical reads. It sounds
better, right?
And if you go and look in the execution plan now, it's clearly
just a seek, computes the scaler aggregate, then we have a sort.
And if you look at the coast estimate here, that's where we're
spending a lot of the cost of the query. So we're sorting on
sales order ID because of the grouping. So apparently the optimizer
came to the conclusion that this is a small enough set, it makes
sense to sort rather than hash aggregates. So we have index seek.
We have sort for group, grouping.
And this is already good. We went from 1,500 logical reads or
pages down to 17.
But let's see if we can do better. So what we can do is if we
wanted to sort this on special offer ID, that's the where clause,
the next thing that's going to happen is the grouping. So if
the index is already grouped or ordered on sales order ID, since
that's what I group on, I want...
I won't need to do the sort operation.
So I recreate the index.
And I go and run the query again.
And now still 17 logical reads because it's the same amount of
data I need to touch, but you can see that the sort operation
disappeared, the first one, right, because the grouping you can
just go and do the stream aggregate. We know that it's already
sorted, so we just go and do the calculation. And then we have
the last sort, which we need, because we want to sort...
the presentation to be ordered this way. So now you can argue
this is kind of the perfect plan for this particular query.
So 17 pages, index sort, and then no sort for the grouping, and
this is, wee, super, super happy. So obviously if the query
runs, you execute this all the time, it's a good idea to create
the right index. If you execute it some of the time, you know,
at some point you'll have to think about this index sprawl business.
But this kind of gives you an insight into what you need to do
in order to get the best performance out of your queries.
>> All right. Fantastic demo to wrap up this module here.
We're just going to do a little brief summary here. We talked
about system catalog views and way for us to review that content
or access that content. Information schema views. We also have
some store procedures, system stored procedures. But as we pointed
out, you want to try to take advantage of the system catalog
views as well as the information schema views to retrieve information
and the dynamic management views, or the DMVs. We told you...
showed you how to create a store procedure and how to include
passing the parameters into a stored procedure, so you can reuse
that stored procedure and be able to retrieve information based
on different value use that you're passing in. Writing...
we talked about ways to improve performance with your queries
by avoiding certain things like cursors and only specifying the
columns that you really want returned versus all the columns
using a where clause versus no where clause is going to return
all the rows. And we looked at the ways for us to monitor the
performance of a query and with the excellent demo that we did
with the Tobias did, actually, with the query plans, how we can
use those execution plans to view the content and understand
if to... if there's better ways for us to be able to access this content.
And as you saw, we tried three or four different iterative approaches
before we found the best solution for that query or for that index.
So what we did today is we went through an introduction to SQL
Server, we talked about the different types of statements and
introduced the basic select statement and other statement elements.
We went into advanced select statements. We introduced distinct,
aliases, scalar functions and case, talked about joins and merges,
how to filter and sort your data. Talked about the different
data types, the date time data type, the character data type.
Also understanding SQL Server function types are available to
provide information back to you. We looked at ways for grouping
and aggregating data. We used the group by and having clause.
We introduce subqueries and how those can be used, the exist clause.
We talked about the inline and the derived table tables that
are available to us. We actually broke for some food somewhere
in the middle, so we took a meal break today, which was good,
all needed. And then we talked about the set operators and how
we can use the grouping sets like pivot and cube and roll up.
We went into ways for inserting updating and deleting data.
Talked about the use of default constraints and triggers to ensure
that data we're adding is validated or good data we'll use and
to avoid the garbage in/garbage out. We talked about programming
with SQL Server and how to implement error handling and understood
and also introduced the idea of transactions, how beneficial
and how they could be required depending on the type of data.
Obviously the banking industry does require the use of transactions.
And we've wrapped up with retrieving SQL Server metadata, improving
query performance by querying system catalogs in DMVs and looking
at creating and executing stored procedures and then how you
can improve SQL Server query performance by using those execution plans.
So on behalf of everyone here at MVA as well as Tobias and myself,
it was a pleasure working with you. We would like to thank you
very much for joining us. We would like to ask you as well to
look at the poll at the bottom of the screen. If you take a
few moments to complete that, we would greatly appreciate it.
And we appreciate you joining us and we look forward to seeing
you in a future MVA class. Thanks very much.
>> Thanks a lot, everyone.