[Music]
>> Welcome back, folks.
Thanks for joining Tobias and myself as we walk you through Querying
SQL Server 2012 and trying to show you some cool little tips
and tricks for getting the most out of your databases in SQL
Server 2012. We're going to move into another module here, so
we're going to be talking about aggregating or grouping and aggregating data.
We've gone through some... pretty much some fundamental, some
basic information about SQL Server, we're talking kind of, again,
level the playing field. We've introduced some of the advanced
select statements. We talked about SQL Server data types in the
previous model and the importance of those as you're creating
your objects and understanding how they're going to be used.
What we're going to do now is looking at aggregate functions.
I call them aggravating because sometimes they can be that way.
Or and as well as grouping by or group by and having clauses.
We'll talk about subqueries, both all the self-contained, correlated
and exists. And we'll take a look at a view, creating a view.
And we'll look at some of these tables. We've had some questions
on inline tables and derived tables. We'll talk about that in
this section as well. So we're going to head right on into that
and have a conversation to begin with on aggregate functions.
And there's three categories of these functions. There's the
common ones that we'll see like the sum and the min, the max,
the average account. We have some of these statistical ones.
And for Friday the 13th I'm glad I was able to say that.
Standard deviation, for instance, and we have the var, the var
P, and we have some other ones like grouping and grouping ID
that are available for us as well. So we have these categories
of aggregate functions that we have available to us.
If we begin working with aggregate functions, they return a scalar
value with no column name. They're going to ignore nulls most
of the time with the exception of the count. They can be used
in the select statement, the having, and the order by clauses.
They're frequently used with the group by clause. And we have
an example of a select count, distinct sales order ID as unique
orders, and we have average unit price as a column name.
Minute... or minimum order quantity. And we have maximum line
total for a particular line item. And we're retrieving this
information from the sales order detail table. And as you can
see an example on the results are in the bottom here where we
have 31,465 unique orders. The average unit price is $465.
We're getting that from the average there. The minimum order
quantity is 1. I would hope there not be a detailed line order
detail for 0 order quantity, so I was glad to see that as 1.
And then we did a max line total is 27,893.619000.
So we did get a retrievalable of content from... and this contains
four aggregate functions within one statement which makes it
nice so we can summarize that content and kind of give us a display
instead of looking at 31,000 records plus to determine what's
going on with the number of items in those... in that details table.
The distinct clause, we talked about that. We've introduced
that a couple times with aggregate functions, provide you that
summary of information.
It aggregates, but during the aggregation it eliminates those
duplicate values, not rows, but it eliminates the information
that would be normally provided. And we have an example here again.
We're doing a count on distinct customer ID and we're using that
information and then returning information about the salesperson
ID, the order year, the all customers, and any unique customers.
So we're trying to find out per salesperson how many customers
they have as a whole and per year how many unique customers they had.
So this is what this... the query will do for you with this aggregate
function used in the distinct clause.
>> Okay. I'd like to just throw something here to kind of disambiguate
a little bit between the various things you can use. And again
I apologize for
what my...
>> Your monitor freaking out on you?
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> It's like come back.
>> I logged out and then it was all fine.
>> Okay.
>> So just looking at this distinct and aggregates and group by,
so let's say I just get all orders.
Right? There we go. Now I want to get...
let's say what I want to get is I want to get really maximum
of one order per customer. So I'm interested in this distinct
thing per customer. So I try and just calculate it. So I'll
just do count, distinct
customer ID. So now we'll know, okay, this is how many customers
are referenced in this table. Okay. So 19,000 something.
What if I now want to have 19,000 rows returned but I only...
but I want the... so one order per customer.
>> Right.
>> But I also want other information. So I can try and do group
by and let's say, okay, give me customer... give me everything
and I want to group this by customer ID.
Well, this doesn't... doesn't make a lot of sense, right?
Because now you're saying calculate some aggregate for every customer.
So I'm expecting to get one row back per customer but we're returning details.
Right? We're not using aggregates. So I could then say, okay,
give me just customer ID back.
And now I'll get just a customer ID and I can say use an aggregate
like com star or something to get the number of rows. But I
want the details in this case.
If I try and use distinct over this, then obviously do distinct
over the entire row.
What I can do is use this row number thing that's very interesting
for this problem. So, again, what I'm after is give me one order
per customer back. So basically the first or last order for every customer.
But I want all of the order details.
So I'll say select star from sales order header, and I'll say,
okay, please calculate now the row number
over partition by
customer ID. So basically start counting again when it's a new
customer ID. And order by... let's say I want the newest orders,
so I want the latest order for the customer...
>> Right....
>> as row number.
Okay? So this would just execute and calculate the row numbers
for me. Now, what if I just want to have now the first for every
order, you would say something like, well, give me where because
I know I can't say where RN because that's not defined yet.
Right? So I'll say, okay, where row number blah is equal to 1,
well, get me an error back.
>> Yeah.
>> Why? Well, because row number in all of these ranking functions
and aggregate... or, sorry, all of these ranking functions, they
are calculated at select time. Right? So in the workloads, we
have no idea what this row number means because obviously if
I change the where clause and if I say where...
oohh. Fat fingers.
>> Felt that one.
>> If I now say saves order ID is less than a thousand, that would
be part of the query and now the row numbers change, right?
They're based on this number. So what I can do instead is I can
say select start from this set and
now RN exists, right? So now I can say where RN is equal to 1.
So what does this mean? Well, it means get me all of the orders,
calculate the row number for each order per customer, right,
and then give me only the first. So this means give me only
the first order for every customer.
And now I should get this number we can see down here in the
lower right-hand corner, 19,119 rows back.
>> Right.
>> So that's an interesting thing from this.
One is using window functions, row numbers in this case as well
as what does this thing mean and what can you accomplish.
So it very much depends on what you're after, if you want to
use distinct, count distinction, or something such as row number
to grab the latest orders. Let's say I wanted to get all orders
that are made in the same day. Now, row number... if they're
made in the same day, they'll get different row numbers, right,
1 and then 2, 3, 4, even if they have the same value and randomly
in the order we find them. But if I would say rank, now I would
get multiple orders... rows because I'll get for every...
all of the orders that have the same order date they will come
back with the same rank. So rank 1 can now be multiple orders.
And in this case... let's see if there's this case. Yeah.
So now I got a few of them are on the same day.
>> Yeah.
>> So 19,127 rows back.
>> Very cool.
All right. So we get the group by and having clause that we're
going to be working with. And this is going to be kind of...
again, we're working with the aggregate functions and ways for
us to create summary data and get that summary data. So we're
going to continue on talking about the group by and the having.
Having, select, and order by must... they must return a single
value per group. All columns in this select, having, order by
have to appear in the group by clause. So you have to be aware
of that. If you're going to use a column in the group by clause,
it's got... or in the... yeah. If you're going to use a column
in the group by clause, it has to appear in the select, having,
or order by.
So it has to have appeared up there already. With the logical
order, we've gone through this already, we've seen this a couple
times on the how the statement is actually processed, the from,
then the where, the group by, the having, back up to the select
and then order by being last. It's very, very important for you
to understand that. If you're using the group by, all the subsequent
phases operate on that group, not the source row. So it's going
to work on the group information. And that's why that order
is important to understand here. This one here is actually just
getting a count. It's going to display it as a count as the header
for it. And we're going to group by customer ID. So we're trying
to see how many customers that we have, we're going to group
by customer ID. And then the second statement here, the aggregate
function is going to refer to any columns, not just those in
the group by clause. So we're going to select product ID, max
order quantity as the largest order. So when we run this, we're
going to group it by product ID. So for each product ID we're
going to see the maximum number of items ordered per product.
So this allows us to use that max aggregate function to be able
to return that content to us.
The having clause provides a search condition that every group
in the group by clause must meet. And this is processed after
the group by. So what we're going to do is we're going to select
customer ID and we're going to do a count as count orders from
the sales order header table. We're going to group by customer ID.
And then we're going to say, oh, all those that are group by
customer ID, once that group is created for each customer ID,
having a count greater than 10, so if we have less than 10 we
don't want to really see much about that customer, we want to
see only those items that are returned to us, those rows returned
to us in those groups, that are greater than 10. So we'll do
a count on those customer IDs that are returned to us and then
we'll return the result set with those items that have more than
10 in that count return... the count orders field to be more
specific here.
If I want to compare... so we talked... the having and the where
are similar, but what's... I want to compare the two. The where
filters rows before the groups are created. The having filters
are rows which controls how the groups are going to be passed
to the next logical phase. So if we look at this, we're going
to use a count expression in the having clause. And this is
going to be useful to really provide a solution for common business problems.
Because this is going to show only customers that have placed
more than one order. So in this case here we're doing a select
customer ID, we're going to do a count on that from the sales
customer as customer. And then we're going to join that table
and we're going to join that table to the sales order header.
Then we're going to give it a table name, an alias. And then
we're going to group by customer ID, but then, again, we want
to only see the content where a customer has placed. We're going
to see content for multiple columns, but we're going to see only
the rows returned to us where a customer has more than one order
that's been placed. So that's going to give us a situation to
find who our repeat customers are. We could even take it up
a notch and say I happen to have an account with more than equal
to 10 customers. So again we're trying to see maybe at this point
who our more popular customers are, our busier customers are,
and we'll get that information returned to us by taking advantage
of some of these statements that we're showing here.
So the group by and having clause, is there another... we kind
of just did that one. Is there another demo on the group by and
having we want to take a peek at? That's... I mean, the last
one was pretty cool.
If there's anything specific that you wanted to show us. If not,
we'll just move on.
>> No, I think we're fine.
>> Okay. We're good. All right. Let's talk subquery.
Subqueries could often be a little bit confusing because you're
looking at the query within a query. So with the subqueries
we have to be careful and aware of how they work, and there's
a few different flavors of subqueries that we have associated
with this. So the really nasty queries, so as I mentioned queries
within queries, the results from the nested query are passed
to the outer query. So the inner query acts like an expression
that's going to be returned and used by the outer query.
The subqueries can be self-contained or correlated where self-contained
has no dependency on the out query, outer query. The correlated
subqueries depend on the values from the outer queries.
Subqueries can be either scale or multi... multi-valued or table valued.
So we'll take a look at a scalar subquery here. We're going
to do a select order ID, product ID, unit price, order quantity.
From, the orders detail.
Where, the sales order ID equal. Now we're going to use the
subquery select max sales order ID. And we'll return that in
the column called last order. And we're going to get this information
from the sales order header. So what this is going to do, it's
going to query the sales order header, it's going to look for
the max... aggregate function max for a sales order ID. And it's
going to return that as the last order.
And we're going to go see what information on the last order
that was just processed.
And as you can see from... so additional information, if the
interquery returns an empty set, the results can be converted
to null. And the construction of the outer query determines whether
the inner query is going to return that single value. So we
actually have that with sales order ID, product ID, unit price
and order quantity. Where, sales order ID equal. And then we
have the subquery which is going to return and determine what
that sales order ID is so it can process that order ID.
Now, with multi-valued subqueries... this one's a little off
keel here... the multi-valued subquery returns multiple values
as a single column set. So what we're going to do is we're going
to use the in clause here. We're going to go and query the sales
order header.
We're customer ID in. Well, in what? Well, we're going to perform
another select statement. Select customer ID from sales.customer
where territory ID equal 10. So now we're going to return content
or the outer query will be performed based on the idea of what
customer ID or territory ID equal 10. So it's going to return
that content for us or perform that query for us based on that subquery.
The keyword exist also could be used or not exist as you can
see here. This is select customer ID and person ID. From, the
sales customer. And we're going to rename that as cust.
Where, exist.
What exists? Well, we're going to do a select asterisk, so we
can't use column names when we're using the exist. We have to
use the actual... the asterisk or return all columns. From, sales.salesorderheader
as ord, so for order. Where, cust.customer ID equal order.customer ID.
So we're going to do a match on customer ID from the two tables
in the subquery. If it exists, then we're going to return that
content to the outer query and that content will be displayed.
The customer ID specifically and a person ID will display it
that way. And we're going to flip that around and do a not exist
as well.
And both of these will provide us information regarding the exist
or regarding the content that's returned from within that query
or that subquery. All right. Demo using subqueries.
Let's jump out here and take a look at just a couple of those
items that we just looked at.
We'll jump back into SQL Management Studio.
Module 4. I've got to close this out here.
And let's open up one of my other items here.
And so here's a couple items here. So this uses that...
the one that's shown that uses several of those different, it
has the count, the average, the min and max, so we can execute
that here, and you'll see it comes back with unique orders, 31,465
average price. Min order quantity is 1. And the max line total
for a particular order was 27,893.
This one will return the all customers and unique customers for
a salesperson. We saw the... we saw the text for it or the command
for it. I just want to execute it so you see the results for it.
So salesperson ID, we have a few null values. But salesperson
ID 274 in the year 2007 had 14 customers; 13 of them were unique.
2006 had 20 customers; all of them were unique. And same with
2008 and 2005. And, again, we order these by salesperson ID so
we can see how each salesperson is doing.
This here shows us a count of all customers and then sorts them
by salesperson.
So we'll execute that. Here's the salesperson ID. So salesperson
ID 274 has 48 total customers. 275 has 450 total customers.
So this kind of gives us a quick count on how our salespeople
are doing and we can compare that to taking a look at the number
of customers that they have.
Here's the group by the having clause that we saw an example of.
We'll go ahead and execute that. Here's the customer ID.
And we're ordering it by count orders instead, so customer ID
11091 has 20 orders that we have and we're just doing the count.
And we're only looking for those items greater than 10.
Again, we're looking for our most... our more popular customers,
the ones that have at least 10 orders in this particular situation
right here.
Here's the information, returns information about the last order
that was submitted. We saw the query for this. We're going to
execute this now.
And they're saying the sales order ID 75123 was the last order
that was submitted. There were three products that it ordered.
The unit price of each of them was 21.98, 159, and 8.99, and
they ordered one item. So this is the last order that was submitted by...
with... and the sales order ID was 75123. They ordered three
different products. The price for those products and the quantity
of those products that they ordered. Didn't spend a lot of money
there unfortunately.
This one's going to return all the sales orders for each customer
in territory 10. So now we're going to narrow it down to a specific territory.
We want to see what's going on in a specific territory maybe
with a sales manager in that territory.
So customer ID 20042 has a sales order ID, 43708. Supposed to
return information. We could add additional information here.
Notice it's returning 3200 rows.
And so this would give us information about... specifically about
a territory. In this case here, territory ID No. 10, we're going
to look at each customer and each sales order ID associated with
each customer to find out what kind of activity is taking place
in territory No. 10 and only in territory No. 10. And, again,
we could have swapped that out and used additional territories
by changing that clause up there.
This is going to display the person ID for every customer who
has placed an order. This is that exist clause. And we'll go
ahead and execute that. So customer ID 1100, the person ID was 13531.
So every person, this is the person ID associated with the customer
ID for each customer that has placed an order. The exists as
and order had to be placed. So a record has to exist in the sales
order header number... or table in order for them to be returned here.
And you'll see we have 19,000 rows available for that.
And that's getting ahead to the next section. So this is different
ways for us to be able to query content. Specifically we're
trying to use content that is a subquery.
>> Oh, Brian, Brian, Brian. Can I show a demo?
>> Yes, absolutely you could show a demo. In fact, the demo slide's
up just for you.
>> Oh. Wonderful. Okay. So I was just sitting here tinkering and
thinking, so I thought maybe we should show something.
>> That'd be nice.
>> And also looking at the... some questions being asked. So I
wanted to just show this example of derived table and what we
also call common table expressions that can be super useful.
So actually let's just take the example that I showed before
with row number. So we can just start with that and just copy
this thing over. So, again, this is called derived table.
So basically it's a set that you query from. So you use the
subquery in the from clause or the join clause for that matter.
So you can say select from a table inner join, left join, derive table.
That works perfectly.
And in this case this was practical for us to figure out the...
get us these orders based on
the first order for each customer. There is another way of writing
this, which is also very useful, which is using a common table expression.
But the problem a little bit with this is if you write a big
query, now you can imagine how it can look something...
something like this, right?
>> Pretty complex.
>> Exactly. So if you're trying to make sense of it, that can
be somewhat tricky, right? So instead of doing that, you can
use this common table expression thing. So in that you declare
these views, if you will, or derive tables or common table expressions first.
So I can say with A as, this is my set called A, and I can just
copy this, then... this thing in there, and now I have A available
to me. And then I can do my select star from A. And where?
Row number's equal to 1 or rank in this case since I'm using rank.
And it's exactly the same thing. There's no performance difference
or anything like that. But you can imagine now if I have a lot
of these, right,
you would have something that looks like this. And with commas
up here just separating the sets, now my query itself is pretty simple.
I would, okay, I will join, you know, A with B or something and
then I will do left to go in this with this other thing. So becomes
a lot easier to follow the logic of the query if you write it
like this rather than as a derive table.
And so let me show you an example also of this with group by.
So let's say I want to
calculate just orders...
number of orders per customer, this very simple thing. So customer
ID comma sum... or, sorry, just count star. So just number of
orders per customer.
Sales order header.
Group by customer ID. Okay. So I have this query.
Now let's say I want to do something actually a little bit different.
Instead of using customer ID, I would like these grouped by
a calculation instead.
So tie these together. So this is something I typically do is
I often forget what the columns are. So I can just do this and
now I'll easily find the column. So let's say we say, okay,
status 5 is okay and all other statuses address are not okay.
So in that case I'll say something like case when status is equal
to 5, then I want to return okay.
Else I'll say not okay.
Right? End as status.
And since this is grouped by, I now need to go and group by exactly
this full clause, right?
So I need to put that there as well.
Because, again, this column alias status isn't available in the
group by clause because this is really what we're typing, right?
Logically we're starting from then comes group by and then select.
So I'll go and execute this.
You can see it works nice... well, okay, we don't have anything locked.
This status seems super useful, so let's not use that.
Let's use revision number instead just for the example.
Okay. Oh, sorry, is equal to 3. Ah. There we go. Okay and sum
not okay. Now, this is officially somewhat irritating that you
are to repeat the case expression.
But with a derived table... common table expression I don't need to.
I can say with A as I define the expression
and then
I don't have the count here anymore. This is just my...
this is the full set that I need, right, so I can do a select
star from A,
which works fine. I get all of the rows back. And now...
obviously now status is a normal column. Right? So now I can
just say, okay, from a group by status, and I would like to get
the status and I want the count.
And now this works fine. Right? So these common table expressions
or derived tables can greatly help you simplify your queries.
Now you may ask, oh, isn't this less performant because clearly
we'll generate this full set and then you'll go ahead and basically
do the calculation on top of this. So what we do in the query
optimization is we... one of the big first steps we do is flatten
the query. So it's not always the case, but, typically, however
you write it through a view derived tabled common table expression,
when it hits the query optimizer, it's just like the flat query
that you would have written directly against the table with none
of these. So they shouldn't actually affect performance.
>> All right. Excellent. Thanks very much, Tobias, for explaining
that for us. We're going to talk about some table functions and
focus just on some of the details on using table functions.
We're going to begin by talking about a sample view. And this
is very simple. And, remember, a view is not an object that's
stored in a database. It's role in object at... it's a query object.
So when I go out and execute a statement, a select statement
against a view, it's actually grabbing the information or retrieving
the information from underlying tables as through this view.
So we're going to create the view called humanresource.employee
list as we're going to select four rows or four columns from
the humanresources.employee, and then we can turn around and
do a select asterisk from that employee list. So now I've got
a view and I can restrict the view. So I may have 15, 20 columns
in the employee lists, and there's probably only four or five
I want some of my... or some individuals to see. But what I
can do is create a view, give them permission to access the view,
and the view will only return that content to them or those four
rows that they have permissions that are displayed in the view
that they have permissions to see. Now, this is showing an example
of creating a view with just one underlying table. You could
actually create a view with multiple underlying tables. We could
use join statement and get information from the employee list
and the employee address list if we wanted to. Or employee list,
we want to see how many employees are also customers, have bought
some of our product. So we could actually use a join statement
here to make this a little bit more complex. But this view here
is just going to take four columns from our employee...
from our employee table and create a view of them. Now I can
get permissions to individuals to access the view without giving
them permissions to access the other columns within that...
within that underlying table. And, again, I could add additional
columns from other tables to ensure that my users are seeing...
are able to see additional content in this view. And, again,
they're not stored... it's not stored as an object, it's more
of a query object here. The table value functions are created
by administrators and developers. We can create a name, a function,
using a create function here. We're creating a function here
for a line total. We're going to pass a parameter called sales
order ID. Notice that's what unique about this, it returns a
type called table. So instead of a scalar function or a value
or a group of values be returned, this actually returns a table.
And then it uses as return, and there's a select statement in
there, and it's going to actually use the cast to do a conversion
and then it's going to create a field as decimal 8 comma 2, and
it's going to grab the information sales order detail.
Where, the sales order ID equal the path's variable, whatever
we passed in for the sales order ID. So it's going to match
it up and it's going to execute or perform this function based
on the sales order ID and compare that in that where clause to
perform that function.
Derive tables are name query expressions created with an outer
select statement. I think we just saw a good idea of those.
Derived tables must have an alias, have names for all columns...
every column has to have a name... have unique names for every
column, are not used in an order by clause, and cannot be referred
to multiple times in the same query. So a few ideas about how
derived tables are used. They may be internal or external aliases
or use internal or external aliases, they may refer to parameters
and/or variables, and they may be nested within other derived tables.
So there's some restrictions and there's some limitations or
limitations that you can be... you should be aware of when you're
looking at the use of these derived tables. We can pass arguments
to derived tables. We're going to declare a variable here called
emp ID of int time with 9. We're going to select order year.
We're going to do a count distinct as customer count. And then
we're going to perform the query. Select year as order date.
And then... or select year... a portion of the order date as
order year, customer ID, from the sales order table where emp
ID equal to past emp ID with a declared variable. And we're
going to set this up as a derived year. And then we're going
to group this by order year. And this will give us information
about the order year on the distinct customer IDs and the number
of items that customers purchase for a particular year. And we're
going to pass the ID of that customer in as a variable when we
run this... or use this derived table.
Now, the CTEs, or common table expressions, we just got a nice
demo from Tobias on this. With CTE year as. We're going to select
a year order date as order year, customer ID. And then we're
going to go in, we're going to do a select order year with a
count distinct customer ID as customer count. From the CTE year,
which is what we decided... what we define, excuse me, with the
with clause. And then we're going to group by the order year.
So this allows us... and, again, this is the demo, this is an
example of what Tobias just demoed for us just a few moments ago.
Are there any other functions that you're interested in demoing
in this particular module?
>> I can go ahead and demo just the table valued functions.
>> Okay.
>> And talk a little bit about that. So basically why would you
use a view versus a table valued function. And there are two
types of table valued functions. There are the inline table
valued that we shown on the slide, and you can also do multistatement
table valued functions, which are a little bit more complex and
you can use for somewhat different types of problems. But typically
the table valued function, it's just a view. It's a view that
takes parameters, really nothing else. So it's useful for you
if you want to force queries to look a certain way. And it's
fairly common that you want to say, well, if you search this
table you really should search on dates because I have an index
on dates.
So as an example, we may say, okay, we want a function or a view
that gives us just total purchases per customer, let's say.
So let's just call this sales.fn
customer sales.
And we require you to take start date
and end or pass and end date as parameters.
We'll use the data type date. And returns table. Now, again,
returns table doesn't mean we create some sort of table in some
special way. It's no different from using a common table expression,
a derived table or a view.
As return and then we have this query. And originally this is
now stored in metadata, so that's the big difference from using
the inline to the CT or the derived table that now you have stored
this so you can reuse it as much as you want. So we'll just
do the simple thing of select customer ID...
or customer ID comma...
I think it's called company name.
And then just say some of something.
So from customer table, and then I'll do a left outer join.
Because I want to include also customers that didn't buy anything.
Sales.sales order header
on sales order header...
sorry, customer ID is equal to customer ID in the customer's table.
And then I want to go and continue running into the sales order
detail table to get the actual prize.
So where sales order ID is equal to sales order ID. And then
now I want to group this by the customer. So customer ID and
I want it to include, okay, let's say a count number as well.
And I want to sum the
unit price, let's just say, as a simple example. And I want...
if this happens to be... now, if we don't find... so if there
are no orders,
we'll get null returned, right, so the sum has nothing to sum up.
Something weird going on here. Okay. So I'll just say if this
returns null, I want to see a return as total sales.
So we go ahead and create this function. Oh, sorry. And then
we require this filtering. So where the order date
is greater than or equal to
my start date that I passed in, and order date is let's say less than...
just to make it easy, end date. So end date is exclusive in this
case, just for simplicity.
So now obviously I force whoever is querying my function to go
and use the order... if I have an order date index, presumably
that can be used depending a little bit on what other indexes
I have on the other two tables. But I'll create the function.
Oops. Some unit price, oh, sales order ID. So it should be order date.
It's hard to compare an integer with the date.
So now we have the function, and now we can just go ahead and
query and say, well, I would like to get everything from here
and starting with 2011, January, and less than 2012, let's say.
Or 2013.
And there's nothing there, so let's go further back.
There we go. So just an example of using an inline table valued function.
>> How many keyboards do you go through in a week? A month?
>> Well, I'll use this... I'm actually...
>> I see that one smoking already. It's only been a few hours.
>> The big problem here is... so this is... someone asked about...
so this is... it's not integrated. It's part of... it's a separate keyboard.
But every time I go to Sweden I always buy a Swedish keyboard,
so I used to... I should have brought one here today, but I forgot.
>> Well, I'm glad you didn't. Because if you're typing that fast
on a U.S. keyboard, I can't imagine how fast you type on a Swede keyboard.
>> Yeah, and it will also be...
>> Fire extinguisher over by the keyboard?
>> Yeah. I would say not select, but it's [Speaking Swedish].
Yeah, it would be different.
>> Well, you're doing great. Definitely. My hands are getting
tired watching you type.
All right. So let's just go ahead and do just a little bit of
review for this module here. We introduce... so three of the
common built-in aggregate function categories, the common, the
statistical, and then the other category. We saw a demo on several
of these as we went through, especially under the common ones
on the other column. So we went through and saw some of these
examples of these. We also talked about more detail on the distinct clause.
We saw some information and detail about the group by and having clause.
And we get some really good information on the demos when we
did the scalar subqueries and multiple value subqueries.
And then Tobias rocked with the table valued functions and the
CTEs and the derived tables. Had some great... some demonstrations
on those as well.
And we also get to peek at how to create a function, one of these
table valued functions and how can we use the return type of
a table which is unique for something that we're... in comparison
to what we normally use. So this is going to wrap up Module 4.
And what we're going to do now is take a meal break. So here
in Washington it is almost... it's about quarter to 12:00, so
we'll return at about an hour from now. So we're going to take
60 minutes, depending on what time zone you are in the world,
60 minutes, roughly 60 minutes, 45 minutes past the next hour,
wherever you may be.
>> Wherever you are, it's still 60 minutes, right?
>> It's still 60 minutes no matter where you are. So it doesn't
matter where you are. It's always 60 minutes. So I don't know
what the time frame is going to be on your clock, but...
>> If it's not 60 minutes in Fahrenheit or there's something.
>> No, it's not that way.
>> No? Okay. Just checking.
>> Regular time. Thank goodness. So all right. So eat up, drink
up, recharge for this afternoon or remaining modules that we
have, because it may not be afternoon for you. We'll be back
in about 60 minutes, 45 minutes past the next hour, and we'll
continue on with our discussion. We still have four great modules
left for us to discuss later on today, and we look forward to
seeing you back here in about 60 minutes. Thank you for joining us.
>> Thank you.