[Music]
>> Okay. Welcome back. Tobias and I want to thank
you for spending some time with us today, and we want to continue
our discussion on querying, but I'm going to use that term loosely
for this module in SQL Server 2012. We've been talking about,
for five modules now, the idea of querying content. We're going
to kind of shift a little bit to talking a little bit about inserting
and updating data and how we can kind of protect that data as
we're inserting and updating that data. So we're going to look
here, inserts, updates, deletes. We're going to talk about the
use of defaults, constraints, and triggers. So one of the big
things that we want is we want to make sure that we're retrieving
content, and we've talked about several modules of how we're
going to do that, but we want to make sure we're adding content
that we understand that the old G/L, garbage in/garbage out.
So if you don't have things like constraints and we don't have
data integrity procedures in place, that when we retrieve content,
it may not be valid content. So we're going to look at ways for
inserting, updating, deleting content, validating that content
the best we can to make sure we've got good content that's going
in, so we do perform some of these tasks that we've been talking
about in the previous modules. We've got good stuff coming back
out, not garbage like we're so... like we had talked about.
So we want to avoid the garbage in/garbage out. We're going
to take a look at in this module here. What we've been talking
about are DD... DML statements. This should be DML, as well.
Let me see what this is. Yeah, this should be DML statements.
DML statements are data manipulation statements. So querying,
using a select team, it's a DML. This is also a DML. We're going
to talk about inserts and updates and deletes. DDL are statements
where we create objects or modify objects or alter objects.
So this should be DML instead of DDL, but we're going to talk
about DML statements, continue to talk about DML statements because
a select statement is a DML, as well. So let's take a look at
how we get content in there. So again, one of our concerns is
we want to avoid the garbage in, the garbage out, so we're going
to look at ways we can to do that. Now, we're going to add content.
This is a pretty straightforward insert into statement.
We're going to insert it into Production.UnitMeasure.
If we don't know the name of the columns or we don't want to
supply the name... or the values in any certain orders, we supply
the column names. So if we looked at the unit measure, there's
name, there's unit measure code, there's modified date. If I
did a select asterisk from unit measure, it's actually unit measure
code, then name, and modify date. That's actually how it's stored
in the content. But if we want to apply values to the columns,
they don't have to be in any certain order, as long as we include
the column headers. That's what we've done in the top example
right here. Now, another way we can add content is insert into.
So this is inserting just a basic row. And notice what we're
doing here. We're adding a value in the name column called square
yards and the unit measure code is Y2, and the modified date,
we're actually going to going to be retrieving the system date.
We could hard code a date in there, but we're actually retrieving
the system date. This is adding just a single row. We can add
multiple rows using a similar statement, but under values what
we're going to do is we're going to add multiple occurrences
of the value. Now we're adding square feet and square inches
and we're going to use F2 and I2 for inches. So this is the
squaring of those types of measurements here. So that's how
we can insert some of the data.
We can also use what's called an insert into the content, but
now instead of supplying the values, we're going to use the select statement.
So instead of insert select option, and what we're going to do
to populate this name and unit measure code and modify date,
we're going to select name, unit measure, code and modified date
from, we'll say, a temporary unit table that was... that exists
out there. So we're going to take the content using a select
statement and we're going to populate that into the unit measure
content table. Excuse me. And we don't have to grab everything.
Because we're using a select statement, we could say we only
want to insert the content from January 1st, 2008. The good
news about this class is I'm going to learn to understand these
time stamps in reverse order. That's my goal. So this is January
1st, 2008, and we're going to only add content that's less than that.
Anything older than that, we're not going to add that content.
So we still have control of what content gets added. The insert
into the execute statement, we're going to insert into these
three columns again, but this time, instead, we're going to execute
a store procedure and we're going to pass at some variables,
the numbers row five and the category ID of 1, and that's going
to execute our only insert content into this table that meets
the only five rows as long as category ID is equal to one.
So again, we're controlling what content that we're adding into
the tables, and that's a big deal, to make sure that we're not
adding that garbage in. We're going to also perform a select into.
Again, we're going to do a select name unit measure code and
modify date into. So now we're taking content into a temporary table.
So back a slide or two before I wanted to use a temporary table.
I could have created the temporary table from content that's
inside the unit measure table. I could do a select name and unit
measure code and modify date, which are columns within the unit
measure table right here, and I'm going to select them and insert
them into a new table called temp UOM table. And again, I'm
going to be specific about what contents ordered in there, are
populated in there because I'm going to put where order date
is before January 1st of 2008. So again, controlling what I'm
doing when I'm adding content in there. Now, one of the things
we may want to do is create what's called an identity column.
An identity column allows me to create a column that I don't
need to populate myself. I decide what items or what numbers
I want in there. So what I do is I created integer value. I think
we've got here... yeah, we've got product ID and identity, and
then we identify what's called the seed in the increment value.
By default it's one and one. So if I don't specify that, it's
one and one. So the very first row I insert is going to get product
ID number one. The second row is going to get number two.
The third row is going to get number three. And the US where
they use Fahrenheit or Celsius, the next row is going to be number four.
It doesn't really matter. But what you would you do differently
here is we can say we want the seed to start at 100 instead of
one, and instead of incrementing by one, we're going to increment
by ten. First row will be 100, then 110, then 120, then 130.
And then it's going to populate that information automatically
for me instead of me having to supply that identity column.
So it's a way for us to automatically generate a number and have
that number populated for me with me defining the increment value
and that seed value where I start with. Now, this is set up
on a table level. Another option is the sequences option.
This is new in SQL Server 2012. This allows me to create it for
the database, so this is going to create sequence called invoice
sequence as an integer, and here's my seed value. It starts
with five, and here's my increment value start with five or increment
by five. Excuse me. So wherever I use this invoice.suq, it's
going to start, the first row is going to be added as 5, the
next row will be ten, 15, 20, et cetera. And then if I want
to retrieve information and what's the last number that was used?
I can select next value for DBO.invoice sequence. So the last
number used was 25, the next value would be 30. If I'm quick
with math, I can do 25... 30 minus five is the 25. So this would
retrieve what the next value is going to be used that's going
to be populated using this sequences option, which, again, new
to 2012 and set up more instead of a table level like the identity,
it's set up at the database level.
Now, ways for us to modify content. We might store content in
SQL Server and realize, oops, I shouldn't have done it that way
or I need to change that. We have the update statement, all right?
Now, we're going to be careful about this. Update Production.UnitMeasure,
set modify date equal get the date... get date. Now, if I stopped
right there and just executed this statement, what have I just done?
I've actually updated every row in the unit measure column, table
to set the modify date to today's date. What I need to do is,
specifically be more careful about is making sure we supply a
where clause where unit measure code equal M2. Now it's going
to only go to that M2, to square miles row, and it's going to
set the modify date to today's date because we're using the system
value here, function to get today's date and populate that.
Again, be very cautious when you're doing update to make sure
you supply a where clause, unless you want every row to be updated.
Very similar to that, we have something, another way we can modify
date is called the merge. Now, this is where I can use a merge
to modify database on any of the following conditions.
Source matches the target, source has no match in a target, or
when the target has no match in a source. So this is a nice
way for us to be able to update content within a database.
>> Yes, I thought we'd do a bit of demo, just look at merge, and
we'll do somewhat of a stray thing to just show a bit of the
XML functionality we have as well in the product, because it
kind of fits nicely in this particular topic. So bear with me
a little bit so we get kind of an interesting example going.
>> We swapped out his keyboard, by the way, because the other
one burnt out, so he should be good to go for a little while.
>> Thank you, Brian.
>> Do you have carpal tunnel or anything, dude? I don't think
you have time for carpal tunnel. I think your nerves don't even...
>> Okay. So let's say that what I want to do is I want to retrieve
products in XML format. Then later I want to be able to grab
that XML being passed from the client and actually update a set
of products, update or insert a set of products based on this
XML definition. So I'll start with just simplifying the table
a little bit so it's not so complicated for me to just perform
the insert because it's so many columns in here. So I'll just
grab product ID, and let's say, name and that's going to be enough
for me. And I'll use this into keyword, and just to be clear,
earlier we had examples where the tables were called temp something.
They weren't necessarily temp tables, which is something differently,
or something different. So I'll just call this table just products.
So I'm just dealing these two columns and putting them in this table.
Now let's start by grabbing this ask XML. So I want to grab
all columns or all products, rather,
where the name starts with an A, let's say, as a filter. Okay.
Good. Three of them.
And I would like this again returned as XML, so I'll say for
XML, and the best... what you typically use is for XML path.
There's for XML row out to explicit and path, but path is the
more powerful one.
Now, why would you like to return anything as XML? It turns out
it's very practical format for interchange between systems.
So if you want to pass a set from SQL Server to something else,
XML is one of the good formats to use.
We get a common ask if we support JSON format, which we don't
do yet. Obviously you can convert XML into JSON and their version
on the client side.
So anyway, at any rate, I'll say, okay, grab me this and for
each row I want to generate an element called product, and I
want the root element, the root called, let's say, products.
So by default
for XML path and... the asterisk in there.
So now you can see I get some XML default back, and this is the
default structure I get back. So this you can see for every row
I get one of those and I get one of the... this root thing generated
as per my... for XML clause. And you can see by default I get
one element, called an element in XML for each column. But I
can call...
name them a bit differently to basically change the format.
So I'll call this one
ID, and the
@ sign means I would like it to be an attribute rather than an element.
And why I use these quotation marks is just because the @ sign
has a meaning in SQL, right? So it's a delimited identifier and
I want the name just like this. Why I make everything lower case
is by definition XML is case sensitive, so for me, at least,
it simplifies if everything is lower case.
And now the XML that I'm getting back looks like this.
Okay? So you can see it's actually...
>> Clean....
>> fairly simple to retrieve an XML document. You can do more
elaborate things with subqueries and create tree structures,
as well, but this kind of gets you started. So now we grab the data.
Now I want to look at what if I want to use this as a way to
insert new data into the table, or update data?
So let's say we're passing this back in through the server and
we actually have a data type called XML. So we'll say, okay,
this, which we support implicit casting to and from string.
So I pass this into the server, and let's add a new product.
And I don't know what ID it's going to get because there isn't
an identity in there, so let me actually just put it in. So 10,000,
100,000 Tobias. Okay. So this is a new one. And let's say we're
going to update this, so we'll add an exclamation mark at the
end of these three. So just seeing now I pass the string through
the server, it parses into an XML structure internally and then
I can go and query it.
So now we're doing the reverse. Before I generated XML from our
results at going from tabular to XML. Now I'm going doing the reverse.
So I'll do select star from my XML variable, and it has a few
methods to it, and nodes is one of the interesting ones. So basically,
say, hey, go and look for this X
path expression, which is kind of like select against the...
from a where clause made basically against an XML structure.
So basically this says for each product found on the product,
give me a row back. And we'll call this XT as... the set is
called XT and it will return one column which includes the XML
element which I will call XC, so the column. So now I can say,
okay, XT.XC.value,
and I can use this to go into the product element and grab things.
So I'll go and say, well, I would like to grab the ID attribute
and I would like you to grab this as an integer, and I'll call
this product ID.
And I would also like you to go into the
element and grab me the name attribute and return this as...
I don't know, NVARCHAR1000,
let's say,
as name.
So let's just go ahead and execute this and go ahead and just
comment out what I have above here. Okay. So again, I pass
in the structure. I say grab me each product element from products
and return this.
Ah, okay. Nice.
>> Nice.
>> I can now parse this XML nicely. And now I have a set.
So now, hmm, what if I could use the merge statement to actually
merge this data from the XML structure into the table. So I'll
say merge into
products, I guess the table was called ask this is the destination, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Using my XML variable, and now I would have to paste this whole
thing in there, but since we know about common table expressions,
I could just say, well, let's call this one source.
>> Or a source.
>> So now I have a common table expression called SRC. So I would
say using SRC,
so now I'm joining the table with my XML document on SRC.product
ID equals destination product ID.
And then I can start using these various events that we will
go through in the merge statement. So basically I can say when
I think it's not matched, so if
the product ID is not found in the destination, then I would
like to insert, obviously. So I'll say go ahead and insert into
obviously the destination, so I don't say anything other than
that column name, so product ID and name, the values, destination.product ID...
or sorry... source product ID,
comma, source name. Okay. So when it doesn't find it, it inserts,
and then when matched, I would like it to update.
So update the source set and product ID obviously can't change.
So set name equal to source product ID. And obviously I have...
no, that seems correct. Okay. Let's see if this works.
Oh, it is an identity.
>> Yes.
>> It is an identity column. Ah-ha. There we go. There we go.
Let's just not include the product ID then.
And let's not include it up in the XML either,
and there we go. So now it actually added these and we can go
and select, run the select statement from the table again for
the XML, to grab the XML and I'll say like A or name like Tobias.
TOB, so we get that row, as well.
And now you can see that the exclamation marks are in there and
Tobias was added.
The final thing I wanted to show, which gets it a bit extra interesting,
is we'll get... let's get the correct Tobias value in there.
So I got 1,000. Okay.
Cool. So ID equals 1,000.
Let's say I wanted to delete, as well. So let's say, okay, I
want to delete this AW see logo cap. How would I do this?
We have something support where you can say when not matched
in source. That's very dangerous because that means if it's not
in this set, then remove it.
>> Yeah.
>> Which obviously then would remove all our products. So what
I could do instead is I can add another attribute and say, call
it delete and I'll say delete equals true. So I would like to
delete this one.
We'll say we'll grab that from the XML document, as well.
I'll say, well, grab the delete field as a bit
and I'll call it do delete, test delete, or insert keyword.
So now I'm grabbing if it should be deleted or not, and I can
just say if it's not found, obviously will return null. So I'll
just say okay, if it doesn't... if it returns null, then we'll
say false, right?
And do delete.
And now I can say when matched, then this. When not matched, then...
sorry, when matched, and do delete equals one,
then delete, right? So I can actually have more complex expressions
in the one clause rather than just say matched or not matched.
Obviously the other one has to be the opposite, right? So we
should say here, well, if it's zero, then don't...
then update. So we'll go ahead and try and execute this.
Seems to work, right? So again, not watched, insert. Not matched
and do delete false update, or match, then do delete false update,
and then matched and do delete one, then delete. And now if
we query,
you can see that the row was deleted.
>> Yeah.
Nice.
>> So then you've got a bit of an entry in what you can do with
XML and SQL Server 2012, as well.
>> Very nice. Now, there are other ways that we can delete content
that's probably not quite as complicated as writing... if you're
not in the need for XML, we can use the delete statement. I know
it wasn't... it's not as fun and cool as what Tobias just did,
but we could just do a delete from the table and, again, very
critical, just like the update clause. If you don't have a where
clause, if I did a delete from Production.UnitMeasure, what am
I going to delete without a where clause? What's going to be deleted?
You got it. Everything. So we want to be clarify about that.
Pretty much whenever you use an update and a delete, you're going
to want to use a where clause just because you want to avoid
what I call RPEs, resume producing events. So you want to make
sure you don't get... have to generate a new resume because you
deleted 40,000 rows of really value information. So delete from
whatever the table is where unit measure equal and specify the
criteria that you want to meet in order for that row to be deleted.
Now, you may want to delete everything from a table. Now, one
way to do that is use this delete clause statement without a
where clause. Another way to do this... but if you do it this
way, by the way, this is logged in your transaction log. If you
use the truncate table to remove all data, we're going to truncate
the table. That means pretty much don't delete the table, but
take all of the data out of table. All right? And the good thing
about this, it's not going to write every row to the...
there's minimal logging for the information that's being written
to the transaction log, so it will go much faster if you have
40, 50, 60, 70,000 rows in there, it will be a little bit faster
for you to be able to delete that.
>> Especially let's say, you have...
>> A million....
>> 5 billion rows.
>> Yeah. A billion rows.
>> Definitely there will be a huge difference.
>> Aren't you supposed to go $5 billion or...
yeah. You probably don't know. What was that show?
>> Austin Powers.
>> I thought you were referencing Swedish shows.
>> Yeah, yeah. All right. So we did inserts, updates, deletes
with XML, just trying to see if there's anything here.
No, I think you got the cool stuff, especially with that merge.
So that's good.
Constraints and triggers. One of the things... so we looked
at adding content and making sure that we can add content several
different ways. Update the content, deleting the content.
But one of the things we need to be concerned about, as well,
is data integrity. So what we can use when we're adding content
are constraints and triggers. And what they can do for us is
to make sure that what we're adding is appropriate or valid,
and we can also make sure that if we're adding content or updating
content, that if there are other tables that need to be updated
as well, we can make sure those are updated. So we can create
four, five different types of constraints. We'll introduce each
one of those. And we can also use, implement what are called triggers.
So I could have an update trigger on the employee table. So on
the employee table, if I update the last name there, I'm going
to fire a trigger that's going to go out and also update the
accounts payable table or the accounts receivable or payroll table.
So anywhere that last name resides in my database, I can have
it go out using a trigger and update every column that needs
to be updated for that last name. So that's the idea of a DML
trigger where I'm doing data manipulation and I'm going to use triggers.
Let's talk about our constraints. We have a primary key constraint.
This is very, very important when you're designing your database
and your rows, your tables within the database. What this does
for you is it ensures that you have uniqueness on that table.
Pretty much every table you're going use in relational database
will have a primary key on it, and that primary key is going
to enforce uniqueness. Now, one of the chats came in earlier
was like, well, does the primary key have to be a composite key
or can a composite key be a primary key? A composite key is a
key that contains two or more columns. So absolutely a primary
key can be a composite key, a foreign key can be a composite
key, a unique constraint could be a composite key. So a composite
key is just multiple columns are required to make that unique.
Let's say, for instance, I'm a driver's license. My driver's
license number is 1234, and I'm from Arizona. Now, Tobias also
has a driver's license and he's 1234 and he's from Washington.
Well, if we put those in the same table, I can't enforce uniqueness
because if we have just the primary key on the driver's license
number for 1234, the first one in is going to win. The second
one is... sorry, we aren't able to 1234, we can't play.
>> And I'll be first in.
>> You don't get a driver's license.
>> No, I'll be first.
>> So what we'll do is we'll actually create a composite primary key.
So we're going to take 1234 and we're going to concatenate on
WA for Washington, and we're going to take my 1234 concatenate AZ.
We'll make that a composite primary key. Now they're unique.
Now they're going to use the columns together to enforce the uniqueness.
Now we can work together. Now we can both be in that database.
AZ is alphabetical before WA, unless they do it in descending
order, so I should win anyway, but that's a side note.
[Laughter]
First one in wins. So what we can do is we can add a primary
key to a table. It can be composite. It requires you... it enforces
uniqueness for us, and pretty much most tables are going to have
that primary key to enforce uniqueness for the values that are
stored or the rows that are stored in that database or in that table.
Now, in addition to that, we have what's called a foreign key.
A foreign key can also be a composite key. It's a combination
of one or more columns that's going to allow us to reference
that primary key, okay? So we look at, for instance, if we come
back down here, this is adding one here, alter table or adding
a constraint called a foreign key. I like to use the prefix
of the type of key at the beginning. So we have primary key,
we have foreign key, we have a couple more coming up, but I like
to put that at the beginning so I know what type of key I'm working with.
It's a foreign key. It's going to reference this table called
sales reason, and it's going to reference the column over there
called sales reason ID. And we're also going to talk about what
happens if we try to delete that, what happens if we try to update that.
We want to cascade that delete or that update, all right?
So we want to make sure that that delete takes place. If it
does take place, it gets cascaded. So alter table or foreign
key is used to reference, normally a primary key could be a unique
constraint, which we're going to introduce next on another table.
So if I'm going in and I'm adding a new product and one of the product...
one of the items are in the product is category, well, category
information is not going to be stored in that table. It's going
to be stored in another table called categories. Well, over
in that second table called categories I'm going to have a primary
key and category ID. I'm going to have a foreign key in the products
table that references that primary key in that category table.
And just to make sure that I'm adding valid content, it's going
to reference to make sure is there a category over there called
Froot Loops or something. I have no idea where I got with Froot
Loops, but we'll go with that one. So we'll reference that to
make sure it's valid data that we're adding. Now, I can only
add one primary key per table, but there may be other columns
in a table that I want to enforce uniqueness on. So what I could
do is use a unique constraint, a unique constraint allows me
to enforce uniqueness on columns other than the primary key.
So we're already going to enforce uniqueness with the state code
in the driver's license. Maybe we want to make sure a Social
Security number's going to be in there. We want to make sure
the Social Security number, because that should also be unique,
but my primary key has already been consumed with the driver's
license and the state code. What could create a Social Security...
a unique constraint on that Social Security column to enforce
the uniqueness on that column. So unique constraints are used
to enforce uniqueness on columns within a table if your primary
key is already enforced uniqueness on other tables or other columns
within that table. We can also introduce another type of constraint
called a check constraint. This enforces the type of content
or the values that are being added. This here is an example
of alternate table called new table. We're adding a column called
ZIP code. It's an integer value with null. We're going to create
a constraint on there called check ZIP code, and what we're going
to do is we're going to set this up to check the ZIP code so
when someone enters in the 05648 or whatever the ZIP code is,
it's going to make sure that no one enters 0546P
because this is going to make sure... it can't go out and say,
all right, is this a valid ZIP code without checking everything
in the country, but it can make sure no one let's slip in accidentally,
you know, puts in an alpha character or some type of symbol.
>> And it better be an American ZIP code.
>> And it better be an American ZIP code if we're going to be
doing that. Exactly. Definitely.
>> And probably it shouldn't be an integer. It probably should
be some bar chart...
>> Bar chart, yeah, because nowadays you have the dash and the
three or four other characters...
>> You're using like, and like you use on strings, so...
>> Oh, i gotcha. Exactly. Yeah. So this would enforce that type
of data or the values being added. Make sure that there's not
adding any type of inappropriate content here. The last type
of constraint that we're going to talk about...
>> Do you have examples of inappropriate content?
>> I just said like 0546P, that would be inappropriate for this column.
>> I see. I see.
>> Just for this column.
>> It sounds really inappropriate.
>> It does.
Well, you were jumping... you jumped all over that one like drool
on a baby.
So the next, in the last constraint we're going to talk about
is in default constraint. If there are values that's probably...
going to get picked on by this...
>> Yes.
>> I'm not from Sweden, so. Alter table, we're going to add a
default constraint. The country region code by default is going
to be USA.
All right.
>> Is that actually... I thought it was US, that's the region
code for the US.
>> It could be. I was just... I thought you wanted a reason to
say why does it have to be US, why can't it be Sweden?
What's Sweden's code?
>> SE.
>> SE? Okay. So we could add US or SE as the default... I forgot
I was to be working with him today or I would have made this
SE to make it safe, but, so instead of me having to supply when
I'm doing insert, instead of me having to supply the country
code, it would, by default, if I don't supply SE, for instance,
it would by default populate that with USA. So just makes it
a little bit easier when we're adding content into a table.
[Laughter]
>> All right. So those are the five different types of constraints
that are used for enforcing the type of data being added.
We're trying to make sure the contents being added is not garbage.
>> And we're enforcing it's USA.
>> It's USA.
>> And by the way, we're going to make that table, that columns
so it can't be overridden. It has to be USA.
Or SE. All right.
So those are the idea of constraints that we can use when we're
inserting or updating content. The other idea that we want to
look at are DML triggers, and a trigger, again, is a way for
us that could be as simple as, hey, I'm going to go in there
and create a trigger on a customer table. After someone does
an insert or an update, I just want to send a message. I want
to raise an error pops up or I can use those XP send mail, and
it can send an email to the manager and say, hey, a new customer's
added to this table. We could use it for an XML, a trigger for that.
We could use a trigger for making sure the data stays consistent.
And so we go in and we have a trigger on the last name column
of the employee table, and that trigger is ever if there's an
update on that column in that table, I want a trigger so it goes
out to accounts payable or it goes out to payroll, and also changes
the last name in that table and it goes to any other table that
contains the last name. So you can also have a trigger that's
assigned to one table that will trip or fire and that will cause
an update to take place on any other table.
>> And there's a few things to kind of mention here, as well.
One thing I just want to mention... we'll get into it a bit
later in the class... but you probably want to use the throw
statement, which is new to SQL Server 2012, rather than the raise
error statement that we have down here. We'll talk a bit more
about that later. But the other thing that's worth noting about
triggers is the most common uses for triggers is really...
one is, just like Brian mentioned, to validate some sort of...
more complex integrity that you can't figure out with check constraints,
foreign keys and so on,
Which is typically a good idea.
And obviously the more triggers you add, the more complexity
you have and there can be performance implications.
The other thing that is also very common is to update denormalized
data, so you have things normalized first nicely and there are
no duplicates anywhere, but then a common thing when you get
into performance issues is, ah, maybe I'll have this column here,
as well, and then I don't need to draw in these six tables to
get this result set. And then it's fairly common to use triggers
to go and actually update this other column when things happen,
and that can get you into trouble if there is a lot of updates
or inserts or whatever you're triggering on. So it's worth considering
does it always have to be absolutely up to date. If the answer
is no, you're probably better off having something like a job
that runs on some schedule and updates these changes.
>> All right. Good information. The last piece we want to look
at is the output clause which is used to return information from
any type of expression or whenever we're performing an insert
update or delete. Here's an example of how we would create that.
Notice in here we've got delete sales shopping cart item output deleted.asterisk.
That output deleted.asterisk specifies that all columns in the
deleted rows, we're going to be returned to the application that
called that delete. So in this case here it might be just query
editor that's calling that delete. And then what we'll do is
we'll verify in the rows our match with the where clause have
been deleted. We'll go back afterwards. So we're going to delete
sales.shopping cart item output deleted.asterisk where shopping
cart ID equals 20621, and then we'll verify that that item was deleted.
>> Brian, Brian, Brian, can I show them a demo?
>> You... I would love for to you show them a demo.
>> Oh. Thank you. So actually, this output clause...
>> Is this going to be in Swedish or English?
>> Oh, Swedish.
Oop. Now, output clause...
let's stay with English.
>> All right. Thanks.
>> So the update or this output clause is super useful. It falls
into, you know, a bit of the same bucket as this Window functions
that are kind of magical. This is not probably as high of a bar
to get into. It's fairly easy to use, but it's super, super useful.
So just the common example is really I update, let's just say,
production, the product table and I want to set the name column
into uppercase, let's say. So I'll just say upper name.
And after I do this, I want to go and do something else with
these particular products. You can easily get into a problem here.
Let's say I have a where clause here and say where list price
is greater than ten, right? Let's say this is a transaction.
I will get into transactions later, but let's say I update first,
and now after I want to go and do something else with exactly
these products, right, that I updated? So first we increase the
price, and then we'll go and do some other things with other
tables related to these products. A problem is that if I just
use the same where clause, if someone else inserted rows after
my update that matched the where clause, right?... where list
price is greater than ten, my update may affect ten rows.
Someone else insert the 11th row, so the next statement that
goes and does something updates now or manages 11 rows.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Okay? That's called inconsistent analysis, and
you need to have a different type of locking in place to protect
yourself against them. But the update clause or the output clause
can really help you here. So what I can do is...
or that's called phantom row, sorry.
Not inconsistent analysis. So I can say, hey, output the product
ID of all of these rows, and you can say into like a table variable
or something, but let's just do this. Oh. Sorry. And output
insert.product ID. So in an update inserted will refer to the
new value, and obviously I didn't change product ID, and deleted
will refer to the old value. So if I do this, now I can see,
ah, 291 rows returned, and those are exactly the products that
I updated.
So what I can now is do obviously on the client side if I just
return this, I know I upped it exactly these products.
The other thing I could do is I can say, oh, I'll have a table
variable that contains
this product ID column,
and I can now go and do into that product ID or that table variable,
and now exactly these product IDs are in there, so then later
in your queries you can now start joining with this table variable
and it will contain exactly those columns that you... or those
rows that you updated. So now you don't need to worry about problems
such as phantom rows, and you don't need to increase the locking
and the transaction isolation level which could basically decrease
your chances of having good concurrency.
>> All right.
Outstanding. So we're going to wrap this up. Just we walked
through some of the DML statements unlike what it said in the
front, DML statements, and these included the insert, updates, deletes.
We showed you different ways for inserting content, specifically
with the insert into statement, the select statement, the exec statement.
We talked about select into.
We also told you how we could use update or merge. We've got
a demo on how to use a merge for updating content.
Different ways for us to remove data include the delete statement
or truncate table statement, which can be used to delete the
content or either a row, or if you want to delete everything
in a table, just use a delete without a where clause or use the
truncate table option. We talked about the identity property
versus the sequence property. Sequence is new in 2010... or 12,
and what this will do for us is it's more of a database level
sequence or column that it can use, and I still have the seed
in increment values I can set versus the identity property that's
been around for a while. That's more of a table.
But again, I can supply this seed in increment value for that.
We talked about the five different types of constraints that
we can use: The primary key, the foreign key, the unique, the
check, and the default constraint. And then we also talked about
the use of DML triggers, and as Tobias pointed out, we specify
the use of raise error. Later on we're going to use the throw.
We're going to talk about how that would be a little more beneficial.
So let's take about a ten-minute stretch and we're going to take...
come back here. We'll continue our discussion into the next module
where we're going to talk about some programming elements, some
error handling, and that's where we're going to introduce items
like the throw and catch. So we'll see you back here in about
ten minutes. Enjoy the break.