[Music]
Welcome back to the Administering SQL Server 2012
Jump Start. I'm Rich Currey. We're here with Mr. George Squillace,
SQL is in his name. George, what are we going to be talking about now?
>> A good module here, Rich. We are going to take a look at maintaining
instances and databases is the big picture. So we will take
a look at implementing transparent data encryption.
>> Okay.
>> Look at compression options. SQL Server product, you know,
is very highly configurable. We have a server-level or instance-level options.
We will look at some of those, maybe some of those that are particularly
good for a heavy workload. We'll also take a look at database options...
>> Okay....
>> and explore a particular category of options just to see how
to change those and such. And then a topic of interest to you...
or really more in your area of expertise, the topic of affinity
and parallelism for really those carefully... those workloads
to be carefully controlled.
>> Okay.
>> A pet favorite topic of mine, automation.
>> There you go.
>> So we will look into the two major automation aspects. I imagine
a lot of the attendees have heard of some of the automation aspects.
But there are certain things for exam prep you just have to have down.
>> Awesome.
>> And I will also suggest it very much helps if you have hands-on activities.
>> Sounds good. So let's start in then, shall we?
>> All right. Security is always a concern. And transparent data
encryption obviously is a security technology.
So in this topic, we'll see the different kinds of encryption
that are out there in the I.T. industry and what kinds of problems
they solve and then specifically what TDE... what TDE happens
to solve...
>> Okay....
>> the problems that it solves. We will then see how it's applied.
That's kind of the big-picture look going in here.
>> Awesome. So what is TDE and why would we use it?
>> It is a data protection technology. As far as encryption generally
goes, I'm concerned about data while it's in motion...
>> Yep....
>> traveling between two points when someone might be able to
intercept it, redirect it, blah, blah, blah or data while it
is at rest that someone could steal, alter, something like that.
>> Oh, that never happens, right?
>> Never happens. Oh, my, I wonder...
>> I have actually been a victim of that.
>> You have? Data theft?
>> Absolutely. Had a laptop that had all of our tax information
on it stolen from the state. So it happens. But how's TDE going
to deal with that?
>> Yeah. Well, to add on to the problem here, now we have terabyte-sized
USB drives that I could attach to an instance, easily copy off
even some very large backup files.
>> Yep.
>> Or as we will see later on, detach some data files, copy them
over, slurp them over to my USB external. And then I'm away
with super important information.
>> Absolutely, absolutely.
>> Now, a concern about any encryption technology is whether or
not it involves changing any other practices involving that data.
>> Okay.
>> And that's where the T in transparent data encryption comes in.
It is just that transparent. As far as an application is concerned,
I don't have to write any special code. I don't write any code.
I just access the database as normally, and the files are protected
on the filesystem from theft.
And if somebody tries to attach them, copy them somewhere else...
>> So I don't have to do any special programming on the application side?
>> No....
>> to make... to utilize TDE in the environment?
>> Exactly.
>> That's cool.
>> Yeah, no special... no special protection.
>> That's very cool.
>> Sorry. No special application treatment. Now, looking into
the next slide here, we'll see that transparent data encryption
is related to a fairly sophisticated hierarchy of encryption
keys that we happen to find in not only Windows but also in the
SQL Server product.
>> Okay.
>> So when I install SQL Server, a key is created for the instance
that then becomes the parent key of potentially many, many other keys.
That's called the service master key.
>> Okay.
>> And then we have derived from that a database master key.
From that, we'll create certificates for additional encryption.
And then, finally, when it comes to encrypting a particular database,
there is a database encryption see... pardon me, database encryption key.
You will see all this in action with your own two eyes.
>> Wow. That sounds like keys upon keys upon keys. You really
need a key ring for that, don't you?
>> You do need a key ring for that.
[Laughter]
So you saw from the key hierarchy diagram a little bit of an
idea of how TDE is applied. I have to create a database master key.
That's... and that will be, of course, derived from the service
master key, then a certificate, and then a database encryption key.
And then think of being on the end of the runway.
>> Yep.
>> Got to get off in the air. Got to hit the throttle. Got to
turn it on.
>> So after you got all those keys, you got to turn them on.
>> Yep. Now, moving to the next area here...
>> Yeah....
>> we have concerns.
>> What kinds of concerns might they be?
>> There are definitely some potential gotchas with transparent
data encryption. You will see some of the items, the possible
areas of concern here. I might not be able to recover a database.
I might not be able to move it if I don't have the appropriate
keys backed up.
>> Absolutely.
>> So I have a couple links here where you can take a look at
some of these things. Obviously, with any encryption, there is
going to be some performance overhead.
>> You mean it doesn't happen for free?
>> No. There's no such thing as a free lunch. We learned that
somewhere along the way.
>> Yeah, no, I know. So what does it cost? Where does that overhead
impact us?
>> Its impact is in IO performance as data is written to...
written to and decrypted from the files there. Now, precaution-wise,
to avoid gotchas, you'll have to back up all the keys in the hierarchy.
So I have an article link here, backing up the service master key.
From there, you can follow the rest of the article links and
look at protecting of the other keys.
>> So when you've got a TDE database, you need to have all those
keys available in order to restore it at some point.
>> And I don't have them on a USB drive that's on the top of my
display that says "I'm the DBA."
>> Oh, sure, you don't want to hand the keys to the car to anybody
that can grab it.
>> Exactly.
>> Can we take a look at it, George?
>> Yeah, let's take a look at it.
>> All right.
So this one we're going to be talking about data encryption and
showing how to put that encryption in place.
>> Excellent.
>> Now, are we going to be encrypting an entire database on this,
George, or just pieces of it?
>> We encrypt the entire database.
>> Awesome.
>> It is entirely protected.
So here we go.
First, we have to create a database master key. If an instance
level key did not already exist, this would then on the fly create
a service master key in the strange circumstance that it wouldn't
already exist.
>> Okay.
>> So I can create master key encryption by password.
Curiously the password I have here has to adhere to Windows password policy.
And, in addition, for those environments that really need robust
encryption, you can have this based on a hardware platform module.
>> Awesome.
>> So for now, this will suffice.
>> So we're creating our service master key.
And then from there?
>> Now creating the master key... and from here we have to create
a certificate derived from the master key.
>> Okay.
>> So you will notice I named the certificate and then I also
give a subject for the certificate under the covers the appropriate
public/private key pair, all that's made.
I don't have to worry about that part. That part is good.
>> All right.
>> And now, let's take a look at a particular database and apply
TDE to it. So, first, I'm going to go ahead and get pointed to
the appropriate database. Nothing real fancy there.
And then, finally, create database encryption key with an encryption
key algorithm. The choice here is AES_256.
Yeah, there are a bunch of other choices. This one is the toughest.
>> Okay.
>> There are reasons to consider using it.
Finally, let's go ahead and set this on.
>> Uh-oh.
>> Oh, I didn't change this.
>> Looks like we tried to encrypt the wrong database on that one.
Oh, well.
>> Yeah. So that actually is an object lesson, huh?
>> Yeah.
>> There we go.
>> All right. So now we've created the certificate. We've created
the database master key. We've turned the encryption on.
The database is?
>> It's encrypted.
>> Awesome.
>> Now, honestly, Rich, after I run this code, it feels a little anticlimactic.
>> It does!
>> It's done!
>> That means that you don't need to do any programming, so don't
let your application guys tell you... that you can't do the encryption.
>> I have a couple of recommendations here in my code. A follow-up
to this would, of course, be to back up all of the keys.
There are other references on that. And then, additionally,
you have to model actually recovering this, should you have to
move it, should you have to recover from a backup that you want
to put on a different machine.
>> So you want to make sure that once you've put that encryption
in place, that you can also get it restored and you got everything
that you need to put it back together.
>> That's right.
>> Awesome.
>> Let's move on.
>> So let's talk about this next topic then.
A little bit on database compression, I think?
>> Yes.
>> Things that you can do to make your database more efficient.
>> Now, just like encryption, there are various compression technologies
that the SQL Server product supports. We are going to look at
a couple of those in particular, answering the question what
is data compression and then seeing what kind of objects can
be compressed. And then, of course, we have to focus on how-tos,
hands-on, you know, those kinds of procedures.
>> Yeah, it is always nice to know how to do something that they're
capable of doing. So let's take a look. What is data compression
after all, George?
>> Data compression is a trade-off. It is a trade-off by using
or observing that you have redundancy in your data using CPU
cycles which are in abundance to compress data which may...
to reduce its size which may not be in abundance.
>> Okay.
>> We'll see here there are two different compression options.
We have page-by-page or page compression.
>> Okay.
>> And row-by-row compression, which we will just call row compression.
There is backup compression. That's not a particular topic we
look at, at this moment.
>> So that can be done independently of any data compression, right?
>> Absolutely. That is an independently used feature.
>> Cool. What kinds of things get compressed?
>> Yeah. So there are a lot of objects that are compressible:
Heaps, cluster tables, different kinds of indexes, single partitions
of a partition table.
So I've just listed a few of the objects that are compressible.
>> So, basically, anything that holds data can potentially be compressed?
>> Yep, general rule of them. Now, if I happen to have file stream
objects, I'm going to use a different kind of compression, so
just keep that in mind. I will use something different.
>> Okay. So how do we go about doing it?
>> As I talk about how we do it, part of this relates to the kinds
of redundant patterns of data that I might have within rows and
also from page to page.
Doing a little bit of a research, you will find out different
kinds of compression applied to different patterns of redundancy.
And that's way more detail than you and I have the stamina to
talk about right now.
>> But would it generally safe to say if you have data that repeats
or if you have got rows that are missing information, that they
might be better subjects for compression than other kinds of data?
>> Absolutely. So if I have lots of null in a particular table
and if I have a number of fixed length columns, that would generally
lend itself towards row-by-row compression. Other patterns of
data redundancy that might be existing across rows within a page,
that might be a candidate for page compression. So you see a
quick little look at the code that you can use to apply this
which we'll put in practice in just another slide. However, what
if I am concerned whether or not compression is going to be worthwhile,
you will see a stored procedure that you can use to estimate
what the potential reduction in storage would be.
>> So I don't need to take a random guess. I can actually go
out and figure out if it makes sense to apply the technology?
>> Yeah.
>> What a great idea.
>> You like to drive. You told me this, right?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> In hearing about the college tour that you did with your son...
[Laughter]
By the way, that was a heroic effort.
>> 2600 miles in five days.
>> Yeah, that's a lot. So in the same way while you were probably
out on the road, listening to the radio...
>> Yeah....
>> lots of restrictions you hear in the advertisements, right?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> "Some restrictions apply." Let's just say in page and row compression,
lots of restrictions apply.
>> Yep.
>> So with that, I have a link to where you can research that more.
Let's take a look at the actual code you would use to apply page
and row encryption...
compression, sorry.
>> Yeah, you get hung up on a topic, right? I don't know about
you, but language sometimes challenges me.
>> Barry, is the text a little better size here?
>> A little better.
>> A little better, okay. So let me just create something to work
with here.
So I have a database. I'm pointed to it. I'm going to add some tables.
>> Awesome.
>> La, la, la, la, la. Notice in the first table, brace yourself
here, Rich, I have a bunch of fixed length columns and I did
not specify nullability.
>> So that means there could be missing values.
>> Could be missing values.
>> All right.
>> And we could also combine the fixed length columns into a variable
length column using the row compression. So, notice, I added
the "with data compression equals" row.
>> So it takes the fixed storage and turns it basically into variable
storage so you are only using what you need.
>> Exactly.
>> Awesome.
>> And then for the next one, we have variable length columns
that might potentially have repeated data from row to row.
>> Okay.
>> And in this case, we can have page compression. Now, I can
also apply these compression features after the fact.
>> Okay.
>> But as you can see, I can apply the features either on table
creation, if I had the insight to know that I would have redundant
data patterns, or after the fact.
>> Awesome. Awesome.
>> That's it for that demonstration.
>> All right. So then let's talk about some of the different options
that are available for configuring servers and configuring databases.
>> Yeah, the SQL Server product is a huge product, and it is a
very configurable product.
I think often Microsoft creates products that would serve them,
a very, very large enterprise. A very large enterprise needs
lots of configurable options. So in this product, we have server
or instance level options.
>> Okay.
>> Database level options. We have to see how to change those.
And then we will take a particular tour through changing some
database options.
>> So are there a lot of different options available at the server level?
>> Think Home Depot.
>> Oh, no, no.
>> Do we have Home Depot everywhere?
>> You mean we can find anything?
>> Yeah, lots and lots of options. Now, the graphic I have here
on my slide is attempting to portray...
>> I don't see slides.
>> They're on. I don't know what to do.
>> Hang on here, everybody.
>> We're having a little bit of a tech issue here, so hang on
one second.
I did hit the power button by mistake, and I powered it back up.
>> Did you hit presentation mode?
>> I was in it and I was in it again, and here's hoping that we
now have success. Hey! How about that! Thanks to the geeks in
the back.
>> Barry, Danny.
>> Without them, we wouldn't have a presentation.
>> All righty. Good job, guys.
>> So let's go back to the Home Depot store.
>> I love this picture. So general rule of thumb, if you don't
want somebody to touch something, you put it out of their reach.
>> Yep.
>> So server option-wise, we'll find that there are 17 basic options.
>> Okay.
>> If we use a particular feature, SP configure, to take a look
at those. Now, there are other options let's just say if Microsoft
has put them out of our reach by default, you should consider
more carefully if you want to use those.
[Laughter]
>> If they're hidden, then maybe you don't want to go looking.
>> This reminds me of the registry editor, how there are certain
things in Windows and in various Microsoft products you can only
configure with the registry. So the point is, it's a feature,
something that's out of the reach of a normal... you know, a
mere mortal.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> The problem is if you turn those features on or change something
with the registry editor, it assumes you are a genius.
[Laughter]
>> You better know what you are doing before you go and do it.
>> Similarly, with the advanced options, we have 69 total options
after you turn the advanced options on. I've listed a couple
of these. Obviously, there are a lot: Minimum server memory,
max server memory.
So if I want to immediately contribute a certain amount of memory
from the Windows operating system to SQL Server, I can. If I
want to throttle to make sure I don't exceed a certain amount,
I can do that as well.
>> So to go out to change them, to view them?
>> Sure. We'll take a look at some of those tools.
So I can right click on the instance, get properties, and there
are some options that are accessible there. Keep in mind, not
every single option is available in the graphical user interface.
>> Okay.
>> This is very consistent with the SQL Server product.
Popular options are in the GUI. Anything, generally speaking,
you can accomplish in code.
>> And that code would be?
>> SP Configure.
>> So I can turn... Tell me if you think this is circular. I have
to turn advanced options on in SP Configure in order to access
advanced options.
>> So you configure the options that you can see them, then you
configure the options, and then, let me guess, you got to configure
them again to shut them off.
>> Yeah, precisely.
>> Perfect.
>> So in addition to turning a particular feature on, you'll notice
there's a follow-up statement, the reconfigure statement.
For the longer version of why you need the reconfigure statement,
you will see the link there.
>> Okay.
>> Just a notable, there's a popular instance level option you
might want to switch. That's authentication mode. More of a
security topic really. But that's something that you cannot change
with SP Configure.
>> You got to go to the GUI or...
>> You can go to the GUI or use an extend system store procedure.
>> Awesome. So what about the database level stuff, George?
>> Again, lots and lots of options on a per-database basis.
>> And let me guess, not all of them show up in the GUI.
>> Bravo. Give him a golf clap, everybody.
>> I'm sensing a pattern here.
>> Good observation.
The options are categorized on a per-database basis, auto options,
cursor options. You see some of the laundry list categories of options.
>> And how do we actually go through and change this stuff?
>> Like you said, with the graphical user interface, when in doubt,
right click.
>> Yep.
>> And select... to effect, I have to select the right object.
So I'm going to right click on the database in question, get
properties, and then I will go to options.
>> Okay.
>> Now, this is kind of startling when you first see this. I think
there are an awful lot of options here, more than there ever
have been really.
>> Yep.
>> Like it as has been pointed out, the GUI can't change every option.
If I do want to change or have availability of any option, you
will in code I will use "alter database," point to the name of
the database, that's the DBX part...
>> Okay....
>> and then often use the set statement or set keyword and then
the name of the option and how I want to set that, like turning
something on, turning something off, et cetera.
>> And you don't have to do a reconfigure statement or anything
like that when you're doing an alter database, correct?
>> Good follow-up.
>> All right. Cool.
>> Excellent.
>> So let's go take a look at some of these. George is going
to show us some of the ways that we can effect database properties
in this next demo. George?
>> All righty. Here we go.
>> So what do we got going here, George?
>> So next up, let's point to our appropriate database.
>> Tiny DB, we are still playing with that one?
>> We are still going to play with the tiny database.
>> All right.
>> And notice we set this to offline. That's one of the availability options.
I should have prefaced this, Rich. In particular, we're going
to explore what we call availability options of databases.
>> Okay.
>> So when I use the offline option, the databases, as you can
see from my notes here, is absolutely inaccessible, cleanly shuts
down the database without having to detach. The drama here...
drumroll, please.
>> Drumroll.
>> We see under "databases" after a refresh that there is a special
icon assigned and a description.
>> Boy, I tell you what. I like that zoom because you can't see
that icon at all without it, can you?
>> There you go. That's a pet favorite tool of mine called Zoom
It for anybody else that likes software tools. Good job, peanut galley.
Microsoft actually acquired a super scary, smart dude a while back.
>> Uh-oh.
>> And I think Zoom It is one of the tools that he contributed
to the pile.
>> For a minute there, I thought you were talking about me, and
I was wondering where that was going.
[Laughter]
>> So now I'm going to set the database state to emergency.
>> Okay. So that's another availability option?
>> Another availability option. Limited access. Only sys admins,
plural, is the key, though.
>> Okay, so multiple sys admins can hit it at the same time?
>> That's right.
>> Awesome.
>> So there are a couple of specific reasons why I might ever
want to go to emergency, like a DBCC repair, we will talk about
a little bit later. And also notice a fancy little icon for emergency.
>> It turned red.
I like that.
So what's the next option we got?
>> This will turn us back into a normal production database by
setting to online.
>> Okay.
>> Now, another option or another state you might need is read-only.
Guess what read-only means?
>> Can't write.
>> That's right. You only can read. Now, can you think of a circumstance
where something like read-only might be particularly valuable?
>> One of the things that you might want to do that for is on
a reporting database where you want to ensure that data is not
being affected by any users.
>> You had a good intent. I was thinking of being a mere mortal
and committing a DB uh-oh.
>> Uh-oh. What's a "DB uh-oh," George?
>> A "DB uh-oh" is if a database inadvertently gets damaged and
before anybody touches it further, you need to inspect it.
So you can take it to a read-only state... notice again the
fancy icon... and determine if and to what degree there might
be damage to determine what you might do from there.
>> Awesome. Awesome. Thanks very much, George.
>> All righty. Now, I could, I suppose, have a query that attempts
to update the table. It's not going to work.
>> Yep.
>> Read-only really means read-only. The opposite of read-only,
of course, means read-write. And notice it has gone back to its
normal state.
>> Cool.
>> Another availability option is single user. So this allows,
well, look what it says, only one authoritative user can connect
to the database. And there is a reason that I might use that
when I want to use a particular repair operation, which we'll
look at later on. And if you like the other icons, Rich, let's
see what you think about this.
>> Oh!
>> Get a little person there.
>> They don't call it a GUI for nothing. Graphical, it is.
Restricted user.
>> Restricted user, multi-user. So we have a bunch of different options.
And now I will set it back and put it in production.
>> Awesome.
>> That's it for that one.
>> Awesome. awesome. Thank you. So the next thing that we've
got on our schedule we're going to delve into a little bit of
affinity and parallelism. George, what's that all about?
>> It has to do with workload,
CPUs, allocation of resources to IO activity, things like that.
>> Okay. And CPU affinity, IO affinity,
parallelism, we got a lot of stuff to talk about here.
>> A lot of stuff to talk about here. Rich has volunteered to
take on this topic.
We'll take a look at parallelism defined, affinity defined, and
then how we stick our hands in the metal-moving machinery to
change things that are not default settings and in what circumstances
we might actually undertake that.
>> So CPU affinity, basically, is the process of telling SQL Server
in a multi-CPU environment which CPUs are going to be involved
in processing queries, in managing the database engine and which
ones are going to be excluded. Now, you might want to do that
for a couple of reasons. You might want to do that because you
have license restrictions. You've only purchased license for
one or two people... one or two CPUs and you have got a four
or eight-CPU box.
Maybe there are multiple applications running on that CPU, things
like that. IO affinity is the same process. It's just a matter
of allowing the CPU to be involved in the read-write process
from the data files into memory and back again.
Now, the default configuration for any SQL Server instance is
for the database engine to make use of all CPUs and all CPU cores,
which means that SQL Server really wants to have a dedicated box.
When you want to change that, when you've got shared boxes, when
you want to be able to control what the box is allocating its
resources to. The default behavior is to allow Windows to manage
all of those executions.
When you set CPU affinity, there is a scheduler created for each
CPU core.
And it then manages the execution threads inside of the database engine.
Now, there is one more consideration and that's NUMA. NUMA is
a hardware design where each CPU has its own dedicated memory
and its own dedicated bus.
Many manufacturers have different design considerations that
need to be dealt. With, so whenever you've got a NUMA machine,
SQL Server does
support NUMA processing. But the configuration that's appropriate
really needs to be set up based on the hardware manufacturer.
You need to talk to them.
>> Not everybody is great at knowing hardware intimately.
And for those that might not know, NUMA stands for non-uniform
memory access.
>> Thanks. I'm acronym challenged. I can never remember TLA,
ETLAs, or anything else. You know what an ETLA is, right?
>> I don't know what an ETLA is >> So
TLA, everybody knows, is a three-letter acronym. ETLA is...
can you guess? It is an extended three-letter acronym.
>> Awesome.
>> Okay. Back to something that's actually worth something now, parallelism.
George, parallelism is the ability for SQL Server to utilize
multiple processors in the execution of a single query, not three
or four.
But you asked a question that spread out among three or four
different data files on different drives.
And it's a complex enough question where SQL Server thinks it
might be more efficient to have multiple people working on it
at the same time. It's like breaking down a software project
into one developer doing everything or four developers working together.
Which one's going to be quicker?
>> Sure, multiple.
>> Yeah. But is there any overhead involved when you got the multiple people?
>> Picture four people trying to paint a closet.
>> Oh, dear.
>> Yeah.
>> I would guess there is some coordination involved in making sure.
>> Yeah, there's some coordination.
>> That's the overhead. In SQL, it means that that is the overhead
involved in bringing the results from all the different ones
back together. Now, there is...
there are a couple of settings available in SQL to control that parallelism.
One is over and above the affinity, you can set MAXDOP for index maximum.
>> Degree of parallelism.
>> Thank you very much, again. My man with the acronyms because
I actually forgot what it was for a second.
There's also a MAXDOP setting that you can put on an individual
query if you want to override the setting for the database, so...
>> Wow.
>> Last, but not least, there is a cost threshold for parallelism
which is set initially at zero which means that all queries are
available to be parallelized; doesn't mean that SQL will do it.
But by setting that to a specific value, you then are controlling
the complexity or the amount of resources that are being used
before a query can be considered to be parallelized, okay?
To configure CPU affinity, there's alter server configuration.
Also, you could right click on the server itself and go to properties,
go to processors, and it will allow you to check it off.
George, can we go take a look at that one?
>> Oh, oh, oh, can I show that one?
>> Oh, I think so.
George wants to go play. Is that okay?
>> Let's go to properties.
>> Yeah, that's okay.
>> All righty. Well, wait a second. How come I can't select any
of these checked boxes?
>> Uh-oh. Is that a problem?
>> It's not a problem.
I just wonder why.
>> Hmm. Could it be that this computer only has one CPU with one
CPU core?
>> Well, it's real hard to allocate multiple processors and configure
them if I only have one to begin with. So you are seeing a good
design of the user interface here.
>> There you go. There you go.
And what about the
IO affinity, processor affinity, that's for both of them.
Down... where is that max degree of parallelism?
There is the check boxes for CPU and IO affinity.
>> Believe me.
>> All right, cool.
So let's move into our next topic here a little bit, and I particularly
like this topic.
>> This is a pet favorite topic of mine as well. There's a chant
that every database administrator should have and that is "automate,
automate, automate."
As we've talked about before, there are good reasons to automate.
So in this particular section, we'll take a look at the automation
subsystems that SQL Server has available. I don't consider that
you've never heard of any of these features before, but I will
say before you take your exam...
well, before you take your exam, you want to be solid on all
these features. So we will take a look at agent jobs and having
scheduled workload in the background, automation steps.
We'll also take a look at having automation security and the
very highly configurable environment there. And then we'll look
at the second major automation subsystem, which is the alerting subsystem.
>> All right. So what about these jobs, George?
>> Big picture here.
>> Okay.
>> You want to look at some of the moving parts of the automation subsystem.
So I have tried to illustrate this briefly. Namely, I can have
one or more jobs where a job is a collection of work that I want
to run either ad hoc, on demand...
>> Okay....
>> or that I want scheduled.
>> All right.
>> So notice job one has one job step. A job step is the work
that will get done within a job. And each job step necessarily
is assigned a job subsystem.
>> Okay.
>> So you will notice in job 2 that I could, for example, have
more than one schedule. Maybe I have something that has to run
at 10:00 in the morning and something that has to run at 8:00
at night. Well, there is not an even number of hours or a way
to get both of those done unless I have a separate schedule.
And what if job 3 is something that depends on when a vendor
sends me a file? And that's unpredictable. I won't even have
a schedule for that. I just run that ad hoc or on demand.
>> Okay. And...
>> I'm sorry. The fun part is the reach...
who's the stretchy guy in Avengers?
>> I don't even know.
>> Help me out here. Mr. Fabulous, I think. Somebody in the
chat will...
>> Mr. Fantastic.
>> Mr. Fantastic, okay. So anyway...
what's that? The Fantastic Four. Okay, I will get straightened out.
>> Not a comic book geek, are you?
>> Boy, am I going to get schwacked on the break time. Oh, my gosh.
So think about having a super long reach, that's really what
the automation subsystem permits because you will see job step-wise,
we have T-SQL subsytem, command_exec, anything that's a batch
file, an executable command file, Power Shell. Amazing things
you can do with Power Shell. Get a free e-book on Power Shell
at powershell.com. Sorry, am I missing something?
Thank you. I can one SSIS packages. So let's just assume all
the automation real estate is covered. Anything I might want
to do I can get it covered. And then a final point is that I
may want to become notified on the basis of when a job completes
and/or if it fails. So lots of moving parts there.
>> Now, a lot of times jobs go out and they have to actually access
resources either in the database or in other parts of the network
or on the computer. How do we manage that whole process and make
sure that they don't do anything inappropriate, shall we say?
>> Sure, sure. We want to make sure they don't do anything appropriate
and that those accounts are not compromised. Well, when it comes
to setting up automation security, there are two major divisions.
The T-SQL job
subsystem is treated sort of unto itself. And the security of
a particular job step, that is configurable...
>> Okay....
>> security on a per job-step basis has to do with ownership.
So job owned by sys admin versus a job owned by a non-sys admin.
We will see that other job steps have other... they have a different
security mechanism. And that's dictated by, again, whether it
is a sys admin owned job or a job not owned by sys admin.
Rather than to go through the painful detail of seeing this on
a slide... or running through all the detail on the slide, this
is more of a reference.
>> How can we provide an identity for those steps to use per se?
>> Yeah. So the SQL Agent...
if I could go back for just a sec. The SQL Agent
has an account that it must run under. We saw that in the earlier module.
So picture, for example, a diameter, a circle with a diameter
which represents maybe an amount of privilege. Now, for every
job and every job step
with this rule book, that will dictate how jobs and job steps
will run. Well, fine then. I might need to change that diameter
to have generally larger privileges but just for a moment.
So I can use "execute as" for T-SQL job steps. As we move into
the next topic, we'll see that for other job steps, we have something else.
I'm going to move over to my virtual machine for just a moment
to reveal something. So if you guys could flip me over.
All right. So I'm looking at the SQL Server Agent, and I see
a very long laundry list of available proxies.
Now here's the relevance. Let's say I happen to have a job, and
it doesn't matter what job I have right now. I'm going to open
up properties of the job.
>> Okay.
>> I'm then going to go to steps of the job.
And when I edit
the properties of the job, notice I could configure run-as.
Now, run-as actually says point to a proxy.
And the only one run-as is not available for is a T-SQL Agent step.
This is where I would use "execute as" in the T-SQL code so I
get the same thing done, I just have a different mechanism.
>> Got it. So what is a proxy then?
>> Yeah, so a proxy is really an alternate identity. If you guys
would flip me back to the slides now for a sec. You are going
to have to follow me deep down the rabbit hole for a second here.
>> Uh-oh.
>> So what I need is an alternate identity that's able to do something.
So I set up a Windows account, and I assign that account privileges,
the privileges I need a job step to have.
>> Okay.
>> Then I have to create an instance level object, a credential object.
Looking at the chain of events here, a credential necessarily
points to a Windows account.
>> Okay.
>> Then I create an agent proxy and an agent proxy necessarily
points to a credential. And then, finally, on a job step-by job
step basis, I can point to a proxy which then will enlarge the
diameter of whatever capability I need for that particular job step.
>> Awesome. Now, is that the only security that's involved in
SQL Agent?
>> Think, Rich, of a really busy server. Maybe I have a couple
hundred databases on a machine. We'll learn more and more about
maintenance where I might have four or five jobs just for a single database.
Multiply that by 100, 200 databases, I could easily have a couple
hundred jobs on a heavy workload machine.
>> Okay.
>> So now I'm at a fork in the road if I'm the system administrator
of that instance. I might need some help. So do I want to raise
someone all the way to sys admin to give them entire privileges
over the job administration system or not?
>> I wouldn't.
>> And if I don't want to take that approach, I have a job delegation
strategy that I can use. Now, over at the right, you'll find
a curious laundry list of database roles specific to the MSDB.
And where I've highlighted, notice that there are the SQL Agent
family of roles and, specifically, there are three. If you are
up for the gory detail, I have a hyperlink here where you can
see exactly what each role can and cannot do. And the roles
are in increasing privilege. So we have the agent user role.
It can manage basically what it owns.
Pardon me. The reader role can do anything the user role can
and some additional stuff, like at least get information on multi-server
jobs, properties, schedules. So it can look at everything even
beyond what it owns.
>> Okay.
>> Of course, the SQL Agent operator can touch and change more
than that. And then the next up on the proverbial food chain
would be a sys admin.
>> So I got to ask you a question, George. Over in that little
box next to where it's showing the instance, I don't see SQL
Agent in there. How come?
>> I was hoping you'd ask about that.
>> I kind of thought so. That's why its owe on the slide.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. So why would the agent not show up there
if someone is not a member of either sys admin or one of those roles?
The agent node doesn't even appear in management studio.
>> If they are not going to be to play with it, they ain't even
going to be able to see it.
>> Yeah.
>> I like that.
>> I do.
>> Can we look at operators and jobs and job steps and all that
good stuff? How do we set up that automation?
>> All righty. So one of the first things that you'll do in setting
up the automation system is setting up an operator. They're going
to be...
Guys, would you go ahead and flip me to my virtual machine.
Thanks. One of the first things I'd want to do is set up an operator.
They are going to be the destination notification of job outcome.
So we'll take a look. And I will tell you, every bit of this
can be configured in code. And we'll see kind of in this demo
a mixture of some code and also GUI-based demonstration. So let's
say we call this...
this operator the DBA team. I'm big on having plural names here.
General rule of thumb, the work stays the same, the worker may change.
>> Okay.
>> So let's just leave kind of a general name here. And for aliasing
purposes, we could have something like...
what do you call that... a distribution list. So let's say...
>> So the operator is not an user. The operator is a message destination.
>> That's right.
>> Awesome.
>> And so I can go ahead and apply the hours of availability for
this operator. This becomes important in the circumstance when
a notification message is sent. I should have a little fun with
this and set 24/7 hours, but I won't bother to do that right now.
>> Oh, why not? That's the real world. Have you ever met a DBA
that doesn't work 24/7?
>> Yeah. so now I have my operator. And subsequent to that, I
will go ahead and create a job.
>> Okay.
>> So let's call this backup system databases.
>> So that will be the name of our job. And now I want to set
up the job steps. I need to pinch a little bit of code here, Rich.
>> Like every good DBA, you prewrote your scripts.
>> That I did.
>> I like that.
>> I will go for double bonus if they even entirely work.
[Laughter]
>> And, of course, I have my task bar up top which I forgot about
and auto hidden. So there is my new job. So next up I'm going
to create a new job step, and we'll call this, after I paste
in my code, backup master.
For brevity, I will just say backup master. You are going to
have better titles. You noticed I have a lot of cheeky rules
of thumb, and one of my other rules of thumb is leave a trail.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> I like documentation. I like being obvious.
>> Self-documenting is a very good thing. You should practice
it in all of your naming conventions on everything.
>> There we go. So we'll find that job steps actually have a humble...
did I say "humble"?
>> You did....
>> a humble workflow capability and lots of configurable options
with a job step. Of course, it would never be within the realm
of possibility for one of my co-workers to already be in the
middle of the night reboot a server when there is some automation
that's supposed to occur. So I can have retry attempts, retry
interval, some basic things like that. After that job step,
I'm quickly going to make two new job steps.
Let's say
backup MSDB.
>> Yep.
>> One more.
>> Let me guess. Backup model.
>> Backup model.
>> Well, those are the system databases you need to backup, so
that works.
>> That's right. Now this last time around instead of going to
the next step, I want to quit the job reporting success.
>> Okay.
>> I'll click on okay.
And a schedule.
>> All right.
>> So I would pick a schedule. Let's just say we want this to
occur every single day rather than particular days.
>> Okay.
>> And maybe we want this to occur at 2:00 a.m.
>> All right.
>> We'll say...
give a schedule name nightly at 2:00 a.m.
The final part
is setting a target for notification. And notice the configurability here.
The operator that I have can be notified when the job succeeds,
also notified same operator when the job fails, or just when
it gives its best effort when it completes whether it finishes
successfully or not.
>> Awesome.
>> Just for drama value, let's see if this dog will bark.
We'll go ahead and start it.
See if I put in my code right.
>> And? Uh-oh.
>> Kaboom. So this is where I could use troubleshooting facilities,
go ahead and view history and find out what it was that actually
went wrong.
All right. So we can drill down notice on a step...
well, actually job outcome status and then step by step.
All right. Awesome.
>> Awesome. So is there anything else you can do in Agent that
might be useful?
>> Wow, lots of stuff. So we have all kinds of other subsystems.
Were you referring to the other subsystems we have?
>> No, I was thinking more along the lines of letting the Agent
tell you when something happens.
>> Yes, alerts, uh-huh. I'd like to...
let me get a quick look here.
Yeah, I'd like to equate the alerting subsystem to a trip wire.
>> Okay.
>> So let's say I had something on double secret probation in
my property, and I wanted to be made aware if somebody crosses
into my property...
>> Okay....
>> and I didn't want them there.
>> Okay.
>> Compare this to SQL Server. I can set up a listening ear to
listen for particular circumstances and should they occur (snapping),
knee-jerk reaction, I want SQL Server to do something about it.
>> Awesome.
>> Now, for your benefit, I have the basic alerting architecture here.
And I think what I would like to do is just show you how I configure
an alert.
Before you flip the slide, notice that I have three...
in the light blue area, three key areas that I can use as the
basis for setting up the trip wire. So let's go over to my virtual
machine now and show some of these.
>> All right. So the performance condition alerts, we can do an
event alert, we can do a WMI, which is Windows management instrumentation.
>> That's right. Now, the first thing I'm going to do is add a
couple of custom error messages. Don't laugh at my messages here.
It is just purely for humor. You will notice the way that I add
a custom error message is with SP addmessage. These are instance
level objects.
Now, a clever thing is that these can actually be called by stored
procedures through the raise error statement. But for right
now, let's just make a mental note that we have an error message
we might specifically be concerned about, 50649.
All right. So just so you know, you can query sys messages if
you wanted to see those custom message IDs. All of them, by
the way, have to have an ID over 50,000. Okay. So now to set
up my alert, I'm going to go to object explorer. When in doubt...
>> Select it first.
>> That's right... right click and now it will say
"error alert." Of course, I'd give probably a better description here.
Notice one of the key things is that I may want to set up an
alert that I'm not ready to enable.
>> Okay.
>> So that's a troubleshooting thing. Make sure that you're...
that the alert is enabled. So now I have the alert condition.
And I want you to observe how the form changes when I pick a
different major area of trip wire, as I described.
>> All right.
>> So we'll use an event alert. The next major thing that we have
to determine is will this apply to all databases or just a particular database?
>> So we can set up instance level alerts or database level alerts?
>> That's right.
>> Cool.
>> And then all alert errors are
all categorized according to a severity. Or I can say that there
is a particular error message number that I'm concerned about.
Do you remember that number off the top of your head?
>> I do not.
>> Of course. I should have copied it. So we will this time.
There. How's that?
>> There we go.
>> So the big deal here is what do I want to do about this?
So one of the things I might want to do is execute a job.
I just picked this one that I made.
>> Yep, yep.
>> That shows that you can pick a job and/or notice the user interface here.
Pink highlighting for the ladies this time. Notice that I can
pick all of my standard notification methods, email, pager, et
cetera, et cetera.
>> Awesome. So just out of curiosity, if you do set up an error
alert, where does the Agent monitor for those errors?
>> Excellent.
So now what we'd find is that I would go to event viewer. A bunch
of ways to open up this.
Event viewer...
time-wise, I'm going to spare actually tripping the alert.
But we would then go to Windows logs, application log, and I
would see the presence of the alerts here.
>> Awesome. So it responds to the message being written to the
event log, and that's where the alert gets monitored.
>> Yep. That's the listening that I was referring to. It actually
was listening to something existing in the event log. Glad that
you pointed that out.
>> Awesome.
>> And then it will kick in to the appropriate action.
>> Now, this segues right into our next topic, which if you're
going to be notifying people and you are going to be sending
emails, well, SQL Server needs to access the mail system.
George, what's that all about?
>> Just a brief final little topic, an area of capability that
SQL Server has is database mail. And we'll see starting with
SQL 2005, so a good number of years ago... everybody sigh with relief...
now this is based on notification of an SMTP server rather than
using the MAPI interface that existed in the past.
Now, there was a particular system stored procedure that has
to be enabled and is used in database mail. You will see the
name of that down below,
sp_send_db mail but this can be used for automation notification
purposes and also for application purposes.
As mail piles up, there is some system tables that you actually
can put your hands on, meaning remove rows, maintain. So brace yourself.
Does this sound circular? I might need a job to maintain some
of the history in email.
[Laughter]
>> Oh, Lord. Maintenance upon maintenance upon maintenance.
>> Yeah, so...
>> That's the way it works with a database.
>> So that wraps us up for this topic, taking a look at server
level options, database level options, setting up the automation system.
>> And we'll be back in about ten minutes with our next topic.
Thanks for hanging out. See you in a little bit.