[Music]
Welcome back to the administering SQL Server 2012
Jump Start. I'm Rich Currey. This is Mr. George Squillaci.
We have the geeks in the background that are helping us out.
Thanks to the geeks. Yeah, without them, you would not be seeing
this, so absolutely, absolutely thanks to the guys behind the camera.
>> All right.
>> George, what have we got coming up now?
>> So look, Rich, we're four modules down already, kind of unbelievable,
but this module, again, a very important module. Something that
you just have to get right. Remember, it's your fault.
>> It always is my fault. Just ask Alise. She'll tell you.
>> So implementing security. A bunch of topics to look at.
And going to the overview, we have onion
layers, I suppose we could describe, onion layers of security
that we can set in SQL Server and we want to take a look at each
one of those layers. Okay. I'll use the proper term.
Scopes of security. We have server-level scope, database-level scope.
We want to investigate the levels of security that we have, server
level, database level, and then some strategies that we'll use
for implementing permissions.
>> All right.
>> That's the big picture for this particular module.
>> So let's start up at the top. What do you think?
>> Sure. So in this particular topic, we'll look at in general
the security scopes, list them by name, give you a picture to
have in mind that will help you put your mind around what the
available scopes are, and then we'll look at some other things,
authentication, authentication modes and allowing someone to
access the SQL Server instance. Then we'll take a look at some
administrative activities at the instance. So that's coming up.
>> All right.
>> Big picture.
The point of the diagram is to show that there are security options
or there is security that can be applied at several different
scopes up at the instance, and you see some example objects that
can be controlled that are instance-level objects.
Then we have database scope objects, schema scope within a database,
and ultimately and most granular, we have individual objects
within a database that can be controlled.
>> So could you talk about scope as kind of like a container,
so like the database scope is inside the server scope and the
schema scope is inside the database scope?
>> Yep. Think rolling stone.
>> Okay.
>> Not so much in the sense of the music, but if I happen to assign
permissions at one scope, generally speaking, and depending on
the permission, those permissions are going to roll downhill...
bless you... roll downhill to the other scopes.
There are some permission specific statements that you'll see.
I like in particular, in one of the courses that I teach, where
it talks about the grant statement and it says something like,
quote: "The grant statement is a very complex statement."
There are a lot of options, but at least the point is obvious.
We're giving access to something.
>> All right.
>> So moving along, one of the first important security decisions
that needs to be made is the authentication mode. As you can
see from the lower right, this decision can be made during installation
and can also be changed after the fact. So it's a little bit
tiny, but you'll see two radial buttons which permits solely
Windows authenticated access to SQL Server. Alternatively, Windows
plus SQL Server log-ins.
>> So basically you can always use your Windows identity log-in,
but SQL Server log-ins have to be specified specifically.
>> Got to throw a switch on, and there's a cost.
>> Uh-oh. What's the cost?
>> The cost is that you're going to have to restart the instance,
restart the database service after you make that change.
>> So anytime you change security, you've got to restart the instance.
>> Well, anytime you change that in particular for sure.
>> The authentication. Okay.
>> Now, for those that have a lot of SQL Servers, consider this.
What actually changes is a registry key, which means then if
you wanted to change the mode universally on a bunch of SQL Servers,
you could actually set up Group Policy to change the registry
key in the policy and apply that to your fleet of SQL Servers,
restart them, and you are good to go.
>> Very cool. Very cool.
>> Now, you'll notice with the Windows identity, that's something
that's already defined in Windows, but if you go back for just
a second, in the upper right we're seeing that we can create
a SQL log-in, which is thumb printed, so to say, to this particular
SQL Server. Quick little side note. Starting with I think this
was SQL 2005, you now can have SQL log-ins pay attention to the
underlying Windows password policy if it's a server operating system.
>> Yep. Yep. You set it in AD and then SQL Server follows along.
>> Yeah. So let's move on to log... pardon me... log-in objects.
And this slide caters to those that might be newer to SQL Server,
and I'm trying to make it very obvious how someone ultimately
gains access to objects within SQL Server.
Think of it as clearing three separate hurdles. First, I have
to knock at the front door and furnish identity of who I am.
>> Okay.
>> And not only do I have to prove who I am, but then I have to
show that I'm invited to the party.
>> Okay.
>> So we refer to this as authentication and authorization.
Now, think about this. If you go in... this is a sort of a private
question, but let's say you go into one of your friends' houses.
Are you're going to wander around and look inside the medicine cabinet?
>> I hope not.
>> No. So similarly, once I get through the front door of the
SQL Server, I may not be able to wander around everywhere in
the instance, and we'll see from the second hurdle, my log-in
object, which is created to permit access into SQL Server, must
then be registered at the database level. To backup for just
a sec, notice that log-ins can be derived from a few different
sources, a Windows account or a SQL Server account, and they
also can involve Windows groups.
>> Okay.
>> Why would you use a group instead of individual accounts?
>> Well, it has to do a little bit with, we'll just say, turf war.
If I want Windows administrators to manage groups, then I could
pass that off and let them populate. But generally it's a measure
of efficiency.
>> Okay.
>> So that's a good point to bring up. Now, at the second hurdle
I have user objects that are then registered at each and every
database where I want to log in to be able to do something.
Similarly, just because I can enter through the front door of
a database, doesn't give me access to everything within that
database, and this brings us to the third hurdle. This will
be what we'll look at towards the end of this module, actually
gaining access to objects within a database. And there are a
few different strategies that you can use for this. Now, when
it comes to the tools that I'll use to build all this, yes, like
a lot of things we've seen. I have the graphical user interface.
>> Absolutely.
>> Like we've seen before, I have code-based methods, create log-in,
alter, drop, et cetera.
>> There you go.
>> And along with these log-in objects, they have configurable options.
>> All right.
>> Not a lot of options, but some. All right. So next up, let's
take a look at administrative capabilities at the instance level.
So we'll refer to these as server-level roles, server-level permissions.
Now, think of being on a cruise ship.
>> Okay.
>> So being on a cruise ship, boy, you would really not want to
fall from one of those cruise ships, because...
>> No....
>> a cruise ship isn't going to be able to stop on a dime.
It's not going to really be able to turn on a dime either.
>> Hope you can swim.
>> So the comparison here is that there are certain things that
have been part of the SQL Server product that have been around
for a long time and they're hard to let go of.
>> Okay.
>> And in particular, I'm referring to server-based roles.
Sometimes they're called fixed server roles, namely, because
I can't change their name, I can't change their permissions.
The one thing I could do is add or remove members.
>> Okay.
>> Drum roll, please. We have some product excitement.
>> Uh-oh, something new?
>> Something new. Now, in SQL 2012, finally, we have the ability
to create our own server-based roles. You'll get to see this
coming up in a moment.
>> Party favors and cheers, please.
>> There you go. All right. Awesome.
>> DBAs have been screaming for that one for a long time.
>> Yeah, namely because often the fixed server roles granted a
whole lot more than you would normally want to for any particular
purpose, so that really made them null and void.
So in order to create both server roles and to be able to assign
more granular server level permissions, we have a few tools that apply.
Any surprises, we have Management Studio.
>> I would hope so.
>> But we also have a system store procedure, if I want to use
code to add a member of a role, and if I want to create a role,
so you see those two code elements there.
>> So would it be safe to say, then, that if you don't want to
assign specific permissions to a user, you use... you create
a user-defined role and assign the permissions?
>> Yeah, good strategy.
>> Awesome.
>> All right. So guys, if you'd cut over to my virtual machine.
>> Let's go take a gander.
>> I'll collapse a few things to tidy up,
and we'll focus at the instance level here. So notice I have
the security node, and under the security node I have server roles.
These would be what we would consider as fixed database roles.
Now, having been with the product for a long time, I recognize
these names. These are all fixed roles. Not a single role is
a nondefault role. These are default roles, so to say.
>> Okay.
>> So with the graphical user interface, I now am able to create
a new server-level role. So let's call this administer log-ins.
>> All right.
>> And now I'm able to grant access to the particular log-ins
that I might want to grant access to, whoever those might be.
So I have one selected. I could grant the control permission,
and of course, I'm able to script out almost any graphical user
interface activity and put all of that in code. So now that
I've created the name of the role, the permissions of the role,
this is where I would determine who the members of the role are,
and now I could add members.
>> Just as an aside, that script button, that is a great way to
record the stuff that you're doing to your database, to your
instance so that when you try and go back and figure it out a
few days later, you can actually remember it.
>> Are you a record-keeping kind of a person?
>> When it comes to databases, I am.
>> Yep. All right.
All righty. So next up,
I'm going to create a couple of log-ins, and
as I'm able to create a log-in with the graphical user interface,
you'll see that I can also create log-ins in code.
And you'll observe from the names here, these are not Windows
naming conventions. A Windows naming convention would require
a machine name or, more likely, a domain name, a backslash, and
then a name, which means that these are SQL log-ins.
>> Okay. And what are those options that you've got set on there,
like default database and check policy?
>> Yeah. So I think I skipped this, pointing this out on a slide before.
I had a little picture of a laser pointer on one of the slides
and skipped stating what the relevance of that was. When a user
successfully connects through the front door of a SQL, they are always...
repeat after me...
>> Always....
>> always pointed at a particular database. So using the default
database option says when someone comes through the front door,
their laser pointer, so to say, is pointed at that particular database.
Now, you can move your laser pointer when the use database statement,
but this sets up a default option. And also, you can determine
whether you want a SQL log into forcefully adhere to a Windows
password policy or not. When you do, that seriously raises the
security and safety of SQL log-ins.
>> So that would be like password expiration and complexity, things
like that?
>> Perfect. I'm glad you brought those up.
>> Awesome.
>> So I can't remember if I ran this or not. Okay. I didn't.
Otherwise I would have had an error, and with the refresh notice,
I have a bunch more... a bunch more objects. So at this point,
I would be able to go to the instance. Let me just look at a
couple of those names. Okay. Bob and Brandi.
Go to properties.
Go to properties of the instance.
>> Okay.
>> Go to permissions.
Now I see the list of log-ins. So let's say Brandi, we want to
grant her, instead of membership in a role, maybe she's a developer
and we want to grant her create any database.
So grant, create any database with Brandi being selected.
>> Awesome.
>> Now, maybe Jane needs more authority than that, and once Jane
is selected, now I assign her a grant control server.
There's a general principle I want to bring out about create
any database, and that is, if I have the ability to create something
and I exercise that privilege, then I own the object I created,
and if I own it, that's supreme.
I have ultimate control over it.
>> Awesome.
>> All right. So that shows how to create a server-based role,
how to create log-ins, and how to assign them privileges.
And now in code, you'll see how I can create a server role in
code, now grant a permission to that particular server-level
role, and now add a member to that role.
>> Neat.
>> I want to give you guys a little phrase here that might help
you out.
Principals are assigned permissions to
securables; a principal being something that can be granted access;
a securable being something that is protectable within the system;
and then a permission ties they will together.
All right. I think that was all that I had for that one.
Just server scope permission. So I also have server scope permissions,
grant control on log-in, grant create any database. So that's
a code-based version of what we saw.
>> Okay.
>> And then a connect permission.
>> So if you've got server-level security set up, does that automatically
give you permissions and abilities to act within a database?
>> No. So what we've just looked at is clearing the first hurdle,
both in the sense of getting into the instance with a log-in
and then having administrative privileges at the instance.
We're now going to echo that, but at the database scope. So we'll
take a look at getting access within a particular database and
then administering a database, as well. So we'll see in this
topic, we'll look at creating database users from log-ins.
We'll take a look at database level roles and a nifty trick,
something you may be familiar with, maybe not, called application roles.
So off to database users.
>> All right. So what is a database user? How do they work?
>> A database user represents the second hurdle of the three hurdles
in my picture, and we see that in order to gain access to a particular
database, my log-in at the instance level needs to be registered
at the database level. I could have an instance with 50 or 100
databases, but I might have only access to one. So whatever
databases I need access to, I'm going to have to have my log-in
registered at the database level in the form of a user object.
Now, I may want to divide the responsibility of administering
a particular database, and in that case, I also have database
level roles. Similar to the instance level, there have always
been fixed database level roles.
Their name... they're called fixed for the same reasons.
>> Okay.
>> Can't change their name.
Can't change their permissions. But I can change membership.
>> All right.
>> Also similar to this server level, in general, they give away
more privileges than I would want to, so we'll often have an
alternate technique for granting administrative privileges.
These... this would be solved in the form of a user-defined database role.
All right. Now, application roles. I explicitly described those
actually in a slide or two, so we'll get to that in a moment.
>> So can we talk a little bit more about those database level
roles, George?
>> Yeah. So you'll see from the screen capture here, I can...
let's see...
I had to see...
get my bearings there. So I selected...
>> It's been a long day.
>> Yeah, been a long day.
In fact, if you guys will cut over to my machine, I think I'd
rather just show this.
So I'm going to navigate to a particular database,
expand the database, go security, and from a confusion standpoint,
notice that I have security at the instance level, but each database
also has its own security node. I think this can be confusing
at times for those that are new to the product. So when I go
to roles, I have database roles, and once again, this represents
my fixed set of database roles.
>> Okay.
>> I also have users defined, and if I want to have a user registered
at this particular database, so that would be the fancy DEB,
when in doubt I'm going to right click, I'm going to choose to
create a new user, and from here I'll define the classification
of user that I want, a SQL user with a log-in... we'll talk
about this shortly... or a Windows user.
>> Okay.
>> Notice the form changes...
>> Yep....
>> based on my choice. If I have a Windows user, I'm going to
obviously have to pick the location of that Windows user and
then either grab a group or I'm going to have to grab
a Windows user.
>> Okay.
>> Or I could grab a SQL log-in, and in this case...
>> You give it a user name, right?
>> I'm going to have to go ahead and pick what particular log-in
it is, and this is where I'll see the laundry list of log-ins
that I made.
I don't know why it picked more than one. So I only wanted to
pick one.
All right. So that's how I would create a database level user.
>> Okay.
>> Except, notice the foil there.
>> You need to have a user name.
>> Yeah. This is... even though this is derived... oops. I lost
my mic there for a sec. Even though this is derived from a Windows
log-in name, strangely, the name doesn't have to match at the
database level.
>> That's a good thing.
>> Yeah, this could be a good thing, because I could have something
like a lengthy or obtuse Windows group name and maybe make a
friendlier name within the database system. But for right now,
I just going to do a quick copy and paste, make that easy.
>> So if it makes sense for traceability and being able to track
back through, it probably makes sense to name the user name and
the log-in the same thing most often.
>> You know, I think so. I'm kind of Captain Straightforward,
and I think, honestly as I age, I like straightforward more and more.
>> All right.
>> All right. Next up, and I'm kind of... I kind of jumped ahead
to our demonstration since it was convenient, but...
>> That's all right. We talk about it while we're doing it.
>> So now going to database roles, notice I can create a new database role.
This particular part of the feature has been around as long as
I've worked with SQL, so at least all the way back to SQL 2000
and probably way before that, as well. So I would identify pools
of people, either administratively or within the database that
needs some access, and I would come up with a name that represents
the kind of access that they need, so something like healthcare
table access.
>> So really what we're talking about is people that serve the
same function rather than have the same identity?
>> Exactly. So after I make a role, that would be one of the legs
of this, I should say after I create a name, then, of course,
I'm going to have to add one or more members. And notice the
members that I can add here fall within these classes, either
users, so log-ins registered at the database level, or strangely,
I can nest a database role within another database role. Be careful
about overengineering that, though. All right. So let's go
ahead and add, even if it's only one person. Now, the final
part of this story...
I can't give this away just yet... is assigning permissions
to the role. That we're going to take a look at a little bit later.
>> All right.
So what about application roles, George? Are user...
are database level roles and application level roles the same thing?
>> No. In fact, let's go ahead and cut back over to my virtual
machine for a second. See, there are some smartypantses out there,
and some of the smartypantses have connected some dots.
They'll say something like...
>> Okay.
>> ...well, hey, I use this application, it connects to a particular
database, maybe somebody gave them some details, they know what
the server name is, maybe they even know some of the objects
they would access, so they could do something like this. In fact,
I don't even remember if I have Office on this machine. But let's
say we did.
>> Hey, we've got one.
>> So now I could go ahead and make a connection directly to a
SQL Server, and if it was based on my Windows or SQL credentials,
I'd be able to make a connection and manipulate objects completely
outside of the applications logic.
>> Wait a minute. Are you trying to say to me that a user who's
got access through an application,
if I create their user name, they can come in some other way
and still get at the data?
>> At the moment.
>> Oh, dear.
>> Yep. So one of two things is true, Rich. That's the way that
I want it, or that's not the way that I want it.
>> So what if I don't want it that way?
>> So if that's not the way that I want it, I actually have a control.
Let me go ahead and get out of this first.
I like to think of Superman when I think of application roles,
and here's why. What you want to picture is someone going through
a telephone booth. Clark Kent, let's say.
>> Okay.
>> He goes through as one identity and comes out as a new identity.
Generally speaking, something with more privileges.
>> Okay.
>> So in that case, I can set up an application role which we'll
observe involves creating a name. Let's call this pharmacy access.
>> Okay.
>> And you'll notice the elements or the building blocks here.
Whoops. Just like...
that's smooth. Okay. Just like with the regular database role,
it has a name.
>> Okay.
>> So da, da, da. And just like a database role, it has securables
or those things that I want to assign permissions to.
>> Okay.
>> What's different is this part. Whoops. This part.
>> All right. That's got a password.
>> Yeah, so notice, this has a password and notice it does not
have members.
>> You know, I was looking at that and I was wondering, how does
somebody use the role if you don't have membership?
>> So let me just put in a dummy password here so that I'm able
to complete the creation of this object.
>> Okay.
>> And that will be the activation password.
So let me go back. If you'd go back to the slides for a moment
there, troopers.
>> All righty.
>> Now, what I need is my front-end application. I'm sorry.
I have to back up. So I'm a human and I open up an application.
>> Okay.
>> I open up a Web URL, I open up a Windows application.
That application is going to have code behind to make a connection
to the database.
>> Okay.
>> From there it will bear my credentials in interacting with
the database, except if I have an application role, I have a
statement that says this connection is going into the telephone
booth and coming out as somebody different, but the end user
does not know that this happened. They neither know the role
name, nor do they know the activation password that I just set up.
>> So SQL's not giving permission or allowing access based on
who they are, but rather, by code telling them what they can do.
>> Exactly. So only based on what their role dictates will they
have access, which means then if smartypants user would now attempt
to use Excel and attempt to make a connection to the database, that...
they wouldn't have any permissions.
>> Okay.
>> Because they would be assigned to the application role.
So there we go.
>> Awesome.
>> All right. That's going to take care of our demo coming up
of us implementing database level security.
>> So the last piece of this, then, is really going to be permissions.
>> Yep. So now we have object permissions... or implementing permissions.
Object permissions, code and module permissions, and we have
to get some to some permission management strategies.
>> Okay. Let's take a look then at
object permissions.
>> All right. So I have a broad class of objects that are contained
within a database. We have tables, views. You see there are
a bunch of other objects there. Object permissions apply to those
particular objects. Now, there's a phrase that I used earlier:
If I have to do something once...
>> I'm probably going to need to do it more than once.
>> ...probably going to have to do it again. So I would tend
to want to avoid giving permissions to single objects, and when
I can leverage a better strategy, meaning if Susie needs access
to table one, then she's probably going to need access to table
two or a broader base of objects. So that means now I'm managing
access on an object-by-object basis.
So the other thing is, Susie may be here today, but she may go,
and that means now I'm going to have to take Patty or Mikey or
somebody else and assign them all the same security that Susie had.
>> Okay.
>> So let's see if there might be a way that we can improve efficiency there.
As far as object permissions are concerned, it depends on the
type of object. So I might need to change the structure of something
like a table, maybe I need to add a column, add a constraint,
so alter permissions might apply. Another possible permission
is broad control where I have, really, unrestricted access to
a particular object. Now, for objects that hold data such as
a table, we have data manipulation language statements that we
can execute, select permission, insert, et cetera. And then
finally, what I call the tattletale permission.
>> The tattletale?
>> I might want someone to be able to look at the code that defined
an object, but not have them change the definition of the object.
It's a minimalist permission, so we have the view definition permission.
>> Awesome. Now, are objects the only things that you can set
permissions on? Are there other things that we're going to need
to deal with?
>> In addition to objects like tables and that, we also have executable
T-SQL code objects such as stored procedures and certain kinds
of functions.
>> Okay.
>> So they also have permissions that apply to them. Some overlap,
but not a perfect overlap. The primary permissions that apply
on a code module would be the execute permission to use it.
So if I wanted to use a stored procedure,
execute it within code, I would need, well, the execute permission.
>> Okay. So how do you set up these permissions? How do you get
them to apply so that you can manage everything?
>> Sure. Consistent within SQL Server we have Management Studio,
and within Management Studio I can start with a principal, that
is, let's say, Mary needs permissions. I can get properties
on Mary and then point her to the particular securable.
Alternately, I can go to the securable and then bring principals
that I want to assign permissions. So it kind of depends on,
well, somewhat preference, but also if I need to assign a principal
to multiple objects, start with a principal. If I have a securable
that needs multiple principal assignments, start with a securable.
>> Okay.
>> So there's no crime either way. You can get the job done.
>> All right.
>> Now, if I want to do it in T-SQL code, I have my normal DCL
statements, data control language statements, grant, revoke,
and deny. Should we talk about those for a minute?
>> Absolutely. I think they're important.
>> All right. So when... I have this nice candy bar. Thanks, Microsoft.
I saw that out in the hallway here. Let's consider this as a
precious resource of some kind, and it is a good one, too.
>> Okay.
>> All right.
Let's consider this is some precious resource that I have.
If I want to extend that to someone else...
>> Thank you.
>> I use the grant statement.
>> If I eat this now, that's going to cause you problems, right?
>> Now, let's say
I had provided something to Rich and I no longer want it to be
that way, I can take it back.
That would be a revoke statement.
There's another circumstance, and that is when... well, Rich,
you're right next to me. I'm going to pick on you.
>> Okay.
>> Let's say you're a member of a role.
So you're a member of a role. Let's say it's the sales role,
and I grant you access to a particular table. I grant the group
access to a table. And maybe that group is granted access to
a number of different tables.
>> Okay.
>> But there's one particular table the group has access to that
they don't want you to have access to.
>> Are you picking on me?
>> Absolutely. And in this case, I'm kind of at a fork in the road.
>> Okay.
>> Neither road will be easy. One road is to create another group
with the same sales members except you.
>> Okay.
>> And that means now I have to manage two separate groups and
remember when to use which one. This is not tidy.
>> All right.
>> Perhaps the path of lesser evil is to keep you in the group,
assign the group permissions to the table the group needs, and
then I explicitly assign you the deny permission.
So that's one way that may reduce my overall effort of administration,
but you have to do that sparingly. It can make your troubleshooting
somewhat more difficult.
>> So you can either let me do it by saying you're granting it
to me, or you can tell me no, you can't do it by denying me.
>> Exactly. And there's one more kind of strangeness. Let's say
that I gave you a negative. I gave you a deny.
>> Okay.
>> I can actually use the revoke statement to remove the negative.
>> Ah.
>> So keep in mind, removing a negative is also performed with
the revoke statement.
>> So grant makes an entry, deny makes an entry, revoke removes
an entry.
>> Good observation, or, you know, good point to make.
>> Nice.
>> And then finally, there is a security anomaly that's been fixed
in SQL 2012. This is...
>> This goes back a long way, too.
>> Goes back a long way. Prior to when I was working with the product.
>> Yep.
>> It's been in there as long as I've known. Namely, I can have
a table level deny and a column level grant that will succeed.
I didn't really talk about column level grants, so you're learning
two things here. First, yes, column level grant has been around
in the product for a while where I grant just certain columns.
But the anomaly of a column level grant overriding a table level
deny no longer exists. Everybody say "ah."
>> Ah.
>> All right.
>> All right. So what about the strategies? How do we apply all
this stuff? What are some approaches we can take?
>> All right. I'm going to take pain somewhere.
>> Usually.
>> So it's just a matter of where I want pain, and normally it's
always better to take pain up front.
>> Okay.
>> And I coined a term here.
I'm going to be famous for this some day. Double abstraction,
and I want to tell you what I mean by this. We're going to review
a couple different ways to implement permissions.
Ultimately, here's my phrase: You want to make sure that you
design so that the design works hard for you rather than make
you work hard.
>> Makes sense.
>> So at the far left here we see that we could have a couple
of database objects and use our database user objects and directly
grant them access to those objects. The thing is maybe one of
those is Bill. Bill might come and go, so now I have to remove
Bill and then I'm going to have to add Susie and grant her access
to all those objects all over again.
>> Okay.
>> Remember, the work stays pretty much the same.
>> Yep.
>> But the worker changes.
>> So I can improve this a little bit in the next model if I use
something like a Windows group. So at least a Windows group will
have members, although I'm still taking the group and directly
assigning them access to objects. Still maybe not the greatest idea.
>> But the odds of getting rid of a group are probably less than
getting rid of an individual user.
>> Absolutely. So this is definitely an improvement.
>> Okay.
>> Now, even better is using a database or an application role,
and I've used them interchangeably for this particular purpose.
Again, the work is going to stay pretty much the same. The workers
will change. So I can create a semi-fixed relationship of assigning
permissions from a role to one or more objects and then just
manage membership. So this is where you want to aim. You want
to aim for managing membership and not doing all the granular
permission changing.
>> That way you assign the permissions one time, and then you
just add people in and out instead of having to keep changing
the permissions.
>> Exactly.
>> I like that.
>> And in the next model, I raise this just a little bit by using
Windows groups that are added to database roles.
>> Okay.
>> Now, in fact I skipped a little detail. You don't add a Windows
group to a role. You would have a log-in defined from a Windows
group, then that's registered at the user level, which is then
made a member of a database role. Okay. So then...
>> That makes a lot of sense, but what about permissions at the
object level? I mean, is there a way to group things there?
>> In fact, what we see... this is the drum roll, big conclusion.
Thank you very much.
>> Hey.
>> We'll find that all objects are contained within schemas, at
least certain data accessible objects, stored procedures, tables,
views, et cetera. They're contained within a schema. The fancy
part is that we can use schemas to collect objects that need
uniform permissions like a bunch of stored procedures that a
pool of people need to execute.
>> Okay.
>> Or a bunch of tables where people need to select an insert
into, not delete, not update. So I can pool those objects inside
a schema, grant permissions to the schema. Now, in this case,
I get double...
easy for me to say... I get double abstraction.
So on one end, I can add or remove objects to the schema and
not have to assign permissions to them. Because the permission
was assigned to the schema, I don't need to worry about permissions
to the individual object, so I add another stored procedure.
It needs execute. Great. Now, the other end of double abstraction,
instead of having to assign permissions, when I get a new Mikey,
a new Sheila, I just add them as a member of the role. So I
have abstraction on both sides of the permission equation, and
Rich, you're excited about it.
>> I'm absolutely over the top. I can't wait to see it, actually.
>> All right.
>> So how about it?
>> Let's move on to that.
>> All right. Let's go take a look at the demo.
And in this one we're going to be playing with those permissions
that we were just talking about.
>> All right. So let's go ahead and create... let's see. I made
a database role,
and next up let's go ahead and create a schema object.
>> Okay.
>> So let's say I create a new schema. We'll call this manufacturing schema.
>> I like that.
>> Do you?
>> Yeah. It means we're making something.
>> All right.
All right. Now, let's see. I have to look at what database I
was in. So I was in the fancy database. Let me make sure I'm
pointed to the fancy database. And now we'll create just a couple
of objects, create table, and we'll get the schema name,
.t1 for table one.
Just make something sort of silly.
>> Yep.
>> Execute that.
>> Easy table.
>> All right. Next up we'll make another table. Actually, this
time let's create a procedure.
We'll call it p1
for proc one
as select * from
manufacturing .t1.
>> Okay.
>> So we've got a table. We've got a procedure. What's next?
>> We've got a table and we've got a procedure. Okay. So now
using, of course, both the GUI or code, I'm going to take my
role and assign it to the schema.
>> Okay.
>> Which way do you want to start, from the role or the ischemia?
>> Oh, surprise me, George.
>> Okay. So let's start at the schema. I'll go to properties.
We'll go to permissions.
>> Okay.
>> And this is where I will assign a database level principal,
a user or a role.
>> Okay.
>> So on one end we have the abstraction of objects being in the schema.
That's already been set up. But now let's go ahead and pick a role.
So object types. We see database level objects, and now let's
pick the particular one. All right. Pick whatever role we want.
The one we're picking isn't material to the demonstration.
>> All right.
>> Just by virtue of picking a role.
>> Okay.
>> And so now I have the three legs of the permission stool, so
to say. I have the securable. That's the schema object and the
items in it. I have the principal, and now we have to combine
those in here...
sorry... in here
and grant a permission. So let's say we have execute, grant execute
for stored procedures and grant insert and select for tables, S.
Whoops, it comes lower in the alphabet.
>> It has been a long day, hasn't it?
>> All righty.
>> I'm having trouble remembering my alphabet today. Don't worry.
>> There we go. All righty. We have a few minutes left with this session.
Can I take a little bit of liberty here, Alise?
>> Yeah. Go for it.
>> There are a few resources that I want to direct people to,
in particular some websites that have email subscriptions.
They'll send some stuff daily to you in your inbox, so at the
expense of piling up a little bit of mail, I've been immensely
benefited by being a subscriber to some of these. So in some
form of follow-up, we'll make sure we get this... we'll make
sure we get this to you, but to list them by name, here are some
of my favorites. First, MSSQLTips.com.
A great one. So MS SQL tips. There are lots of contributors,
lots of real smartypantses that contribute there. Another one, SQLServerCentral.com.
Pretty parallel sites in terms of what they offer.
Email-based subscriptions, tips, code.
Lots of great stuff.
Another one, these are from... these two are... at least one
is a former Microsoft employee and they live here in Seattle
Metro area, this is Paul S. Randal and Kimberly Trips, their
group, SQLSkills.com.
An interesting thing, Paul Randal is a big book reader and he'll
often tell you what he's reading, and he reads some crazy stuff.
So when I say crazy, I mean a broad variety. That's pretty nifty.
So thanks for putting up the
Web URLs. And then a couple of other things. Rich, would you
add up SQLSaturday.com.
They're are SQL Saturday free one-day training events.
>> If I can spell "Saturday," I'll be happy to.
>> All over the planet, and I've got to put in a little plug for
SQL Saturday Kalamazoo, Michigan coming up in November. You know...
>> That would be that one right there, huh, George?
>> You know what? We'll have people come from Chicago, Ohio, all
over Michigan, and there's some real smartypantses that work
hard and contribute a lot to that event. This will be my third
SQL Saturday Kalamazoo. Maybe my fourth, but really good stuff.
>> And I just want to point out that these are not just events
that are here in the US. As you can see from the listing here,
Lima, Peru, and Kona, Italy, Slovenia. So no matter where you're
viewing this from, check this out because they're may be an event
that's pretty close to you and you can get the benefits from
it as well.
>> Two more, if I can.
>> Uh-oh.
>> You know what? I think we'll save one for the BI one, pragmatic works.
We'll wait on them.
>> Okay.
>> But one more. Go to SQLPASS.org, if you would, please.
>> SQLPASS.org.
>> SQLPASS.org. So this is the laundry list of PASS oriented user
groups all around. Somewhere on there see... you'll find a local chapter.
It's in the upper right.
>> Okay.
>> Or towards the right.
>> There we go. If it were any bigger, it would have hit me.
>> Danny, what state did you grow up?
>> Illinois.
>> Okay. So let's do PASS region, United States.
>> There's Canada, US.
>> US. Let's see. Illinois, so Midwest heartland I think is what
they call it.
>> Okay.
>> Pick one. It doesn't matter and just search.
>> All right.
>> So I can pretty much guarantee if you're anywhere near a major
city, there are going to be some PASS chapters nearby.
>> Awesome. Awesome.
>> I've benefited a lot from being involved. See, in Michigan,
you show where you live by holding up your hand. I'm right smack
dab in mid Michigan, so I'm not from far Grand Rapids, a little
more than an hour. Not far from Detroit. A little more than
an hour. So I'll participate in both user groups, and most recently
I was able to speak in our Detroit user group. A lot of fun there.
>> And again, just want to point out that as with the last website
we showed you, there are lots of international chapters available
as well. I just very quickly pulled up some of the Asia Pacific chapters.
There are others in Latin America, in Europe as well, so, again,
great resource and being able to connect with folks that have
the same interests, the same professional responsibilities can
be invaluable. So...
>> Yep. Good stuff. All righty. So that concludes this particular segment.
One more segment left, and definitely...
>> That would be it....
>> an important and a very interesting segment, something I've
put a lot of time and enthusiasm into, and that's high availability.
So we're going to take a short break and after that...
>> Yes....
>> session six of six.
>> Oh, my goodness. We're coming to the end. Oh, no. I'm disappointed.
See you back here at top of the hour.