[Music]
Welcome back to the Administering  SQL Server Jump Start 2012.
We are still here. We're still talking. I'm Rich Currey.
Mr. SQL in his name, George Squillace. George, what do we got
going in this module?
>> Thank you. You can see from the intro slide here now up is
performance optimization and troubleshooting. Quick little,
I don't know,
tracking the trail here. So we first learned how we are going
to install the product, make sure it gets put on a good foundation.
Then we saw server and database level options that we may sit...
or that we may set. But you know, Rich, SQL Server is a dynamic environment.
>> Absolutely.
>> Lots of things can change moment by moment. So I have kind
of a rule of thumb.
>> And what would that be?
>> We need tools...
>> Okay....
>> that give us facts.
>> Okay.
>> But a fact isn't good enough. If an airline pilot knew they
didn't have enough fuel to get to their destination...
>> That wouldn't be a good thing.
>> Not good. Beyond facts, I'm then going to need to make conclusions.
I don't have enough fuel. I don't have enough resources for this task.
>> Okay.
>> And then, finally, I need to do something about it.
>> Awesome.
>> So the focus in this particular module are on tools and the
facts that they provide. So moving along, we're going to take
a look at a general principle, general definition "locking."
We'll see how that ties into blocking and then how that ties
into something particularly negative, deadlocking. We will look
at couple other tools: Profiler, auditing and some other tools
that relate to performance data capturing.
>> So what is locking and blocking and deadlocks? What are those
all about, George?
>> All righty.
So general principle in SQL Server, when data... when data is
under modification, picture an eagle with its talons on that
particular unit of data, whatever it might be.
>> Okay.
>> Whether it is a table, an entire table, or an entire row and
a key value. There are ranges of lockable resources. And it's
kind of like... (slapping)... slapping a hand, making sure that
nothing else can touch that data while under modification.
>> Okay.
>> In a multi-user database system, locking is natural and expected
and, in fact, required in order to maintain data integrity.
>> So locking's a normal operation, happens all the time.
>> Natural and expected. And we'll see that SQL Server...
Who wrote the code to do this?
Dynamically SQL Server will shrink and grow lockable resources
based on its efficiency rule book such as locking just a key
value or locking a whole row or a page all the way up to very
large scale locks. For example, I restore database, well, the
whole database is locked then.
>> So SQL Server manages the locking escalation itself.
>> Thankfully it does all of it by default. We do have opportunity
to stick our hands in the machinery when we absolutely need to.
We won't be looking at that. So next definition then is "blocking"
which we will see firsthand in a moment. But for now, blocking
occurs when one connection is waiting for other connections to
release their locked resources.
And in a multi-user database system...
>> Happens all the time....
>> some blocking is expected. So at what point does this become
out of whack?
>> Probably when it keeps people from getting the information
they need.
>> Yes. So excessive blocking is undesirable. And then we take
this up even one further notch. We'll also see this in an upcoming demonstration.
A deadlock occurs when two connections have locked resources
and now they're seeking each other's resources.
>> Okay.
>> And neither... neither connection can terminate until they
have each other's resources. As you can imagine, this would produce
an infinite loop. SQL Server does something about it, but I can't
give the end of the movie just yet.
>> Uh-oh. And it is a movie, right, "Catch 22"?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Oh yeah. So how do we discover them? How do we solve them?
>> So we have seen thus far that there are often a number of tools
for any particular job. There's no difference here. We have
client error messages that will tell us about deadlock problems specifically.
Activity Monitor will tell us about locking and blocking.
We have dynamic management objects, a separate topic coming up.
We have Profiler, a separate topic coming up. And an area which
is getting more and more momentum is Extended Events. If you
want to find out more about Extended Events, there are some people
out in the industry that are particularly excited about those.
So there's a reference there.
Now, finally, deadlock problems are solved... wait, that's not
quite accurate.
>> I was going to say.
>> You cannot completely solve deadlock problems. Even some deadlocks
are just going to occur.
>> Yep.
>> But you want to minimize them.
>> Okay.
>> So some of the ways that you'd minimize them would be making
sure the stored procedures that access a series of objects access
them in the same order.
>> Okay.
>> Also, think special operations team.
When I say "spec ops," Think of, you know, the Navy SEALs.
They get in in the cover of darkness, they do their stuff, they
are out of there accomplishing their mission before anybody knows
what happens.
>> Okay.
>> No jokes, please. We will also find out to a degree you can
stick your hands in a machinery by setting a connection level
setting called the transaction isolation level.
And then also you don't want to be browsing data while it's already
under modification, explicit
or implicit transaction.
>> So can we take a look at one of the tools that we might use
to find blocking issues maybe?
>> Yes. Let's take a look at Activity Monitor.
We'll have some fun here.
Now, you'll notice at the moment, for whatever this is worth,
I'm connected to the Adventure Works database. And Adventure
Works happens to have a table here called person.person. It has
got about 20,000 rows, just for giggles. And we will notice
that I'm freely able to query this. If I look down, you will
see I have about 20,000 rows.
>> Okay.
>> So nothing too dramatic right now. But next, I'm going to
copy this code... by the way, psst, take a look at the server
process ID here.
>> Okay, process ID 54. Got it.
>> So every connection is assigned, we call it, a SPID, server
process ID. By the way, a little shoutout to SPID.
That IS the SQL Server... actually, SQL Pass In Detroit, the
SQL Pass user group. So... I'm from Michigan so I got to put
in a plug for our own little SPID there. We have a great group there.
>> Whoo-hoo.
>> Anyway... Yeah, whoo-hoo. I will create a new query window
and I will paste the same code in here and run it. What we find
is that window by window, I can execute and use the same data
at the same time. Nothing dramatic thus far.
>> So everybody can do everything, no blocking going on.
>> No blocking at the moment because no data is under modification.
So next up, let's make a change. Let's update person.person.
>> Okay.
>> And let's see if this would be, as you call it, Rich, a resume'...
what's the RP? Resume' producing event.
>> Okay. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> Let's cause a resume' producing event or at least come close.
>> That typically would be a change that is not a good thing within
the database.
>> And notice my change here. I'm changing all 20,000 context
to last name Smith without a where clause. Woopsie.
>> Okay. That's... oh, capital P.
>> That is... that's right. It is a collation thing.
>> Yeah, this database was put in with a collation sequence that's
case sensitive.
>> Yep. Thanks for covering my tracks there. And same thing here.
>> Yeah.
>> Of course, I didn't prewrite out the code for this one.
So...
>> There we go.
So the change is going on. It is updating all the records.
We got 20,000 records updated, basically.
>> And to see if it really occurred, let me scroll through a whole
bunch of rows here. What do you observe?
>> Yep. It's all Smith.
>> So I got a whole lot of Smiths. But now let's see what happens
if I go to another window and
I attempt to access that same data.
>> Okay. Now, is it my imagination or did it actually come back
already when you did it earlier?
>> No. In my other SPID, I should say my original SPID, the one
that's holding onto the locked resources, it actually is able
to look at that data. That's a special privilege for that particular connection.
But what I'm seeing right here reminds me of Ferris Bueller when
he is expected to be in class.
>> Bueller? Bueller?
>> Bueller, anyone?
>> Yep.
>> And, of course, this data will never be returned until we have
the other transaction complete or terminate. And this is where
Activity Monitor comes in.
>> Now, if I were to get a phone call from somebody saying, "Hey,
I have been sitting on this query for a while," how can I figure
out what the cause of that block is?
>> Exactly. That's where Activity Monitor comes in. So, strangely,
they moved it from the user interface in Object Explorer a version
or two ago. And now it is just a button up here in the tool bar.
>> Okay.
>> So I click on Activity Monitor. We're not going to take the
full-time to look at all of these areas, but there's just a lot
of great information here.
>> Okay.
>> We're going to focus on processes.
Now, you may remember, the original SPID that started to modify
data was SPID 54.
>> I remember that. You asked me what it was.
>> Excellent. And as I... as I
scroll over here, we'll see the head blocker, if I was to expand that.
SPID 54 is blocking one other connection. That's what I know
from here.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> Next, if I go to SPID 55, we'll see that it is being blocked
by SPID 54. So this point, Rich, you got your phone call.
Hey, what's going on? You know, I'm... can't seem to finish
whatever I'm trying to do.
>> Okay.
>> At this point, one available option to the DBA is to determine
which process they might want to kill; or they could, of course,
do this in code.
>> Awesome.
>> So now I'm going to head back to my original connection, SPID 54.
And I will roll back the transaction after I spell it properly.
And let's quickly flip over to the other SPID. Observe now,
A, I have results and, B, notice all the last names came back.
>> Yeah, no more Smith.
>> So Activity Monitor could be a really useful resource to find
out why somebody might be blocked at the moment.
>> And is that the only way that you can get information on what's
going on, George? What's one of the other tools that we've got?
>> Oh, we're loaded with tools. And next up, we're going to take
a look at Profiler. Profiler is broader than merely locking tracking.
Think of Profiler as capturing general kinds of activity that's
going on in SQL Server. And, in fact, as I move to the topic
slide, this is going to introduce us to the topic of tracing
which then will lead us into the topic of what Profiler... pardon me...
and what it does.
>> Awesome.
>> So what is tracing? Tracing is the under-the-covers capturing
of activity by the SQL Server process. And you will find that
it can record and track all kinds of activity which we refer
to as "events" that are contained within event classes. So notice
the hierarchy from the side here. I might have one event class,
like the locking class, and then the deadlock or blocking events.
Another class might be the T SQL class and then T SQL statement
begun, T SQL statement completed would be events.
>> Okay.
>> Now, using system stored procedures, I can, A, turn tracing
on, determine what I want to capture, then perform all aspects
related to tracing completely without an user interface.
And the link that I have at the bottom of the slide will lead
you to a further study there.
>> Awesome. Is it only through stored procedures? Is there another
way that you can get that tracing going?
>> Well, for some of us who are mere mortals, or at least just
exploring, keep in mind there is a graphical user interface into
the tracing subsystem. This is a good way to get a head start.
Brace yourself, Rich.
>> Uh-oh.
>> I have heard stories from some of my student customers saying
that based on being told by Microsoft product support services
that they have to turn this on to capture something that it will
generate gigs and gigs of data in no short time or no quick time frame.
>> Absolutely. The bigger the database, the more the data is going
to be generated.
>> So you'll observe... although the screen shot is a little bit
detailed, what you see is, A, a laundry list of captured events.
And then when one particular event is selected, you get a lot
of detail about it.
>> Awesome.
>> So Profiler is a graphical user interface tool. I will add
it that it adds significant amounts of overhead to the tracing
subsystem, which is why the pros like to trace using the system
stored procedures.
>> Which, by the way, there is an easy way to get to because once
you've got your trace configured in the GUI, you can save it
and generate the stored procedures from the GUI, from the file
menu on a trace.
>> Fabulous. So I'd like to think of Profiler as a three-legged
stool configuration. That's what the graphic is implying here.
One of the first things I have to do when I'm configuring trace
is determining the particular events in their particular event classes.
That is, of course, of major concern and we'll find out that
a template can be used to help us along the way there.
There's some premade templates. And, Rich, knowing that you are
overzealous as you are...... you can make your own templates
and readily use those. So after I pick the events and event classes
of activity I want to capture, I then may need to go to an extra
level of detail in that there are standard columns of information
like the start time of an event, the duration of an event, other
aspects of what gets captured. But I can add more columns to
what gets captured, if there's some extra stuff I need to capture.
This will make more sense when I do my demo in just a moment.
And, finally, just a general rule, when it comes to capturing
data of any kind, only capture that which you're actually going
to bother to look at or that you actually need, and especially...
you don't want to have to find a needle in a haystack.
>> That wouldn't be good.
>> I will promise tracing can create a haystack.
[Laughter]
Now, we have to have another drumroll.
>> Uh-oh. Drumroll, please.
[Drumroll]
>> Awesome. One of the niftiest things that came about with SQL
2005 is the ability to take Windows performance monitoring data
and profiling data and merge them into one screen where I could
then capture the... basically, I could capture data in both environments
and happen to see if there's any correlation of system activity
to SQL Server activity.
>> Okay.
>> This was brilliant and really nifty. If you want to see
what that might look like, I have a link there. Also, some of
you are going to want to take Profiler to the next level.
And there's a book... a free e-book that's been put out by Simple Talk.
I think it is Brad McGee. If anybody wants to double-check me
on that go to simple-talk.com/books.
By the way, I'm big on free stuff.
>> That's... I think everybody likes free stuff.
>> I'm big on free stuff. And Simple Talk, it's armed by Redgate.
Redgate does a great amount for the community. They have a bunch
of free e-books there. So if nothing else, attending this segment,
you just got a few hundred dollars worth of free e-books.
>> Absolutely.
>> So we're good. Well, next up, let's not hold off any longer.
Let's show them how Profiler works.
>> That sounds like a plan. So what are we going to do here?
We're going to go and try to generate a deadlock and see what happens?
>> Exactly.
>> Sounds good.
>> So first up, let me go ahead and configure Profiler to be able
to capture the information that I want. Thanks for letting me
tidy up for just a little bit. And now I'm going to go to my
start menu. We will go to all programs. Yes, SQL Server 2012.
But now I'm going to go to performance tools, a different compartment.
And notice we got both kinds.
That's a "Blues Brothers" reference.
>> Uh-oh.
>> We got both kinds. We got Profiler and we got the DTA. So let's
open up Profiler.
>> You realize, that's going to go over the heads of a lot of
people, myself included.
>> Yeah, okay.
[Laughter]
Being a '80s kid, "Blues Brothers" you couldn't hardly escape.
>> I wish I could say I was a '80s kid.
[Laughter]
All right. So we got Profiler coming in.
>> Now, by virtue of seeing that we have to authenticate, this
tells you that Microsoft wouldn't have wanted just anyone...
or I should say, you as a DBA wouldn't just anyone profiling
and putting a burden on a machine. So after we validate identity,
we're going to take a look at the first leg of the stool.
So let's just call this... What's today? Wednesday?
>> Yeah, seems like it.
>> We'll just call this Wednesday AM trace. Sorry for those that
are 12 hours away, but we are glad that you're here.
Next up, I could use one of the standard templates, remember.
>> Those are the ones that choose it for you.
>> Overzealous Rich might have some of his own on his own machine.
And then I have to determine where I'm going to put the output
of the trace. So I can save that to a file. I will just pick
any old location. If this was going to accommodate a large amount
of data, then I'm going to have to put that somewhere else or
at least be concerned about where it goes.
>> Awesome.
>> So, remember, this dictated the events and event classes which
we're now going to see when we go to the next tab here, event selection.
So the standard template we'll see has picked these particular
event classes in bold and then these particular events in those
classes and then also standard. It's taking a look...
oops. That's nice you can undo the most recent scribbling.
Notice the columns or, I should say, the standard columns of
information here.
>> Okay.
>> Now, I'm going to adjust one of the legs of the stool by saying
that I want to show all events and in particular observe all
of the classes that we have. I don't really want to look at that
in super great detail, but I do want to go to the locks area.
>> Okay.
>> So from here, I'll pick, let's see, deadlock graph, lock deadlock,
and lock deadlock chain. Let's say I have an application and
I seem to be getting an inordinate amount of deadlocks, more
on the definition part there.
>> All right.
>> Okay. Next leg of the stool. I get my standard columns, but
maybe I want to expose those particular areas that offer other columns.
So I might want to say, let's say, the ID database to see...
to be accompanied with the deadlock chain and other ones.
>> So if there is a column for some events that's not included
but you're filtering on it, will that event show up in the trace
or won't it?
>> Only that which I have selected is going to show up and not
only that, but I can also filter such that events that would
normally be captured aren't... they won't go in the trace.
And, notice, I don't have a huge amount of criteria; but all
the ones I would probably want filter by database that I want
to capture, only activity in this database, or all except a particular
database and also on behalf of an application, particular user.
So I have a bunch of criteria there. So that is the third leg
of the filter. And now I'm going to run my Profiler trace.
Now, on a busy machine... this is just a lightly loaded virtual
machine, almost no activity, it will not generate a lot quickly.
A busy machine...
>> (multiple speakers) >> On
a busy machine, this would be scrolling and probably going crazy.
Next up, let's take a look at some activity or generate some
activity that's going to be captured.
And module 2... or, I'm sorry, Module 3 deadlock.
So let's first go to the marketdev database. Sorry, we're already there.
And I want you to make a mental note of a couple IDs in particular.
>> Okay.
>> So we have two different prospect IDs.
So 6800, 7800. They are going to be easy to remember. Now, movie
spoiler: Two different connections are going to end up requiring
each other's resources never to be finished. This is exactly
what a deadlock is.
>> Okay.
>> So when two resources...
I should say when two connections have holds on resources that
yet need each other's resources, this will produce an infinite
loop of those objects never being released. And we'll have to
see what SQL Server does about that.
>> Okay.
>> I won't tell. Now, notice, every connection has a SPID.
And I can use @@SPID to determine what the SPID is of my particular connection.
>> All right.
>> So let's also make a mental note I'm in SPID 55. And what
I want to do is update the first ID in the first connection.
>> Okay. So we just changed one record.
>> So I have data under modification. Notice, very sneaky, I
did not commit the transaction so now a lock is held on that
resource, all right? Now, for what it's worth, I have a couple
different ways of showing locks, sp lock. And later on in the
module we will look at dynamic management views. So we will
just leave those alone for right now. Okay. Next, open up another
connection and I'm going to have to paste the code below into
that window.
>> Okay.
>> So let me take a look at that.
Observe, new SPID 57.
We'll also notice that we can confirm that. That's sort of the duh.
But now I want to put the second ID under modification.
And it's under modification. Also notice I did not commit it.
>> All right. So we changed one record in the first window, a
different record in the second window.
>> And did not commit either. So notice, I'm now back in the first connection.
>> Okay.
>> And I'm going to attempt to update the second ID.
Now what I'm going to do...
>> That's kind of sitting there.
>> Now what I'm going to do... so notice grinding, grinding, grinding.
Now I want to go to the second connection and I want to attempt
to update
the first resource.
>> I see red. Red is not a good thing.
>> So how is this for one of the world's scariest messages?
Well,maybe not the world's scariest but transaction process blah,
blah, blah was deadlocked on locked resources or locked resources
with another process and has been chosen as the deadlocked victim.
Here's when you know you are overdue for a vacation. If you
know IP addresses of certain machines off the top of your head,
you're overdue. And if you have memorized SQL Server error message
numbers like 1205...
>> 1205 is every DBAs nightmare....
>> Rich, it is time to go to the Bahamas.
>> Never a good thing. Never a good thing.
>> So let's go back up to Profiler and see if it found anything.
You know what? Did I run it?
>> I think you are connected to the wrong database.
I have a feeling.
>> You know what? I connected to the wrong one. That was dumb.
All right.
Well...
>> Oh, well.
>> I needed to connect to pros.
>> Back to Adventure Works. Life goes on. But you know what?
The deadlock graphic that gets generated does show you all the
objects and the statements being executed, so...
>> So what do you think? Is it worth to run this again or should
we go on?
>> Nah, I think it is time to get to the next topic.
>> Well, the drama here is that I would have actually seen in
Profiler the deadlocks being listed. And then, graphically,
I would see how they acquired each other or attempted to acquire
each other's resources. And in hovering over the deadlock graphed
elements, I would get useful intel for troubleshooting. So that
was really the point of that one.
>> Awesome. And another technology we've got available to us over
and above tracing and Profiler would be auditing. What's that
all about, George?
>> So in the same way that Profiler and tracing can capture data,
auditing can capture data, too, but for a particularly different
sort of purpose. So let's take a look at a number of the auditing
techniques and then we're going to focus on one particular type
of auditing feature which literally has the name...
>> "Auditing."...
>> "SQL auditing."
>> I like that.
>> In the past, a little legacy, we had some military standards
or governmental standards...
>> Yep....
>> I guess you would consider those. C2 and common criteria were
their common names. These were...
is "implementable" a word?
>> Yeah, it is. It works.
>> It is a word today. So you can implement those in SQL Server
at the expense of lots of overhead. Now, the funny thing about
auditing is that you might need to turn auditing on to capture activity.
>> Yep.
>> You don't want people that you are trying to capture to be
able to turn it off.
>> That would be a good thing, yes.
>> So there are some safeguards there with the auditing features.
It turns out, they had a lot of overhead and have fallen really
out of mind share at least in the SQL Server community. So we'll
consider these as older methods, a lot of overhead associated
with those.
>> All right. What are some of the other ways we can audit the
database and catch information?
>> We have a bunch of different triggers that exist in SQL Server,
DML triggers, so we could capture data modifications and then
store that or use a trigger to store that in a table. Same thing
with modifying database objects. Like, if I create a table,
if I modify a table, schema, I have DBL triggers, we have a log-in triggers.
But it is good to know that they're there. They fulfill a particular purpose.
But there is a trigger limitation.
>> What's the big limitation?
>> The limitation is someone can turn it off.
>> Ooh, that's not a good thing.
>> So you don't want the person whose traffic you want to capture
be the one to turn off, you know, auditing.
>> That would be like giving the fox the key to the hen house?
>> Something like that.
>> Oh, dear. Oh, dear.
>> Next up, let's take a look at the feature SQL auditing.
>> Now, this is the one they want us to use going forward, right?
>> That's right. What does this feature provide compared to other
types of general auditing methods?
It's very granular similar to some of the previous auditing methods,
and we can track not only instance-level auditing activities
but also database-level auditing activities.
And it leverages a technology that's now part of SQL Server Extended Events.
And it's essentially, pardon me, a preconfigured Extended Events environment.
>> Okay.
>> There's some terminology we are going to go through during
the demonstration that you will have to become familiar with
in order to implement auditing.
And we'll see the configuration steps. There are actually a
series of configuration steps involved in this.
>> So what do you think? Why don't we just go and walk it through
and explain it as we show it to you.
>> Good plan.
So let me close Profiler.
>> All right.
So SQL auditing, again, it allows us to capture Event Activities
similar for what Profiler does but a little bit different technology.
>> All right. And here we go.
Now, one of the things that we have to determine when we're going
to audit is to determine the destination of our audit data.
This might be an important concern from an integrity standpoint.
We have two destinations of the log data.
>> And what are those?
>> We have the application log, and we could also specify a file
system location that maybe we exclude access to.
>> Okay.
>> So with that, I'm going to create a server audit...
create a server audit object. Notice the name of this. We will
call it MarketDevLog and dictate the destination of this.
>> So we are going to be writing the messages to the application log.
>> To the application log. Next, I'm going to go to the database
level and I'm going to create an audit specification. Now, there
are server-level audit specifications and database-level audit specifications.
And they dictate what it is that I actually want to track or cover.
>> Okay.
>> So the code is fairly readable here. I'm creating a database-level
audit spec. I give it a name and then on behalf of a particular server.
And the activity I want is any selecting within... or activity
on the marketing schema objects. And notice whom I'm tracking
would be anybody within public, which means everyone.
>> So you define the action, you define the object, and you define
the user that you want to audit.
>> That's right. So if I wanted true to... really all over the
SQL Server product, I have meta data to retrieve any conceivable
information I want.
All right. Next up we have to throw a switch on.
>> Okay.
>> So pointing to the master database, I have to throw a server-level
switch on, alter server, alter MarketDevLog and I have to turn
that on. Now that I turned that on, I have to turn a switch at
the database level. Now, point to the proper database and now
that specification that I created a moment ago, I have to turn
on as well. And next up
the bear trap.
>> All right. Let's see it, George.
>> Let's go ahead and perform some activity that may be caught
and some activity that might not be caught. Notice a bunch of
meta data queries that you can run. I will leave that just in
the code here. It was brought up on the break time that some
of you are interested in the code, and the code will be made available.
>> We'll have details coming up a little bit later on how that's
going to work.
>> I'm flattered you think... Some of this code is right from Microsoft.
And we'll give details on where you can get a hold of that. But, yeah.
All right. So notice that this object is within marketing, and
this object is not within marketing.
>> Okay.
>> So I'm going to involve some activity
that should be audited.
>> Interesting.
>> That's okay. That was actually not activity to be audited.
>> No.
>> So now we have to take a look at the application log.
>> So we're going to go out to event viewer, look at the application
events, see what shows up.
>> Yep. So let's go to Windows logs, application log.
Uh-huh. Audit event.
(Making noise).
>> Very cool.
Now, you can also get that activity by going to audits in the
GUI, correct?
>> Yeah. In fact,
I can configure a lot... really for all practical purposes, all
of this within the graphical user interface.
So all of that is available.
>> Cool.
Cool. So, there's a lot of information about activity and tracing
and all that good stuff. What about getting activity about getting
information about configurations and how my databases are set
up and things like that.
You know, is there stuff that we can learn there?
>> So SQL Server is a dynamic environment. There are things that
are moving, changing all the time. So that's one point.
Next point, there are all kinds of facts that I might want to
get about my environment. And in increasing measure, there is
a recommended way to get that information. And this information
is retrieved via catalog views and dynamic management objects.
So these are the things that we're going to take a look at in
this next little subsection. So I want to start off with a definition, Rich.
>> Please do.
>> So what is metadata? Metadata is retrieving information about information.
So there are very typical pieces of information that database
administrators, maybe even database devs would want to retrieve.
Fortunately, Microsoft has laid it in our lap or made it accessible
easily through normally queriable objects.
>> Okay.
>> Now, I'd like to demonstrate something. So if you guys would
flip over to my virtual machine for a moment. Let's say just
on a whim here I create a new database.
>> Okay.
>> So let's call this busy database and immediately...
oops. And immediately
we'll go ahead and create it.
Now, in my list here, I see my database and observe when I go
to views.
I don't have any views... user defined views.
>> We haven't created anything.
>> But observe what I have immediately accessible under system views.
Now, for the most part, information schema views, they're queriable
objects that they have. But they seem to be falling out of favor.
I will say that's an opinion. What seems to be gaining momentum
is this remaining set of objects starting from here and then
going downward. Notice the sys prefix. So generically we're
going to call all of this catalog views.
>> Okay. So the catalog views.
>> And some of these are queriable objects that get instance level
information, something like sys.databases.
>> Okay.
>> Or I have other objects at the database-level like sys.tables.
>> Now, the catalog views are mostly static information, though, right?
>> Exactly. So catalog views are static information. But as I
scroll down a little bit further,
I'm going to get to some objects that have a different prefix,
an added prefix. Notice the sys.dm_ prefix.
>> Okay. What does that dm refer to?
>> So the dm refers to dynamic management object. And if I can
flip back...
actually, if you guys would flip back to the slides then,
let's go through a quick little classification system. But before
we advance, you'll see that having normally queriable objects
are static catalog views in our dynamic management objects.
I can apply all of my normal querying mechanisms to get the information
I want. If I can add a little editorial comment.
>> Uh-oh.
>> Generally speaking, the catalog views and the dynamic management
objects provide way more information that you care about.
>> Awesome.
>> So you are going to come up with your own custom script code.
You are going to use where clauses, column lists. You can aggregate
where clauses, like I said, all the normal queriable mechanisms.
You will come out with your own custom code. Time out.
There are lots of resources out there where they already have
some of these queries made, and you can appropriate them rather
than write them yourself.
>> It sounds like a plan to me.
>> All right. I don't know if we will have enough time at the
end of this session; but if there is one of the sessions today
where we do have a couple extra minutes, I will talk about some
of my favorite Web sites that I think you should subscribe to.
And I have swallowed my own medicine. I'm also a subscriber
of every that I would recommend.
>> That would be a good thing.
>> Moving on, you can argue that there are two major classifications
of any of the dynamic management objects; that is, those that
have the sys.dm_ prefix.
Generally speaking, we call all of them dynamic management objects,
or DMOs.
>> Okay.
>> Further, those that require no input, we refer to as dynamic
management views.
And those that require...
those that require input are called dynamic management functions.
Strangely, I can't just look at the name of them and determine,
wait, that's a function, that one's a DMV, or dynamic management view.
>> True.
>> I got to put a plug in for Books Online. I know you are a
big fan of Books Online.
>> The best help system ever written.
>> Every single dynamic management object, probably every catalog
object, you can get information you want about... in Books Online.
That part is good. Now, let's...
A point of reality here. So I've stated we have DMOs and then
DMVs and DMFs in sort of a hierarchy, and everyone mangles the names.
>> Yep.
>> We will just graciously suffer everyone that doesn't know our
taxonomy, sorry, and just roll with it.
>> There you go.
>> Now, for those that have a particular interest, another Michigan
person, an awfully busy man, part of one of the west Michigan
user groups, Tim Ford, has co-written a book called... I think
it is "The Periodic Table of Dynamic Management Objects."
So that's a resource. Also being a frequent speaker, conference
presenter, had he a presentation that's still out there online.
You can easily Google for it here called "The Periodic Table
of Dynamic Management Objects." A couple of other resources to
run with before we actually take a look at using these, at Redgate,
one of their free e-books is called "The DMV Starter Pack," not
only an e-book reference but also a bunch of code you can use
to solve very typical problems about a busy SQL Server environment.
>> That's a good thing to have.
>> And then I know at one time, Quest which is now more recently
owned by Dell,
they had a poster with, I don't know, a whole bunch of dynamic
management objects listed on it. But now that you know there
are resources, let's take a look at some of the dynamic management
objects and see some of the things we can obtain from them.
So here we go.
>> So what are we going to be looking at here, George?
>> So we are going to take a look at... really just a strafing
run, a big-picture survey of some of the big dynamic management objects.
And we will have this conclusion. Man, I can get anything.
Man, I can find out anything I would want to. Honestly, you
might have to write a little bit of gnarly query code, but you
can get what you want. So that's the conclusion you will have.
First, let's take a look at a dynamic management object called sys.dm_exec_requests.
Any input required here?
>> Mmm, doesn't look like it to me.
>> Nope. So this would be classified as a dynamic management view.
>> Okay.
>> Now, we'll find that if we scroll one of the columns...
and this is good insight into one of those that has an awful
lot of columns... somewhere in here we'll find the column is
user session... or is user process.
Heck off the top of my head, I don't even remember where it is
and I probably passed it anyway.
>> Yeah.
>> Think I passed it?
>> Probably.
>> So let's take a look. Is user process.
Can I skip scrolling?
>> Yes.
>> Let's just use a where clause and execute this to only show
non-system processes. I'm using a where clause "is user process
equals one."
Next up. We'll find that often it's valuable
to combine the use of dynamic management objects. These are
also DMVs. So, A, we're joining, B, a where clause and, C, we're
specifying particular columns. So we're going to use that column
to filter the currently executing requests by joining the two
tables on session IAD.
Notice this has revealed me.
>> There you go.
>> Next up.
Note we can also retrieve details of the SQL batch that's being
executed instead of just the handle. And we can do this with
a function. Sys.dm_exec_sql_text function. And, like I said,
if you memorize some of the function names or DM objects by name,
you need a vacation.
[Laughter]
>> Seeing as there are several hundred of them, I would agree
with you.
>> So now I'm not only going to perform a join on a couple of DMVs.
But then I'm going to outer apply that across a dynamic management function.
Let's see what this provides.
And we will see this will supply me the program name I'm using,
the general statement that I'm using, and my actual query code
and a couple of other facts as well. Okay. Take a deep breath
here, Rich.
Now, it says, "Don't be too concerned about the complexity of
the subquery below but note that it's possible to find the actual
statement being executed rather than the batch."
>> Can I let it out now?
>> Yeah, there you go. Go, sorry. Good job. That is somewhat
gnarly query code. But as I scroll here, notice I get statement...
>> Wow.
>> This would be... this would be even more fun if I expanded
that all out.
>> So you can do a lot of the things that you are doing in Profiler
and Event Tracing and all that through queries as well.
>> There's so many ways to get information.
>> Wow.
>> Part of this might be my preference. And so let's see.
>> So what about... is Extended Events similar to Profiler?
>> I'm sorry. Say that again.
>> Extended Events, I've heard a lot about that. Is that similar
to Profiler? Are we doing the same kinds of things there?
>> Saw a comment from the student... or from the attendee pool there.
Extended Events are not going to be part of this session.
They are not in detail really at all on the exam, so we're only
looking at Profiler for this point. Yep, Profiler is a deprecated...
deprecated feature. That means... here's my nickname for a deprecated event.
It is a dead man walking. It is going to be going away. It is
not gone now, but it is going to be going away. In some cases,
we are not even told in how many versions it will go away but
it is going away.
>> So Extended Events is there. It does the same kind of functionality;
but at this point, it is not really a big objective on the exams.
>> No.
>> And Profiler is not going away any time in the short-term.
>> That's right.
>> All right.
>> So next up, one of the things that you might be interested
in is a precious resource, and that is the procedure cache.
So I'm able to query, let's just summarize, all the points of
interest so I can get plan cache details. I can find the top
ten executing queries.
Lots of good stuff here.
>> Very cool.
>> Like I said, there are places out there that will give me...
that will hand me this code in my lap and can help me solve various problems.
Let's go ahead and move along now.
>> All right.
So the other thing... we've got these dynamic management objects.
We've got the catalog views. We've got Profiler and all that.
Is there a technology that kind of brings all that together and
pulls it into a way that it becomes useful for us over time?
>> Especially. There's... the D in dynamic management objects
which describes that it's dynamic information.
>> Okay.
>> It's changing information. It's not persisted in any way, which
brings us to our next topic. Might it be wonderful... by the
way, this is where you say "yes."
>> Yes.
>> Might it be wonderful if I could capture some of that performance
data and some of that tracking data, store it long-term, maybe
even be able to create some wonderful reports off of it. Of course,
the answer is yes. General troubleshooting rule, if I don't know
what "normal" is, how can I take my current condition and determine
if something is wrong or not?
>> You can't.
>> Have you ever had a he said/she said some kind of thing?
>> Yep, yeah.
>> Let's take a look at the management data warehouse.
>> Cool.
>> All right. The management data warehouse is a really SQL Server
database that I can make that has some other mechanisms place
on it to grab data from either the current instance and/or other instances.
>> Okay. It's configured through a wizard. Actually, I even looked
into seeing if I can configure it in code. But I configure it
and set it up with two different wizards. What it ends up doing
is setting up schedules,
SSIS packages, and jobs to grab performance data, put it in what
they call the management data warehouse, and also build some
wonderfully accessible reports that are viewable from management studio.
>> Very cool.
>> Very nifty.
>> Very cool. How do you set that up? How do you get data collector
up and working?
>> So as you can see from this slide, there are two wizards that
you will invoke. First, I have to get started. I have to create
the management data warehouse. An you will see from the first
radio button implying that I'm going to run the first wizard.
After that, I then set up data collection and do the rest of
the configuration process. And you will see in going through
these two wizards two sets of roles exist. There is a role for management.
And notice there are three different roles, each which are their
own privileges, and there are specific database roles for configuration purposes.
>> So once you have got the data collector set up, you have set
up the management data warehouse, what's the next step?
>> Next is allowing it to do its work through the scheduled jobs,
and you will see a couple of the... well, two of the three reports
that can be produced. Let me ask a rhetorical question.
>> Ask away.
>> If there were resources on a SQL Server system that you were
concerned about, what would be some of the ones you would be
most concerned about?
>> Probably disk space.
>> Disk space.
>> Maybe memory or CPU utilization. I mean, those are the things
that get used on a computer.
>> Sure. And if you guys will go back to the slide, you'll take
a look that at least on behalf of these two...
these two reports, they show exactly what you were talking about,
Rich, those things like disk usage trends, CPU usage, memory,
et cetera, some really good stuff.
>> So can we take a look at how to set it all up and get it going, George?
>> Sure.
>> So walking through, you are going to show us the wizards and
how it all comes together. And at the end of the day, hopefully
we have a data collector.
>> That's right. So you will notice from here under management,
let me just collapse a little bit to simplify the user interface.
Under management, you will notice I have data management.
And if I refresh, well, I don't have anything there right now.
General rule of thumb in Windows, when in doubt, yeah, I'm going
to right click. So right click, configure the management data warehouse.
[Laughter]
Here are my two radio buttons. Let's get started with the first one.
First up, what instance do I want to put the warehouse on?
>> Okay.
>> And do I already have a warehouse? Or do I want to make one?
It probably wouldn't be a bad idea to already create one ahead
of time. But skipping a little of the detail, let me go ahead
and make the management data warehouse.
>> And that's just a standard create database dialogue.
>> Standard database.
So here is where I can map log-ins and users to the management roles.
I don't need to do any of that just yet. And from here, I can
click on not Swedish but "finish." [Banging on table]
>> That would be the collective grown from the peanut gallery, please.
>> If I didn't get up enough on the last break for my comments...
>> Keep going, keep going, keep going.
>> Next up. We will run the wizard again, set up data collection.
So, enter where you want to cache, collect the data locally before
it's uploaded.
>> Okay.
>> I will just pick a dummy location for right now.
In reality, you would probably want to pick a location that you
are going to have enough space for.
>> Okay.
>> So let's go ahead and designate the server and database that
will host the data warehouse.
>> All right.
>> And honestly, I thought I put that on prose wear but...
>> You defaulted to Instant Works.
>> So there's our warehouse.
It is always nice having a second set of eyes.
Let's click on finish.
>> And the wizard does its wonderful thing. It spins, it grins.
It winds, it dines. It slices, it dices. And it's done.
>> now, what we would want to do is generate some activity, give
some time to let the...
let the schedule jobs work to collect data. And then we get
the nifty reports. So right click on data collection reports,
and there are the three very pretty reports.
>> Awesome. Very, very cool.
>> So that is... those are the basics of configuring the data warehouse.
So in this module, we took a loot at SQL Server being a dynamic environment.
Lots of ways...
or lots of tools that we have that can give facts. Facts can
produce conclusions. And from... from the conclusions, we can
then implement some changes.
>> Awesome. Thanks a lot, George. We will be taking a meal break now.
We appreciate the time you've spent and look forward to seeing
you back here at the top of the hour.
>> And I got to tell you, I'm excited about some of the stuff
we are going to look at this afternoon.
>> Oh, yeah, we're going to have fun. We're going to have fun.
See you in a bit.