[Music]
Good morning everyone. Welcome to the Administering SQL Server
2012 Jump Start. My name is Rich Currey. I am here with Mister
George Squillace. He's got SQL in the name. Good morning George.
>> Hey. Good morning Rich.
>> How about a little bit about yourself sir?
>> All righty. Well, I come from New Horizon's Great Lakes based
in Michigan. I've been a long-term Technology Trainer. Been a
long term Microsoft Certified Trainer. Over the last bunch of
years my focus has solely been on SQL Server, which I like.
Rich, can I brag on you a little?
>> Yeah. Go for it.
>> I want to brag on you and well, maybe that's not the right
word, but some of you are here for the specific purpose of certifying,
preparing to certify, icing off that particular preparation process.
One good thing, we've passed all seven SQL 2012 exams- >> Oh
yeah.
>> And I know you've satin the exam booth on awful lot of times-
>> Nowhere near what you have though, George.
>> 96 times in the exam booth.
>> Mister professional test-taker right there. That's hard to
do, let me tell you.
>> So for those who are in particular interested in that area
you're going to have a good day. A bit of other background too.
Now how about you?
>> Well, I have been a trainer with Microsoft Technologies for
about the last 10 years with the New Horizons, and prior to that
I spent about 20 years in Industry. I've been playing with computers
since I was 10 years old, and we're not going to tell you when
that started because that would tell you how old I am, and I'm
not going to do that. I have been a DBA professionally, a developer,
and a bunch of other stuff, and hopefully some of that experience
is going to come across and help you folks out of this day.
So George how about it? What are we going to be doing today?
You want to give us an overview?
>> Excellent. I like this product. I just want to go on the record
saying I like the product. One of the things I like about it
is that this product is huge, and we have an awful lot to take
a look at in terms of administration. So we'll take a look first
at how we got the product on a box and some of the installation
decisions along the way.
>> Okay.
>> Module Two, after we get to the product on the box, now what?
What are some of the server level, database level settings and
things that we do? What are some maintenance tasks that we do
because the product does need some care and feeding.
SQL Server operates in a dynamic environment, and things are
always changing and we need to figure out what's going on, improve
performance, troubleshoot; so we'll take a look at some tools
in that area.
>> I'm looking forward to that one because I haven't done a lot
of troubleshooting. I just don't tend to have problems.
>> Well, there you go.
So then we'll take a look at managing data. After that a module
of particular concern, Implementing Security.
>> Okay.
>> So we'll see the various onion layers of security, the moving
parts of the security subsystem, and then, again, a pet favorite
topic of mine and that is High Availability.
>> Yeah. That's going to be a good one.
>> So we have a lot of the High Availability options and, you
know- >> Awesome.
>> So we're going to get decent survey of those. And you will
want to have a good overview survey of those before the exam.
All righty. Setting Expectations.
This particular jumpstart would serve a number of people, those
that already have some experience with SQL Server you still have
plenty to learn. We'll definitely cover an awful lot of topics.
You're going to pick up something. There are those who all of
a sudden now sit in front of a SharePoint Server or some other
box that requires the SQL Server product. We call them an Accidental DBA.
You're going to you have lots to gain from this as well.
>> There are a lot of those out there too.
>> Oh, no doubt. I mean so many Microsoft products now require
a SQL Server and another third product products as well and after
that, those that have a laser focus on passing that 70-462 Certification Exam.
>> Absolutely.
>> Some suggested materials to help you out and to describe the
personal, be in the best position to succeed, got to have basic
familiarity with the product. Our session here is designed for
those that have at least some exposure to the product and definitely
relational database exposure too.
>> Makes sense.
>> Also, if you are brand-new to Windows and the User Interface
and things like that this will be a tougher session. So got
to have some Windows Server experience.
>> Okay.
>> Book wise.
So with the books we've actually got Microsoft Press, the Exam
Training Kit for the 70 - 462, Administering SQL Server 2012
Databases is a great resource; and additionally, if you like
what you're hearing today and you want some more foundation,
there is a five day Microsoft Official Curriculum Course, the
10775 class.
That class is offered by the folks that we train for, so you
might actually get a chance to spend five whole days with us.
That would be New Horizons. If you go to the Microsoft Learning
Site and search on Classes you'll get more information there
as well. So George, how about that MVA Community? We've already
been a part of that a little bit, right?
>> No doubt. Big online community.
>> It is. Lots of folks, lots of things to learn, and you get points.
If you log in and use this voucher code, which is
AdminSQL, not
DWSQL, the slide has a little bit of an issue there, so AdminSQL
is the correct code, put that in. It expires on November 19,
and you will get 50 MVA points.
>> So George, you ready to get started here? Should give these
folks something to think about?
>> Let's roll.
>> All right. So this first module, go at it, bud.
>> All righty. So first module, Installation and Configuration
of SQL Server. We can't get into the really grimy details of
all the decision-making that you have to do, so we want to take
maybe a tree top or a little higher level look at the major decisions
along the way, and in particular, some of the critical decisions
along the way.
So in addition to installation decisions we have an IO bound product.
So we have to design storage well.
>> That makes sense.
>> There are certain particular errors that a DBA can make in
relationship to growth, storage, etc. So we have to lay those
out on the table as well.
>> Absolutely.
>> And always being security concerned and efficiency concerned
we want to sculpt appropriate service accounts for running the
SQL Server product.
>> All right. So let's get into that first topic, Installation Decisions.
George, what do we need to know about installing the product?
What are the critical points?
>> Sure. Well, first off, we have a lot of decisions to make.
There's quite a number of Wizard steps in installing the product.
And it's not that it's hard, it's not hard, as a matter of fact
could you, yeah, that's fine. It's not that it's hard to install
the product, but you just have to know what decisions you have
to make and there are a couple that are very hard to overcome
if you don't make the decision right the first time around.
And also, should you make certain decisions poorly you're going
to have a poor foundation.
>> So it's like the old Carpenter's Rule, measure twice, cut once.
>> Exactly. All righty.
So Installation Decisions.
We'll take a look, yeah, yeah, yeah. We're good.
Let's go on to Determine the Appropriate Hardware. Thank you.
All right. So laying out some of the hardware decisions.
Should we virtualize or not?
>> Yeah. That's a question that has been going around with a lot
of DBAs for a long time. Virtualization has always been viewed
as not really a great choice for SQL Server, but the reality
is that in the last several years virtualization's come a long
way and it has really gotten to the point where virtualization vs.
hard systems, very little difference. Is that what you see as
well George?
>> Yeah. Clearly the trend is towards a virtualization of SQL Server.
Maybe not every single workload, you'll have to carefully consider
that, but it used to be a crime or a sin. That's clearly not
the case anymore. No. For CPU sockets and cores the balancing
act with hardware in general is that you want to make sure the
workload can be handled. Whatever workload SQL Server has to
do you got to have the hardware to handle it, but I don't want
to give away a lot of money away either.
>> That's true.
>> This, of course, is one of the reasons though that has been
moving us in the direction of virtualization. We can use our
hardware much better.
>> Okay.
>> Memory wise, a lot of times this is a function of the Windows
Operating System, especially for the highest edition, so SQL
Server's a memory loving project. It serves query code or answers
queries out of memory, so the more memory, in general, the better.
>> Good.
>> Storage wise, you have questions there to.
>> Absolutely.
>> So for maybe a smaller shop you may have one SQL Server, a
handful of SQL Servers, not going to be worthwhile to have a
storage area network oriented storage. You'll have directed
detached storage, and you'll have to manage that per server.
But for a larger shop, 20, 50, 100 instances you're not going
to manage storage server by server.
>> No. You're going to have a block of disks that's available
to everybody. So- >> Another
trend we're seeing is the increasing use of solid state storage.
I have a link here where you can take a look at maybe some of
the places where that could apply, but it's something that needs
to be put on the table especially for some of the heavier workloads.
>> Absolutely.
>> And Rich, you pointed out something yesterday while we were
just chit chatting stuff about solid state storage.
>> Yeah. One of the things that you do need to kind of be aware
of with solid state storage is that it does have a life cycle.
With all of the read write cycles that go on there is a tendency
for it to wear out, so you do need to be aware that solid-state
in the case of TempDB it's a trade-off. You can have some performance
advantages from having the speed, but there are also some maintenance
issues that you need to deal with to make sure that it doesn't
run out and wear out while you're dealing with it. So that's
really what's going on in that area right now.
>> Great. For those that are going to have the very heaviest of
workloads consider a couple of free tools that are unsupported,
by the way, did I say free and unsupported?
>> Yeah. They kind of go together sometimes.
>> So you're on your own for those, but these, let's say you're
considering a workload running on a particular hardware platform.
Maybe you can persuade your vendor to drop something off for
you to test. Without having to install SQL Server you can run
these particular tools which simulate different kinds of IO patterns
and can tell you if this particular platform is good for the
job or not.
>> Awesome. So what about the operating systems? I mean is there
something that you have to deal with with OS selection in there?
>> Oh yeah.
>> Really?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> What might that be sir?
>> Well, you have to make sure that you have the right Windows
Operating System for the job as well. There are certain features
that are operating system abound. From this slide I'd like to
make a primary point.
In general, whatever Windows Client you have or whatever Windows
Server you have, one way or another you can get SQL Server on
the machine.
>> So it's really more of a matter of choosing the right OS for
the situation that you're in rather than to support SQL Server.
>> Yeah.
>> That's good.
>> All right. Now an innovation with SQL 2012, I don't know if
this is considered earth shattering by the community or not,
but Server Core has been around for a while now- >> Yeah.
>> And SQL Server supports Windows Core.
>> Awesome. That's great.
>> Funny nickname for Windows Core.
>> Uh-oh.
>> Windows without Windows.
>> Ooh, I like that.
>> From a details standpoint I would not bother memorizing what
the max memory, CPU sockets, what versions or editions of SQL
go on what editions of Windows, don't bother with all that.
>> So what you're saying is basically any hardware out there is
going to have the ability to run SQL? It's just configuring for
what the specific data loaded is.
>> Exactly.
>> Good.
>> So let's take a look at selecting the appropriate edition of
SQL which in my mind is a particularly important decision.
>> All right.
>> It basically goes like this. I'm either budgeted limited so
I'm going to spend the money that I have or I'm feature driven
and I have to get whatever edition has the features I absolutely need.
>> Okay.
>> What would be considered the cherry edition?
>> The cherry edition, it's Enterprise.
>> Well, no doubt.
>> Any time you've got a full workload and you need to do everything,
it's Enterprise.
>> No doubt. So I have a link here for you to take a look at,
an edition comparison, often I'll ask myself well wait a second,
this minute feature, is that supported on this edition or that?
I don't remember and I don't want to remember.
>> No.
>> So I have the link here.
You'll see there are the principal editions, Enterprise, BI,
and Standard, and if you want to download an edition to play
with it's time-limited. Well, I have a link for you there.
There's a specialized edition web and I want you to be aware
of a couple of other editions that might serve you for a no-cost edition.
>> Oh. That would be Express.
>> Express Edition, and you know what, it used to be that the
predecessor for Express was fairly minimally capable.
Express can actually do a lot. One CPU, a gig of RAM, but you
can have a 10 gig database. Comes with GUI tools, can have reporting
services, a lot of goodness Rich.
>> Okay. But do I have to go out and get a full license if I'm
working on developing something and I'm not ready to roll it
out or something like that? Is there an alternative I can use there?
>> In fact there is. I have linked here a link to the Microsoft
Store where you can get Developer Edition, 60 bucks.
>> Okay.
>> 60 bucks. A few pennies under 60 bucks, but absolutely Enterprise
Edition, feature full, one legal restriction Rich.
>> What's that?
>> Of course there's a legal restriction. You can only have developer connections.
>> So no production on that one.
Very cool. So what are these instances all about George?
>> Sure. When I am installing SQL Server I must make a decision
at the Wizard step that you see here in the screenshot- >> Okay.
>> And that is, do I want to have a default instance or do I want
to have a named instance? So there are two aspects here.
First, naming and connecting, but the bigger picture here is
that I can have more than one instance on a machine.
Picture, Rich, that each one has an electric fence around the instance.
>> So like a boundary.
>> Yeah. It's exactly a boundary. So I would have a different
essay, a different a system administrator for each instance- >> Okay.
>> Have a different system administrator, I could have different
security assignments, I can have different service level agreements,
different collations. I've listed a bunch of the reasons on the
slide here why I might want to have a separate instance.
>> So it's more about being able to control how that instance
is operating without having to affect other installs that are
being used for other purposes.
>> Precisely, precisely.
>> Cool.
>> Curious, just a curious fact. Now this isn't important for
the test just curious, every single edition of SQL Server supports
up to 50 instances.
>> That's a lot. I think that's more than most people are probably
going to ever put on a single machine.
>> Yeah. No, you and I both have teenagers, so we know you just
because you can doesn't mean you should.
>> I like that. Yeah.
>> So one of the things that goes into instances are collations.
Can you talk a little bit about that?
>> Sure. I have one little follow-up thing on instances; and my
reigning heavyweight of those instances or those circumstances
out in the world that I'm aware of, one of my customers or one
of our students, 19 instances in production on one operating system.
>> That's pushing it.
>> That seems like that's pushing it to me too.
>> Absolutely.
>> Okay. Collations. So let me start off with the definition.
>> Okay.
>> So a collation is a rulebook of text based sorting in comparison
rules, and part of the relevance here is that I must pick a collation.
Now as we were discussing, one thing that's good during installation,
the SQL Server Installation will look at the language of your
underlying operating system and at least grab you by the nose
and make a strong suggestion as to what you should pick.
>> Okay.
>> There are still two major decisions, as you can see from the
screenshot here, whether I use a Legacy SQL Collation or a Windows Collation.
Strangely, a SQL Collation is the default but Windows Collations
are suggested.
>> So you can use the Legacy or you can use the current ones defined
in Windows.
>> Absolutely.
>> Good. So can you show us a little bit about that George?
Let's go over and take a look maybe.
>> I would. So first thing up we know that you have to make a
collation decision. And I want to come up with the corny phrase
to help everybody grasp something.
>> Okay.
>> And the corny phrase is like begets like.
>> So we'll find then, let me flip over to my demonstration environments-
>> All righty.
>> All right.
When I installed my instance I stepped in a bear trap.
>> Okay.
>> A collation was set at the instance and I'm able to look at
this both in the graphical user interface- >> All
right.
>> And also in code if I want to.
>> Okay.
>> Now one of the impacts of this is that my TempDB database is
going to have the same collation as Dad, so to say. And that
is not configurable. One other curious thing, I'd like to point
out some of them naming conventions just real quick. Notice that
this says it has a SQL Collation that's a prefix, as opposed
to Windows Collation, and without getting too gory we see a couple
other sensitivities here. We see case insensitive and accent sensitive.
>> So this CI is Case Insensitive, the AS means Accent Sensitive.
>> No. Do you have memorized list of all the other sensitivities?
>> No.
>> I don't either. But I remember the I and the S for insensitive
and sensitive. That's about as far as my memory goes.
>> Yeah, same here.
>> All right.
>> Let's say now I create a new database with the Graphical User
Interface; I of course have to refresh so I did not, as you see
in code, specify a particular collation.
>> So it assigned one for you?
>> So guess what happened?
Like begets like.
>> Okay.
>> It's going to have the same collation as Dad.
>> All righty.
>> And in fact, just so everybody gets to see this, if I wanted
to see this in code well I have a function that I could use,
point to a particular database and use a function that will return
the particular collation of the
database that I am currently pointed to.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Next up, do observe that when I create a database
I can specify and override collation. Are your kids just like you?
>> I hope not.
>> No, my kids are not just like me.
And refreshing my list of databases I go to my multi-lingual
speak DB and now, of course, I see
these specified collation.
>> Awesome. So you can change the collation for an individual
database if you need it.
Can you, do have finer grain control even?
>> In fact, I do have finer grain control, and with the code seen
here you'll observe that on a text column by column basis I can
specify the collate clause that will then dictate how text based
comparisons and sorting will work for that particular column.
>> Awesome.
>> So following a trail we now know we have instance collation,
we have database collation, and text based collation.
>> Okay.
>> To drill down real quick I'll go to Tables, I see this particular
table, I see a column, let's pick one of these, I'll go to Properties,
and what do we see?
>> Yep.
>> We see an override collation.
>> Awesome.
>> And Rich, you know it goes deeper than that.
>> Sure. Sure it does because you can actually specify it
>> Down to the query level.
>> Awesome.
>> So that's what we're going to take a look at next. I'm going
to create a table,
and if you observe carefully, once again I'm using per text column
collations- >> Shh.
>> One being case insensitive and accent sensitive and the other
being sensitive to both.
>> Okay. So two different collations, two different columns.
>> That's right. So notice I'm inserting mixed case data into
both of these which I'll take care of- >> All
right.
>> And now querying the case insensitive data column I'm now going
to query using text data that it did not match what was inserted.
>> Capitals in one, lower case in the other.
>> That's right. But now when I query that I actually have a row
returned because it is a case insensitive collation.
>> Awesome.
>> Let's see where this goes now when I query the case sensitive
data column with all lowercase data. You can probably figure
out the end of this movie and- >> Ah,
yeah. Nothing comes back. No match is found.
>> All right. Drum roll please.
So now we see
that I can actually override collation behavior on a per query
basis once again using the collate clause. So I'm querying for
the presence of all lowercase data against the case sensitive
data column but I overrode that with a case insensitive collation.
>> A very cool.
>> Okay. There are a couple other things in here we can take a
look at, but that's good for now.
>> All right. So overall, basically there are some things that
you can
choose, there are some things that you can't choose, there are
other things that you can change if you choose them wrong.
>> That's right.
>> So installations about trying to get it right the first time
but not being absolutely locked in on everything.
>> That's right. So certainly with collation we have some liberty after-the-fact.
>> Yep. Awesome. All right. So then one of the things that we
need to take care of also is ensuring that we have all of the
storage set up, that we've got somewhere to put our data.
Can we talk a little bit more about that?
>> Let's do that.
Good news is more than ever before in SQL Server you can set
a lot of default locations, as you can see from the screenshot
here, and that doesn't mean you can't place files in locations
outside of these, but they are just that they set default so
if I backup data, if I create a new database, I can specify a
data and a log file location, things like that.
>> Okay.
>> So in this topic we'll take a look at a general file system
design principles, we'll also take a look at some advanced database
design and the circumstances that may encourage that and some
of the building blocks that go into that.
>> All right. So what's the first thing that we really need to
think about?
>> Principal number one, Spreading.
>> Spreading.
>> Don't put all your apples in one basket?
>> Something like that.
>> All right.
>> So let's take a look at a typical Windows Server, SQL Server.
It's going to have Windows IO activity, we'll have the data file
IO activity which is a random and also involves reads and writes.
>> Okay.
>> And then finally we have logged file activity which is sequential
and write oriented.
>> Okay.
>> One of the biggest IO taxes is moving that IO head so we don't
want to move the IO head, in particular, on the log file.
And also in the log file I don't want to have the overhead of
RAID parody.
>> Okay.
>> So I have here in a diagram a few different file system design
suggestions starting off with a lab machine which is a fictitious.
I have everything of importance on one a drive letter.
>> Okay.
>> Again, just because I can- >> Doesn't
mean you should. Absolutely.
>> So then I have a progression of maybe a small, very low workload
server up to something that's much more industrial strength.
>> So what is the most important thing you need to keep in mind
when we are talking about setting up these drives?
Is there something to worry about as far as keeping data and
log files a separate or TempDB separate? What are the things
that you need to think about?
>> Like we see on the slide there, you want to separate log files
and data file activities. So that's clearly, especially for a
heavy workload, one of the most important design considerations.
>> Cool.
>> You're still going to have to come up with RAID levels for
each of the storage units that you allocate. You have a lot
of choices.
And some of you are hardware savvy, others may be coming along
learning your hardware; I have a link here to, well it calls
itself RAID.edu.
So if you want to learn the difference between RAID 10, RAID
0 plus 1, RAID 6, RAID 5, etc., etc., there's some nice little
multimedia graphics. I like to give that out to my students.
>> Cool. What about separation of data files themselves?
Anything that we need to think about there?
>> In fact, yes.
Looking at a more advanced database design we'll see that this
will involve multiple file groups which are supported by at least
one file, possibly multiple files.
>> Okay.
>> And as you can see from the diagram here part of the point
is positioning space occupying objects over different file groups.
>> Okay.
>> So using the principle of Spreading I now can spread out the
IO in querying activity ind the maintenance activity over multiple
read write heads. I have a general rule though.
>> What would that be?
>> General rule is for every single file that I'm going to add
to a database better be on its own drive letter.
>> Yeah. That kind of makes sense because otherwise what's the
sense in having multiple files?
>> I'm going to have the same read write heads fighting for the
same data file activity.
>> Yep.
>> Now even though my diagram shows multiple log files it's only
so that you know you can, this is not a recommended procedure,
it's only going to be used if the first one fills up.
>> The only time I've ever really seen that used is to migrate
from a transaction log from one drive to another is really what
that helps out with.
>> Yeah. Now I want to spy, before I go to the next slide, I went
to spy into one particular circumstance. Notice that I could
have let's say a table in one file group and a non-clustered
index in another file group, but observe the top of the diagram
where I could actually have one single table spread out over
multiple file groups.
>> Multiple file groups?
>> Multiple file groups. Now the reason that I'm going to go to
this design to begin with would be twofold.
>> Okay.
>> Performance, meaning more read write heads involved in reading
and writing, that part I already brought up, but maintenance
I've smaller units of maintenance that can be done over, well,
smaller units.
>> Awesome. So is there anything else that you would use multiple
file groups for George?
>> I can back up one file or one file group at a time as well.
>> Okay. Cool.
>> Yeah. So let's say I had a
multi-terabyte database. I might want to back that up in pieces,
maybe one file per day, one file group per day, I'll tell you
from experience though if you go to that more advanced design
you a better model your Disaster Recovery.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> You'd want to have a military drill where you really know how
to do this.
>> Yep.
>> Just deviating from the plan here a little bit, I find that
every time there's a disaster situation there's always some X
factor, something that wasn't accounted for, something that changed,
and it's tough enough to get it right or tough enough of a situation
by the time you start adding X factors plus other problems, you
just want to avoid that.
>> And by the way, we are going to be talking a lot more about
that later on today in a module coming up. That would be the
one on Managing Data, so stay tuned for that as well.
George, are file groups use at all in partitioning?
>> They are. And in fact, we'll see from the diagram here, not
to go into too much detail, but this shows the primary building
blocks that are involved in creating a table that's divided among
file groups. So I have to have file groups, we see that in green,
and then I have to have a partition function, partition scheme,
finally I make a table that then leans on all the other dependencies.
So again, the purpose is to spread, maybe I have one partition
with many gigs of archive data, I'm not going to load data into
that partition, I'm not going to change the data in the partition,
so I can have that on, maybe I don't even back that up is quite
as regularly, and then I have another partition. Maybe that's
where I load my regular data into.
>> Awesome.
>> I can also have Index Maintenance performed on a partition
by partition basis. So for particularly large tables this would
be a design idea. Now I have a couple of links down there, which
for those that are interested in finding out more, very practically
applied code and examples of how to load data into a current
partition, fold that into an existing partition, make a new one
for the next load cycle, and I think you'll find that interesting.
>> Super. So have you got something to show us now on doing some designs?
>> I do.
>> And some creation here?
>> Sure. We'll take a look at first at creating a database with
an advanced design using the Graphical User Interface.
Now the first thing that we'll observe is that we can create
containers of files.
Let's say we have an archive file group.
>> So the containers are the file groups, right?
>> The containers of objects or those that hold objects are file groups.
So I can make a couple of file groups, go back to my General
tab, and now I can add one or more files
and add them to our particular file group. Now just for typing
simplicity and that I'm going to give fairly
non-descriptive names.
>> Normally you would want to name it something that applies to,
that has meaning to you.
>> Good suggestion. So thanks for letting me off the hook here Rich.
>> That's all right. We'll let you get away from it this time.
And it also helps if you name in the database to, huh?
>> Oh, yeah. Wouldn't that help.
Nancy DB.
>> There we go.
>> Now we are good. Okay. So this is for row data.
I already know from this point on
this is where I could now create objects. In fact, let me go
over here.
>> So the objects are specified to a particular file group when
they are created?
>> Exactly. This is exactly where I'm headed.
Now we'll find in just a moment,
in fact that's exactly what I'm going to show. Now for this
next part I want to simulate a more advanced database design,
but to do so I have to make or stimulate the creation of lots
of drive letters.
>> We don't have lots of disk drives, so you're going to create
directories the just simulate their existence.
>> Yeah. So I just have a virtual machine- >> Perfect.
>> I don't want to make all the storage for all that. That's fine.
So next up you'll observe as I scroll through this I have multiple
data files, multiple file groups in those files, and only to
be crazy, not to show necessarily good design, notice every file
can have an individual initial size, max size, growth, all of that.
>> Cool.
>> So let me finish creating this
and refreshing there is now my advanced design database.
>> Awesome.
>> And if I go to Properties, we'll go to File Groups, notice
multiple file groups. If I go to Files,
all beautiful naming conventions- >> At
least naming conventions.
Awesome.
>> Now to finish the drama of the story,
notice I can create, actually I have to go back for just a second,
one confusion that I think people often have is confusing the
Default File Group vs. the Primary. And you're good about pointing
out Rich that the Primary File Group holds system objects, system
tables, the recordkeeping of the database and such; and when
I only have one File Group, the Primary, well guess which one's
the Default?
>> That's pretty easy. It'd be Primary.
>> Exactly.
>> So what if you don't want prime, everything going into Primary though?
>> Yeah. A general design rule of thumb is that if I'm going to
have even a one file group beyond the Primary then set that one
as the Default File Group. But I have an object lesson here.
>> Uh-oh.
>> Let's take a look.
You know me and my object lessons. So I'm now going to execute
a table creation here, and we're going to play investigator and
find out where it might exist.
>> Okay.
>> So I'll get properties
on this and I go to Storage and observe the file group that it
went on is the Default File Group.
>> Okay.
>> This time around I'm going to designate the particular file
group that it goes on, and I have a rule of thumb I tell my students
often, SQL Server doesn't do what you want it to do, it does
what you tell it to do.
>> Okay.
>> And if I told it to go on a
particular file group, well guess what?
>> It went there.
>> It did exactly that. So there we go.
>> Awesome.
>> All right.
>> So that was pretty good. But one of the things you mentioned
in there is putting objects in the right file group, making sure
that they go to where you expect them to. Is there a reason
for that? Like maybe
we keep running out of space or something?
>> That's right. So our next topic we're going to take a look
at, Planning for Growth and Capacity. We'll see that as a responsibility
of the Database Administrator there are two particular pitfalls
you want to try to avoid when it comes to growth and space.
We'll look at those. And as far as major responsibilities, managing
space, we'll take a look at how to grow files manually, how to
set up auto-growth, and some others just general space- related behaviors.
>> All right. So what are the biggest things that can go wrong?
>> The good news is there are only really two primary space errors
that you can create. I either fill up a file, log file or data
file- >> Makes
sense.
>> Or I fill up a whole drive letter.
>> That's a little harder to do.
>> It has happened certainly. And in particular, this is even
worse for a machine which has much more than just a SQL Server
rule that may mess up other operations, so to say.
>> So what are the ways that you can kind of take care of making
sure that a file doesn't run out of space?
>> Well, this is a lead in, a beautiful lead in actually towards
our Automation lesson which will come up later. But if I am
aware of a space problem I can easily solve it before it becomes
a problem. Notice, as I'm showing here, I can get properties
of a database, pick a particular file, just grow the size.
>> All right.
>> As long as I have the space that's not hard. But you know
one of my rules of thumb, if I have to do something once- >> You're
going to have to do it more than once.
>> I'm probably going to have to do it again, so I might as well
have a code-based version of that. Stay tuned for a version later.
>> And is there a way where maybe you don't have to intervene
all the time?
>> In fact, let's take a look at auto grow options and we'll see
that on a file by file basis we can set up auto growth. I do
want to say we know some deviates that will have strong feelings
about whether this might be appropriate or not, and I try to
take a balanced approach. What I mean by that is there are, for
a small workload, why put my hand in the metal-moving machinery?
>> Yep.
>> Just let it auto grow.
But if you do, make sure you have an auto grow percentage large
enough so that it won't happen frequently and use percentage.
If you're going to buy into auto growth that would be, well that
should be the way you do it.
>> Good.
>> For other workloads, maybe very large workloads, some are very
strong-minded about saying this is not a good idea and you should
only handle this, growth that is, via Automation Subsystem namely
because I don't control when SQL Server starts to run out of space.
It decides, hey everybody you have to wait and now I have to grow.
>> So would it be safe to say that you manage it manually but
you allow it to grow automatically in cases of emergency?
>> You know, I'm really tough on blanket statements. I'm going
to say generally yes.
>> All right.
>> I want to deviate and show something, deviate from the quick
little plan here, if I go to the model database- >> Okay.
>> And quickly get properties and options, we'll review options
later on, we'll see a couple of auto categories,
you know what I lost my mind for a second. I was thinking of
something else. It's that easy.
>> Oh, it happens.
>> Never mind. Different movie.
>> And one good thing about it George?
>> Yeah?
>> You got the peanut gallery laugh on that one.
>> Yeah. Totally lost my mind.
>> All right.
>> I don't even have my kids here to blame.
>> All right. Let's go back to this auto growth and growth thing there.
Is there a way to monitor?
>> There is. And in fact there are multiple ways to monitor.
It's funny just how many ways you can solve problems with this product.
So the first thing you'd have to do is determine when you're
going to grow and be aware of it. So we have agent jobs automation
that we can set up. We'll see that later. We can set up alerts
or we can even a self-healing mechanism. I don't give away too
much of the movie, but we'll see that later.
>> No, no, no. Save it for later.
>> We can collect data about storage in the Management Data Warehouse.
>> Okay.
>> We're going to look at that later. We have catalog views,
dynamic management views, stored procedures, let's just say we
have no shortage of ways to determine space.
>> Awesome. Now I know databases typically grow forever, right?
But what happens if somebody comes in and says hey, we are running
out of space and all that. What do we do?
>> We are able to, let's just say that, you're able to
attempt to shrink a file if you want to. Now I have not met
one database professional I don't think ever that's recommended this.
But just note you can shrink or attempt to shrink either database
wide or on the basis of a specific data file, you get more control
when you use or attempt to shrink a specific data file.
>> Yeah. Rarely if ever have I ever seen a database get smaller
as it keeps on getting bigger.
>> And, if you have a sense of humor Rich, isn't it kind of like everything?
Everything wants to grow.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> The stuff in your closet, the government, companies, everything
wants to grow, databases tend to grow too.
>> Oh, yeah. Absolutely. So how about we go take a look at some
of this stuff there bud? What do you think?
>> There we go.
>> All right.
So you're going to show us how to make the data files bigger
at this point?
>> That's right.
So one of the databases that we have is our little tiny database.
I'll get properties on it, go to files, ooh, it has all of the
four whole megs allocated to it. Let's say we go to 25 whole megs.
Let's raise our log file size as well. So as long as I'm, well
on top of the situation I can go ahead and assign new sizes.
Everything is just dandy.
>> Awesome.
>> For a little bit of dramatic value- >> Uh-oh.
>> Hold on, hold on.
>> I don't like drama George.
>> All right. We might be in the wrong room then.
>> Son of a gun.
All right. Keep going then. Keep going.
>> Let's go to disk usage.
>> Okay.
>> So these are built-in reports to Management Studio, I didn't
need to do anything with reporting services etc.- >> Wow.
>> So we can see the full size of the data files etc. and other
activities down here. I just want to make sure everybody knows
about this. I don't really want to go into the detail of the report.
>> Very cool.
>> Now also here,
let's just take this down a little bit and Danny, how visible
is this? Kind of a little bit small? Okay. I'll try to adjust
that for the next time around. Notice using the Alter Database
Statement I'm able to dictate the size of a data file and I can
use that grow. Looking a little bit closer to see it's about
100 meg. So execute that.
Now to play doubting Thomas, so to say, let's go to files- >> It
will exist if you show it, right?
>> That's right. So we see that we have 100 megs there and then
also, should I go back to my report, you'll see the report also
immediately updates both.
>> Cool.
>> So that is our drama value for the moment.
>> All right. So you had one more topic that we wanted to talk
about in here. And that one is going to be Service Accounts.
>> That's right. Talk about another area where some people have
some passionate feelings. There's a lot of passionate people
in the SQL Server community.
>> Yeah. You have to be.
>> Let's take a look at our topics for this section.
>> All right.
>> First of all, depending on the services or features that you
elect to install, services often, along with those- >> Okay.
>> And along with that you have to pick a Service Account for
those services. Strangely, when was the last time a Microsoft
product removed a feature in a future version? That doesn't happen
too often.
>> No, that doesn't happen often at all.
>> There was a button in earlier versions of SQL Server Installation
where you could say, have every single service and use the same
user account.
>> That seems like it would make it a lot easier for the DBA to manage.
>> It would if that was the choice you actually wanted.
>> Oh.
>> So we'll see that there are reasons to pick different service
accounts for different services. Let's take a closer look here.
>> All right. So what are some of the choices that you've got?
>> Kind of a quick funny story, one of my kids accused me of being
or acting like the Godfather, Don Vito Corleone. It was kind
of a funny little situation, but I'm going to act like Don Vito
and I'm going to back you into a corner giving you only one possible
decision here.
>> I hate it when he does this to me.
>> So here we go.
>> Okay.
>> So we have two general account decisions. We can either use
a built-in account, you see the laundry list of accounts there- >> Absolutely.
>> Or- >> SQL
Service, Network Service.
>> Generally speaking, all of those are either going to give too
many privileges or too few privileges.
>> Okay. So that basically rules all of them out.
>> Thank you very much. So this means you're going to have a created
account which will be either on the local SQL Server machine
and that SAM Server,
Security Accounts Manager, or you're going to use a Domain Account.
>> Okay.
>> And because the service accounts, well in particular some may
need to crawl out across the network, access other resources,
you're going to use a Domain Account.
>> Okay. So can I use the same Domain Account for all of them?
>> Excellent, excellent question that is.
Your, we'll just get to the quick part of the story. You're going
to use a different account for every single box meaning if I
have one hundred database engine instances it is worth the pain
of creating every individual account for every instance of the
database engine.
>> Now that is the recommendation. That's cool. So what happens
if six months from now you've got some new stuff and you need
to change it?
>> Excellent. So you'll see from installation or the screenshot
here they can make those choices during installation, but you
can use SQL Server Configuration Manager after the fact should
you have a design change, a policy change, or something like that.
You know the rule of thumb though when it comes to changing services.
>> Tell me George.
>> You're not going to use the normal Windows Management Console
for managing services. You're going to use the SQL Server Configuration Manager.
>> And why is that?
>> Let's see. You had a good phrase for that yesterday. What was that?
Basically all the appropriate security gets assigned when you
use the SQL Configuration Manager.
>> And if you use the Windows Services Applet it doesn't do what
SQL needs it to do. So you end up having to do it manually.
So what are some of the rules that go into choosing those Service
Accounts, George?
>> Yeah. The database engine in general is not going to need anything.
I see privileges, so just create I call it a dumb-dumb user,
name it appropriately, don't give it any special privileges,
Domain Account. Some of the other services, Browser, Full text,
don't even bother. Just leave the Default Accounts that are suggested
during installation. Now one of the bigger ones is the agent.
>> Okay.
>> The agent has to touch other stuff so it may have to touch
mailboxes, file system shares, other SQL Servers; so that you're
going to give its own account and assign whatever privileges
that that account needs. I have a link here, Configure Windows
Service Accounts and Permissions, if you're willing to throw
off the hockey gloves and do a little, get open-ended about what
their suggestions are that might be of interest to you.
>> Awesome. So can we go take a look at that real quick?
>> Sure. Our last little bit here we'll see now that, and I
think I put my taskbar up at the top. Yeah.
>> Oh, that's cool.
>> Tricky, tricky, tricky.
>> I like that. I'll bet most people don't even know you can do that.
>> So I'm going to go to All Programs, SQL Server 2012, by the
way if I lose my mind and forget that later don't forget to tell me.
I won't be embarrassed. All right. SQL Server Configuration Manager.
So general rule of thumb in Windows, select to affect.
>> That makes sense.
>> General rule number two, when in doubt in Windows, right click.
>> There you go.
>> So let's say it was the SQL Server Agent Service of the marketing
instance whose account I would want to change. I'd go to Properties,
click on Browse, now make sure you're going to browse for the
account from the appropriate location, you might need to point
to an Active Directory Domain, and from there pick the appropriate account.
Low and behold,
oh, M for Mia. That's right.
Mia as in Miami. So I would have an Agent Account created for
this particular machine, click on Okay. Quick little security
note, I can't change the account if I don't know the password.
>> Awesome.
>> So that's just a built-in feature. That's really all we had
for this session. So we looked at taking, putting SQL Server
on a good footing, looking at the major installation decisions;
and now that we'll have SQL Server on a good footing, in the
next session we'll take a look at what changes we might make,
Post Installation
Configuration and changes and such.
>> Awesome. So we're going to take a short break now. We'll be
back at the top of the hour.
Enjoy. See you in a bit.