[Music]
Welcome back. Module 6,
our final one of the day. I am Rich Currey, still, and will continue
to be. George Squillace, still, and will continue to be.
George, what've we got coming to end things up tonight?
>> An interesting and a really vital topic to a SQL database administration,
the topic of high availability, a bunch of different things to
take a look at within high availability. We'll first have to
take a look at what high availability is and the particular kinds
of things that it covers. And then, we're going to drill down
into a number of high availability technologies.
>> All right, so...
>> Now I want to be clear, a couple of these are really not covered
on the exam whatsoever; that's not so much the relevance.
For example, replication: not really covered at all on the exam
but because the topic is high availability I want all of you
to have a decent big picture look at the availability options
that are within the product. So I'll have an inclusion of all
those at least a little bit, for your sake not so much for exam purposes.
>> So let's start out, what is high availability all about, George?
>> When I'm trying to protect my environment, I need duplication
at some level or levels. So high availability refers to having
something available after some form of failure.
>> So if a machine crashes or if a disk file breaks.
>> Exactly.
>> Disk drive breaks, something along those lines.
>> So I could have media failures. I could have complete server failures.
I could have complete datacenter failures. There are failures,
really, at a number of different catastrophic levels.
So we have different kinds of high availability technologies;
some protect against hardware. Well, one in particular: failover
clustering or what I'll call traditional failover clustering
protects against hardware failure. I have a lot more to talk
about there so we'll save the more detailed explanation until later.
>> Okay.
>> Now in particular there are multiple technologies that protect
against media failure, the loss of a database, database file,
along things like that. And so we'll see that all of these involve
duplicating database data, the entire database or a portion of
a database somehow.
>> Okay, so what's the first one that we want to talk about?
>> Okay so the first one we want to take a look at is replication.
And what you want to picture here is Grandpa's old cottage.
This is something that's been around for a long time; it's tried
and true. It's loved. It's useful.
To tell you the truth, though, replication is a handful.
It's very highly configurable and there are a lot of ways that
you can architect it. Rich, you know you're in trouble when you
go to look up books on replication and you see that any of the books...
There are only a couple of books available on it but they're
over 500 pages.
Simple Talk is coming up with a free ebook on replication; it
should be out any time now.
>> That's a good thing because I don't care what you're doing,
replication at some level, you're probably going to have to deal
with it in your SQL server career.
>> And not only that but it's probably going to get tangled at
some particular point and you're going to have to learn how to
untangle it as well. Now every one of the topic areas in this
module is going to have a general pattern like: what are the
facts, the basic facts, the basic technology that it uses or...
>> Okay.
>> ...movement or duplication method? Then, what are the hands-on
or general hands-on processes for implementing it? And then,
sorry, not a single one of the technologies is perfect.
Every one has something glaring that's omitting or some potential drawback.
And that's even true with the very newest technology which has
a lot to love, and that's AlwaysOn technology. So let's get
busy and take a look at replication.
>> So let's start out with the basics: what's replication all about?
>> Okay, replication allows me to identify objects within a database,
specific objects which we call articles.
>> Okay.
>> These could be things like tables, even a filtered table where
I have a portion of columns, a portion of rows, so we will refer
to that a portion of an object or a whole object. And I have
a collection of articles that are then contained within a publication.
>> So kind of like a magazine and the articles in a magazine.
>> Yeah. And then, that is made available to one or more SQL servers.
So the machine which is making the data available is a publisher.
The machine which is consuming it is a subscriber.
And in a more elaborate architecture there will be a role somewhere
on the publisher, on the subscriber or maybe even on a separate
box that is doing the data movement and that's called the distributor.
>> So kind of like the U.S. Postal Service sometimes.
>> Sure. The distributor can be on anyone of those machines.
and in a larger environment I might have a dedicated distributor.
>> Okay. Now as far as...
>> Data distribution, that's part of what this is all about; data
duplication, data distribution.
You're going to see a graph on the slide here which illustrates
a balancing act, so we have autonomy versus latency. Now there
are times where I might have a copy of a database or a copy of
an article and I want it transactionally very consistent
with the original object. And notice, that moves us towards very
low latency. But if we happen to lose a connection between the
two machines that are replicating then we have no autonomy so
we're going to have problem.
>> So very little time for them to have to be...
in the difference between them, very little time to make them
the same again, but there's a high dependency between each other.
>> Exactly. Now on the opposite end we have very high latency
that allows maybe a lack of connectivity for an extended period
of time. But no worries, maybe I don't need the latest data,
so we have other ways of being able to handle that high autonomy
but also with high latency. Now I don't need you to memorize
all the terms in between the two extremes; just realize you have
a lot of choices.
>> Oh yeah.
>> There are a lot of ways to weave this, and I have a lot of
respect for those that wrote the code to get all of this to work.
>> In one of my previous lives, George, I had 120 databases that
we were synchronizing data with, going through with replication
in different levels and I've got to tell you: it was a lot of work.
It is a great technology that requires a lot of attention.
>> Okay. Now I've already stated what some of the possible articles are.
I could have a complete or filtered table, but there are some
other objects such as a stored procedure that produces rows,
a view. Now a curiosity is that whenever I pick an object with
dependencies, like a view or stored procedure, the underlying
objects come along with it.
>> Okay.
>> You know, you have to select those too. So in the process
of configuring replication, I have to determine a schedule for
how frequently I will want the propagated updates to go to the
target or subscriber. In this case agent services are going to
have to communicate with other agent services. So whether you
use code or the graphical user interface, you're going to have
to configure agent security. These are the basics of replication.
>> So what are the broad types of replication available?
>> You'll see on the next slide that there are a number of different
replication types, and I've shown you one of the wizard steps
involved in setting up a replicated set of objects if you use
the wizard. So we have Snapshot, Transactional and Merge; those
are the broad types. And notice we have two different kinds of
Transactional Replication.
So with Snapshot I'll have a large amount of changes; maybe 80
percent of the data in an article changes from cycle to cycle.
So rather than tracking the individual changes moment by moment,
we just take everything wrapped up in the publication and replicate it.
>> So it'd be like taking a picture of your kid once a week and
replacing it in the frame.
>> Exactly. That's a good analogy. Now on the opposite end, Merged
Replication would be like...
If you're familiar with domain controllers, I might have three
different Active Directory domain controllers, each holding full
copies of the object. And if an object changes in one copy then
that's going to change in the other copies as well.
Transactional Replication would be when I have some modification;
I want that more immediately reflected in a destination.
And like I said, there are many configurable options with this.
>> So how do I implement it? What are the different steps that
go into it?
>> Well, taking a look at implementing replication there are lots
of things to like when it comes to high availability because
I'm duplicating data. You'll notice it can support not only one
subscriber but I can have multiple subscribers for one publication,
so I can have even more than one copy.
>> So I could take data from one spot and send it out to a whole
bunch of different servers?
>> A bunch of different servers anywhere on my network. So this
could be geographically distributed... That's what I'm trying
to point out in the lower right part of the diagram... so different
IP subnets, different SQL servers even in different datacenters.
Now there's no automatic failover. So if I'm pointing an application
to some data on one machine and it fails, there is absolutely
nothing that
redirects a client. This would be an entirely manual process,
and it depends on how the application makes a connection.
If you can point to a different IP address or change the connection
string of the application, that would dictate in part how you
would perform failover. There are shared folders where replicated
updates are stored and the distributor will pick them up there
and then move them along. Lots and lots of moving parts here.
>> Cool.
>> So let's take a look at the strengths and weakness. A strength:
replication has been around for a long time.
It's tried and true. You've said you've used it...
>> Absolutely.
>> ...a lot.
>> Lots of configurability. I don't need any specialty hardware
so I can have completely different hardware configurations, one
as a publisher and one as a subscriber; as long as I can handle
the workload, that's fine. I can span datacenters which covers
a catastrophic datacenter loss and I can have multiple secondary copies.
And depending on the replication method that I use, they also
can be locally modified and the changes replicated back.
>> But what about weakness? What are the things that might keep
you from choosing?
>> They all have a price, right?
>> Absolutely. Everything does.
>> We saw no manual client failover and in fact depending on how
my application makes a connection to SQL server that could really
be a handful. So you need to look at that for your own environment.
Also, this is not really a system data kind of protection; this
is for user data, user database data. And unless you select
every single table in your database, it's only partial database protection.
>> Okay.
>> And by the way, you're not going to likely select every table
for replication.
>> No, no, no.
>> Tell me your own opinion, I'm looking for an opinion here,
have you ever gotten replication really tangled up and it really
caused some snarls to get it back up and running?
>> Frequently one of the things that we ran into was when you
had a problem with replication, just about the only choice in
some cases was to delete it and start it all over again.
>> So you killed the subscription...
>> Yep.
>> ...and started over. Yeah, I've heard...
>> ...of this as a plan of attack, do we call it?
>> Yep. Yeah, one of the things that is highly recommended with
replication is that when you do set it up and configure it that
you script out the replication and save those scripts because
that will make it a lot easier.
>> Excellent. Good piece of advice.
Okay, so next up if you guys would flip to my screen,
we'll take a look at how we would walk through the publication
creating process. So I'm connected in Management Studio.
You'll notice there's a replication node, and from there I can
choose New Publication.
No surprise: I get to a wizard. It welcomes me and from there
I have to dictate where the distributor in this architecture
will be. So with this particular architecture I'm saying that
the publisher will also be the distributor. Remember, lots of
different choices there.
So after that we'll find that there has to be folder designated
where updates can be found that the distributor will pick up
on and then move to a target location. So if there are enormous
amounts of updates or you have a number of subscribers making
connections, you might want to make sure that you specify a place
that has enough space.
Now another thing to keep in mind compared to our other technologies,
all of this occurs within a single database. So notice as far
as the scope of protection, we're actually inside the boundaries
of the database. So I have to pick the database within which
I want to replicate and then this should look a little bit familiar.
>> Yeah, I saw that one earlier.
>> Now think about this, there are certain doors you go through
in life, the door slams behind you and there's no knob on your side.
>> Okay.
>> And similarly when we change the publication type, that's a
door we don't go back through. There are several other choices.
You step in a bear trap, you have to rip the subscription or
publication out in order to make a change.
>> So once you've set it, that's about it. Okay.
>> You're going to have to stick with that.
>> So next up, this is important: you'll see this is the list
of articles. You guys got to go back to my slide. Thanks.
You have to pick from within the boundaries of available articles.
So you can read, we have tables, stored procedures. But notice
that we have the plus signs next to a couple of the objects.
So we can expand those and see the individuals on each one.
And in fact on a column by stinking column basis, I can...
>> Oh, so you don't even have to do a whole table.
>> That's right. So I don't have to do all columns but in addition...
Let me get up to this next part... I also can filter by rows.
So seriously what if I have a table that has
data from a bunch of regions and I only want the American region
or North American region? I can essentially write a Where clause
here and from the Where clause determine only that data which
I want.
>> That is pretty cool.
>> Granularity is the big deal here. Now there is a potential
to have more than subscriber. We saw that as a strong point.
So after we've configured this, we have a place where an additional
subscriber can go to pick up changes and also on an ongoing basis
for those current subscribes. And now I'm at the Snapshot Agent
which sets up on what regularity will a
replication cycle occur. So this is going to end up creating
an agent job and use the normal agent job and scheduling process.
>> So a snapshot is only going to update when the agent tells
it to.
>> Exactly.
>> Okay.
>> And for agent security, depending on what particular type of
replication I'm going to use, I'll have to make an association
of the agent in one instance to the agent in another instance.
I just wanted you to see that; not necessarily all the gory detail.
Now towards the end of the wizard, it asks me do I just want
to script? But I don't want to do it. Do I want to create the
publication but not script? Or, what Mister Safety would do...
>> Absolutely. You do them both.
>> I'm going to do both, and from there it asks me more questions.
Basically how do I want to create the script file?
So, do I want append the new script file to an existing?
Maybe I have a whole batch of replication script code that I
want to have and a couple of other options there. And then,
finally complete the wizard. I name my publication
and then it gives me a status update.
>> Awesome, George.
>> There you go. So after that I would then see in the list of
publications, I would see a publication.
>> Awesome. Awesome. So replication: all about getting data from
Point A to Point B. It's more about the movement of the data
than it is about everything else, right?
>> Yeah, and also the fact that I can very carefully control the
type of data in the frequency that I want to send it. So I think
replication really isn't considered a pure high availability
technology but it's duplicating data.
>> So if I move one step closer then and I want a database to
be more tightly coupled to its replica, what would I do there?
>> Well, let's take a look at the next technology, log shipping.
Again, log shipping is a tried and true technology. Let's go
to the next slide and we'll take a look at the big picture here.
So we have the same pattern that we'll look at for log shipping
that we did in replication and the other technologies too: the
basics, how we put it together, how failover works and a strength
and weakness comparison. Now if you'll go back for just a second,
one of the things that you'll see here, in the screenshot I've
gotten properties on a particular database. And you'll notice
at the bottom we have log shipping as one of the pages.
What is the key place to get that started? Well, of course enabling it.
So let's go on the basics and I want you to focus on the diagram here.
We'll say that right now I have SQL Server 1 in the upper left
and it's serving the production copy of a database.
>> Okay.
>> So I have maybe a web app, a windows app that's used to make
a connection to that and so I'll have clients on a network probably
close to that machine.
>> Okay.
>> Now I run through the log shipping configuration and a bunch
of moving parts are put in place. First of all this primarily
applies to user databases but the entire database, its schema
and its data, so this is clearly a high availability technology.
>> So no longer do we have the ability to choose individual objects
to filter out data. It's all or nothing here.
>> Yeah, it's all or nothing.
>> Okay.
>> So as I walk through the wizard first I create a schedule that
says to take the transaction log of the current database, back
it up, generally pretty frequently and then, store those transaction
logs in a shared folder preferably that's nearby.
>> So does that schedule for the transaction log backup, does
that drive the latency between the two databases?
>> Definitely. And in fact before we get done we will see there
are several schedules that can be carefully crafted so that you
get exactly the latency that you want. And this can very much
work in your favor. Hold on to that thought for a second....
>> Okay. Hanging on, baby.
>> All right. So next part of the wizard: we have to determine
on what level of frequency will take the backed up transaction
logs close to another shared folder that may be in the same datacenter
on a different SQL server on a completely different subnet, completely
different area of the network meaning a different geographical location.
As long as the SQL Agent can connect to you in C share, it's reachable.
So in the worse of cases we could have a datacenter failure and
as long as all our mission critical databases were log shipped
to another destination, all that data is there, everybody say, "Ah."
>> Ah.
>> We're not done yet, though, Rich.
>> Oh.
>> Because...
>> There's more?
>> ...now we have a third schedule. And by the way these can
all have different timeframes; that's part of the point.
>> Okay.
>> So I can back up, let's say, every ten minutes, take those
backups every hour in one folder, copy them to anther folder
and then, the third schedule basically does a perpetual mini-restore.
So it keeps the transaction logs restored over the top of the
destination database or databases because I can actually have
more than one copy of a log ship database. That's good news.
>> Absolutely.
>> And in fact, this is strategic: I could actually have different
restore schedules, maybe one aggressive and one not aggressive,
so it could account for maybe a DB uh-oh. I have maybe a four-hour
delay with one log ship copy, and in that case it's not going
to receive an error for hours based on that. That may help me
position well in a recovery situation.
>> That's pretty cool. Now is the recovery the only thing that
you can use log shipping for or are there other things that you
can do with a log ship database?
>> Well, one point to bring out is that with the database there,
there's a setting that says what is going to be important: read-only
querying of the destination Log Shipped Copy or
the restore job. So, one of those is going to win. So let's
picture something.
>> Okay.
>> Let's say I have a connect user that's read-only querying a
log shipped copy.
>> Okay.
>> One of two things is going to win when the next restore schedule
comes up. Either, the user that's connected in querying is going
to be allowed to win and continue querying until he or she is
good and done or the backup job says, "Honey, I'm home."
Boom, comes in. Does the restore. Kicks out the connected user.
So which one are you going to pick?
>> It depends.
>> Excellent. That's the answer to every consultant's question.
>> You fell into that trap perfectly.
All right, so that's the essence of log shipping. Lots to like
about it. So now that we take a look at log shipping, let's go
to implementing it. So I can configure this in Management Studio.
You'll see an example of this coming up and there are lots of
stored procedures that can weave all of this together. I didn't
mention this: I think there are over a hundred stored procedures
just related to replication...
>> So let me guess...
>> Whatever. A whole bunch.
>> Given a choice, I'd want Management Studio to use its wizardry?
>> He he he. Badoomp, shh.
>> All right. So it's late in the afternoon, I apologize. Keep going.
>> So I can use... As a matter of fact if I script the whole process
out, these are the stored procedures that I'm going to see.
>> Awesome.
>> I have to have a recovery model that can use the log file and
more than likely this is going to be the full recovery model.
And so looking at the architecture diagram we see that multiple...
well, a backup job is going to have to be created, multiple copy jobs...
or, I should say a copy job and then restore jobs to perpetually
restore the database.
There is an optional architectural element called a monitor server
which can be queryable and it doesn't need to be any fancy addition either.
I can have that as part of the architecture too.
>> And what does the monitor server give you?
>> Why don't you run with that one?
How's that for tossing the hot football?
[Laughing]
Okay, so you're going to put me on the hotspot. So the monitor
server is going to watch the process and then, if it fails, if
the primary fails it's going to help me failover?
>> No, it's not going to help me failover. It's really more of
a tattletale object honestly. So there is no manual failover
whatsoever with log shipping. And in fact let's go over to failover
basics where we can take a look at this.
So if I have a failure, it depends on what happens to the source.
If I have a catastrophic server loss, well, I
sure don't have any transaction log data there to grab.
>> Nope.
>> So if I happen to have a problem where maybe the machine is
still available but the SQL server service is not running or
there is some damage to the database, at least grab those most
recently backed up transaction logs and copy them near to where
I want to recover. So back up the primary database log with no
recovery; that's going to capture the tail of the log too.
So I'm going to bring all of that data over and I'm going to
perform a normal database recovery on the destination.
It's going to have some jobs associated with being a secondary.
Disable all of those. You may want to turn it back on later,
so don't kill the jobs, just disable them. And then, what you
may want to do is to establish high availability at the destination,
you're going to want to configure log shipping on that machine.
But what do you with clients?
>> You got me on that one, George.
>> So a couple things you could do with clients; it depends on
how the application is architected: if the application is a connection
string that points to an IP address, well, you can change the
IP address of the destination.
>> Okay.
>> That's one way. Another way you do it is if your application
connect string points to a DNS name, well, you can change the
IP address in DNS and then, clients are redirected transparently
as well. So there's not a perfect transactional failover while
somebody's using the log ship machine, but those are
some of the failover options. So notice totally manual intervention.
But there's opportunity for being graceful.
>> And for log shipping just like with replication, there are
strengths and weaknesses, right?
>> So strengths: it's been around forever.
>> That's a good thing.
>> I'm sure a lot of people know how to use it which means you
might be able to get help untangling it. You have multiple copy
jobs and restore jobs with their own schedules, so I can have
more than one copy. And like I mentioned before maybe on aggressive
log ship copy doing a perpetual restore, maybe only a few minutes
behind the original server, the production server, and a maybe
another copy that's a few hours behind.
>> Okay.
>> Just to help. It's not, as you'll see from the demonstration,
too difficult to initially configure or manage and no specialty hardware.
That's good.
>> That's a good thing.
>> Now because copy jobs can move from UNC path to UNC path this
means anywhere in my network where I have access I can even span
geographical regions.
>> Okay.
>> My secondary database is read-only queryable based on how I
have that set up, and alert jobs can be set up if a replication
cycle doesn't occur. I just said the R-word. If I have a failed
job either in restoring or copying and it doesn't occur within
a certain threshold, I get an alert. Everybody say, "Ah."
>> And what about the weaknesses? What are the things we need
to look for?
>> So manual failover as described. This also has to be configured
on a per database basis, so it doesn't protect the entire instance.
And it can't protect master.
So you're not going to turn the
full recovery model on master so that is an, what would you say,
un-protectable database?
>> Yeah, that sounds...
>> We'll go with that.
>> ...like it. Okay, so let's take a look at log shipping.
If you guys will zip to my machine for a sec. Actually hold
on for just a sec.
>> Ah, you were a little bit late on that call there, George.
>> Okay. All right, so taking a look, I'm looking at properties
of a database and the point to focus on is
the recovery model. I have to have something that has logged
transactions that are not going to be overwritten like in the
simple recovery model. Now from there I'm going to go to the
transaction log shipping page, properties of the database, and
after I'm in the right recovery model what do you think I'm going
to do?
>> That checkbox that's sitting there staring at me looks like
a good place to start.
>> So that's like kicking off the domino chain. After I click
on Enable, a whole bunch of action occurs.
So enable this as a primary database; this'll be the production
database copy. And then, I would click on Backup Settings.
I really don't need to look at that. That's just going to set
up a job with a schedule. So that's really business... Excuse me.
Excuse me... as usual.
[Laughing]
Squeaky, over here, doing the demo.
>> Yeah, squeaky Squillace.
So transaction log backup settings. So transaction log backups
are performed by an agent job running on the primary. I'm going
to have a place, a shared folder where I'm going to place my
backed up transaction logs.
>> And that's where the partner servers can go and grab it from.
>> Now I could actually do this two ways: I could have one folder
for storing the logs and then copying those to another folder
nearby or I could actually specify that through the same folder.
>> Okay.
>> So, Consultant, how are you going to pick?
>> Let's see, it depends.
>> It depends. I would say if they're geographically distributed,
I would pick different folders. If they're in the same datacenter
then maybe big deal, what does it matter that they're different?
>> It's probably going to be the same server anyway. They're going
to have easy access.
>> Lots of controls here. So I can delete transaction logs that
are older than a certain time, get an alert if no backup occurs within.
If I want to carefully have naming conventions for these related
jobs, fine. I can do all that. So after that,
let's see I think I just did that. So let's go here.
Again, business as usual. Job schedule. Sorry, didn't need to
go there.
Okay, next up.
I now have the secondary database settings. Now I have to point
to the instance where I want to have this database, and the database
names don't actually have to match. Please, Rich, keep it straightforward.
Have the same database names. And this would seem to make sense,
but now I'm in the first tab Initialize the Secondary Database.
Do I want Management Studio to restore a backup? So I may already
have a database copy there. Maybe it's already there. Or, I
can actually set up the process right here and now.
>> Okay.
>> So after that...
Did I jump ahead here? Let me see.
>> Nope.
Nope. So you set up the database. You set up the destination.
You're specifying the locations, right?
>> Yep, so specify locations. If the secondary database will be
created when the backup is restored, specify the place for data
and log files.
>> Okay.
>> That's if it didn't already exist. So next up I'm in the middle
tab Copy Files. So this is where I could specify a second folder
if I wanted to or point to the original folder where I had my
backup jobs.
>> Okay.
>> My normal inclination is to have separate locations.
And if anybody has a lot of experience with this and has a strong
feeling on the matter, it might be interesting to see what some
of the pulses are there. But I set up a UNC path here. And again,
delete copies after a certain threshold of time. Have a copy
job name. Set up the schedule. So all that, of course, is independently
configurable as well.
We don't really need to look at schedule.
Now finally we're on the last part of the configuration.
And you'll see two radial buttons there which answers the question,
what's going to win. Do I want users that are querying the database
to have precedence or do I want the restore jobs to have precedence
and cut out those connected read-only users?
Notice I have delay restoring backups at least a certain amount
of time,
alert if no restore occurs within and then, again, a job name.
>> So the three pieces are: How often do you want to back it up
and where do you want to put the backups? How often do you want
to copy them and where are you going to copy them to? And then,
how often do you want to restore and will you let people query it?
>> Excellent summary. And so finally if I wanted to monitor server,
yeah, I'd have to go through some of the same configuration there,
how I'm going to have the agents talk to each other or which
instance is going to do it, the job that will handle it.
And then, I'm at the end of the wizard.
>> Cool.
>> So that's basic log shipping. Now it's really beyond the scope
of showing how to perform the recovery but there are lots of
good references when it comes to rolling over or taking a secondary
server and putting it into production.
>> So the key there with log shipping is that we've got the ability
to control the schedule of shipping but there is still a time
lag there. And we really don't have any failover capabilities.
What's the next step in the progression here?
>> Let's see, did we take a look at strengths and weaknesses of
log shipping...?
>> Yes we did.
>> We did. Okay. So next up, exactly like you said, having something
that's a more automated failover, and that's database mirroring.
So database mirroring entered the picture in SQL 2005 and it
was a very exciting feature at the time namely because a technology
we're going to look at, failover clustering, was there
and it has certain strengths and advantages. Log shipping has
its strengths and advantages, and neither of them addressed what
mirroring did at the time.
>> Okay.
>> I have to give away a little bit of the end of the movie.
In the very worst case of failover clustering, you could have
a very long failover time; automatic, but it might be long.
>> All right. Well, let's hold off on that a little bit.
>> Yeah, we'll have to hold off on that and take a look at mirroring.
So same general pattern: what are the basics, how do I set it
up, strengths and weakness, etcetera. So let's take a look at
the basics.
So I have one instance, we'll call it the Principle Instance,
and it's serving a production copy of the database.
>> Okay.
>> Now with newer .NET technologies that were out at the time...
I don't remember what .NET version. Maybe even 2.0 back then.
But anyway, that's immaterial. So with a newer .NET connection
string technology you could not only have a primary connection
string but an alternate server name in the connection string.
And this is part of the automatic client failover trickery.
>> Okay.
>> So I have to have a recovery model. I don't know if it has
to be full but you would only set it up in full. You wouldn't
even use bulk log. And essentially it works like this: I have
a secondary server and on a transaction by transaction basis,
I have transactions going over the network, maybe to the same
datacenter, maybe anywhere where I have IP connectivity in my network.
And picture people marching together... Left, left...
transactionally each copy, transaction by transaction, are kept consistent.
>> So it's almost like log shipping with no delay.
>> No transactional delay whatsoever because... well, actually
with two out of three of the options. One of them actually allows
a delay but hold that thought for a second. So I have perfectly,
transactionally consistent copies of my database.
But we're still on a one database at a time instance.
Right?
>> Yeah, this is protecting on a per database instance. Now there
is some overhead here, Rich. The database destination is inaccessible.
It's considered to be in a perpetually recovering state and so
unless I... Please don't keel over here...
set up database snapshots, this could...
>> Oh dear.
>> And they're not bad. They have a place. I like...
>> Yep, yep, yep, yep.
>> ...snapshots. But that is the only way that the destination
copy is queryable. So am I going to set up mirroring on maybe,
you know, a 5MB database?
>> Nah, I wouldn't.
>> I'm going to set this up on something that's more mission critical,
which means I'd probably allocate a secondary box for this.
So I might specify another 5, 10, 20 grand server that basically
is not serving another role unless something goes wrong.
>> A just-in-case server instead of a just-in-time server.
>> Exactly. All right.
>> So how do we set this up? How do we configure mirroring?
>> All right, so looking at the configuration options there are
three possible ways we can set up mirroring and I want to focus
on the one that really is the jazzy one, the one that provides
the best amount of high availability and in fact immediate, within
ten seconds, failover guarantee.
>> Sounds like a plan. If I'm doing it, I want to go for the best.
I have a primary server. I have a secondary server, and I configure
objects called endpoints which, for all practical purposes, are
listening ears that one machine uses to send transactions to
another TCP-IP Endpoint. So it has a port number. I'll configure
authentication, probably configure encryption, so that I don't
have to worry about that data being intercepted.
>> Okay.
>> So that's the principal and the mirrored copy. I then also
have a tattle-tale or a tie breaker. And this is absolutely
necessary for the automatic failover. It produces a tie-breaker
or core.
So in the circumstance where the principal is unavailable to
server its role, you have to have quorum between the mirrored
database and the witness. And within ten seconds, the mirrored
copy and the witness agree that there has been a failure.
The final transaction is rolled back, and the secondary copy
is put into production that quick. Now that covers database failover.
What about client redirection? Well, remember in the newer...
Well, it was new back then. In the newer .NET connection strings
they also could list a secondary server so client connections,
after they had a hiccup connecting to the first one, you'd set
up a retry and they'd automatically reconnect to the secondary
copy and be put into production.
>> That sounds pretty cool. That sounds pretty cool. Are there
any geographical limitations or anything like that? Is mirroring
restricted at all?
>> No, in fact as long as I can reach from one machine to another
via IP then mirroring is a possibility. So this would cover
a catastrophic datacenter failure as well.
>> So theoretically I could put it on a public Internet IP address
and mirror across outside of my own domain even.
>> I probably wouldn't do that. Probably I would have either tunneling
connections, VPN connections among my sites. And this would
be within my own personal network.
>> Security always comes first, doesn't it?
>> So mirroring strengths and weaknesses:
one of the biggest advantages is that I have automatic database
failover, automatic client failover and within ten-second recovery.
>> Okay. So those are some of the strongest features about it.
Honestly, as you'll see, it's really not that tough to initially
set up, especially if you use the graphical user interface.
>> Cool.
>> Now log shipping we saw; it didn't require any specialty hardware.
The other high availability technology at the time did, so that
made mirroring look really nice. No specialty hardware. I can
have mismatched hardware.
>> That's always a good thing.
>> Different CPUs. Different memory. Different vendor brands.
None of that is material when it comes to mirroring.
>> So weaknesses? Uh-oh.
>> Uh-oh.
>> The D-word.
>> No.
>> Mirroring is deprecated. It is a dead-man walking feature.
>> Please tell me. I'm going to try and give away a little bit
of the end of the movie. Is there a replacement?
>> Thankfully there is a replacement. That's going to be...
>> We're going to be talking about it, right?
>> We will hopefully real soon. But, yeah.
>> All right.
>> So it's deprecated. I have to have three servers. I don't
need three servers with log shipping; have to have three servers
in order to get high availability mode.
>> But the witness doesn't have to be anything special, right?
>> Doesn't have to be anything special.
>> Okay.
>> Mirroring has to be configured on a database by database basis.
So if I had ten production databases that I want mirrored, I'm
going to have to configure mirroring on behalf of each and every one.
>> Okay.
>> So now let's multiply that. If I had a hundred or two hundred
databases on an instance, that's going to be a lot.
>> All right.
>> Finally, no system database protection with mirroring.
>> Okay, so replication can't be used to protect system databases.
Log shipping can't be used, and neither can mirroring?
>> Nope.
>> All right.
>> This brings us... Oh, let's take a look at how we implement mirroring.
>> Absolutely.
>> And actually hold off on the screen for just a second while
I get some things arranged.
>> Okay. Roger that.
>> So I start off the same way I would often when in doubt: right-click.
So, I'll get properties of a particular database, and additionally
I still have a mirroring page.
>> Okay.
>> So I go to the mirroring page, and how about if I start up
at the top? Configure security.
>> So they have to be able to talk to each other and there's security
involved in doing it.
>> Yeah. If I'm shipping transaction logs transaction by transaction,
something has to do it. It is the agent. The agents have to
talk to each other. So when I click on that button, yeah, I'm
going to have to walk through a wizard to configure how those
agents will communicate. So after I start the wizard it asks
me, do I want a witness server? And remember, for the highest
level of availability, the fanciest option: yes, I must have
a witness.
>> Okay.
>> So after that
I have to involve the particular servers to configure.
Now that I have identified that I do want a witness, I continue
the wizard this way.
So now configure the principal, meaning if I said that I want
to have a witness, of course I have to configure the principal.
Of course I have to configure the secondary. And, yes, I do
now want to configure the witness. But first up is the principal.
Now an assumption is made. If I started at a particular instance
in a particular database, it must mean that instance, and I can't
change the name right there. I can change whether or not I want
encryption, and I probably want it. I can change the port and
I'm going to have to communicate with my firewall folks if I
have VPN connections from site to site and I want to have cross-site mirroring.
And an object, a listening ear object, is made called an endpoint,
and I may have naming conventions I want to adhere to. At least
I get the ability to name that.
>> And that port is not the database engine port; it's a separate
port that's set up specifically for mirroring, correct?
>> Absolutely. Now a little bit of a fluky thing here, when I
was running through this...
Don't do this in real life... I had all three instances on one
machine just to reduce some of the moving parts. And that's
why Listener Port 5023 was suggested. I can't have the same
port used on the same machine.
>> Yep, makes sense.
>> Normally I'd have the same port across all of the machines
but I can't do this within one machine. So that's why a separate
listening port was suggested so I have a second instance, a different
point and an endpoint name.
All right, from there I have to validate identity by saying who
I am and then, finally configuring the witness. So pretty standard
stuff there: create an endpoint, port, etcetera.
All right, have to validate identify to the witness; pretty straightforward there.
And then, supply service account on behalf of each of the instances.
Remember, they may not be the same accounts.
>> That's true.
>> Please tell me they're...
>> As a matter of fact...
>> ...different accounts.
>> ...I was going to say if it's best practices, they won't be.
>> Yeah. So I walk through the wizard and there I go. There's mirroring.
Now the fun part: so it'll show progress
and then ask me if I immediately want to start synchronizing
transactions from the principal to the witness. And it asks
me if I want to start mirroring right now or maybe later on.
>> Okay.
>> Now after... And by the way I clicked on start so that it would
have started. And this is when I get back to the mirroring page
and there is a significant button here.
Notice the Failover button.
So the Failover button allows me to manually failover and gracefully.
So I might do this for something like a rolling upgrade. So I
apply a service pack on the secondary
machine, reboot it, make sure mirroring is re-established, failover
to that one, rinse and repeat on the primary and then, get back
to my original configuration. If I need very high availability
I have to have a technology like this. All right, so this is
where I would have manual failover. It would probably be a little
bit more dramatic to see
pulling the network cable on an actual machine that's being mirrored
and see it automatically failover. That would be kind of cool.
>> Yeah, but we don't have multiple machines.
>> All right.
So if I did click on the Failover button, we'd see, "Failover
database mirroring will swap the roles of mirror and principal,"
basically go through the rollover process. And that's it.
>> So what's the technology now that's replacing mirroring?
Where are we going with SQL Server?
>> All right. So the hot technology, really a game-maker, is a
new technology in SQL Server 2012 called AlwaysOn. And this
will be especially noteworthy after we look at our final technology
because it really overcomes all of the weaknesses of all of the
other models, the other high availability technologies.
>> So this is the last of the SQL Server options for HA?
>> Yeah. So we have the standard plan of attack here: basics,
how we implement it, failover, etcetera. So first of all, this
is a new feature in SQL 2012 and we will see that it provides
failover for a collection of user databases. So I can have what's
called an availability group define multiple databases and have
multiple copies.
>> Wow.
>> See, my mirroring copy was not readable and I could only have one.
>> Yeah.
>> Here, I can have multiple copies and I can failover multiple
copies at once. There's lots to like about this. Really only
one drawback but that's another slide.
>> Yeah, I was going to say, "Wait for the strengths and weaknesses.
Don't give it away."
>> So a collection of primary replica databases support read-write collections.
A collection of secondary replica databases, up to four, support
read-only connections, but it requires a particular Windows feature
technology called Windows Clustering.
We find also just like with mirroring that we can have Synchronous
Commit mode. That means before a transaction is considered committed,
it has to have already committed on all of the destination copies.
That's synchronous meaning marching in step.
Asynchronous would mean I send a transaction log over to a destination.
I continue business as usual. Maybe it commits right away; maybe
it doesn't. And then, we also have planned and automatic failover
with no data loss other than maybe the transaction that was in
progress at the time.
>> That is pretty cool. How do I get this going? What do I need
to do to put it together and make it work?
>> So each instance hosting an availability group must be a Windows
Server Failover Clustering node. I have to add the Windows Clustering feature.
>> So this is an OS-level requirement.
>> That is an OS-level requirement. And fortunately the building
or using the failover clustering feature has gotten a whole lot
sweeter over the years.
>> Okay. Probably no surprise. I have to have the same instance
collation on all of the possible member copies in the availability group.
>> Okay.
>> And then, I have to enable the AlwaysOn availability group
feature on each instance. Multiple ways to do that. After I
enable it then I walk through a wizard. It waves a wand...
He, he, he, he, he....
[Laughing]
>> It waves a wand over a number of activities. You have to configure
what databases you want to have as part of the availability group.
You have to configure a database mirroring endpoint. Does that
sound familiar?
>> Yeah, it does.
>> All right. So there's some familiarity there. Create an availability
group listener. Specify replica copies. And then, select an
initial synchronization option.
>> That's pretty cool. Now what about failover? What happens with
failover with all of these on?
>> Okay, so we have a couple different... well, three different
failover modes: automatic failover, which would be the most glamorous
of them and, other than maybe the current transaction that was
in progress, no data loss.
Like mirroring we can also have planned, manual failover without
data loss. And then, in the case where we have some serious problem
but not an automatic failover we can tell it... Well, these
are my words... "Dang it, failover!"
>> Okay.
>> So forced, manual failover possibly losing transactions.
>> And what happens when they do failover?
>> During failover, the failover target takes over the primary
role, recovers its databases and brings them online as the new primary.
The former primary replica when available, if it were to self-heal...
Maybe somebody did a server reset or something like that...
will switch to a secondary and its databases become secondary copies.
Then based on policy, the forms of failover that a given replica
supports are specified by the failover mode property.
>> So, okay, we've gone through all this: what are the some the
strengths and weaknesses we can expect from AlwaysOn?
>> All right, strengths: very fast and automatic database and
client failover like mirroring.
>> Okay.
>> Very flexible configuration with multiple failover replicas
unlike mirroring.
>> That's cool. So you get more than one DB at a time.
>> Read-only access to replicas which we did not get with mirroring.
>> Yay!
>> Can backup replicas to offload work. So take my replica, which
is transactionally consistent, put the backup load on it rather
than the one that's serving production.
>> So now I'm distributing my resource load using AlwaysOn not
just getting HA.
>> That's right.
>> That's cool.
>> No special hardware necessary unlike another technology we're
going to look at. And I can also span datacenters because of
having endpoints that are reachable across IP subnets.
>> Very cool.
>> And my own opinion: this is not particularly trivial.
>> No.
>> So that's it; it's not particularly trivial.
>> Yeah, it is an expensive option but it gives you a whole lot
of possibilities for both resource utilization and high availability
disaster recovery.
>> As far as... I don't have a canned demonstration for this but
I actually can do better.
Use Bing and find the URL for Microsoft Virtual Labs. I don't
know if it's MicrosoftVirtualLabs.com or what. Somebody find
that out. And there is actually a library of a bunch of different
SQL Server-specific virtual labs. They have two specifically
on AlwaysOn. So guess what? You can put your own hands on it.
Run through those particular configuration labs; I think you'll
find that interesting.
>> That is very cool. Very cool. So what then is the last HA
possibility that we've got here?
>> All right. The last one we take a look at is also tried and
true, failover clustering. Lots of places out there with failover cluster.
So we have our typical blueprint here: basics, implementation,
things like that. So let's take a look at the basics.
With all of the high availability technologies, you must understand
the scope of protection.
>> Yep.
>> What we're trying to protect. Now what we're trying to protect
with failover clustering is a hardware node failure. So should
I lose all the power supplies of a machine, I have a motherboard
meltdown, I lose availability of the hardware node then the SQL
Server service is going to rollover to another node and run on
that machine. But keep in mind, the databases that are attributed
to that particular cluster as it's called are not redundant.
Their data is not redundant. The redundancy protection here is
the server hardware node.
>> So we're not talking about data storage protection; we're talking
about resource availability protection.
>> We are talking about hardware. Now in order to implement this,
I have a lot of hardware that I have to architect and it's particular.
This is partly opinion; there are others that might have other opinions.
I think it's particular. So I'm going to set up my physical hardware
first, install Windows then I must implement a Windows Failover Cluster.
It requires a certain configuration. And then, I'm going to
add one or more additional nodes that will be part of the Windows
Failover Cluster. The restriction here is that ultimately what
I get is a portable name. I get a name that clients are going
to connect to. That name and all the resources that pertain to
it can run on one hardware node or can run on any other node
in the same cluster.
Only specific services and applications support this kind of
behavior, so shared folders, a couple of other Windows key features
and then a couple of applications like Exchange and SQL Server.
SQL Server, specifically with this, you must install after you
already have your Windows cluster and some other things occur
after the fact.
Now architecturally... In fact, let's jump to the architecture
diagram and I think this is going to help point out some other things.
So notice I need at least two physical nodes.
>> Okay.
>> Well, even with virtualization I can actually virtualize a
cluster; that's way too complicated to talk about right now.
So the picture you're looking at really is more typical of something
I'd see a few years ago.
>> So two physically separate computers.
>> Yeah, two physically separate computers. Notice they're going
to have a network adapter for clients to connect to.
They're going to have a network adapter for their own personal
traffic among those nodes in the cluster. And notice the heart
there represents a 1.1-second packet. Every 1.1 seconds the
heartbeat packet is used to establish kind of a keep-alive among
the other cluster members. Now the other part of this is that
I'm going to have a storage area network. In the past before
SANs were popular, there were some other technologies. But essentially
we have to have a technology that allows more than one possible
box to control the same LUN. So this could be iSCSI; this could
be a fibre channel. But I allocate resources such as
a bunch of disks for data files, a bunch of disks for log files
and then, I have another resource which is called the Quorum.
As seen in this diagram, I have to have a tie-breaker kind of
resource that says, "This is the node that's actually in charge."
In the past this would be just another small unit of storage,
like seriously a few megabytes, on the storage area network.
These days and more typically and better this could just be a
UNC file share on some third machine.
>> Awesome.
>> And I would say that's more typical.
>> All right. So after I have all this hardware set up...
And word on the street has it that you want these machines absolutely identical.
You're not always told that, but you want the same firmware in
your host bus adapter, same motherboard, same network adapters
in the same slots with the same amount of memory and memory speed.
I mean, you want them as identical as possible.
>> So once you've got all that configured and everything is good
to go how do we then deal with the failover process itself?
>> A couple other little architectural elements: I have
after my Windows Cluster installed SQL Server, and the portable
name here, the SQL cluster is what clients will connect to.
And then, we have failover.
Let's say I have a hardware node failure. There's going to be
a policy that says, "If I have more than one extra machine in
the cluster, prefer to failover to this one." And, will I allow
it to be automatic? Yes or no? So failover is determined by a policy.
Now there has to be quorum or agreement among the nodes in the
cluster as to who is actually serving the instance.
>> Okay.
>> So this could be determined by a couple different ways: node
majority, node and file share, node and disk majority, disk only.
So you have options there. This is expanded from what you might
have had maybe ten years ago.
>> All right.
>> Okay, brace yourself.
>> I'm braced. Give it a ride.
>> Now essentially when my cluster fails over, the SQL Server restarts.
And if I have a hundred databases on that instance, we know every
time SQL Server restarts, every one of those databases has to
go through the redo and undo process. So failover in the worst
of cases could really be lengthy which means it's not quite as
attractive as always on or mirroring, but it protects the entire
instance which the other technologies do not do.
>> Awesome.
>> A good point is that there is zero client configuration.
Clients point to a portable name. So this pretty much dovetails
into the strengths and weaknesses.
Clustering has been around for a long time. That means a lot
of people know about it, have established policies of how to
do it. And setting up the hardware or validating that the hardware
will work right is done with a nifty wizard, the Windows Cluster
Validation Tool.
Weaknesses: specialty hardware required.
It's more expensive. It requires more expertise.
For those who don't know how to operate a cluster role, you may
introduce the opposite of high availability; you may reduce availability
by causing a problem.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And then, keep in mind: data is not duplicated with a failover cluster.
So it's often the case if you were to use this, you would combine
it with one of the other technologies like log shipping or mirroring. Or...
>> Or?
>> ...you're going to use AlwaysOn.
>> AlwaysOn. That would be the one.
>> All right, Rich. So that wraps up all the stuff that I had
for today.
>> That's awesome. George, I want to thank you for your time today.
>> Thank you.
>> I appreciate it. Also, for those of you out here on the view
watching us, in the bottom of your browser there is a poll.
This poll is probably the one that we really hope that you add
your feedback into. It really is how we know how well we did
and gives us a chance to get better in future ones. Again, thank
you so much for joining us today. For George.
>> Thank you.
>> And Rich. And everybody out in the back that helped out,
Elise and Danny and Barry, thanks very much. Hopefully we'll
see you again down the road. Have a great... Woah!
>> I want to put in a plug for your session on Friday.
>> Yeah, we'll see. We've got another one coming up. Check the
schedule on the web if you're interested. We've got data warehousing
in SSIS in a day or two. Thanks again. Have a great evening,
afternoon, morning, whatever it is wherever you are.