[Music]
Welcome back folks.
Thanks for coming back. We are here to finish up this afternoon's
Administering SQL Server 2012 Jump Start. I'm Rich Currey.
I'm here with Mr. George Squillace, SQL in his name.
George what do we got coming up next?
>> Well for the back nine we have some good topics.
Now that we have a solid platform of SQL Server, we've installed
the product, have configured server and database level options,
learned how to make sure the product is running optimally.
Now we have to take a look at some data stewardship.
That'll be Managing Data Module 4, security and high availability
to follow. So for this particular module we're going to take
a look at Managing Data, Data Stewardship, things like that.
>> Alrighty.
>> Moving over the overview.
There's a phrase that the DBA should take to heart and that is
"Tag I'm it".
[Laughter]
>> Usually we end up with everything.
>> Yeah, "Tag I'm It". So I am as the database administrator,
I am the data steward. So we'll take a look at protecting data
as a data steward, which means not only duplicating it via the
backup process. But also when the chips are down Rich we got
to be able to put it back down.
>> Yeah.
>> Got to be able to restore. So we'll look at backups, backup
strategies, restores, and then some other database maintenance
and administration kinds of tests. Like moving databases entirely
or just relocating their files, maintaining database integrity,
some other tools like that, so. That's up for this particular module.
>> Alright so of course whenever anything goes wrong you want
to make sure that you have a...
>> Backup strategy or restore, what?
>> A backup.
>> Yeah a backup.
>> Absolutely we got to be able to back it up so that we can recover
it later.
>> Now I imagine especially for those of you that have a good
amount of experience with the product, the backing up and recovery models.
They're not brand new, but I do want to challenge you for the
exam that you've walked all the way through the process of learning
the different backup, or different recovery models, different
backup types. I will tell you there is an X factor, some aspect
of unknown when you actually come to a point where you have to
restore or recover a database, or a whole system. Some unknowns
that are going to pop up, you must have walked through the process
to recover.
That way when the X factors come up
it won't be any more difficult than otherwise.
>> Absolutely.
>> So the first thing we have to take a look at is a quick look
at the recovery models. Note there are only three. So that makes
the decision making process a little easier.
>> As long as you know what they are and what they do.
>> So the model database is used whenever a new database is created.
It's copied, so whatever options it has those will be applied
to a new database unless they're overridden. The model database
after installation is the full recovery model. This is the most
complete recovery model. It permits point in time recovery and
recovery from failed medium. Bulk-logged recovery model, actually
I'm going to skip to simple for a moment. With the simple recovery
model we'll find out that we are able to restore full backups
and differential backups. But the way that the log file is maintained
is different with the simple recovery model. Transactions after
they've been logged into the log file and then rolled forward
into the database are truncated, which is where the previous
name of the simple recovery model got its name, truncate log
on check point.. So there's no data in the log file that permits
point and time recovery. In fact if you try to perform a transaction
log backup on a database with a simple recovery model it's not
even an available option, so now picture startling between two
different possibilities. That's really the bulk-logged recovery
model and it's not really a perpetual model that you'll stay in.
This is an interim model that you'll use when you're going to
perform bulk operations.
So the point is certain operations are minimally logged and when
in the bulk-logged recovery model you'll take up less log space,
there's less overhead with the bulk import operation, so it's
more efficient.
>> So the full model recovers all of, has the ability to trace
and track all of the work done. The simple just gives you enough
to restart the database if you need it.
>> Exactly so there are times where maybe I have a developer copy
of a database. It doesn't need to have absolutely everything
to the nearest moment, or maybe I have a database that I can
refresh easily from some other process. So a simple recovery
model might make sense for some of those. I have the options
because they're reasonable in certain cases.
>> So what about the backup itself, what are the different statements
and options that you can use there?
>> So you can see that not only do we backup the database files.
But we also have a separate statement for backing up and protecting,
and managing the log file. There are a bunch of options that
come along with each of these. In particular for the test takers
you are going to want to know the most popular
options, like with differential, with init/noinit, format, some
of those other ones.
>> What about making sure that your backups actually were successful,
that they worked. That you can go out and make use of them later.
>> Sure, picture a scenario where I might have an awful lot of
databases and an awful lot of backup files.
Now, let's say you're the primary DBA, you're out with an unexpected
gallbladder operation.
>> Oh boy.
>> Tag I'm it.
>> Yep.
>> Now I'm the one that has to go in and restore. I might not
know what your particular strategy was for storing and naming files.
So now I have to take a look at the contents of those backups
before I actually use them. So we have a number of integrity
and fact finding kinds of statements that we can use against
backup files.
>> Cool, what are those all about?
>> So we have restore verify only, restore header only.
We'll see these in an upcoming demonstration and the types of
information that they provide, lots and lots of facts other than
one of them.
>> What's that?
>> Three give a lot of facts and we'll get to the one that doesn't
give us a whole lot of information other than, okay, or not okay.
>> Alright, so leave me sitting on the edge of my seat.
We'll come back to it.
>> As I often do.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. Alright, so is it the, do we have the same
concerns about backing up system databases that we do backing
up user databases?
>> Some general concerns are the same. But there are special
considerations related to the system databases. First of all,
with a couple of the system databases if they are corrupt to
a certain degree you're not going to have a usable SQL Server.
Let me be more clear. So the master database, if it's corrupt
to a certain degree the SQL Server Service will not start.
>> Okay.
>> In that case you don't have a SQL Server instance. So that's
obviously a game breaker. Additionally, if your MSDB database
is corrupt then the Agent Service will not start.
Although I've never run into this, if the model database in some
weird way would get corrupt, I don't know how, but if it were
that could also actually stop the SQL Server Service from, pardon
me from running.
>> Okay.
>> Additionally. Additionally you don't want to change the recovery
models of the system databases.
The right there means there is the possibility of changing that
on MSDB if you wanted to. But more than likely you're just going
to back that up in full every time you back it up. You would
restore it in full rather than worrying about a point in time recovery.
I know, sorry don't press me up for off the top of my head.
But with one or more of the system databases even if you change
the recovery model, it doesn't change what actually happens.
It's a peculiarity with them.
>> Cool, so why don't we go take a look at that.
George is going to show us how the backup statements work and
the different effects that they've got, and some of those backup
integrity statements that he was talking about just a minute
ago, as well.
>> Alright, so let me make sure I see what instance we're connected
to, just to double check.
>> Okay, so.
>> So I'm going to create a database that we'll use for our purposes.
Some of the information that I used for preparing for this presentation
is this link up there, just wanted you to see that.
Now what I'm going to do is create a destination for the backup.
I'm going to use what's called a device, pardon me.
>> Okay, what is a device do?
>> A device is a friendly name; really it's no more than a convenience
feature, a convenient destination, friendly name that I'll use
for a backup destination rather than some lengthy complicated
path with spaces, and things like that. So I'll create my device,
strangely if you were to right click on that device under server
objects, backup devices.
You tried to look at its contents; it would say that nothing
is there right now. So there won't be any content until you actually
back that up.
>> So...
>> Now I'm going to put some data in the database and then I'm
going to back it up. I'm going to use just a basic backup statement,
backup the database. A couple basic options and this will be
the first backup that I have for that particular database.
Let's see what I biffed here.
Did I add an underscore in the name?
>> Nah it was giving a device, file doesn't exist I believe, so...
>> So we'll just make this easy.
>> Yep just specifying it and that brings up a good point.
That you do have the ability to use devices or you can code the
actual location in using single quotes around the location.
>> Both, that's right. So this time let's go professional and
check my code.
Well Rich we're getting a little...
>> File equals disk equals.
>> Oh yeah I have to, see that's a syntax change.
With the device I don't need that.
>> Right.
>> So now let's check syntax and I do appreciate you being my
second set of eyes.
>> Okay, this is one of those moments that every DBA and every
developer gets into. You can stare at the trees for ten minutes
and you still can't see the forest.
So let's,
da, da, da, da, good effort on troubleshooting here, corrections...
>> I tell you what how about we just back it up with a gooey.
>> There you go and then we'll script it out, how's that.
>> So we're going to add in our device here,
specifying the location in the gooey,
and giving it a file name.
Keep talking.
>> Alrighty, and now that I have the destination,
I have my backup.
>> Alright.
>> So now I'm going to change some data, backup the log.
>> Okay.
>> And then
I'll have to back that up to a device as well.
>> So we're going to go back in and again using a gooey this time
we are going to choose a transaction log backup, and specify
the destination. We can either put it to the same file as its
set here, or we can send it to a different destination.
>> Yep, and notice that I'm going to append to the existing backup set.
That equates to the T SQL option of with noinit.
>> Okay.
>> So that means add to the current file.
Make some more modifications. So next what I'm going to do,
we'll take a look at the backup device that I made, and Rich
remind me what was that?
>> D:\ backups\hc.bak, does that sound right?
>> We'll find out in a second won't we?
>> We'll find out in a second.
>> When you go off the reservation with backups.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> Unscripted.
>> Yeah unscripted, yeah, yeah it happens all the time.
>> Or is it from file equals?
>> Yep.
[Laughter]
>> Is it warmer in here now?
>> It's getting hot.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> That's what happens when you're under the spotlight and things
are going south here.
>> I promised I looked at this.
>> Right click go to backups, find the device.
>> Sorry, right click where?
>> So if we go in, let's verify that file location first off.
>> Yeah, okay so we have to go to Windows Explorer,
no that's of my local machine not my virtual machine.
>> There it is.
>> Yeah, D drive.
Well isn't that curious.
>> Huh, we lost the file.
>> Well actually the folder didn't exist. I thought I had an
automation procedure to make that so, what wasn't made to begin with. Okay.
>> Alright.
>> Let's try this for recovery now.
At least I imagine we're getting some pretty funny comments.
[Laughter]
>> Okay, so this just goes to show that no matter how long you've
been doing things and no matter how many times you've done the
same thing. Yeah, it's called brainous interruptus, okay.
>> My goodness.
>> And we'll give George a second here to kind of get things going.
>> Yeah, I think...
>> But really and truly what we're talking about here is trying
to look at the contents of the backup file to retrieve what's
in there, right George?
>> Absolutely, so let's say I did use a command or I listed, this
was going to be part of the punch line. I had maybe a couple
of full backups. I had a couple differential backups intermingled
with some logged file backups. Now I need to find out what's
in that file, when it was last taken, maybe the range of log
sequence numbers to compare that with another log, with another backup.
>> Yep.
>> All the good juicy information that I would want to find I
need to be familiar with these verification statements. So we
have restore verify only. I have to give away then to the movie now.
And what we'll find out is when I use restore verify only, if
there's no problem I get absolutely minimal feedback. It just
says the backup is okay.
>> Okay.
>> So not much there. Now these others if I want to get a look
at maybe the subject line of the backup. I have restore header
only, I can get facts on the particular items within the backup
file, so files within files, file list only, and then also label only.
They all give me slightly different overlapping information depending
on what I happen to be seeking, so.
>> Okay.
>> So those are the verification statements that we planned on
looking at.
Alright, that's good for that.
>> Alright and this also does bring up a little bit of a topic.
You really, really do want to make sure that as you're going
through your backups and setting them up, this is a good place
to kind of throw in when backups go bad what do you need to do?
You need to test them and make sure that they actually worked.
This is a good lesson on that one.
>> Very good object lesson indeed.
>> Alright.
>> For our next topic we're going to take a look at Restores and Recovery.
So there's a process that's undertaken by the database engine
during a restore. You want to be familiar with that. There are
different kinds of restores, actually a pretty good laundry list
of available restore options you want to be familiar with those.
There are restore statements in the same way that there were
backup statements. Then, yes system databases have special consideration,
as well.
So one of the Charters of the restoration process, and to back
up just a little bit, if you have enough instances and databases
it's not if...
>> It's when.
I was telling you the other day about the story that happened
to me. Nobody likes paying their auto insurance, right.
Nobody likes doing that mundane, you know the kind of work that
you're not really congratulated for. But something when my son
was two possessed him to scratch all the way around my car.
>> Oh dear.
>> I kid you not. The auto insurance company decided to process
a claim for it. I was grateful for that. But nonetheless, that's
when you want it to matter. When you need the recovery part,
and so backing up is great but you're going to have to be able
to actually perform restore. So we'll see that there's a process
involved in the recovery process. Namely, I have to lay all
of my backed up data on the file system so the combination of
full backups, differential, and log backups. After that we're
going to have all of our log data.
In the log data for our running database likely there will be
transactions that were hardened to the log that were not completed.
They need to be peeled out.
There are transactions in the log that were hardened but never
got applied to the database. They need to be rolled forward.
So collectively we refer to this as copy, redo, and undo.
Now from a big picture standpoint there are a few general principles.
Well first you don't want to make the situation worse.
So I guess that's just a general principle. Calm down, you might
be found in a stressful situation.
There's a situation where my server maybe intact but maybe my
data file somehow has a problem. I lost the media or the LUN
that it sits on. In that case as long as the SQL Server Service
is running you're able to capture all the way to the end of the
log, the tail of the log we call it, which means you're going
to want to back that up. That's going to be one of your early
on procedures in the recovery process.
In fact built in to the product, if you don't attempt to backup
the tail of the log you will be barked at. It will tell you,
you have to override to do any other kind of behavior there.
>> Absolutely.
>> So now, what would be the normal series of restore events that
you'd have? We see these at the bottom of the slide. I'm going
to lay down my most recent full, followed by my most recent differential.
>> Okay, alright.
>> Differentials are cumulative so I only need my most recent
one, followed by the series of every logged file since that differential,
followed by the tail of the log.
>> So you've got all those different actions but what are the
different ways that you can apply them? What are the different
combinations that you can use? Are there different kinds of restore
strategies that are available?
>> Yeah, sure. So if I have the simple recovery model, we looked
at the fact that I have no log data to restore.
>> Okay.
>> So I'm only going to be able to restore either just a full
backup or full plus most recent differential, if I incorporated
that into my strategy.
>> Okay.
>> I will tell you you're going to want to know the sequence of
events in the series of the process, so for the exam well, definitely.
>> Alright.
>> Now if I have a full recovery I have more to work with.
>> That's true.
>> So I have the full database that I have to lay down as what
we call a baseline restore.
>> Okay.
>> After that the most recent differential and then a series of
logged files all the way till the end of the log, unless I want
something fancy that we'll take a look at shortly.
>> Alright.
>> I might have to restore a system database, so a system database
restores, and then some fancier or esoteric kinds of restores.
If I have an advanced database design I might need to restore
just a single file or all the files in a particular file group.
Now an ultimate fancy, if my application is already architected
for this.
>> Alright.
>> Is that I can perform an online restore where I bring the database
online file group by file group.
>> Now wait a minute. If I hear the word online I'm thinking it's
available for people to use?
>> That's right it's available in pieces on a file group by file
group basis.
>> So you would have had to have backed it up file group by file
group to start with, right?
>> It's very strange, I can actually backup the database in full
and still do a file based restore. I wouldn't usually do it
that way. I would've probably performed a file by file backup,
but I can actually do a per file restore from a full backup.
I've don't this before.
>> Awesome, awesome.
>> We also have a piece meal restore, which is a smaller more
granular kind of restore. Then per page if I happen to have page
corruptions, that's an Enterprise edition feature.
>> Wow, so just like with backups there are options on the restore
statement as well, yes?
>> Yep, so I not only have backup statements, of course I have
restore statements. I have restore database and I also restore
log, each with typical options. I've listed some of those here.
These are ones you'll definitely want to be familiar with.
In particular when you take a look at restore a log, notice that
I can restore all the way to the end of the log, but I can also
stop short of that particular point in time, if I want to.
>> Does that take care of those so called user induced errors?
>> Yes, yep so as long as I have an idea of when the "U-Oh" occurred
then I can pick a point in time.
>> Awesome.
>> A little caveat though, keep in mind the clock time on a system
versus the watch that somebody's wearing, versus real time.
Those might not perfectly correlate. So if you think you're
being very precise you just might want to be careful about that.
>> Good tip, good tip.
So what about the system databases? Do we have things that we
need to be worried about there? Are there different approaches
there as well?
>> Yep, the system databases require some special treatment.
So in the worse case, let's say master is corrupt.
>> Okay.
>> I'm not going to have a running SQL Server at that time.
You'll know it.
>> Yeah you're going to go and start SQL and it's going to yell
at you.
>> Yeah you're going to know it. So in fact what I need is a,
basically a factor fresh puny little master, just enough so that
the SQL Server Service will start. After it will start then
I can restore the, of course I have a backup of master somewhere.
>> One would certainly hope so.
>> So I restore master and then the rest of the planets will align.
[Laughter]
Alright, now that's when master is corrupt. When master is not
corrupt then I just need to restore right over the top of it.
Keep in mind that master is aware of all the instance level settings,
instance level security. It's aware of every database that's
on the instance, every data file, every database option that's
set on every database. So it's particularly important.
>> So minimally you should probably backup master whenever you
do anything major for sure, and on a regular basis anyway.
>> Yeah, I have, I agree with both of those. I would have a routine
process that would backup my system databases at least daily
so I have at least that. But then I'd want to have a knee jerk
reaction any time I make an instance level change, I would have
a job that I could run Ad-Hoc. So related to our previous module
and that would backup the system databases and put that in some
handy place.
>> What about Model MSDB, TempDB the other system databases, are
there any issues there that we should be aware of?
>> Sure if model is corrupt then SQL Server again will not start.
So I would have to restore model from a backup, but as long as
master or, I
lost my train of thought there.
>> That would be the derailment, it happens.
>> Yeah there we go.
>> So with model then it's just like we're covering a user database,
is model...
>> Yep, model...
>> Is that what you were trying to say?
>> And recovering
MSDB, if it fails then the Agent Service will not start. So I'm
going to have to recover that in order to start the Agent Service.
>> And TempDB, what a about TempDB is there anything there.
>> No there's nothing there, why not?
>> Well, I don't know you tell me.
>> The TempDB is rebuilt every single time that the instance is started.
So you'll never incorporate that as part of your backup strategy.
>> Alright, so can we go take a look at the restores or?
>> Yeah, let's take a look.
>> We venture off into demo land once again.
>> Let's see what do we have up for this?
>> Okay, let's see what happens.
>> So let me make sure I have a folder that will accommodate our
backups first.
>> Alrighty.
>> Let's see how this goes, Rich. We'll be up for a little bit
of excitement, make a couple of devices.
[Laughter]
>> You always wonder if the next one's going to break the trend.
>> Yeah, alright.
So I'm going to make a database, make some stuff in the database.
>> Okay.
>> Perform some changes, so I'm just going to, so notice create
a bunch of columns. They have some default values.
>> Bunch of tables and back it up, yep.
>> So next backup my database in full. I'm going to run this
one alone before I run the rest of them. You know that's a whole
lot better isn't it?
>> It, I like seeing that backup statement work.
>> Yeah, so then run some modifications, backup the log, and then
I'm going to fast forward through a bunch of the rest of them.
>> So basically to sum it up, we're making changes to the database,
adding data, modifying data, capturing the work through the backup
log statements.
>> That's right, so more changes, backup the log, more changes,
backup the log, lots of changes.
>> Okay.
>> Then we'll backup the database, notice with differential.
>> Okay, so the backup log's capturing the work, the differential
is capturing the data that's changed.
>> In fact with the differential backup, notice the option I used
to select that.
It only marks the extense in the data file that I have any particular change.
This is kind of a play on statistics.
>> Okay.
>> What I mean by that is within a database there are often hot spots.
So those tables that get the most action that might be the biggest.
So statistically if only those extense that have changes occur
within the differential backup then that's hopefully not going
to be anywhere near as much data compared to a full backup.
>> So differentials typically you would use when you've got a
small percentage of the database that's having the greatest percentage
of changes done to it?
>> A lot of action.
>> Okay.
>> Now another advantage with the differential is that if I have
aggressive log backups. Let's say every ten minutes, every 15,
every 30, something like that. Picture maybe the requirement
to restore from ten in the morning all the way to six pm.
That's an awful lot of log restores in that circumstance. I have
a general rule of thumb. As you know I often do.
>> Yep.
>> Whatever reduce the amount of moving parts, keep low the number
of moving parts. What I mean by that is the number of restore
operations you want to minimize.
>> Absolutely.
>> Okay, so, what did I just do there? So now I have some more
inserts backup log. Let me just go to the bottom of this.
Another differential, more log backups, and then we have to get
to the exciting conclusion.
>> And here we come.
>> Alright.
>> So can we take a look
at the contents of the device?
>> Right, so now I can go to media contents and there's actually
stuff there. I would probably want to expand these, but lots
of useful information. Now this is a pretty version of what I
could also get my queuing tables in MSDB, so keep that in mind.
>> Okay.
>> Alright, this part I'm going to use for the restore stuff.
So that concludes the part on backing up.
>> Include your recovery and restore.
>> So did I misspeak?
>> So take a look at the restore part of it now.
>> Yep.
>> So keep right on trucking there with it George.
>> Oh, you know what
I'm supposed to show that now.
>> Yep, we got the backup working finally. So let's finish up
with the restore now.
>> Okay, so I want you to observe if I refresh the databases node
and look at the manufacturing database. It looks like any old
regular database.
>> Okay.
>> So let's say something comes to my attention, maybe somebody
can't query that database, within that database. I realize I
had a media failure.
>> Alright.
>> So now I can go ahead and backup the tail of the log.
>> Capturing everything that happens since the last backup.
>> Alright and it would probably help if I actually ran all my
code and used master.
>> There we go.
>> Alrighty and after a refresh I'd like you to make an observation.
Notice this has kicked the database in the side and immediately
placed it into a restoring state.
>> Okay.
>> I want you to see something wonderful here. Notice if I were
to use the gooey and go to do a restore.
It shows all of the elements that I would need to bring it up
to the moment of, you know all the way to the end of the log.
>> So it does all of the telling in what needs to be restored
based on the history tables.
>> In fact it shows
that I need the most recent full, most recent differential, not
all the differentials.
>> Yep.
>> Then of course all the logs that I'd need. Now as bonus round
notice if I go to, let's see
I'm missing some of the user interface here. I'm looking for
the point in time recovery.
>> Main page.
Do, da, do, da, do,
and that's going to be...
>> Oh, you know what that might be.
Let's see.
>> Yep.
>> Oh, timeline, duh.
>> Right there in front of our nose.
>> Come on, come on. Alright so from timeline here notice I have
the ability to restore not all the way to the end of the log file.
That was the punch line.
>> There you go.
>> So we have a slider, we can use a specific date and time.
In fact you can use a date time value to go to milliseconds if
you had that degree of detail.
Right, so that wraps up the backup and restoration portion.
>> Alright, so the next topic we're talking about here comes up
when you have a situation where you want to move a database from
one instance to another, or something along those lines.
>> Yeah I have a dynamic environment, especially if I have a pile
of SQL Servers I might need to move a database to balance load.
That's one possible reason. I might want to put a copy of a database
somewhere else, that's a possibility.
From a work load standpoint I might want to balance the work
load on a particular LUN and just move one data file, or move
a log file. Maybe I add storage and I now want to move a file
up to that. So that's what we'll take a look at next Moving Databases
and Database Files.
We'll find there's a division here once again between normal
user databases and system databases.
>> Ah, you got to treat the, some databases special. What a great idea.
[Laughter]
>> Alright, so moving and copying databases to other instances,
multiple techniques, no surprise. We've seen this all a long
in the SQL Server product.
>> Yep.
>> You can use Management Studio when in doubt. I'm going to
right click, so I can right click on a database and perform a
process called detaching it. Now to compare something, if I were
to right click on a database and delete it...
>> Yeah that would scare the heck out of me.
>> The files are gone,
completely gone.
>> Makes our last topic kind of important.
>> Kind of important. If I merely detach a database the files
are still in the file system, but the SQL Server instance no
longer has any claws or any hooks on them. In fact I could rename
them, delete them, do whatever I want. They're just dumb files
in the file system then. Whereas something, the data files when
the database is attached I cannot touch them, I cannot rename
them, move them, nothing, which is why this procedure's relevant.
So after I detach I then would move one or more of the files.
Then I would attach, that's the general procedure name in contrast
to using Management Studio, SSMS. I can use SP detach DB and
I could also move or copy databases using SQL Server integration services.
There are specific tasks for that.
>> Yep.
>> But I can't talk too much about that. That's your thunder
for Friday.
>> Oh, do you mean you want people to come back.
>> Oh yeah.
>> That would be cool.
>> Yeah I got to dangle some hooks or some carrots out there for that.
>> There we go.
>> There's a lot of fun stuff there on Friday. I'm looking forward
to Friday.
>> So as a newer procedure using the SP attach DB, which has existed
for a good long time, is being discouraged and now create database
with some additional syntax elements and the for attach clause
is now being promoted as the way to attach.
>> Awesome.
>> As with a number of file maintenance and file manipulation operations.
I have to use the logical filenames. But what if I don't know
what they are?
>> Let me guess, you can query.
>> Yeah.
>> Catalog view.
>> Of course, I've catalog views that will reveal everything like that.
So let's move on. Take a look at relocating database files within
a single instance, so if I want to move a database from one instance
to another. I'll have to detach and then I can attach, but what
if I just want to relocate one file within an instance?
Well I'd use alter database for that and no surprise it will
require the use of logical filenames, so.
>> Okay and once you've done, you have to actually move the files
to so.
>> Well yeah and then but I have to move the files in the file
system endpoint properly.
>> That makes sense. So what about the system databases?
>> Yep they need some special treatment. In particular a master,
if I for whatever reason that I would decide to move it I'm going
to have to use a special startup option. So I'll have to go
into SQL Server Configuration Manager. You can look of up the
gory details, as long as you know you need a special switch,
is it minus M?
>> Yeah.
>> I think it's minus M, but whatever some startup switch.
Then you'll restart the SQL Server Service. Other system databases
they'll also require altered database, but you'll have to restart
the SQL Server Service.
So with that let's take a look at moving a user database.
>> Alright, so are we going to move it between instances this
time, George?
>> Do you know what, I don't even remember off the top of my head.
I have something squared away.
>> Aright, so.
>> So first I'm going to make a database in the default instance.
So the default instance I've connected to down here. I'm going
to create a database called
DB2B moved.
>> I love your naming.
>> Don't you.
>> It actually tells me what you're going to do with it.
>> Alright so we happen to see this having been created in the
graphical user interface. I see it here right now. So from here
I can go ahead and detach it.
Now I suppose it would be a little more dramatic if I tried to
rename those files, drop them while the database is attached.
[Laughter]
It's not going to work. But for right now I'll click on okay
and notice this is no longer part of the default instance.
>> Now it didn't delete the files it just disconnected it from
the instance.
>> In fact we're going to see this because now what I want to
do is attach that database to another instance, whether this
is halfway around the planet or you know another machine in the
rack, that's immaterial.
>> Okay.
>> The process is the same. So let me go to Windows Explorer and
I have to move a couple of things.
>> Alrighty.
>> Let me get my task bar here.
We'll find in the default instance here's my database to be moved.
The other instance
is in the marketing folder. Now that's my data file. Next up
I'm going to have to go to...
>> The log file, L-L-L, in the L drive.
>> There we go,
L and we'll take my log file and we'll move it to marketing,
as well. Alright, next up let's go to the non-default instance,
right click on databases, and let's attach.
Let's point to our new file location, DB2B moved.
Observe with the log file it thinks well it's actually thumb
printed in the file where it thinks it's suppose to be, and guess what?
>> It's not there anymore.
>> Its cheese was moved.
>> Alright.
>> So we have to point appropriately.
So now we have to go to the log file location and here's DB2B
moved, click on okay, and there it is.
>> And we are back in business, very cool, very cool indeed.
>> Let's see if I had any other fun, let's
call that good for now.
[Laughter]
>> Alright, so our next topic George. We're going to be talking
about something that really has a lot to do with the backups
and restores database integrity?
>> Yeah, it's not likely that the database engine will ever, or
I should say it's not likely the databases are corrupted.
But before you backup a database that is, you don't want to backup
a database that's corrupted.
>> No.
>> You'd like to find out if it's corrupted and then maybe proceed
in a maintenance routine through the backup process. So we have
to take a look in general at insuring a, I'm sorry, database integrity.
This is going to involve the use of some DBCC statements.
This would be part of your normal maintenance routine like we
saw maintenance routines in an earlier module today. So we're
going to take a look at DBCC in general and then specifically
related to integrity checking statements.
>> Okay.
>> How we execute it and in the rare and unfortunate event that
it reports errors, what we're going to do about it.
>> Oh dear, so what is DBCC after all?
>> Alright, so first of all it's the name or the, you know the
acronym starts for Database Console Command. This is a new version
of the acronym; formally it was Database Cons, easy for me to
say, Database Consistency Checker. And now as you can see or
as you would see from the link there are lots of DBCC statements.
>> Okay.
>> The time when a database might become corrupt would not so
much be likely with the SQL Server System but with the IO System.
Maybe I have a corrupt caching controller or a host bus adapter,
something like that. Now some of the statements that we'll see
in DBCC they're categorized. We have informational statements,
validation statements, maintenance, etcetera. So there are lots
of those, it would probably be a good tour of duty to at least
become basically familiar with some of them.
>> DBCC can be an extremely useful tool when you're looking at
the databases.
>> So the one that we're going to look at now, let's go to the
next slide is DBCC CheckDB. Its purpose is to validate integrity
of the database structure and the data inside it. Strangely it
actually spawns other processes, other DBCC statements like check
allocations, check table, and DBCC check catalog.
>> Okay.
>> If I have a large database whose integrity I'm attempting to
check, there's some options I might want to consider, namely
because it might take seriously hours and hours and hours to
run this. So notice some of the options that we have physical
only, no index, all error messages. This might be if I just
want to see error messages. I don't care about all the detailed
reporting that it can provide if I want.
>> Yep.
>> And another one estimate only. So just give me an estimate.
>> Of what it would take.
>> Next up, in the rare circumstance where a database would have
corruption we have repair options. This part is easy there are
only two. The other part that's easy is if there's corruption
that's reported, it will state what the minimum required repair
option of the two is in order to fix something.
>> So it will tell you what you need to run.
>> It will tell you what you need to run. Now my database is
going to have to be in single user mode.
I'll use, as we saw earlier that's a database availability option.
I'll have to go to alter database to put that in single user mode.
>> Okay.
>> And now for the two options that I have, Repair_Rebuild.
Notice no loss of data integrity within the database and it does
some shuffling under the covers to put the database back in good order.
Now very unfortunate, if you are advised to use the Repair_Allow_Data_Loss
option, this is absolutely the last resort. This is if you have
no backups, absolutely out of altitude and ideas, as they say.
This is your only choice, picture a gun to your head. You just,
you have no other choice.
>> Oh dear.
>> That's when you're going to pick that.
>> Alright.
>> Now after you perform your operation you're going to want to
make sure that it doesn't occur again. So you're going to have
to aim at getting to the root cause.
>> Okay, can you show us how it's done George?
>> Yeah, let's take a look at using DBCC CheckDB and some of the
things that it reports.
>> Alright.
>> Let me make sure I'm connected to the right instance.
So I'll run DBCC CheckDB targeted at a particular database.
You'll notice it's...
>> Boy there's a lot of messages there.
>> It's somewhat verbose, lots and lots and lots of stuff here.
>> So I got to read through all that to find out if my database
is all set?
>> This is kind of like the boss that says I'm thinking of Alise
here, just give me the facts please.
[Laughter]
Are we okay?
So you'll notice at the end it says, Alise is here in the room.
[Laughter]
She's managing our project here. Notice it says zero allocation
errors, zero consistency errors. So it took all that to get
to that conclusion.
>> Yeah, okay tell me George; is there a less verbose way of doing it?
>> Let's take a look at running DBCC with no info messages.
>> That would be a good one.
>> So we'll run that, notice this database is not particularly large.
What did we get? Yep, you're okay.
[Laughter]
Yep, you're okay.
>> Alright.
>> Alright, now I have a problem child.
>> Okay.
>> Let's see, I want to make sure my path is right here.
>> Alright, so let's...
>> So D SQL Admin Jump Start.
>> Got that one in the wrong spot, uh.
Did I put that on F? Okay, well that was an easy fix. Yep that's
an easy change, change it from D to F.
>> Okay, let's see if that dog will bark.
>> There we go.
>> Alright, you've been a patient guy with me Rich.
>> I try George, I try.
>> You know you've got to be though.
>> That's probably because I've been there, done that, got the
T-Shirt on these things once or twice myself.
>> Yep.
>> Hey wait a minute there's red ink.
>> Ooh, red ink can be bad.
We observe down below
there are errors.
>> Okay.
>> No allocation errors but there are consistency errors and it
got worse than that, not in red. What's my only available fix here?
>> Repair_Allow_Data_Loss.
>> Now strangely how might someone even become acquainted with this?
Well I might perform a query and notice I'm doing a select *.
>> Yep.
>> So all columns, all rows.
>> This is going to retrieve every page in the table, ooh.
>> Logical consistency based yowsa.
>> So let's say an error like this is reported from an end user.
They're going to call a help desk, tech support, something like that.
Somehow that's going to get the Data Team, but take a look at this.
Notice, depending on where the query is made there might be unaffected
areas of the same table.
>> So some of the data's good, some of the data's not.
>> Yep and just a little, this is a little Ad-Hoc here Rich.
Let's say I selected * from
MSDB.DBO suspect pages, ooh, on target. This would also show
up to 1,000 corrupted pages, pages where the check sum didn't
match the data that was read.
>> That's one of those tables you'd really want to keep an eye
on over time.
>> And strangely the product is set to only store 1,000 rows of
suspect pages. I think that's reasonable.
>> I hopefully you go, don't have that many.
>> If you had anywhere near 1,000 pages you have bigger problems.
>> Yep.
>> Alright, so next alter database, set single user with roll
back immediate.
Here we go over the waterfall, Rich.
>> And we're doing that because we restored a corrupt backup.
So that kind of gets rid of restore doesn't it?
>> We lost all altitude and ideas. We had absolutely no other
choice but to repair. So now let's go ahead and put the database
back in production, so to say, notice we can query the table now.
>> Yep.
>> We at least don't get an error.
Notice that well our integrity has been maintained.
>> That's cool.
>> The only thing is though it paid no attention to foreign key
references, which means this shows all the order details that
are no longer associated with orders. Basically we are in seriously
hurting shape.
>> So we lost data.
>> We lost data. Now that...
>> Well that kind of is expected with Repair_Allow_Data_Loss.
>> Yep.
>> Alright, so what about other maintenance that we do. Are there
things that we want to be aware of and things we want to take
care of?
>> Yep, last up, last topic for this particular session is dealing
with Indexes, Statistics, Maintenance. So we have to take a
look at a couple of table structures that are out there, indexes,
and then some other objects and their maintenance. So with that
up, let's go to table structures. If I were to create a table
in SQL Server without any special options we would see that A,
the data is stored in pages as normal, but the pages are in no
particular order within the data file.
>> Okay.
>> In addition, the rows within those pages are in no particular order.
>> Okay, so it's just a heap of data.
>> Just a heap of data.
>> Alright.
>> Often for various query improvement purposes, we will want
to impose not only an order of rows within a page, but a logical
order from page to page.
>> Okay.
>> Then some extra pages are stored outside of that clustered
table that are used to navigate and find those objects.
>> Okay.
>> Alright, so now that we know what the two table structures
are, we have to take a look at what our indexing options are.
There are various ways that we want to query data in SQL Server.
We have objects to make sure that those queries are efficient
index objects. Now an index is just a list of sorted values.
>> Okay.
>> Let's keep it simple.
As an add on that list of values may impose uniqueness or it
may not. I often find that the constraints that are used to make
indexes are confused with the index names. So to help you along
the way I've made a little matrix here of the different kinds
of constraints and indexes, and how they map.
>> So what do we need to be aware of with indexes, other than
the fact that they help us look stuff up?
>> In variably over time data's going to change and indexes are
going to get fragmented. So that's going to impose upon us, the
Database Administration Team to maintain those indexes.
We'll see a couple of ways that we're able to do that. Now before
I get there, well there's another object we want to talk about
and that is statistics.
>> What is statistics do for you?
>> First of all statistics are objects that basically compute
the estimated number of rows or actually calculate the number
of rows in a table. This can be important for the query optimizer
when it goes to produce a query execution plan, it may impact
the join order of one table to another based on the number of
rows in one table compared to another. Also statistics will
gather things like, if I'm querying for the name Smith, I might
have 10,000 Smiths. If I'm querying for a Squillace I might only
have one. That may impact the query execution plan.
>> Okay.
>> So statistics are valuable objects is the big picture here.
>> Alright.
>> Now some good news, if I can cut over to my virtual machine
for a moment. Let's take a look at the model database. If I
go to the model database, we'll notice under options there are
a couple of options here. Let's use green, first of all we have
the auto create statistics option and we have the auto update
statistics option. Now on smaller databases and I don't mean
puny, but on something that's not gargantuan these are fine to
leave on. There are some that have some very strong opinions
on whether or not these should be on, and for the largest databases
you'll probably want to have a background automation process
to have those updated, or create and update them. The impact
here is that if I make a new database it will have the same settings
as model.
>> Okay.
>> So now that we know that, let's go back to our regular slide,
if you would please.
We see that statistics can also become outdated as data changes.
So we now have laid on the table that there are indexes to maintain
and statistics to maintain, which brings us to the topic of index fragmentation.
>> Okay and what's fragmentation all about?
>> There are two kinds of fragmentation that can occur in indexed
and tabled data. So we have internal and external fragmentation.
Internal fragmentation is kind of like this, let's say I have
a little kiddy pool of water.
>> Okay.
>> I have a bucket that I want to use to carry the water from
one place to another. If I only fill the bucket up half way I
have to make double the number of trips.
>> Makes sense.
>> This is like a page of data that's only half full. SQL Server's
going to have to read the page into memory in order to use it
for querying, which means it's taking up twice the amount of
space that it needs to. It's more IO operations to get the pages in.
So often I don't want this. However, if I know I have lots of
rows that I'm going to be adding in then I may want to have it,
have pages partially full, and there's a percentage that I can
use to dictate that called fill factor. Now external pages relates
to the physical location of pages within a data file. When they're
spread out the read-write head of the spindles going to have
to move, any time the read-write head has to unnecessarily move
that is negative performance impact, and you don't want that.
Now, sorry.
>> So how do you now get the maintenance to trigger off? How do
you actually execute that maintenance?
>> Alrighty, well one of the things that you'll want to do is
you may have a particular table that seems to be performing poorly.
So one of the things that I may do, let's say I go to our market
dev database, pick a particular table.
Let's say I go to a particular index, I can get properties on that.
>> Okay.
>> Now this is when I would have the foreknowledge or concern
about a particular index
out of maybe 10,000 that I have in the instances that I operate.
Notice that I can see the fragmentation here and the page fullness.
>> Okay.
>> General threshold, if I see a number above 30% I want to perform
one operation. If I'm maybe ten to 30% I want to perform another operation.
>> Okay.
>> So with that...
>> What are those operations that we want to do?
>> Those operations, I wanted to go back to the slide for just
a second. I showed how you could use the gooey and this is the
index fragmentation page.
So I think that's back one, perfect. So at the bottom you'll
notice I can use the graphical user interface to determine fragmentation.
Also I have a dynamic management object, some of those we looked
at early on. This is a very broad reaching DMF. Notice that
I can look database wide across all indexes in the instance to
determine fragmentation, and more granular than that. Okay, let's
go on then. Then finally, notice that I have automation steps
that I can use to maintain indexes. For indexes I can reorganize
them, which is more of a shuffling and modest efficiency improvement,
modestly improving of fragmentation. Then rebuild actually takes
space to completely recreate the index and then collapses the
old one and replaces with a brand new rebuild index.
Rebuilding takes more time. Enterprise edition has some online
versions of the maintenance operations, and a curious thing when
I reorganize an index if I cancel that in the middle the work
that's been done up to that moment is retained. If I cancel
a rebuild well it never made it to the finish line that I'm not
able to use.
>> Oh, that's too bad.
>> You'll notice from the graphic on the slide also, I'm using
the SSIS version of the maintenance task. Notice I can rebuild
and index, reorganize, and I also can update statistics.
These are very granular, so.
>> So rebuild and a reorganizer are exclusive to each other.
You wouldn't do one and then the other?
>> No.
>> You'd do one or the other.
>> That's right, so what I might do is first have a query that
looks for those objects which have a certain threshold of fragmentation
and reorganize those, and completely separate look for those
objects that have a greater threshold of fragmentation, and then
I would rebuild those.
>> Alright.
>> I do want to go on record saying there are lots of very polar
ideas about what the proper thresholds are how often you should
do this, whether or not you should even bother doing that.
So do a little bit of research there.
>> Alright.
>> And now the final thing that's, let's see you want to see this
last one?
>> I think we can do this last demo, absolutely.
>> Okay, I think it's pretty quick, but let's see.
>> So in this one, we're going to go and after we've already looked
at the fragmentation, as you did in your last little demo.
Now we're going to actually do some maintenance on an index George?
>> Oh, you know what,
oh yeah here we go.
>> Alright, so what do we got going on here?
>> Alright, so I'm going to create a table in TempDB. I'm going
to populate it with some data.
>> Okay.
>> Next up the population.
So we're going to put 10,000 rows in this.
>> And hopefully that one doesn't take to, too long. Boy that's
good SQL's quick, I like that.
>> Yeah, alright next let's check the level of fragmentation using
a dynamic management object. Notice the number, the number of
inputs that this function can take. Notice options like detailed.
>> Alrighty, so we've got a clustered index on the table and it's
telling us what, George?
>> Alright, so now I see the average fragmentation and percent
at the moment.
>> Okay.
>> And another one of particular importance is the average page
space used. Notice it can't be more full than 100%. So it's
fairly jammed packed.
>> I'd say 99. something is pretty doggon good.
>> Now there's some fun query code written here to scramble everything
around and fragment the heck out of the data that's within that
particular table.
>> Okay.
>> So this time around
we'll now query using the same dynamic management object, but
observe now the fragmentation in percent.
>> Yeah, boy.
>> And let's also take a look at the average page space used.
>> Okay.
>> Notice much less used.
Now one of my maintenance options is to use alter index all.
That says on behalf of a table object that I have I'm going to
rebuild all indexes.
>> Okay, that went pretty quick so I would say that was a pretty
small table.
>> Pretty small table. So now let's go ahead and determine if
there is any fragmentation that remains after a rebuild.
You probably can predict the end of the movie, right.
>> Yeah, let's hope so.
>> Average fragmentation and percent, zero.
>> Awesome, awesome.
>> Alright and then average page space used in percent, there
we go.
>> Back up there, a good level, very cool.
>> Okay, so in this session we took a look at data file maintenance,
other kinds of maintenance, data stewardship.
Next up is security.
>> Yeah, we will be back in just about ten minutes. Thanks very
much, see you in a few.